Hi guys, welcome to this section where we're going to be making bowling pins
and a bowling ball! What are we going to cover? Well more complex meshes. The
whole idea here is that we step outside of our comfort zone again. You just got used to box modeling,
now we're going to introduce you to curvy things like bowling pins. How are they going to make
a bowling pin, Mikey? Well in this module, we're actually going to
suck in some reference material from a picture, so we're going to bring that into
Blender and use that to trace our model. So reference material,
real world reference material, that is a pretty handy technique! And then we're going to move on from there
and look at shading, a little bit of real world shading. Just basic stuff, we're just going to put a
red stripe, or whatever color stripe you want, around that bowling pin and show you how to
make different parts of your model appear different for the first time. So
we really want you to do that. In fact, maybe, Mikey, you can stress how much we want them to customize.
Yes, you could make anything. Make it your gnome!
Your gnome? Make the bowling pins gnomes!
It's an intentional slip of the tongue. You're going to make gnomes! You see what he did there, he's a really funny
guy. Make it your own, make it your gnome, garden gnome. You've got to make garden gnomes now!
I think they understand that. I think they've got it. O.K. so another thing that's
important is, we're going to be talking about the whole workflow in this section.
So I'm going to show you, at the end, how to export your model and then,
just as an example, how to import it into another package and I'm going to use Unity as the example, You
don't need to follow along. You don't need to download Unity, it's a very big package. If you've already got it,
sure. But you'll be able to see the impact of the way that you build your
model in Blender, and how that manifests itself over in a different package.
OK, and there are things to consider, like the scale of the model, like the rotation
of the model. The normals of the model. The normals, back to those old chestnuts.
Yes. And also, the way that your hierarchy of objects is arranged and named.
So all of that type of stuff is going to impact how it's exported,
and it's important to begin with the end in mind. Good old Stephen Coby... Coby? ...or even
Covey will tell you that. So that's what we're going to be doing! Yep! And always
remember to enjoy yourself throughout this entire section, and if you do have
questions, ask, and make sure you post your results in the discussions, so we can
see how you're getting on.
<<<<<<< HEAD:Blender/Section 3/BP01 Welcome to Section 3.srt
=======
>>>>>>> 61fb7349cf669f249b4a9560c07cf0816c59420a:Blender/Section 3/BP01 Welcome to Section 3.srt