Welcome to Blender Model Scale! In
this video we're going to talk about from around 0.01
Blender Units to 100 Blender Units,
Blender works really well; however outside of that, Blender
does not work well outside this range and that's very important
when you're working with your models. As a rule of thumb, the best
thing to do is use the grid floor, that we'll look at
in a moment, as a stage for whatever model you're doing,
and if it looks right on there, then great model at that
size. And finally, pick an order of magnitude as to how
big this object is, different to how it is in real
life. It might be an order or magnitude of 1, it might just be the same,
suitable for the level of detail for the model you're working on. So
let's quickly hop over into Blender!
When we open up our default cube, our default
scene in Blender, we have this cube here. Now this cube
has a radius of 1, i.e. it's 2 along every
edge, it's 2 Blender Units on every edge. And this
grid floor here, this is the stage that I'm talking about. So if we
imagine that that cube was sat on the stage, that's a descent size
for that particular cube. That's great! Now, if
we were to work with something much much smaller... So let's
delete our Cube there and create another Cube, and in the
Operator Panel, let's set its Radius to
0.001. So
that's quite small, that's an order of magnitude beneath what I've mentioned before,
and we can't even zoom in that far. It becomes a real
pain to see it. In fact, here I can see it. If I turn off the 3D Manipulator Widget
and move our 3D Cursor over there, we can just about see
our cube but we cannot zoom in any further. We'd have to start
playing with Blender in order to still see that, and we don't want to
do that, that makes our tool more difficult to work with. However,
if we change the Radius now and go to
0.01 our cube is
just on the edge of working. If we zoom in much more than that, it starts
the clipping thing again. As you can see that cube is not displaying properly,
and if we zoom in so far, well we start seeing through our model
in some weird manner. Now the same happens
if we increase this Radius now, to let's say 100.
Oh, it's a really really really really really big cube!
We can still work with that, that's absolutely fine! However, if we go
beyond that to about 300, I belive we'll start
getting some clipping. I can see it happening in the bottom
corners here. I can see that's clipping away, so that really is the absolute
maximume. If you go much higher than that, let's say to 500,
you can see straight away that Blender does not handle that very well,
and you're going to have to start, as I say, changing the settings
in Blender and that's no good! So as a rule of thumb, you really want to
work on a scale that fits this grid here. That's a
good rule of thumb. Not always, sometimes you may go beyond it if
you're making a large building or something like that, but as a general rule of thumb,
stick to that grid.
It's challenge time!
I'd like you to now think of the order of magnitude that you'll be
working with. So I've filled in part of this chart, so you can get
an idea of what we're working to. Our first column here, the
Object, is a real world object, and I've put its real
size in. Now, obviously you will find ants and grasshoppers that deviate
from these sizes. I'm 1.6 meters tall, so I've
based my human on that. Now that's actually quite short [Laughs] in
some cases. So you know these are just general, real,
sizes, not exact. And I've gone through the motions
of, which way am I scaling it? Am I scaling it up? Am I going to keep the
scale kind of the same, so 1 meter equals 1 Blender Unit,
or am I going to reduce the scale?
Pause the video now, go through
this list, give it some thought about how big you would make this Object,
on the left, in Blender.
OK welcome back! This is how I would do
the scaling myself. So let's start from the Car. The Car's
about 4 meters long in general, and I keep the scaling the
same in Blender. There's plenty of scope to do millimeter
level stuff, all the way up to the meter scale, so that's absolutely fine
we can keep that the same. And similarly with the House, you can keep that
the same as well, 10 Blender Units 10 Meters, absolutely fine.
Obviously some houses are smaller than that and some can be much bigger, that's
absolutely fine. Next, is an Oil Tanker! Now, we're starting to get into
the realms of very large objects here. Now a real size
Oil Tanker could be in 400 meters or so, some are even
bigger I think, but you certainly scale that down, you would not work on a scale of
400 in Blender. As we've seen when you [Laughs]
approach 300, you start having problems anyway. So
I would scale that model down. Now, I would either scale it down by a factor of
10 or 100, and that depends on the level of detail that
I want. So in this case, I'll scale it down to 4
or maybe keep it up at 40, if I wanted that extra level of detail.
It depends on it's end application. Our Bridge,
right Golden Gate Bridge is nearly 3 Kilometers long, for instance
but you wouldn't want to make it 3 kilometers long in Blender.
3,000 Blender Units, that's going to be crazy, so you'd scale that down.
And again, depending on the level of detail you needed, you could make it
3 Blender Units if it was something you were viewing from a distance in a game or
just a low poly model of it I suppose. But if you wanted more
detail, you'd probably bump it up to 30 Blender Units. So
it would be slightly larger than our grid that we start
with but that's absolutely fine! Now, finally the Earth!
Now that's a big big object, 12,000 kilometers,
and obviously we're going to be scaling that down, but how far? Again it depends
on level of detail. I certainly won't go any larger than 120, and
I'd probably keep it around 12, unless I needed an excess
amount of detail. But once you start needing a lot more
detail, one of the things to remember is, you can always produce
another model. So for instance, let's take this Earth as a quick
discussion point.
So let's talk about scale, level of detail, and models!
So one model does not have to contain its all! Use
multiple models when necessary. So imagine
you're zooming in from outer space, you're approaching the Earth. Well
when you far away, you can use quite a low poly
model of the Earth, it just needs to be a sphere, and then, we're zooming in,
so it's going to have to get more and more detailed at some point. But
we don't need to include all that detail on the one of the Earth
that is millions of miles away before we reach it, and
we certainly don't need to include all the of the detail on the Earth. By the time we're zooming
in to the level of let's say a city, and as we go more and more detail,
we can focus on the bits that we need. Now, you would have to make multiple
models for each level of detail but that's absolutely fine!
Think of the end in mind,
and you'd simply transition
between these low detailed models to higher detailed,
when you need to. Let's move
on to the next lecture!