Welcome to Choosing the Right Primitives! So
why your choice matters, when you're picking a starting primitive.
Now, starting with a primitive the same symmetry and
shape as your target model will save you time. So if you're
starting off making a book, perhaps you're doing a fairy
tale story book, then if you started off with a sphere
it would take you a long time to get it down to a
book shape. And similarly, if you were making a ball,
you wouldn't necessarily start with a cube.
So it can be very hard to remove all traces
of that original shape. As I said, if you start with a
completely different shape, it's going to make your life difficult.
Fair enough if you want the challenge, but not a great idea!
So here's a challenge for you guys! Which primitive would you use?
So we've got some examples on the right-hand side, and
they're planes of symmetry. So if you were to cut through that object,
it would look the same on either side.
Obviously these are basic examples of that. So pause the
video now, and fill out which primitive you think would
suite the examples on the right.
OK welcome back! Here we go! So let's
explain these, as we go through!
So a Cuboid has 3 planes of symmetry.
So imagine a book, smart phone, in general you could cut them through
3 ways. You could cut them through the middle, the top, or
the front, and they would be the same, from a starting
point. Remember this is the starting point, not the end point. Obviously, after you've finished modeling
a car will have an actual top and bottom to it and start to lose
some symmetry. Now a Cone and a Cylinder.
Well they're actually the same thing, a Cylinder is a special case
of a Cone. So if you imagine a lamp shade, it's
kind of a cut off Cone, but if you widen that out it eventually
become a Cylinder and then it goes the other way again. So if you were modeling
any sort of bottles, a cup perhaps, the
Christmas Tree type shape, you would start with a Cone or a series of Cones
in order to make that. Finally, we have a
Sphere. So if you were making some fruit, like
an apple or a lemon or a rugby ball or anything spherical, it would
be an obvious place to start, by using a Sphere.
I hope you guys got on very well with that! Let's get on to the next
lecture!