Welcome back, Ben with you again!
We're going to be talking about Assigning Materials to Faces! We want to put some stripes
around the neck of our pin. So in this video we will introduce the Material Properties
Panel, tell you how to create and name materials.
We'll be talking briefly about users of materials and how that impacts trying to delete
them, and we'll also, of course, show you how to assign a material to
the face. So the bit I want to bring your attention to is, on the
right-hand side of Blender over here in this panel
here. Now, what is the panel? It's called Properties! You can see from the icon. So in the Properties
Panel, I want you to make it a little bit larger, and you can actually scroll
left and right. There's a lot of little controls in the Properties Panel, I'll show you. I can
either hold down the Middle Mouse Button or I could scroll up and down,
or for the sake of clarity, I'm just going to make the panel bigger for you guys. OK.
So click on materials there! And what I want you to do, to start with, so that
this view looks like the slide is, I want you to go to where I'm hovering
at the top rightish where it says "Add a new material slot", because the materials
panel slot's very very sparse. There's no slots, there's nothing to be had. So you
click plus and now you're going to get a little bit more information,
and then, I want you to click New. So we've made a slot, it's just an empty
slot for a material on the pin. Now click New. And that's
now you're going to get to this view, which can look a little overwhelming, especially if you scroll down.
A lot of stuff there! I just want to focus above this line here, for now.
So I've got a slide for you, which will help you to focus your eye in on what's going on
at the very top of this Materials Panel. So we've already done the thing at the top, which is we've
selected the Material Tab. The next thing you see is a bread crumb, it basically
tells you where we are. What are we dealing with? Are we looking at the scene? That's that
first little icon. Then, the cube is the object that we're dealing with, and then, we're
looking at the materials of the cube. So it just reminds you where you are and what you're working on.
The next list is a list of applied materials, or it's
at least a list of material slots for this particular object,
so now the pin has one material slot. And we did that on the right-
hand side, with the Add, Remove, Copy/Paste buttons. And then, you've got another
little sliver along the bottom, which we're going to be using a lot, which is where you actually manage the material.
So let's dive back into Blender and take a look at how this works! So
here we made a Material slot, and you can make your Material slot panel
bigger if you like, by dragging like this. And we created a new one, and we called it
Material. Well let's call it Pin. So click into here, where I'm highlighting, and type
Pin and Return. And now, you'll see that we have a material
called Pin. OK, now there's another type of material we're going to
want on the pin, of course, which is going to be for the stripes around the neck. So let's
go ahead and make a second slot. Now,
you get a simplified interface. You need to make a second material.
There it is, again it calls it Material, and we're going to call it Stripe.
So now we have two materials, Pin and Stripe. And if you click
here, to the left of the word Pin or Stripe, you'll see Browse Materials. You can also
see those two materials. This is like a library of materials that you could pick up, and you can
actually apply these to other objects in the scene, if you want later. There's some other more advanced
controls over here, we're not going to worry about for now. What we do need to do is give our stripe a
different color. So if you scroll down a little bit, you'll see under defuse, which is the
color that it scatters off in all directions, it's currently white. Let's make it whatever you like, let's say
red. OK, so we have two different materials, they're both
simple diffuse materials. You can see the preview here, one is just a kind of very
boring gray color and the other is a slightly more interesting red color.
OK fantastic! So what I want you to do
then is to go into Edit Mode, because now that we've setup
our materials for our pin we cannot apply them to individual faces, until
we are inside Edit Mode. So let's go into Edit Mode!
Alright, and then, what I want you to do, once you're in Edit Mode, is I'm going to challenge you
to actually create the two stripes around the neck of the pin. I'm going to choose
a couple of face loops, this one here and maybe one a little bit
further up, but I'm going to leave it to you to actually do this for yourself.
I just want to bring your attention to one more thing, which is now that you've entered
Edit Mode, three new buttons have come up here in the
panel on the right-hand side, under the materials slots. You have Assign, Select,
and Deselect. So Assign assigns the currently selected
material, in the slots above, to the geometry that you have selected
in the Scene View. The Select button selects the entire thing,
so the pin, and Deselect would just deselect the entire object,
i.e. the pin. So if you wanted, for example, to apply the pin material to the whole
object, then you would click Select, which would select the whole pin, click on the word
Pin, and then click Assign. You'll actually find that's already happened, by default, when you create your
first material, it gets assigned to the entire object. So when you're going to make this stripe,
you're going to need to select the face loop geometry,
by doing that in the 3D View. Then, you're going to need
to select the strip and click the Assign button. So those three buttons only come up in Edit Mode.
So select a face loop for one stripe.
Hint, you can select a face loop by holding down the Alt key in Edit mode and
then using Face Select, so you've seen that in a previous video with
Mikey. Assign the Stripe material to that face loop, and then, repeat
again for another face loop to create the second stripe. So basically,
make two stripes on your pin. Go ahead, pause the video, and try that now!
Cool! Welcome back! So let's take a look!
A few things to check, before we go! Firstly, you do need to be in Edit Mode here, because we are dealing at a Face
Level, not just an object level. Second thing is, I want to make sure you are in Blender Render here,
you'll get some very different menus if you're not. OK fantastic! So we
need to select a face loop. So we go into Face Select Mode, down at the bottom of our screen,
and then, we hold down Alt and then
we click on one of the faces
and there you go, we get a face loop selected. Now, with the
correct material selected over here, you click Assign.
Boom, there we go! Now to do it for the other one, it's the same job! You hold down, you
right-click, face loop is selected, click Assign.
Perfect! Look at that, we have stripes on our pin! Now you can preview this in various ways, you can come
out into Object Mode, if you wish, and then, this is where you can use the various different
rendering modes for the Viewport. You could say Wireframe. Now in Wireframe, of course, you're not gonig to see
any of the materials, that's the whole point of Wireframe. You could go to solid
colored. Now this is just a very fast preview mode, for use inside the
Viewport here, for when you have complex models, and you do see your colors there, whcih is cool!
You could go to texture, which is similar, but it's actually using the scene lighting now. It's just
using this Lamp, which is why you only see it lit from one side. Or
you could go to Rendered. Let's just leave it with that, and that would show you what the final
Blender Render output may look like. But for now, we are just considering
solid, which we have been all along. We are staying with default lighting,
and we're just trying to get different faces, different colors. And we've done it, we've got a whole ring of faces
in red, which is pretty cool! So congratulations with
that! Do feel free to customize these things, if you want. You can always click back
onto the Pin. You can go back, say, into the Pin's material
and play with its Diffuse color here and have a vile different color for the
pin, if you wish. You can also do the same for the stripe, and if you want
to get a little bit more adventurous, we're going to explain all this later in the course. But if
you want to play with things like Specularity, and some of these other things, it's not going to do any harm
you're welcome to go and explore! But for now, the important thing is that you know how to put like a white
color or whatever color you like, on the back of the pin, and a different color on those
face loops around there. So well done,
you've got a colored pin! And we'll see you soon!