Hi it's Michael again! Welcome to
Creating Collider Meshes! So in this video I will show you
how to control the number of vertices and we can do that
in a couple of ways. Firstly, we'll be creating a
Convex Hull, so the collision mesh works properly,
and we'll be introducing the Decimate modifier.
So let's hop straight on over into Blender!
So here we are in Blender! And the first thing to
realize is that what we're about to do is destructive.
So we've got a couple of options how to move forward. We can
either create a duplicate of our pin and then work on that
mesh, or we can create a whole new file. So in this
case, I'm going to create a whole new file just to keep things simple, so we don't
have multiple models in our scene. And
also, so when we look at the Info Pane, at the top here, we can
see the number of vertices and we can just read that out and know that we've met
our design requirements. So I'm going to go to File,
Save As, and I'm going to save it as
BowlingPinCollider! An imaginative name, as you can imagine!
So, at the top here, I can confirm that's the case, BowlingPinCollider!
Excellent! So the first thing I'm going to do is make sure this is simple, because when
Ben imports it or when we export it to any other package,
we need to make sure that we don't put in a load of other gumf as well,
So really, some of these things in the Outliner can go.
So we can get rid of the Camera, we don't really care about that, in this case.
The Lamp can also go and the Pin Outline can go.
Secondly, I'm not interested in any materials,
because this is literally a collision mesh, it's not going to be seen by anything, So, in this case,
I'm going to delete those two materials, and I'm going to check in this
here that they've got a 0 against them. Great, so we know
I've just reassigned it, so I'm going to get rid of that again. That means that,
on the save and reopen, those materials will go.
So now we've got our basic pin down. The first thing
we're going to do is actually make the whole of our shape,
our model here, convex. And we can do that in
two ways, and the first way is hopping over into Edit
Mode, selecting all of the model that we will
want to adjust, going to Mesh,
Vertices, and then, up here we have
Convex Hull. Now the other way of getting
to that point is, in the 3D window here, if we press the
spacebar, we... Oh, it looks like that was the last thing I searched for!
But we can type in here an action we want to perform, and
in this case, Convex Hull is in there and we can just press Enter. And it
makes our model convex immediately, so we've got no more
of the pin neck coming in. And we can take a quick
look at the number of vertices to see that it has dropped, and it's dropped
down to 482, so we're not quite at our
256 limit yet. So the next thing that we can do is start
simplifying our geometry. Now we could go in manually and start doing that, but there is
a tool called the Decimate Modifier that will do that for us.
So if we go over to our wrench over here or spanner,
we can Add a Modifier, and we have here,
on the second column, the Generate column, Decimate. Now,
if you click that and we start playing with the
Un-Subdivide, it's a nice one to look at because
it's easy to see and visualize how it breaks up our geometry.
And if we increase the Iterations, nothing happens!
Why does nothing happen? Well two fold, number one, we're not in
Object Mode, so let's hop back over into Object Mode! Oh, and that looks a bit
funny, so let's bring the Iterations back down to 0 again. So we've got our
basic pin shape here, once more. Now we do want to change the Shading
back to Flat and the reason for that is so we can see what's going on.
So we can see here, with iterations, we can increase that and
the model gets simpler and simpler. So what I'd like you
to do now is a little challenge.
I would like you to create our
collider mesh. So remember we've got a hard limit of 256
vertices. Ensure, if you've not done it already, that it is a convex
model, and finally, the base must be flat. There must be something
for it so it stands up. So hop into Blender
now, pause the video, and complete this task!
OK guys, welcome back! Let's hop
over into Blender and do those tasks!
So the first thing is deciding how many
Un-Subdivides we are going to do. So if we
increase our Iterations we can see that, at one point,
it becomes totally unusable. At
5 iterations that's complete garbage, so let's reduce
that and see what happens in the rest of them. So here I
think this looks like this maintains the original width really well. So
a 0 that's fine, we've got the original width. At
1 we've got the original width. At 2 we've still got the original width,
but it starts from 3 and above getting thinner.
Now that's not going to be any good if we've got a bowling ball hitting a
pin. In fact, the bowling ball would end up going inside the pin
and hitting the collider beneath the surface. So looking at this, I think
2 Iterations would be good! And let's see the number of Vertices that lowers to. That
lowers well inside our limit to 122.
And finally, I'm going to click Apply on this modifier,
so it changes our mesh and so this is now
the mesh we're working with. Excellent! So the next stage
is actually making this bottom flat. There's a couple of ways of
doing that, and I'm going to go in, I'm simply going to View it from the
Bottom. So View, Bottom, and I'm going to hop into
Edit Mode, so I can do some work. And let's zoom in! So we
have the bottom of our pin here, and it's really just this area here that
we need to be flat and we can double check that. So I'm going to go into
Edge Mode and select this edge loop inside
here. So remember, that's Alt and right-click to select
an edge loop. Then, I'm going to flip back over into Front
View and make sure that is the right edge to select.
Well let's go back into Front View and go down. So
here we have... Oh we can see there that it's certainly not flat, and I
think I can still do it? I deselected the edge loop there going around.
Excellent! So the final thing we can do there is,
if we open up our Properties Panel of the 3D Editor,
we can set the Z coordinates
to that entire edge loop to 0. So we're going to go in there,
making sure it's globally 0. And there we go,
that's totally flat. So that's going to make sure that's not going to rock or fall
over for Ben. So let's save this file now! I'm going to send it over
to Ben and make sure that it works as he expects it to.
Thank you, Mikey! So I've imported your much more compact mesh
here and added it to my pin. There you can see the
Convex lower poly mesh there, and I've given it a bouncy material.
Let's see what happens! Boing! Ha ha, much better!
Awesome! Now that's a game dev and an artist working well together! See you soon!