Welcome to Extruding to a Normal!
In this video we are basically going to change the
axis for extrusion, for finer control.
So let's hop over into Blender and play with that now!
So the first thing that we can do here is, we can correct my
obviously deliberate mistake of this extrusion into
our model. Now fortunately, it looks like it
has gone down and through the center of our model.
So how do we make sure that we can pull it back out
and line it up here? Well there are a couple of ways to that, but one of the easiest
ways is, once we have these
six faces selected, they combine all as
one to generate a normal, a common normal, which is
actually the same as the vertex normal in the middle here. It'll be pointing
upwards, so towards us. Now down
here with the 3D Manipulator Widget, that we've played with in the past,
you can change that from where it says Global
to a couple of other things, one of which is Normal.
Now, if we change that to Normal, and I'm
surprised we can't see the blue one anymore because it's pointing right at us.
So the normal coming out of this vertex,
in the middle, is facing right towards us. So if we rotate around
we can see, there it is. And what we can do at this point is,
we can literally pull that back up and that will be perfectly
in line. So we can move it up or down, as much as
we want. Now, bowling balls have holes going inwards, so going out is no good,
but what we can do, [Laughs] at this point, is go ahead
and select the Snapping Tool, select
the... I don't really care which one we do it to, we can just
align it with a Face, and this time, when we move it backwards
and forwards, we can hover over a particular face we want to align it
with. And I don't think face is actually going to be the right one in this
case. I'm pretty sure that is now aligned, but I can't be 100%
sure, unless it's really to a
Vertex. Let's do Vertex instead! So again, let's
move it up and down, and snapping, that is definitely
the right place now. Now because we've moved it all the way down and brought it back
again, that would have produced a series of doubles. So before we do
anything else, I'm going to now push it into our model
to a certain level
and that is 1 Blender unit.
So let's push that in now, by 1 Blender unit, so
that is -1 in the Z axis. And I'm going to turn Snapping
off. There we go! So if I type
-1, have I lost the opportunity to do that? Yes I have!
So let's grab that and move it in the Z axis.
And remember, that will now be moving in the Z axis, that
is normal because that's what we've set.
In fact, at this point, I'm just going to undo to here.
So we're going to move that, not extrude in this case. The other
ones we will extrude, but this has already been extruded and it's just on top of one another
and in the Z axis by -1. And that should go inside
our model and it hasn't!
You see it's moved in the wrong Z axis. So along
here, have we got the orientation? So in the Operator Panel,
is Orientation that's currently set to Global. So
because we used to shortcut keys it's assumed something different
to what's down here. So if we change orientation back
to Normal it will go in and, in this case, exactly what
we want, in towards the center of our
sphere. OK, so there we go,
that's how you do that! Let's give you a challenge to do the other
two!
That
doesn't look quite the right depth, so I'm just going to
increase that a little to 1.5, and because I haven't gone
off of this yet, I can set that Z Constraint there to
-1.5. I think that will be better!
So let's go and do a challenge!
It's challenge time! I'd like you to create the remaining finger holes.
So use the circles that we have created,
extrude them along the Normal Z Axis,
and then, set them to a depth
of 1.5 Blender units. Pause the
video now and give that a go!
OK guys, welcome back! Let's hop over into Blender
and complete our bowling ball!
OK, so we've successfully done that bowling
ball there. Let's go up to the top here, and
I can see straight away we've got one thing to do to our circles.
We need to inset them a little, before we actually
do anything else, so let's go ahead and do that
straight away. We can grab them both, so they're inset by
the same amount, and inset them, it doesn't have to be much.
And there we go! So now we're ready to do this! I know the extrusion
itself will not work, if we try and do them both at
once, because it will take a normal that's between these
two points, instead of the points themselves. So we're going to have to
select the faces themselves. It's
selected on Normal,
and I can just extrude, make
sure we are extruding and start to push it in. Now I can see that,
in the lower-left, it says it's
moving on the Normal. We can see that
straight away, it's done that by default which is great! And we can
set that, immediately, to -1.5.
And there we go, that's inside our pin!
So let's select these ones here, as well,
and it was set to Normal here, so if we press E this is also
going to extrude along a normal. This is brilliant! And let's set that to
-1.5. Now there is a chance that
these two will cross one another. So there we go! So a design
problem with our specs, straight away, is that the holes
themselves, these two, as they move in are going
to hit one another. But it doesn't look like the overlap is
that much, so, in this case, I'm going to simply
pull one of these back out, until they're not touching anymore.
So I'm going to grab that bottom, I'm going to move it in the Z axis,
but not the global Z axis, I don't want that.
I want to move it on this axis here, so I'm
just going to grab that instead and just pull it up ever so slightly. I can't see
what I'm doing.
We don't want geometry crossing, that's bad
bad bad. And there we go! So a
consideration there if someone gives you a spec that has a
fault in it. Do mention it to the person as quickly as
possible. I've already mentioned it to myself.
Let's do the final thing now and hop into
Object Mode and look around our model, and that
looks absolutely fine! In fact, that doesn't look too far
apart now, that's looks absolutely fine!
Right, so the final thing that we will do on
this bowling ball is give it some color, it's looking a bit bland at the moment!
So let's go into our material properties
and add a new material slot, create a new material,
and I'm going to call it, very imaginatively, BowlingBall.
Now, I'm going to scroll down here on Diffuse,
I'm going to change that. What color should I have it? Why not
a yellow, a bright yellow color. Great! So there we go, we've got
our bowling ball all colored in. I'm going to make sure I remember to
Save that as well, very important. And that's ready to
use wherever you want to use it! Now, some of you may be thinking, well
I've seen bowling balls and they're sparkly or they've got textures on them or
words, etc. Don't worry about that, for the moment, in the next couple of sections,
we'll be going into much more detail with our models.
But do remember, the skills that you've learned so far, you can now go back
and practice, you know, color in the models that you've already made and saved in
your project folders. So that's great, and I will see you guys again
soon! Take care!
<<<<<<< HEAD:Blender/Section 3/BP17 Extruding to a Normal.srt
=======
>>>>>>> 61fb7349cf669f249b4a9560c07cf0816c59420a:Blender/Section 3/BP17 Extruding to a Normal.srt