Welcome to the Final Scene! So
it's challenge time, straight away! You need to make 10
pins, correctly spaced. Now, if you're unsure about the spacing,
that they need to be, use reference material for the correct spacing,
and remember, you may be working at a scale. We're
working, in general, at 10 times at the moment, so 30 centimeters would
be 3 Blender units. You're going to have to create
9 additional pins in our scene.
So you can do that in a number of ways, I'll let you choose how you go about that.
There's a couple of ways I can think of, you can just duplicate and move,
you could use the Array Modifier. It's up to you, go ahead and try that!
Name your object in the Outliner, and you can use the reference material for
the numbering of the pins, for instance. And go crazy, make it exciting,
so manipulate those pins, make them look like they've been smashed in to by the ball! And
I want to see your final composition! Please
share in the discussion, it would be great! So pause the video now and go and
give that a go! So here we
are, back in Blender! Let's go ahead and multiply
our pin! Alright, so the first thing we need to consider
is, how many of these do we want? We want 9 of them, and there are several
ways we could go, we could literally just duplicate 9 of them and manually position
them, or we could use an Array Modifier and go
through that way. I'm going to use a combination of them both. So I'm going to
create four of them first, by going to the Array Modifier.
So with our pin selected I'm going to go to our wrench,
I'm going to go to Add Modifier, and go to Array,
and I want four of them, so I'm going to put the Count at 4.
Now, before we used Relative Offset, I'm going to use Constant Offset
this time, so it's not spacing off pins, it's actually a
distance between. And I think they're about 12 inches, which is about
30 centimeters. I'm not going to do the exact number to keep
things easy for our calculations here. So that would transpire
up, because we're working at 10 times scale to 3 Blender units.
So there we go, with a constant Offset of X equaling
3, we get our four pins ready. And I'm going to apply that
straight away. So now that that is
applied, the next thing we need to do is create our additional pins. So I'm simply going
to duplicate this new mesh that we've made. So there we go, I'm
going to lock it to the X Y axis, by holding down Shift and
Z, so now it's not going to fall through the floor or end up in the air. Now we need to do
some positioning here, and I know we're going to be moving this one forward
by 3 Blender units and then moving it across by
half of that, so 1.5, so we're moving along here. And
we look down at our little axis, that is positive Y to go that way
and then positive X. So
I'm just going to go and move that,
I could do it in the Operator Panel, that'll be far easier,
because then I don't need to worry about where it is. So X needs to be 1.5.
There we go! And Y needs to be 3.
Excellent, so that's in the right position! Yes we've got an odd one over here but we're just
going to delete that in a few moments. And I'm going to do exactly the same
process again, I'm going to duplicate it. Job done!
Oh, I've positioned it in a very weird place, but that's OK, because in this Operator
Panel we've got X, Y, and Z there. So I can set the Z back to 0!
The Y again, so it's forward by 3, so I've almost got that
right there, but the X needs to be 1.5 again.
And then, I'm not going to produce another four
or another three additional ones here, I'm just going to go into our
objects here, and I'm
going to separate them out. So I do need to be in Edit Mode to do that, so select one of
these first of all, select this first group, and we're going to separate
all of these. So let's hop over into Edit Mode and
then P to Separate, and then,
we need to choose not by selection, like we've done before, but By
Loose Parts. So all of these bits of geometry are not
connected to one another. So first thing, before I do that, I do need to highlight
the entire mesh, there we go, otherwise we'll be separating that little
window that was selected at the front. So P,
Separate, By Loose Parts. And you can see it's generated
a few more meshes and we'll go ahead and name those, in a moment.
And let's go on to this section here, hop
into Edit Mode! Select all of our model,
Separate, By Loose Parts. And we'll do it once more on this
top one, so we're going to simply go into Edit Mode,
select everything, press B,
Separate, By Loose Parts. So again, we're here
and I'm going to use one of these, so let's leave them.
I'm going to use that one there and actually move it to the forefront here for
us. So I'm going to use that, I'm going to move it in
the X by
-4.5 I think, Yeah brilliant, that's in the middle! Then, I'll just need to move it
again, in the Y by 3. So there we go,
we've got that sorted! There are our pines laid out! I'm going to
select these two and delete them.
Brilliant! So we should have a count
of 10 pins. 1, 2, 3, 4, 5,
6, 7, 8, 9, 10. Brilliant! Now the reason why
you can't just count the ones on the screen is, because if there was a pin on top of a pin
you wouldn't necessarily see it, but that's not the case in here.
The Outliner shows 10 pins, but they're not named correctly. So let's go get
the naming convention and see how we're supposed to name them!
Wow, so we didn't have to go far here to see our
layout and what the numbers are. So that's great, now we've got that for reference, We can
hop straight back over into Blender and name our pins!
Alright, so let's whiz around here, I feel like this is the way they
should be labeled. So this one's going to be Pin 01 and it's blatantly
not, at the moment. And because we're going up to 10, I'm going to leave the dot
in there and call it Pin 01. There's 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8,
9, 10. So a very arduous thing, I may
need to speed up the video, if I can't bore you all with waffle.
So I'm just going through here,
really quickly, renaming all of our pins to the appropriate
names, making sure that I'm referencing them correctly.
OK, so with all of our pins
labeled now, we can start being crazy with it! So let's
move this bowling ball into a much more dynamic position. Let's
move this over here, let's move it right
into the middle of our pins, and now, let's move these pins
with a bit of artistic license.
So I'm just going to grab a pin,
rotate it around slightly, lift it up, have some fun with it.
This one, of course, because the ball's come in, will
be somewhere over here, so shift it over there, rotate it around.
Brilliant! And we can just play with this to our heart's
content, until we've got something looking relatively
dynamic and exciting. In fact, I think that's getting...
Well these two look too similar, I think. Well I suppose they would be, if they were falling
in the same direction, but let's just rotate this one around a bit more
there and move it there so it's a bit more
dynamic. That's great! This one here... In fact, let's
go a bit crazy! Let's just lift that one right up out of here, so it's going
absolutely flying. Well that's starting to look really good! And let's put this one
having a slight wobble. You see it's going into the floor there, we do need to watch
that. So we can select it and just pull it back up again!
Of course, because these things are moving, they can be slightly off of the ground, that's absolutely fine!
And this one's obviously been impacted by the ball, because the ball's
inside it. So we can move that one over here, and just, again, play with it,
be more dynamic! The ball hasn't reached here yet,
so that's absolutely fine! And then,
we can look at it from various angles, and there we go, I think that's a pretty dynamic
scene! How did you guys get on? Please share in the discussions,
and I'll see you again soon!