Hey guys, contratulations
on getting to the end of section 3! You've learned more about manipulating
meshes, you even learned how to create multiple layers of detail and had your very first
go with materials! What next for them, Mikey?! Well I'd like you
to go ahead and make your pin unique and remember to share it
with us in the discussions. And go back now, you've got a pyramid and
several other models we've gone through, have some fun with those and use the
skills you've already learned and apply those to the models.
Absolutely! So well done on getting this far! Why not dive straight into the
start of the next section, right now, and just to break that resistance to starting and
get the momentum. See you soon!
See you there!
<<<<<<< HEAD:Blender/Section 3/BP99 Section Wrap Up.srt
=======
>>>>>>> 61fb7349cf669f249b4a9560c07cf0816c59420a:Blender/Section 3/BP99 Section Wrap Up.srt