So hi. and welcome to your first real game.
We're going to be jumping into creating a
ten-pin bowling game all in 3D to get you
introduced to all the 3D concepts that you're
going to be needing to build more complex
games. So it's quite cool. it's a pretty simple
game that you'll have fun playing and have
fun making and it's got some scope to create
your own stuff. So what can they create in
that game that's their own really?
Well you could customise the lane itself.
you could put an image down across the lane;
you can make your own pins. even if you just
want to use primitives at this stage which
is fine. maybe just a sphere on top of a cube
or a cuboid. that's absolutely fine. If you
want to be more sophisticated and you know
something about blender. or another program
for creating 3D art meshes and 3D art then
go ahead and do that. and just share and just
have fun with this. We've chosen this game
because you can get a surprisingly rich emergent
behaviour using Unity's physics engine for
relatively little input and we think that
it's a good starting point 3D entry into your
programming. So enjoy this section. anything
else they're going to learn in here Brice
we should know about?
No. I have a request for you guys though.
if you are going to be modelling your own
things I want you to model some garden gnomes.
I want to be ten pin bowling with some garden
gnomes. So have fun with that if you want
to take up the challenge.
Please. I'd like to knock over some gnomes.
See you soon.
=======
So hi, and welcome to your first real game.
We're going to be jumping into creating a
ten-pin bowling game all in 3D to get you
introduced to all the 3D concepts that you're
going to be needing to build more complex
games. So it's quite cool, it's a pretty simple
game that you'll have fun playing and have
fun making and it's got some scope to create
your own stuff. So what can they create in
that game that's their own really?
Well you could customise the lane itself,
you could put an image down across the lane;
you can make your own pins, even if you just
want to use primitives at this stage which
is fine, maybe just a sphere on top of a cube
or a cuboid, that's absolutely fine. If you
want to be more sophisticated and you know
something about blender, or another program
for creating 3D art meshes and 3D art then
go ahead and do that, and just share and just
have fun with this. We've chosen this game
because you can get a surprisingly rich emergent
behaviour using Unity's physics engine for
relatively little input and we think that
it's a good starting point 3D entry into your
programming. So enjoy this section, anything
else they're going to learn in here Brice
we should know about?
No, I have a request for you guys though,
if you are going to be modelling your own
things I want you to model some garden gnomes,
I want to be ten pin bowling with some garden
gnomes. So have fun with that if you want
to take up the challenge.
Please, I'd like to knock over some gnomes.
See you soon.
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1:Unity/Section8/BM01 Into To 10 Pin Bowling.srt
Bye.