So welcome back. it is time to install Unity
5. We're going to talk about how to keep Unity
4.6.3 on your machine as well as Unity 5.
we'll be installing the latest version of
Unity 5 and then taking a quick tour of what
is different. So the first thing to understand
is that on your machine right now you'll probably
find if you go to your applications that you
have a single folder called Unity. and what
we want to end up with is two folders - one
called Unity 4.6 and one called Unity 5 to
be explicit.
So the first thing you need to do is find
your Unity folder and just rename it from
Unity to Unity 4.6 so just go ahead and do
that now. rename your Unity folder in your
applications to Unity 4.6. OK by the way.
in the future Unity may change the way that
Unity 5 installs so that you can choose whether
you overwrite or upgrade but this is a surefire
way of making sure that you keep Unity 4.6
if you want to - you don't have to because
we can upgrade all of the previous projects
to Unity 5 but if you want to keep 4.6 this
is how you do it.
OK so the next thing is to install the latest
version of Unity 5. how do we do that? Well.
go Unity3D.com. click on Get Unity and it
will bring you to a page that looks like this.
or similar to a page like this it may change.
and you are looking for a personal edition
of Unity 5. go for the free download and you'll
notice that when you click download what it
will install is not actually Unity 5. it's
a download assistant for Unity 5. so it's
a new way of deploying Unity 5 so when you
open that download assistant and run it you'll
get the standard warnings on your platform.
and then you'll get to the point where it
starts to ask you about licence agreements
which of course you'll read every word of
and then carefully agree.
Comme ça. and then here you go. It's going
to ask you about components. do you need all
these things? Just leave it like that if I
were you. Unity 5. the web player and the
standard assets. they're all useful. I would
argue that the example project is not particularly
useful. but if you do want to look around
it and you've got plenty of time and broadband
capacity then go ahead. Then you get to chose
your destination etc. Now I'm not going to
go through the installation here because that's
boring and at this stage in the course I'm
pretty sure that you can install a software
package.
So I'm going to back out of this installation
altogether and just show you what a finished
Unity 5 looks like so here we go. When you
open Unity 5 you'll have a new screen looking
something like this although of course this
has got some projects in it. This is very
very different from how Unity 4's opening
screen looks. so at this point you want to
create yourself a new project and I would
be calling it BowlMaster because that's the
title of this section. Alright? I'm going
to store this somewhere temporary because
I already have that repository set up.
But choose a folder where you already know
where it is and if you're using version control
like Github or anything like that then put
it in there. OK cool so you wait a moment
and up springs Unity 5 now it immediately
seems different. it mainly seems different
to be honest because by default this little
button here has the Skybox and fog and flares
turned on. If you notice when I turn those
off we're back to something that looks pretty
much identical to Unity 4.6.3. in fact the
only two ways that I think that you can easily
tell that you're in here is number one you
could go to Unity and about Unity and it would
tell you that you are using version 5. and
number two. you can see in brackets it tells
you a licence edition in Unity five here.
it says personal.
There are several other little tell-tale signs
such as if you click game you'll see that
you have a mute audio option. so there are
a few differences. Now for more differences
you can click on our blog post. let me show
you the slide. At the bottom here you can
go to completeunitydeveloper.com you can just
search our blog for differences or click in
this very .pdf and you will see this blog
post here which will show you all of the differences.
all of at least the superficial differences
between the two versions in some detail.
So that's it. your challenge now is simply
to get Unity 5 installed and working. ensure
that you can open it. take a look around and
then create yourself a new project called
BowlMaster and that will be the end of the
video because I have already shown you basically
how to do all of that. So good luck with that.
and see you soon.