Hey guys. Ben and Michael back! You may remember
Michael from earlier in the course. my 3D artist friend.
So it's a this stage that. we really need some 3D assets. and this time
we need a bowling ball and a bowling pin. Of course. I've provided them for you.
but guess who made them? Hi! It was me!
Mikey made them! So. over in the Complete Blender Creator. we
take you through actually making exactly that bowling ball
and pin and showing you how to customize it to your own needs and import it
into Unity. Yes. So. what are the basics. Mikey. of making something
like let's say the bowling pin? How do we get that shape over in Blender? Well. we
use a system called Bezier Curves. and then. it makes
a nice smooth finish. around our pin itself.
so we make our pin from that. But with
Unity you cannot just use this really high polygon
model. lovely pin. to collide
with. because that ball is going to be rolling forward and hitting that
pin. And so. we're also going to teach you how to make a Collider Mesh. to go
along with your wonderful 3D assets. as well.
So. to clarify on that. specifically. Unity has a 255
polygon limit on Collider Meshes.
So. we want a mesh that very much replicates the shape of the pin.
but you're going to see that we can't just us the Full Render Mesh. because it's
just to high polygon. So. Michael actually. over in the course
and in supplied assets. is going to create two meshes. A
Visual Mesh and a Physics Mesh and put them into the same model.
So. here is a second opportunity. and it's the only other
time I'm going to mention it in this course. apart from the very end. for you to go over
into the Complete Blender Creator and get yourself learning
Blender. in parallel with this course so you can actually create assets
as you go. So. the URL is udemy.com/
blendertutorial. The coupon code you need is.
Unity Student Special. and that will give you the cheapest price that we're going to offer
on this. And I hope you decide to take that course as well. It's every
bit as good as this Unity course! Take care guys!
Hope to see you there!