Hi. welcome back. In this video we are going
to show you how to install Blender. So Blender
is a 3D art program. it lets you manipulate
meshes. textures. animations and much more.
Why do we need it? We need it to import .blend
files we're going to be providing you with
the pin for example. the bowling pin as a
.blend file. It's amazingly powerful but tricky
to get started with. you only need to install
it for this course. not use it. If you want
to know more go to www.CompleteBlenderCreator.Com
to learn more.
So that's the summary basically it's a pretty
simple job this video. we just want you to
go to Blender.org. pick the right version
for your machine. install it then close the
program. before you get scared of its interface.
then test that it's working in the next video
by importing the pin as we show you how to
do. So good luck with that. now go ahead and
install Blender on your machine now. pause
the video. Fantastic. welcome back. how did
you get on with that? So I'm going to install
Blender in front of you just to help out in
case you have any issues.
So right now the Blender homepage looks like
this but this background image will change
a lot and the structure of their page will
change so when you watch this video it may
look different from this. So. 2.74 is the
version at this time. it doesn't really matter
which version you use I'm pretty confident
that whichever version you use. as long as
it's 2.7 or later you'll be fine. So. you
click on download and then obviously you go
and find the version which is relevant to
your platform. In my case that's Mac OS and
it's a bit funny but right now you just click
on this download here. or you go and specifically
find yourself a mirror in the USA. Germany
or the Netherlands.
I'm just going to click the cloud. because
I'm scared of choosing a mirror. Now do consider
donating to Blender. it's completely free
and open source software and they can't keep
it at this amazing quality without some donations.
so we are strongly considering donating 5%
of our current Blender Kickstarter to this
foundation but in the meanwhile please consider
donating if you like Blender; but for now
the purpose is just to install it. that's
all we're trying to do here is get it installed.
So once the Blender zip file has finished
downloading then go ahead and install it as
you do on your platform on a Mac you just
drag it into applications.
In the case of a PC you may need to just go
through a standard install process. Open Blender.
is the main thing we need you to do here.
there it is. it's going to give you a splash
screen. something like that. and the interface
will look pretty much identical on Mac and
PC. Now you don't need to go any further than
this. we actually don't need you to know how
to use Blender at all. you can quite safely
close Blender right now and carry on to the
next video without any fear or problems whatever
because now that it's installed you'll find
that over in Unity you will be able to actually
open from our start pack the Blender imports
like the bowling pin. In fact if you were
to go to Unity and double click your bowling
pin you should find it pops up in Blender
like this. which is cool. so you actually
have everything that you need right now.
If you just want to know a tiny bit more about
Blender I'm not going to go into much detail
at all. that's what the complete Blender creator
is for but if you want a tiny bit more detail
then stay on this video right now and I'll
show you the most important thing that I know
about Blender which is roughly how this crazy
interface works. So here we go. what is it
about Blender's interface that is so hard
to get hold of? You have file up here and
then view down here and then view again here.
what the hell is going on?
Let me just show you the overall structure.
You have multiple editor types indicated so
then here we have our self one editor type.
it's a 3D editor type. Down here is another
one. which is a... so this is a 3D view. you
can see from the icon. this one here is an
information editor type. this one here is
a timeline. So they're all kind of overlaid
on top of each other and to add insult to
injury if you go to a division between sections
and you try and drag. if you drag in the wrong
place you end up duplicating your interface.
Now that's really confusing. but what you've
actually got here is you've just got another
3D editor. you could change that to a graph
editor. so it's completely customisable which
is the great thing about it.
Now to control where your editors are what
you need to know about is that you have to
grab this little grippy thing. and provided
you have the same number of editors in the
space that you're trying to drag into you
can over-write what's there. So this guy here
will be able to over-write the one above.
this guy here will be able to over-write the
one below in theory. if I grab and drag right.
there you go and the same here. I just need
to grab right. there you go. so we're over-writing
the other pane. and then this main pane will
be able to over-write the pane on the right.
you see and even the top pane will be able
to over-write the one below.
So if you understand that logic. and that
you'll always be able to change the editor
type here. it's actually completely configurable
- we're just looking at the pin from inside
right now. So remember that you change the
editor type here and that you need these little
draggy things here and if you're really stuck
and you need to bring up another menu or header
bar click the little plus icons that you'll
see. OK that's a brief overview of Blender.
that's all that I need to show you for now.
the rest of this course of course focuses
on Unity 3D and as I say. if you're curious
go to www.CompleteBlenderCreator.com where
we're going to work the same magic for Blender
as we do for Unity. See you soon.