Hi, welcome back and I'm really looking forward
to getting into this bowling game with you
guys. So we're going to get used to 3D controls,
create a bowling lane floor according to the
Game Design Document, and set your main camera
to look down the lane. So firstly go find
your game design document, it's actually at
the start of your section notes; it's also
in a separate .pdf at the beginning of the
section, and in there you'll find the bowling
lane specification. We're going to use centimetres
as our unit of choice here because it just
fits really well with this game, it's a centimetre
scale game.
Metres are simply too big, and millimetres
are simply too small. So if we check the specs
from the Wikipedia article linked at the bottom
we'll find that it's 18.29 metres or 1829
centimetres from the foul line, i.e. the line
that you're not allowed to cross when bowling
to the front pin, the head pin. So we're going
to make it 2 metres, which is 2000 centimetres
long, a hundred and five centimetres wide,
I'm actually going to make it a cuboid and
give it some height, so we're representing
a physical floor that of course must have
some depth, that's going to help with collisions,
things like that.
OK so let's dive over into Unity 5 and take
a look at this game. So here you've got a
brand new Unity project, all I've done is
created myself a scene here called game, OK
so I've simply gone save scene /game I think
that you get the idea by this stage in the
course. So create yourself a game object - game
object / 3D object / Cube. Go ahead and do
that now, let's put a simple cube in the scene
and if you want to focus on it double click
on it in the hierarchy.
Now talking about the hierarchy you'll notice
that there's one other difference in Unity
5 and that's that you'll always get a directional
light right off the cuff, that just comes
in there that's fine, and your main camera
gizmo here's rather large, if you find that
annoying like I do click on gizmos in the
scene view and then drag down on the top on
your 3D gizmos slider to make your camera
gizmo much smaller. You can also click here
at the top of scene view if you can see where
my mouse is and that will give you the option
to turn off that skybox in the background.
I think that I'm going to leave it on just
so that we make it very clear at a glance
that we're in Unity 5 but that's called a
Skybox and we'll be dealing with that later
when we change it to a nice starfield and
make it a nice space bowling game. So there
we have a cube. Now you need to know how we
navigate around in the 3D world. So how do
you do that? Well, I suggest using a 3 button
mouse if you possibly can; if you haven't
got a 3 button mouse then just click here
with a Q key or at the top left on the little
hand icon and you can also use a tracking
pad. 2 fingers forward and back or zoom on
the trackpad does the same as a mouse wheel,
goes in and out. The left mouse button translates
like this left and right, up and down, as
does dragging on your track pad with three
fingers with a Mac or with a single finger
click down if you really want to give yourself
RSI.
You've also got the option to right-click
with a mouse which will tilt your view, or
on a trackpad that is two fingers held pushed
down. So have a little practice of just saying
to yourself for instance I want to see the
underside of the cube, how am I going to get
it? Well I'll zoom in a little bit, I can
use the middle mouse button to translate and
the right mouse button to rotate so there's
the underside. Or you might say you want to
see the top so you'd just come up to the top
and there's the top surface lit brightly by
this directional light.
Now we'll cover more detail about what a directional
light does later, but just so you don't get
confused right now I want to explain that
a directional light doesn't matter where it
is in the scene, if we go to translate mode
and we start moving this light around it will
have no effect whatsoever. It doesn't matter
how far away from things, it doesn't matter
where it is in the scene, it only matters
what direction it's pointing in. So one of
the other tools that we can use is a rotate
tool at the top left here.
That's "e" on your keyboard; and you'll notice
that if I grab the rotate tool and start moving
this directional light around, watch what
happens to the cube illumination in the background
there I'll zoom in a little bit for you, you
see it is being illuminated differently depending
purely on the direction of this light you
see it's a light being cast across the whole
see depending on the direction in which it
is pointing and it has parallel light rays,
as you can see. It's a bit of a weird light,
there's not really any real light like this,
but it's a very simple light to get you off
the ground.
Great so have a play, get used to a work flow
that works for you, a combination of mouse
buttons, and possibly modifier keys down the
bottom left of your keyboard, ctrl, function
shift etc. Have a play, keep your eye up at
the top left see what effect your keys are
having on your view mode and just make sure
that you know how to move around the scene;
that you know how to use this tool here which
is the translation tool to move things independently
in x, y and z by grabbing the appropriate
arrows, and also free-form by grabbing the
box in the middle; and then also you have
a rotation tool again, you can free-form rotate
by clicking on the object or rotate around
a particular axis by grabbing its' coloured
ring; and then you have a scaling tool which
works in a very similar way. You can scale
the whole object by dragging the box in the
middle, or you can scale in a particular axis.
OK? I'm now going to reset the transform of
the cube and refocus on it by double clicking,
There it is, it's a one by one by one unit
cube now we're calling units centimetres so
it's like the size of a sugar cube right now.
Always keep it real, always think what this
means what this would be like in real life,
try and relate it. OK now we're not going
to try to adjust this thing's size by dragging
because that's a little bit crazy, what we're
going to do is use the inspector; but I want
you to do this bit so let's go back to the
slides and look at your challenge.
So what we have for you is I want you to create
a lane floor. Refer back to the GDD for the
dimensions, use x for the width, the 105;
y for the height, the 1 cm and z for the length,
that twenty metres. Apply a texture as a bonus,
if you can work out how to apply a texture
to it there's a texture in the course assets,
there's a bowling floor wooden texture, or
get creative, go and make your own texture,
go draw something and make sure that it looks
right from above when you look at the lane,
that's a bonus for you if you know how to
do it and a hint it use a cube don't try to
use a mesh or a quad; sorry a plane or a quad
so go ahead pause the video and get your bowling
lane laid out in that orientation right now.
OK welcome back, so let's do it, let's make
this bowling lane right. So we're going to
change the scale, the x scale so I need to
refer back to my GDD for the dimensions that
I need, so where are they? Here they are,
bowling lane specification, 1829 so 20 metres
by 105 by 1. OK so it's 105 in the x, fine,
1 cm high that's fine a sort of wooden width
by 20 metres, or two thousand, so it's gone
crazy it's gone absolutely crazy inside the
scene view, it's gone crazy inside the scene
view because we're so close to it. So you
double click it and it will frame the whole
object.
So there we are, we have a bowling lane. It's
a bit white right now and that's because of
the material on it so the next thing that
we need to show you how to do is how to apply
a sensible material to this guy. So if you
look over in the inspector when selected on
cube you will see a materials arrow and you'll
see it has a single element - a single material,
we're only going to be dealing with single
material at the moment, but it's a default
material, and that's not a lot of use to us,
we actually need to create a new material.
So if you go to your assets menu, create and
material and you can just call it floor there
it is. So we now have a floor material which
we can apply to the cube, and you can do that
by just dragging it to the cube if you want
and if you check over in the cube then you
can see that it has actually put it in to
the element 0 of the floor materials. You
can have multiple materials but we're not
going to bother right now, we're going to
have a single material. So let's take a look
at this material we've just created, click
on your floor material in your assets and
over in the inspector we can start to take
a look at what it's all about.
So in Unity 5 we have a standard shader which
is the one that I'm going to suggest that
we use for now and it's actually very powerful
and very configurable. Now of course a bowling
floor would be slightly shiny and reflective
but I'm going to leave out the issue of making
this reflective at least until the end of
this section, possibly until much later in
the course because it's a little bit more
detailed and I want to focus on just getting
you used to the 3D environment for now. If
you want to as a side project try and make
the floor reflective then that's entirely
up to you. so firstly it's the albedo is what
we're going to focus on today with this so
if you click under main maps and then albedo,
you can see that you can give a colour cast
to the entire floor, this is called its' diffuse
colour, its default colour so you can just
drag around in your colour picker and make
your floor a flat colour of whatever you like.
So that is fine if you just want it to be
a flat colour but how about if we want a texture
on there? If we want to put an image? So this
is where you have your first opportunity for
creativity is to go and find your own image
on google images or create your own and you're
going to need to tile that image down the
floor or have a very long and thin image.
So to help you off the ground we've given
you an asset package at the beginning of this
section if you go to import package / custom
package we have our bowlmaster assets. Why
not just import them all.
Now this time for the first time in the course
all these assets are going to import into
a subfolder called start pack. That makes
it easier for us to export and somewhat easier
for you to choose. So, our floor, looking
at our floor material again if you click the
little circle next to albedo there, then it
will bring up a list of textures one of which
now should be the lane texture so choose the
lane. A couple of things happen here firstly
it renders a very strangely stretched, very
ugly piece of wood onto the floor, why does
it look like that? Well, if we look at the
image we gave it it's just this lane image
here, and that has been applied once sideways
and once in the z direction so it's very,
very very stretched, OK that's currently the
problem.
So the other thing you should notice is that
if you look at the material is that it gives
you a slight preview of the material right
here in the inspector. It's giving you an
idea wrapped on a sphere what that material
may look like. A material is simply something
that tells you how things are going to look.
So the first thing that we need to is to tile
this material appropriately, so here under
cube, and then inspector if you can't see
the details of the floor material by the way
it's a bit strange but you expand out with
this little triangle or by clicking the grey
bit where I'm clicking now and that will toggle
whether you're seeing details of the floor
shader.
So you have this piece of wood in you can
still adjust the albedo which just multiplies
basically each of the red, green and blue
components by your colour, so you can offset
the colour if you want to. We're going to
leave it as it is for now. The main problem
that we have is this tiling so looking at
our floor image, how many times do we want
this to tile left and right? Well, one of
the easiest ways is to click on the x and
just drag it until it looks about right. Well
now you can't tell because it's tiling far
too infrequently in y so drag your y until
it starts to look about right; and you can
just iterate here getting closer to the floor
until you get a parquet floor effect - or
whatever texture you guys want to use - that
looks something like what you're satisfied
with.
So maybe I tile this guy maybe 50 times in
one direction, and, well, how many in the
other well we ought to use the same aspect
ratio potentially so 50 by 2, 50 by 1, whatever
looks right at the end of the day you know,
does that look right? Looks OK, looks a bit
weird, 50 by 12 obviously too much in the
x direction. So look, it's up to you guys
to make this floor look beautiful, I'm just
trying to show you; give you the tools of
how to do it. I have a floor that has a tiling
- now it's not the tiling on the floor material;
it's the tiling on the cube.
The tiling on the cube is 2 by 50 which means
that we're taking that image, that floor image;
we're repeating it twice in the x direction
and 50 times in the y direction as we go down
the lane. Alright? So that gives us a somewhat
convincing floor. Later, at some point in
the course we'll talk about how to make it
reflective. Fantastic, so the final thing
I said that we were going to do here is to
make the main camera face down the lane. We've
been moving around in the scene view, but
if we click over to game, well, it happens
to be facing down the lane, but let's imagine
that we want to put it somewhere different,
how do we do that?
Well one easy way to do that is to go to where
you want the camera to be in the scene view
like say here, get it how you want it, select
the main camera and then you've got a very
useful game object / align with view, so the
game object in question is the camera and
we're aligning it with our current scene view
by doing that we now move the camera so when
you click play and switch over to the game
view we get exactly what we wanted. That's
everything we need to do in this lecture,
congratulations on getting your first 3D object
created and I'll see you soon.