Hi and welcome back. So in this video were
going to be importing a bowling pin from Blender.
learn about render and collider meshes. create
a pin prefab. and lay out all of our ten bowling
pins on the floor according to the GDD. So
you can find out more about Blender at www.CompleteBlenderCreator.com.
I've teamed up with an old friend and 3D artist
Michael Bridges to bring a huge course similar
to this one to you called the Complete Blender
Creator because it's such an important skill
now that we're moving into 3D to be able to
manipulate meshes. so go out and take a look
at www.CompleteBlenderCreator.com.
So. that's the challenge that we're going
to be doing a little later but for now let's
just take a look around. In your start pack.
if you haven't already got your start pack
for instance if you created your own floor
then go and get it now; import package / custom
package and then navigate your way to your
BowlMaster assets at the beginning of this
section and there's a Unity section there
that you can import. In there you'll find
Blender imports and there's a bowling pin.
Try just dragging that bowling pin from your
Blender imports to the scene. It's going to
look a bit weird to start with and I'll explain
why in a moment.
Drag it in and drop it. look at this default
shadowing in Unity 5. by default. That's really
cool. So. what do we do when we drop a new
3D asset in? Well. firstly we need to make
sure that it looks right. Now because Blender
and Unity play together nicely. and this bowling
pin has been set up nicely or fairly nicely
over in Blender. we can actually get the two
to play together very easily. So what have
we got here? We have a bowling pin and what
is it? Well it's a transform and an animator
for now. Well we don't really need an animator
so we could remove that component.
Then let's look in and see what the subcomponents
are. Well we have a pin collider. So we have
a collider mesh and that's the funny purple
things you're seeing there and then we have
a renderer on that collider mesh we don't
need that. So the collider mesh is the mesh
that's going to be responsible for calculating
how this pin interacts with other pins. So
you can remove the renderer mesh from the
collider sub-object. You'll understand all
this a bit better in a bit. but basically
we just need a coarse collider mesh on there.
and when we add a collider itself. let's do
that now. add a mesh collider.
There you go. so you're looking at the bowling
pin its pin collider sub-component and add
a component called a mesh collider. There
it is. So that mesh is of a lower detail than
the render mesh. So if you zoom in to the
pin by rolling in as we showed you then look
at the triangles in the render mesh. in the
blue here compared to all the triangles in
the collider mesh; a much more coarse mesh
and there's a good reason for that. In order
to make the pin interact and bounce off other
pins the mesh needs to be something called
convex which means that it has no concave
elements like this curve here like the waistline
of the pin.
If it's not convex then this pin will not
be able to hit other pins it's a performance
optimisation element of Unity. So we need
to click convex. So on your bowling pin pin
collider your mesh collider element click
convex and it'll immediately become convex
like that. which is great. You wouldn't be
able to do that with the render mesh because
if you look at the documentation for a mesh
collider and then look up convex - there you
go convex - if enabled then mesh collider
will collide with other mesh colliders. we
need that. we need pins to collide with pins
but they are limited to 255 triangles.
SO Michael has kindly when he made this bowling
pin made us two separate meshes - one to make
it look prettier. which is the render mesh.
and then another for the collider mesh that
we are now making convex. So the end state
of your collider should be no renderer - we
don't need to render the collider. we don't
need to see it; convex and looking something
like that. Now it's not perfect. it's not
going to collide exactly like pins do because
it's going to act like it's impacting things
even right out here to the sides of the mesh
but that's the limitation that we have with
Unity and convex meshes; and then if you look
at the rendered that's doing fine.
Now you'll notice that again because the asset
was set up nicely in Blender to import it's
got several things on it. It has a mesh and
then a mesh renderer but then it has also
populated this materials array with two different
materials now. we have a material for the
majority of the pin which is white. which
you can see here. under material element zero.
pin body. and then material element one which
is pin stripe. Now if you're wondering where
those materials exist well they're in this
materials subfolder automatically and they
are just plain red and white albedo materials
just like the floor. but just plain white
and red.
OK the other things that you'll see in this
Blender object when you expand it out with
the little triangle is a default take here
which is to do with animation and also a bowling
pin avatar again also used for animation.
They come across by default; we don't need
to use them. Fantastic so we have a single
pin which is great news. Let's go and put
the single pin where it should be now. If
I remember rightly it's in the middle x. y
well I believe should be 0. right on the floor
let's just check that this is going to depend
on the pivot point of your 3D object. Yep
that's on the floor. Now if you're adventurous
and you want to have a play with this pin
your second customisation point for this game
after you've made us a different and much
more interesting lane is to double click on
your bowling pin if you've got Blender installed.
get into Blender. and to modify this pin and
to make it your own.
Now Blender can be a bit of a face full to
get used to and that is exactly why we have
created this course. You have issues in here
with this interface and how to get a handle
on it. I find it really tricky but that's
why we're making a course on it. Anyway try
and find another bowling pin or modify this
bowling pin if you can at least change the
colours of these stripes. that is simple to
do. right you just go into the pin render
material here and you could go to the stripe
material and you could go into here and you
could change it to let's say a blue stripe.
Alright? So at least customise the colours.
if you really want to get detailed you could
go into here and you could start putting a
texture onto the pin itself and have a play
around with all of how that works and the
pin properties. Great opportunity for you
to create and explore and make a mess. OK.
so we have a pin. It lives at 0. 0 and then
1829 was the position of the head pin I believe
from the document. Let's go focus down on
that pin. OK so the z position is negative
and that's fine. we can have all of our z
positions in the negative. or. you can switch
your play space around so you need to decide
now do you want to be dealing with negative
z's or do you want to have positive z's from
the line that you launch?
Well I want to be dealing with positives.
so let's move our floor. so firstly I'm going
to rename my floor object so it's more clear
what it is. I'm going to move my bowling pin
to the bottom just for tidiness and now we
need to look at where this floor object is.
well it's 20m long but it centres in the middle
here. What I actually want to do is move it
out in the z like that so the line that you
launch your ball from is right at the origin
here. So we need to be minus a thousand centimetres
here and the effect that that has if we put
a reference cube in - game object / 3D / cube
and then reset that cube. remember that this
is a one by one centimetre cube.
Where is it? Well let's take a look - its
right there. it's one hundredth of the width
of the play space and it's right at the bowling
launch line. Perfect. The other thing that
we can do with this reference cube of course.
being one centimetre tall is to move it up
one centimetre like that and then to move
it to 1829 in the z direction. so that it's
sitting right next to the pin. Now it's moved
in positive z. look at this little gizmo at
the top here. and our playspace disappears
into negative z so you need to be careful
with your positives and negatives.
I think that the whole game would be a lot
easier to manage if the playspace. i.e. the
floor. went not into negative z but into positive
z. So these are the sort of fiddling around
that you're going to have to do. OK what have
we got now? We've got a bowling pin that shouldn't
be at 1829 negative but positive. we're just
flipping our entire playspace around. Where's
the camera? Well. it's kind of in the wrong
place now but that's fine. we can go to the
end of the playspace. this is a good chance
for you to navigate. or we could either go
to the end of the playspace. spin around.
and then align the camera with the view. or
we could do this from the inspector.
We could say that we want the camera to be
at y = 5. that was fine before. it could be
at x = 0. right in the middle of the lane.
and then at z = 0. and then where's the camera?
Well let's just take a look at it in the scene
view. Do a bit of moving around with the right
mouse button. click on the camera to visualise
it. there it is. So the problem with it right
now is its rotation around the y axis. How
do you know that? Well look at these axis
indicators here. it's the y axis that we need
to spin it around. 180 degrees. there you
go; and the camera preview looks about right.
and actually it's great. we're looking down
the lane.
So now the position of our camera. if we set
it to 0 z. is right at the launch point of
the lane. We can't see the pins at the end
now. why not? Well because the camera viewport
is too wide. We need to zoom our camera in
a little bit. Click on the camera again. maybe
go into game view so that you can see what
you're doing. and just turn the field of view
of the camera down. OK? And then again you're
going to have to adjust it a little bit until
you can actually see what's going on. So get
used to manipulating these objects. move the
camera viewpoint up; now what's wrong? Well
the camera has a far point clipping plane
of a thousand which is how far it can see.
Why don't we say 2.500? There you go.
Now it can see out to 25 metres distance.
and you can see that reflected here; you see
as I move this far point. you see it moving?
So beyond that things aren't rendered for
this camera. it's like the fog of war.
So if your camera is sitting now at the start
point. basically at the origin but lifted
up a little bit by 25 cm off the deck - maybe
we should go higher than that. maybe we should
go 150 cm off the deck. more like a human
height. Sounds like a good idea but it just
doesn't look right with this zoomed in camera
so I'm going to put it back down to where
it was. You see sometimes you just have to
be non-realistic and just play with things.
Is it right in the middle x-wise? No it could
be. that'll be fine. Probably more boring
if it is. and we could play with the camera
more later. You get the idea. we want it at
the origin. looking down the lane. the lane
wants to extend from the origin. i.e. 0.0.0
all the way down. 20 metres in the positive
z direction as indicated here. the floor is
at 0.0.1000 because it's 20 metres long. it
has to be offset by a thousand.
Where's this reference cube? It’s right
down here. actually inside the pin at the
moment. so let’s go to the translate tool
which is up here. and just move it next to
the pin now it needs to be at y = 1. there
you go. and now you can check and see is this
guy roughly the right size? Well how big was
the pin supposed to be? Well twenty something
centimetres right? So why not scale your cube
20 cm and move it up 10cm? And that's 20cm
so you can check against your game design
document how big your pin should be and just
use physical objects as measuring sticks if
you want.
Somewhere here we have a pin specification.
here you go. It should be 38 cm tall. So over
in Unity if we set the y scale to 38 half
of that's going to be under the floor. so
we need to move it up by 15 _4 or half of
38 which is 19 so it sits perfectly on the
ground. you see right there and you see that
is the height of the pin or thereabouts. So
great. measuring stick. That's what I used
the cube for. Just to get a handle on what
this space is. Remember we're choosing for
our units to mean centimetres. they have no
meaning until we give them one.
Great. so we have the pin in. let's take you
onto your challenge right now. So I want you
to find your own pin. or modify the pin if
you want to. otherwise use ours from the assets.
ensure that the dimensions match. or are close
to the GDD. test that the pin sits on the
lane properly like we have there and set up
all ten pins according to the game design
document that means lay them out and that's
a bit of a hassle but it only needs to be
done once because we'll prefab the pin set
up. So go ahead. get all that done and I will
see you in a moment.
Cool welcome back. so now it's just a question
of firstly I just need to make sure that the
pin actually collides with the floor. so that
it will let me play the game here. and the
pin well. it probably does collide with the
floor but there's no gravity on it yet. We'll
deal with the physics of the pin in a little
bit but for now all I needed you to do was
to make sure that they sit on the floor graphically.
If you've been a little more advanced and
already added a rigidbdy to the pin and noticed
that it falls to the floor then extra bonus.
but let's cover the physics of the pin in
a separate video.
Cool. so for now we need to just replicate
these pins in such a way that they match the
game design document for the pin layout. So
that's at the beginning of this section. you
have this document here and we have a 30.48cm
spacing between them sideways and a 52.71
spacing this way. That's a bit weird. So how
are we going to do that? Well I like to have
an empty parent object called pins. and it's
good practice to pop that at the origin. Or.
to pop it at the position of the head pin
actually. which is what I'm going to do. 1829
so it's here. the game object is there.
Then when I move the bowling pin into it.
it's offset the head pin is not offset at
all from the pins object so the pins object
is relative to that headpin. Now it's just
a question of duplicating the pin. and actually
what would be useful because it's going to
auto-number the pins for you is why not delete
that first one and just duplicate like this
- 2. and then bring it back put it roughly
in place. duplicate splodge d. 3. again command
or control d. you see the idea here and we
can just duplicate these pins out moving them
into roughly the right position I suggest
is a good idea. Careful about using this box
translator as it'll move it in 3 dimensions
and that will be confusing. So it's probably
easier just to use your red and your blue
handles; and also remember that you can move
your viewpoint. don't fight in a 3D view if
you don't need to be; and now you could actually
label these exactly as they should be so if
this is pin 1. 2 and 3 as we look from above.
why not spin it around. get above it and then
make sure we're doing pin 1. 2 you see two
and three are round the wrong way as such
so let's just get them right.
1. 2. 3. and then 4. 5 is inside four at the
moment because of the way that I duplicated
it. we're just going to do a rough layout
to start with. then six and the beauty of
duplicating these after deleting the first
pin is that they auto-number. isn't that easy.
Seven. eight and I suggest immediately that
you duplicate them that you move the new object
out so it doesn't end up too confused. and
there you go we have a set of pins. Now they're
not lined up perfectly. and that's not surprising
because we haven’t yet actually inspected
them to line them up perfectly.
So how are we going to do that? How are we
going to make sure that the pins are in exactly
the right positions? Well you just need to
go through and do a little bit of calculation.
so if it's - looking at this vertical dimension
looking from pin 3 to 9 that's going to be
the same as the dimension from pin 1 to 5
so let's start there with number one; and
we need to make sure that the dimension 9
to 3 or 3 to 9 is 52.71 cm. let's remember
52.71 so we need pin 5 to be 52.71 cm back
from pin 0.
So pin 0 is at 0. 0. 0 relative to the pin
array. which is a nice. that's the head pin
so that makes sense. Pin 5 we want to be at
x = 0. y = 0 because we want it sitting on
the floor but 52.71 back. Now to me that looks
like that's too far back but no but it's OK.
it's just a bigger gap than we expect. This
pin has ended up all the way back here. That
seems like it's a long way back to me. in
fact that is too long a way back for sure.
Let's just take a look where pin 2 would be.
that would put pin 2 maybe it is OK?
Pin 2 there. pin 3 here. yeah maybe that's
fine. So pin 4 would come down here. see a
messy business of just laying out the pins
roughly right in the first place and then
we just have to move the back layer of pins
all the way back and you could actually multi-select
those to do that by holding down command.
OK. so maybe they are that spaced out. It
feels a little bit odd. looks a little bit
odd. but let's make sure that it works. Pin
1 is at 0. 0. 0. pin 5 is the first one that
we have a handle on is at 0.0.52.71. That's
what it says. let's just keep going then.
So we have 30.48cm sideways between two pins.
So that means we have 15.24cm is half of that.
right? So that's where this guy needs to be.
pin 2 needs to be at -15.24 going half the
distance sideways and then how far back? Well
half of 52.71 now we're stretching my mental
calculations a little bit so let's just use
a calculator. 26.355 you may as well copy
that from your calculator to be precise. and
just pop it in here. There you go. So it's
pretty obvious now what pin number 3 is going
to be. it's going to be the same type of thing
as number 2 but with the opposite x co-ordinate
so 15.24.
OK look. now I'm not going to bore you by
going through and showing you the final layout
of these pins so I'm just going to cut to
the end result where I've applied the same
calculation to make sure that all these pins
are in the perfect positions. So a couple
more tips to help you with this. I've laid
out most of my pins I just want to show you
two more options. one is don't be afraid to
delete pins if you find that it's going to
be easier just to duplicate like that perhaps
and then move this guy across maybe to 15.2.
that's one option for you.
The other thing that you can do if you have
a rough set pin like this pin number ten here.
let's imagine that it's in a weird position
like so. and you say well it's pretty much
the same position as this guy. he's just the
opposite x component. what you could do is
go to the transform of say pin 7 or whichever
one. copy the component. that copies the whole
transform component. click on the destination
pin and paste component values and it will
snap right on the top of this guy and then
if you remove the negative then that's another
way of doing it.
Now if you still think that this looks weird
then you can change your camera from perspective
to isometric. Now perspective is obviously
how we see the world. isometric is like a
camera at infinity and now there is no perspective.
and actually from this point of view it's
all looking a lot more sensible in the perspective
view and maybe down here they look too spread
out but we're just so used to seeing bins
from down here that it just doesn't match
our intuition. It looks a lot better down
here right? Again isometric here looks weird
but perspective here looks right. and isometric
from above looks right as well.
So congratulations! All our pins are laid
out beautifully in the play space and if we
look at our game camera you can see something
looking like a bowling lane and we have a
master game object so perfect! Well done looking
=======
Hi and welcome back. So in this video were
going to be importing a bowling pin from Blender,
learn about render and collider meshes, create
a pin prefab, and lay out all of our ten bowling
pins on the floor according to the GDD. So
you can find out more about Blender at www.CompleteBlenderCreator.com,
I've teamed up with an old friend and 3D artist
Michael Bridges to bring a huge course similar
to this one to you called the Complete Blender
Creator because it's such an important skill
now that we're moving into 3D to be able to
manipulate meshes, so go out and take a look
at www.CompleteBlenderCreator.com.
So, that's the challenge that we're going
to be doing a little later but for now let's
just take a look around. In your start pack,
if you haven't already got your start pack
for instance if you created your own floor
then go and get it now; import package / custom
package and then navigate your way to your
BowlMaster assets at the beginning of this
section and there's a Unity section there
that you can import. In there you'll find
Blender imports and there's a bowling pin.
Try just dragging that bowling pin from your
Blender imports to the scene. It's going to
look a bit weird to start with and I'll explain
why in a moment.
Drag it in and drop it, look at this default
shadowing in Unity 5, by default. That's really
cool. So, what do we do when we drop a new
3D asset in? Well, firstly we need to make
sure that it looks right. Now because Blender
and Unity play together nicely, and this bowling
pin has been set up nicely or fairly nicely
over in Blender, we can actually get the two
to play together very easily. So what have
we got here? We have a bowling pin and what
is it? Well it's a transform and an animator
for now. Well we don't really need an animator
so we could remove that component.
Then let's look in and see what the subcomponents
are. Well we have a pin collider. So we have
a collider mesh and that's the funny purple
things you're seeing there and then we have
a renderer on that collider mesh we don't
need that. So the collider mesh is the mesh
that's going to be responsible for calculating
how this pin interacts with other pins. So
you can remove the renderer mesh from the
collider sub-object. You'll understand all
this a bit better in a bit, but basically
we just need a coarse collider mesh on there,
and when we add a collider itself, let's do
that now, add a mesh collider.
There you go, so you're looking at the bowling
pin its pin collider sub-component and add
a component called a mesh collider. There
it is. So that mesh is of a lower detail than
the render mesh. So if you zoom in to the
pin by rolling in as we showed you then look
at the triangles in the render mesh, in the
blue here compared to all the triangles in
the collider mesh; a much more coarse mesh
and there's a good reason for that. In order
to make the pin interact and bounce off other
pins the mesh needs to be something called
convex which means that it has no concave
elements like this curve here like the waistline
of the pin.
If it's not convex then this pin will not
be able to hit other pins it's a performance
optimisation element of Unity. So we need
to click convex. So on your bowling pin pin
collider your mesh collider element click
convex and it'll immediately become convex
like that, which is great. You wouldn't be
able to do that with the render mesh because
if you look at the documentation for a mesh
collider and then look up convex - there you
go convex - if enabled then mesh collider
will collide with other mesh colliders, we
need that, we need pins to collide with pins
but they are limited to 255 triangles.
SO Michael has kindly when he made this bowling
pin made us two separate meshes - one to make
it look prettier, which is the render mesh,
and then another for the collider mesh that
we are now making convex. So the end state
of your collider should be no renderer - we
don't need to render the collider, we don't
need to see it; convex and looking something
like that. Now it's not perfect, it's not
going to collide exactly like pins do because
it's going to act like it's impacting things
even right out here to the sides of the mesh
but that's the limitation that we have with
Unity and convex meshes; and then if you look
at the rendered that's doing fine.
Now you'll notice that again because the asset
was set up nicely in Blender to import it's
got several things on it. It has a mesh and
then a mesh renderer but then it has also
populated this materials array with two different
materials now, we have a material for the
majority of the pin which is white, which
you can see here, under material element zero,
pin body, and then material element one which
is pin stripe. Now if you're wondering where
those materials exist well they're in this
materials subfolder automatically and they
are just plain red and white albedo materials
just like the floor, but just plain white
and red.
OK the other things that you'll see in this
Blender object when you expand it out with
the little triangle is a default take here
which is to do with animation and also a bowling
pin avatar again also used for animation.
They come across by default; we don't need
to use them. Fantastic so we have a single
pin which is great news. Let's go and put
the single pin where it should be now. If
I remember rightly it's in the middle x, y
well I believe should be 0, right on the floor
let's just check that this is going to depend
on the pivot point of your 3D object. Yep
that's on the floor. Now if you're adventurous
and you want to have a play with this pin
your second customisation point for this game
after you've made us a different and much
more interesting lane is to double click on
your bowling pin if you've got Blender installed,
get into Blender, and to modify this pin and
to make it your own.
Now Blender can be a bit of a face full to
get used to and that is exactly why we have
created this course. You have issues in here
with this interface and how to get a handle
on it, I find it really tricky but that's
why we're making a course on it. Anyway try
and find another bowling pin or modify this
bowling pin if you can at least change the
colours of these stripes, that is simple to
do, right you just go into the pin render
material here and you could go to the stripe
material and you could go into here and you
could change it to let's say a blue stripe.
Alright? So at least customise the colours,
if you really want to get detailed you could
go into here and you could start putting a
texture onto the pin itself and have a play
around with all of how that works and the
pin properties. Great opportunity for you
to create and explore and make a mess. OK,
so we have a pin. It lives at 0, 0 and then
1829 was the position of the head pin I believe
from the document. Let's go focus down on
that pin. OK so the z position is negative
and that's fine, we can have all of our z
positions in the negative, or, you can switch
your play space around so you need to decide
now do you want to be dealing with negative
z's or do you want to have positive z's from
the line that you launch?
Well I want to be dealing with positives,
so let's move our floor, so firstly I'm going
to rename my floor object so it's more clear
what it is, I'm going to move my bowling pin
to the bottom just for tidiness and now we
need to look at where this floor object is,
well it's 20m long but it centres in the middle
here. What I actually want to do is move it
out in the z like that so the line that you
launch your ball from is right at the origin
here. So we need to be minus a thousand centimetres
here and the effect that that has if we put
a reference cube in - game object / 3D / cube
and then reset that cube, remember that this
is a one by one centimetre cube.
Where is it? Well let's take a look - its
right there, it's one hundredth of the width
of the play space and it's right at the bowling
launch line. Perfect. The other thing that
we can do with this reference cube of course,
being one centimetre tall is to move it up
one centimetre like that and then to move
it to 1829 in the z direction, so that it's
sitting right next to the pin. Now it's moved
in positive z, look at this little gizmo at
the top here, and our playspace disappears
into negative z so you need to be careful
with your positives and negatives.
I think that the whole game would be a lot
easier to manage if the playspace, i.e. the
floor, went not into negative z but into positive
z. So these are the sort of fiddling around
that you're going to have to do. OK what have
we got now? We've got a bowling pin that shouldn't
be at 1829 negative but positive, we're just
flipping our entire playspace around. Where's
the camera? Well, it's kind of in the wrong
place now but that's fine, we can go to the
end of the playspace, this is a good chance
for you to navigate, or we could either go
to the end of the playspace, spin around,
and then align the camera with the view, or
we could do this from the inspector.
We could say that we want the camera to be
at y = 5, that was fine before, it could be
at x = 0, right in the middle of the lane,
and then at z = 0, and then where's the camera?
Well let's just take a look at it in the scene
view. Do a bit of moving around with the right
mouse button, click on the camera to visualise
it, there it is. So the problem with it right
now is its rotation around the y axis. How
do you know that? Well look at these axis
indicators here, it's the y axis that we need
to spin it around, 180 degrees, there you
go; and the camera preview looks about right,
and actually it's great, we're looking down
the lane.
So now the position of our camera, if we set
it to 0 z, is right at the launch point of
the lane. We can't see the pins at the end
now, why not? Well because the camera viewport
is too wide. We need to zoom our camera in
a little bit. Click on the camera again, maybe
go into game view so that you can see what
you're doing, and just turn the field of view
of the camera down, OK? And then again you're
going to have to adjust it a little bit until
you can actually see what's going on. So get
used to manipulating these objects, move the
camera viewpoint up; now what's wrong? Well
the camera has a far point clipping plane
of a thousand which is how far it can see.
Why don't we say 2,500? There you go.
Now it can see out to 25 metres distance,
and you can see that reflected here; you see
as I move this far point, you see it moving?
So beyond that things aren't rendered for
this camera, it's like the fog of war.
So if your camera is sitting now at the start
point, basically at the origin but lifted
up a little bit by 25 cm off the deck - maybe
we should go higher than that, maybe we should
go 150 cm off the deck, more like a human
height. Sounds like a good idea but it just
doesn't look right with this zoomed in camera
so I'm going to put it back down to where
it was. You see sometimes you just have to
be non-realistic and just play with things.
Is it right in the middle x-wise? No it could
be, that'll be fine. Probably more boring
if it is, and we could play with the camera
more later. You get the idea, we want it at
the origin, looking down the lane, the lane
wants to extend from the origin, i.e. 0,0,0
all the way down, 20 metres in the positive
z direction as indicated here, the floor is
at 0,0,1000 because it's 20 metres long, it
has to be offset by a thousand.
Where's this reference cube? Its right
down here, actually inside the pin at the
moment, so lets go to the translate tool
which is up here, and just move it next to
the pin now it needs to be at y = 1, there
you go, and now you can check and see is this
guy roughly the right size? Well how big was
the pin supposed to be? Well twenty something
centimetres right? So why not scale your cube
20 cm and move it up 10cm? And that's 20cm
so you can check against your game design
document how big your pin should be and just
use physical objects as measuring sticks if
you want.
Somewhere here we have a pin specification,
here you go. It should be 38 cm tall. So over
in Unity if we set the y scale to 38 half
of that's going to be under the floor, so
we need to move it up by 15 _4 or half of
38 which is 19 so it sits perfectly on the
ground, you see right there and you see that
is the height of the pin or thereabouts. So
great, measuring stick. That's what I used
the cube for. Just to get a handle on what
this space is. Remember we're choosing for
our units to mean centimetres, they have no
meaning until we give them one.
Great, so we have the pin in, let's take you
onto your challenge right now. So I want you
to find your own pin, or modify the pin if
you want to, otherwise use ours from the assets,
ensure that the dimensions match, or are close
to the GDD, test that the pin sits on the
lane properly like we have there and set up
all ten pins according to the game design
document that means lay them out and that's
a bit of a hassle but it only needs to be
done once because we'll prefab the pin set
up. So go ahead, get all that done and I will
see you in a moment.
Cool welcome back, so now it's just a question
of firstly I just need to make sure that the
pin actually collides with the floor, so that
it will let me play the game here, and the
pin well, it probably does collide with the
floor but there's no gravity on it yet. We'll
deal with the physics of the pin in a little
bit but for now all I needed you to do was
to make sure that they sit on the floor graphically.
If you've been a little more advanced and
already added a rigidbdy to the pin and noticed
that it falls to the floor then extra bonus,
but let's cover the physics of the pin in
a separate video.
Cool, so for now we need to just replicate
these pins in such a way that they match the
game design document for the pin layout. So
that's at the beginning of this section, you
have this document here and we have a 30.48cm
spacing between them sideways and a 52.71
spacing this way. That's a bit weird. So how
are we going to do that? Well I like to have
an empty parent object called pins, and it's
good practice to pop that at the origin. Or,
to pop it at the position of the head pin
actually, which is what I'm going to do. 1829
so it's here, the game object is there.
Then when I move the bowling pin into it,
it's offset the head pin is not offset at
all from the pins object so the pins object
is relative to that headpin. Now it's just
a question of duplicating the pin, and actually
what would be useful because it's going to
auto-number the pins for you is why not delete
that first one and just duplicate like this
- 2, and then bring it back put it roughly
in place, duplicate splodge d, 3, again command
or control d, you see the idea here and we
can just duplicate these pins out moving them
into roughly the right position I suggest
is a good idea. Careful about using this box
translator as it'll move it in 3 dimensions
and that will be confusing. So it's probably
easier just to use your red and your blue
handles; and also remember that you can move
your viewpoint, don't fight in a 3D view if
you don't need to be; and now you could actually
label these exactly as they should be so if
this is pin 1, 2 and 3 as we look from above,
why not spin it around, get above it and then
make sure we're doing pin 1, 2 you see two
and three are round the wrong way as such
so let's just get them right.
1, 2, 3, and then 4, 5 is inside four at the
moment because of the way that I duplicated
it, we're just going to do a rough layout
to start with, then six and the beauty of
duplicating these after deleting the first
pin is that they auto-number, isn't that easy.
Seven, eight and I suggest immediately that
you duplicate them that you move the new object
out so it doesn't end up too confused, and
there you go we have a set of pins. Now they're
not lined up perfectly, and that's not surprising
because we havent yet actually inspected
them to line them up perfectly.
So how are we going to do that? How are we
going to make sure that the pins are in exactly
the right positions? Well you just need to
go through and do a little bit of calculation,
so if it's - looking at this vertical dimension
looking from pin 3 to 9 that's going to be
the same as the dimension from pin 1 to 5
so let's start there with number one; and
we need to make sure that the dimension 9
to 3 or 3 to 9 is 52.71 cm, let's remember
52.71 so we need pin 5 to be 52.71 cm back
from pin 0.
So pin 0 is at 0, 0, 0 relative to the pin
array, which is a nice, that's the head pin
so that makes sense. Pin 5 we want to be at
x = 0, y = 0 because we want it sitting on
the floor but 52.71 back. Now to me that looks
like that's too far back but no but it's OK,
it's just a bigger gap than we expect. This
pin has ended up all the way back here. That
seems like it's a long way back to me, in
fact that is too long a way back for sure.
Let's just take a look where pin 2 would be,
that would put pin 2 maybe it is OK?
Pin 2 there, pin 3 here, yeah maybe that's
fine. So pin 4 would come down here, see a
messy business of just laying out the pins
roughly right in the first place and then
we just have to move the back layer of pins
all the way back and you could actually multi-select
those to do that by holding down command.
OK, so maybe they are that spaced out. It
feels a little bit odd, looks a little bit
odd, but let's make sure that it works. Pin
1 is at 0, 0, 0, pin 5 is the first one that
we have a handle on is at 0,0,52.71. That's
what it says, let's just keep going then.
So we have 30.48cm sideways between two pins.
So that means we have 15.24cm is half of that,
right? So that's where this guy needs to be,
pin 2 needs to be at -15.24 going half the
distance sideways and then how far back? Well
half of 52.71 now we're stretching my mental
calculations a little bit so let's just use
a calculator. 26.355 you may as well copy
that from your calculator to be precise, and
just pop it in here. There you go. So it's
pretty obvious now what pin number 3 is going
to be, it's going to be the same type of thing
as number 2 but with the opposite x co-ordinate
so 15.24.
OK look, now I'm not going to bore you by
going through and showing you the final layout
of these pins so I'm just going to cut to
the end result where I've applied the same
calculation to make sure that all these pins
are in the perfect positions. So a couple
more tips to help you with this, I've laid
out most of my pins I just want to show you
two more options, one is don't be afraid to
delete pins if you find that it's going to
be easier just to duplicate like that perhaps
and then move this guy across maybe to 15.2,
that's one option for you.
The other thing that you can do if you have
a rough set pin like this pin number ten here,
let's imagine that it's in a weird position
like so, and you say well it's pretty much
the same position as this guy, he's just the
opposite x component, what you could do is
go to the transform of say pin 7 or whichever
one, copy the component, that copies the whole
transform component, click on the destination
pin and paste component values and it will
snap right on the top of this guy and then
if you remove the negative then that's another
way of doing it.
Now if you still think that this looks weird
then you can change your camera from perspective
to isometric. Now perspective is obviously
how we see the world, isometric is like a
camera at infinity and now there is no perspective,
and actually from this point of view it's
all looking a lot more sensible in the perspective
view and maybe down here they look too spread
out but we're just so used to seeing bins
from down here that it just doesn't match
our intuition. It looks a lot better down
here right? Again isometric here looks weird
but perspective here looks right, and isometric
from above looks right as well.
So congratulations! All our pins are laid
out beautifully in the play space and if we
look at our game camera you can see something
looking like a bowling lane and we have a
master game object so perfect! Well done looking
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1:Unity/Section8/BM07 Import pin from blender.srt
this far and I'll see you soon.