Hi, welcome back. In this video we're going
to use the camera to track the ball down the
lane. We're going to create a CameraControll.cs
script for the main camera, or rather you
are; we're going to make the camera track
the ball down the lane, and then stop when
it gets close to the head pin. So let's move
over into Unity and see what I mean by that.
So we've got our ball sitting here, and at
the moment in the game view the camera is
at a fixed distance from this ball, but it
just stays there when we push the ball, and
not a great experience because we can't really
see what's going on.
So what I'm going to do is create a camera
control script against the camera. So go ahead
and do that now, click on your main camera
and add a new script simply called camera
control; and you add that script. Fantastic,
so let's go into the camera control script
and think about how it's going to attain a
fixed offset from this ball. So Monodevelop's
loading in the background right now - and
here it is. Fantastic so I need to just open
my camera control here it comes.
There it is, OK so the first thing the camera
control script is going to need to do when
it's created is it's going to have to have
a concept of a ball so I'm going to give you
the outline of this script and I'm going to
ask you to actually write it so we're going
to need a public Ball ball that we'll drag
in to the camera control. Because I've written
that line I'm going to go ahead and write
that immediately. Well looking at the main
camera now it's saying well what do you want
me to track? What ball do you want me to track?
So I'll give it a ball.
Fantastic. Another little hint for you is
that it's privately going to need to know
about an offset so it's going to be a Vector3
Offset between the ball and the camera; and
then it needs to find that at the start, and
then obtain that offset by moving the transform
of the camera relative to the ball's transform
every frame. So I've given you enough hints
there, I think that at this stage in the course
that you are able to do this. The final thing
that you are going to need to do is stop it
when it gets to the head pin, so here's your
challenge: Write the rest of CameraControl.cs
Keep the camera a fixed offset from the ball.
Use an if statement in your Update loop to
stop the camera at the headpin - i.e. 1829
- and just test that it works. Go ahead, pause
the video, and have a go at that challenge
now. So let's take a look at how we're going
to do that. Just before we do we need to consider
how we're going to calculate this offset vector.
So, what we want to do every frame is take
in the ball's transform which is in bold because
it's a vector, and add in the offset so ball
+ offset becomes the camera's position.
So a bit of maths for you, we subtract ball
from both sides, we wish that we would have
listened in those algebra lessons so if you
take ball from both sides of that you get
camera - ball and you can see that in the
little arrow, imagine that the ball was moving
to the right you have an offset vector which
tells you how far away we want to keep the
camera from the ball, and in future just basically
remember that offsets work as head minus tail
so camera minus ball gives you the offset
that you need. Or do the maths like I just
have.
Say what you want, ball+offset = camera and
work it through. Fantastic, so what we need
to remember for now is that the offset is
calculated as camera - ball. So, let's go
ahead right into the monodevelop where we
were and make all this happen. So what we
do in the start just once in the beginning
is we capture the current offset between the
camera and the ball where we are starting
from; i.e. this offset here at the very beginning.
So let's capture that, offset = camera but
it's not camera that was just what I used
in the slide, it's the camera's transform
but we're on the camera so it's simply transform.
Position minus ball.transform.position.
OK so there's our offset vector, we capture
that once at the start, now what we do every
frame is we say well we want to set the position
of camera.transform.position equals balls.transform.position
plus this offset that doesn't change. Because
we captures it once at the start and it doesn't
change. Now let's take a look at the effect
of that, click play. OK I think that I clicked
play twice there. Boom look at that the ball
lands, OK It's going a bit slow and I know
that the football texture's a bit dodgy but
we'll change that later. The good thing about
the football texture is that we can see what's
going on so look, the camera, it works, right?
So what is a little bit strange is that the
ball climbs up, or tries to climb up over
that pin.
So it's going to be a little bit hard to organise
the stopping camera stopping element of that
script if it's going to keep hitting that
pin right? So what can we do about that for
testing purposes? Well we could fire the ball
off to the side a little bit. If you look
at our ball script at the moment it has no
x velocity; what is our launch speed well
let's take a look, we have a launch speed
currently of two hundred units in the z direction,
so what you could do temporarily is change
your launch speed in your ball.cs from a float
to a Vector3 and change it from speed because
speed is not a Vector3, speed is a scalar.
So we need to say launch velocity now and
then instead of constructing a new Vector3
here we are just saying that the ball's velocity
on start is the launch velocity. Now over
in the inspector; hang on let me just go back
a little bit and digest that. I've changed
the float for the launch speed into a vector
velocity and just changed it for that velocity
vector down here in the start. That means
that in the inspector we have the opportunity
to say to the ball in more detail how we want
it to travel; not only 200 in the z but what
would happen if it travelled 20 in the x?
Well it should go flying off to the right
now and it does. OK so that's fine, now we
want it to get towards the position of the
pins and then the camera needs to stop.
So a little bit tricky if it falls of the
edge, so maybe we just move 2 to the right
- just enough to not hit the headpin. So adjust
your launch x velocity, in fact stuff this
I'm going to adjust the y velocity as well;
the z rather because it's too slow for me.
OK try this. Boom much faster, takes a while
to land, goes down, it's going to hit one
of these pins and do something really weird
but the important thing is that we need to
stop the camera at that z position, remember
the challenge? So how are we going to do that?
Well, in the camera control script we are
currently always just updating the camera's
position.
How about if we said if, and then we need
to talk about the transform of the camera
not being more than 1825 so if transform.position
is less than or equal to 1825, 1829 I can't
remember. What was the position of the head
pin? 1829 cm. 18.29 metres. So if the transform.position
of the camera is less than or equal to 1829
cm which means in English, and it's good to
put a comment in here, in front of head pin,
then make that update every frame otherwise
just simply do nothing, we don't need to say
do nothing, let's see what happens if we put
that condition in.
OK so I've done a booboo and that's because
we need transform.position.z we can't just
say that the 3 dimensional vector is less
than or equal to 1829, that doesn't make any
sense, we need a .z on there and we'd better
put an f for float on the 1829 because we
can be damn sure that the z position's going
to be a float. Let's see if that builds; control
or splodge b, I'll put my keyboard shortcuts
up so ctrl or splodge b like that, does a
build, build successful that's encouraging,
the real proof of the pudding is will it run
in Unity. So it's running, and now what happens?
The camera completely fails to stop does it?
No the camera has stopped. It has stopped
right there. Now where's the camera stopped?
Go and inspect it. It has stopped at z = 1829
so let's go and watch that from another perspective
- go into the scene view and click on your
camera and watch its z position up here in
the inspector and it stops around about 1829.
It's a little tiny bit over just because of
rounding and the amount that it moves per
frame. So if' you've got some code that looks
something like this then congratulations because
you have managed to achieve that challenge
and you've got 3 dimensional control over
your camera; you'll regularly be doing these
type of offset things in 3D so well done,
and if you needed a little help great that's
absolutely fine too. So congratulations and
I'll see you in the next video.