Hey welcome back. So in this video we're going
to be talking about 3D collisions and convex
meshes. All will become clear shortly. So
we're going to be adding a rigidbody to the
pins, adjusting the physics so that the collisions
work properly and then creating a new altogether
richer pin prefab. Fantastic so what's happening
right now, let's look at the problem before
we start solving it. Here goes the ball, beautiful
camera tracking script, the physics system
is making the ball spin but, look at them
stubborn pins they just won't move anywhere.
Now why is that?
Well if you look at a pin it is just a transform,
and anything in the world that is just a transform
with a couple of renderers as sub-components
well it's not going to do anything. The most
that we have on here is a collider which is
just a mesh and a mesh collider and then we
have a mesh renderer on the pin. So it looks
right and the collision physics looks right
but the thing itself actually has no physical
properties because we don't have a rigidbody.
So let's add a rigidbody to one of our pins
for now. Fantastic so that front pin now has
a rigidbody attached to it. Now you'll notice
that this pin is a prefab, but it's not - if
we now select this and say select prefab we've
got a pin over here. So we have a slightly
odd prefab what it is is just the blender
model. So what we're going to need to do basically
immediately is to re-prefab the pins, in fact
all of the pins now that we've got a rigidbody
on it. So let's do that and then we can make
our changes to all of our pins at once.
So add a rigidbody to one of the pins, number
one would make most sense. Number two drag
that pin into the assets area to make a bowling
pin prefab. It doesn't need to be one, it
just needs to be plain bowling pin. Fantastic,
OK, and then now we have a bowling pin one
instance of that prefab there so I can name
it one. Now bowling pin 2 is not an instance
of that prefab any more but it needs to be.
So how are we going to link it to be a full
prefab, because you see if you look here carefully
it says model on bowling pin 2 up in the inspector,
whereas bowling pin one says prefab.
So bowling pin one is linked to a prefab whereas
bowling pin 2 is just linked to a 3D model
that has no more information than that. So
you could say why don't we add the rigidbody
to the model so that we don't have to do any
more work. Well, let's try that. Add it to
the model, fine, but you can't apply it to
the model; and that's kind of good because
the model is just a mesh model. So we're going
to have to play around with changing all of
these pins into prefabs. So how do we do that?
Well, if you drop a bowling pin into the scene
now it will have some physics on it and we're
just going to have to replace all of the pins.
But before we do that let's just test the
physics of the front pin, which is different
from the rest because it has a rigid body.
Let's click play. Firstly the good thing is
that it doesn't fall through the floor, that's
encouraging, now I think that we're going
to miss the front pin, we are, so change your
launch velocity so that you actually hit the
front pin, right? Now you've got control over
it down here, keeping all of the launches
perfect right now so that we can re-create
conditions. It lands, drag makes it spin,
it spins it hits the front pin, the front
pin goes mental and the rest of the pins don't.
Great so we have the right type of behaviour
on that front pin so that’s great news.
Now what we have to do is make all the rest
of these pins be the right type of object.
so one way to do this is going to be to replace
each of these pins one at a time and then
you copy their transform components so you
go copy component, this is a really useful
facility, of pin 2 and then you delete pin
2 altogether, we don't need it any more, leaving
a glaring gap.
Put the new pin roughly in the right place
and child it to the pins so and this you can
play with here making sure that you drag things
around in the hierarchy so that they end up
in the right place. This becomes pin two which
is now connected to a prefab you see here
in the inspector and now you can paste - if
you hit the right button - you can paste on
here component as values and it will snap
to precisely the right place. So that's what
I want you to do now, I want you to go through
all of your pins and reinforce the idea that
the difference between them being connected
to a model and being connected to a prefab
so bowling pin 3 in my case is connected to
a model, bowling pins one and two are connected
to a prefab, and the prefab is here.
So if I say change the mass of the prefab
to, well let's set it correctly now, go to
your game design document, find out the mass
of a pin which will be under bowling pin specifications,
1.53kg. So if we set that to 1.53 the beauty
is with prefabs is that if you look at bowling
pins 1 and 2, if you look in the inspector,
have that mass. So you just pop through and
make that change to all of your pins and I
will do the same and I'll just do it in the
background quietly while you do
it.
Look at that. Perfect. So the final thing
to do is to have a test of that and make sure
that it works how we want it to so the ball
lands, it starts rolling, it hits the front
pin, oh look at that. Look at them fly. Now
there's something weird of course, there's
everything's moving a little bit slow like
it's in treacle, so your job now becomes to
modify the parameters so that it moves in
a way that looks right to you. They are just
going a little bit nuts. I think what I'm
going to do is give you the option to go to
project settings and physics and possibly
to turn up gravity.
Maybe try -20 under edit / project settings
/ physics. Not physics 2D but physics and
you can turn gravity up. If you do that, see
the effect that it has on the balls. So the
ball will move slightly differently it actually
picks up more spin and then the pins move
differently as well. So that's one thing that
you can adjust. The other thing that you can
adjust is on the pin prefab you can look at
whether you want more angular drag on the
pin or not, you can try variations of drag
and angular drag on the pin. You could also
possibly make the ball artificially heavy
so click into your ball and take a look at
the mass of the ball and again its drag.
Have a play with those parameters and try
and get it how you want it. So over to you,
time to adjust those physics parameters to
taste. You can change physics settings / gravity.
This is a game after all, it doesn't have
to be right, quite often in a game gravity
is not set to 9.81 like earth but it's higher,
or lower, often higher because speeds are
higher than usual and sometimes you need to
get things back to the ground quicker than
in real life. You can adjust your ball's mass
and drag parameters and you pins' mass and
drag parameters. Have a good play test, fire
your ball lots of times. Try changing your
ball's launch velocity a little bit and keep
iterating until you're happy with the way
that the ball looks when it's hitting the
pins.
So one thing that you may have noticed when
you are trying to adjust these physics parameters
is that when the ball hits the pins everything's
looking a bit slow motion; you see how slowly
these pins are falling? So why is that? Well
it turns out that there's pretty much nothing
that you can change about the properties of
the pins or the ball to affect that, it's
actually the strength of the local gravity.
So let's look at that again in edit, project
settings and then physics, that's where you
get your gravity settings, and if you take
a look over here we've already tweaked it
to -20 remembering that normal gravity on
earth is -9.81, about -10, but we actually
need for this to be realistic we need it to
be more like minus 981.
A hundred times larger than earth's normal
gravity and that's because the scale that
we've chosen here is one centimetre for every
one world unit. So for example our lane is
105 world units wide or 105 cm whereas Unity's
default is that each world unit is one metre.
Because our world is quite small centimetres
are more convenient so we have to make gravity
one hundred times smaller to end up with the
right gravitational strength in cm per second
per second. So let's just take a look. If
we do that, well the ball runs far too slowly
so you'll need to turn up the launch velocity
of the ball significantly if we are going
to have such a high gravity otherwise it's
just going to roll far too slowly because
of the extra drag.
So let's try much faster - boom, you see how
that pin is more convincing, 4000 is of course
far too much so pick yourselves a launch velocity
that works and you see it coming to a halt,
and that's because of the drag so you would
also need to turn your drag down for example
your angular drag maybe down to zero let's
try that. So that's a little bit better, it's
still stopping very quickly so let's keep
trying to tweak our ball, let's see what happens
boom. Very fast.
OK but what we're going to do is we're not
going to optimise this right now I just wanted
to explain that that's how we were going to
end up doing it we're going to work on this
towards the end of the section so I'm going
to leave these settings as they are, all the
launch velocities etc. and we're going to
tweak that towards the end but that is the
missing setting for making this look really
realistic, OK? There you go. Fantastic so
the final thing that I said that I was going
to talk about in this video was the concept
of convex meshes again, we've already talked
about it but I want to go through it a little
more.
So a convex mesh means that it's curved like
the exterior of a sphere; it's bulging outwards
not inwards. Mesh colliders must be convex
to self-collide so for a pin to collide with
a pin they must be convex. The maximum number
of triangles in a convex collider is 255,
that's why we have two separate meshes to
render the pin and for the collisions, and
these are all because of performance limitations
of the physics engine. So take a look at Unity's
docs there if you're having trouble getting
to sleep.
Fantastic so let's just take a look back in
Unity and reiterate this a bit more. Now we
have ten bowling pins, they are all linked
to pin prefabs now or to this one pin prefab.
You can tell that by clicking through that
and seeing the word prefab up the top right
of the inspector. Let's take a look at a pin
a little more closely, maybe the head pin.
There it is, what you're seeing on there at
the moment in green is the pin collider and
that is a convex collider.
If you try and make it non-convex it actually
disappears altogether and that's because you
can't have a non-convex collider on something
that has a rigidbody on it; and you'll also
find when we do that that look the pin has
disappeared altogether and we have a red warning
at the bottom: Non-convex mesh colliders with
non-kinematic rigidbodies are no longer supported
in Unity 5. They added that error message
I think since I reported the bug. But a non-kinematic
rigidbody is a long way of saying something
that has a rigidbody on it and that it's not
kinematic which is our pin.
OK so the collider must be convex, it's an
optimisation issue. Which means that pins
won't quite collide exactly as you might expect
because you can see how they're going to collide.
They're going to collide as soon as they touch
this green extent. Remember that we have a
render mesh, which is a much much finer mesh
we need to zoom right in to see the triangles
on this one which is what gives it its much
more nuanced shape but a separate collider
mesh that must be convex.
I hope that that makes sense, that's how you
make pins collide with pins. Remember that
in future when you try and do some physics
and something with a mesh collider doesn't
collide with something else, it's probably
because you're not convex. You also may run
into the problem where you haven't got a sufficiently
simple model for your collider which is why
the pin we've given you has two separate meshes
with it; a collider and a render mesh. OK,
point sufficiently driven home I think I will
leave this slide on the screen for you about
convex meshes and I will look forward to seeing you on the next video.