Hi and welcome back. Now we are going to use
a render texture so we can have a top-down
camera looking at the pins. So in this video
we're going to create a render texture ready
for the camera output. read more about them
at Unity's docs there. Position a top-down
camera looking at the pins. then we'll create
a user interface panel and embed a "raw image”
with this render texture. Lots of new terms!
Render textures are a brand new feature to
the free version of Unity - they were always
available in Unity Pro but you can access
them for free now.
That's pretty cool right? So the first thing
that I'm going to do is just start tidying
up. I now have too many things in my root
here. so it's a good time to start putting
scripts into my scripts folder and other things
away as we need them. I'll just do that for
now. scripts and scenes is all we need for
now. Now scenes are so important to access
that I often prefix my scenes folder with
an underscore so I can quickly get to it because
it floats to the beginning. Right? So we also
have prefabs. Now remember that we ultimately
want everything prefabbed but the pins themselves
- each one of them is prefabbed.
Bowling pin ten probably wants to be named
bowling pin ten; but also we're going to want
to prefab the whole pin array - so why don't
we do that now quickly? We're just having
a tidy up before we move on. So now in our
prefab folder we not only have the pins themselves
we have our entire pin arrangement ready to
instantiate when we need to reset the pins.
Great. so that's blue. I like that. The floor
we don't need to prefab yet because in another
scene. if we had another scene of the game
we might have a completely different floor
but the ball. I think that the ball's worth
prefabbing for sure and the light and the
camera we'll leave for now.
So that's a little bit tidier isn't it? That's
fantastic so the floor is a material; so I'm
going to make a new folder called materials
and textures; or just textures for now. Now
I should let you know. there's another way
of finding things here in Unity - you can
organise by prefabs script etc. but we've
slightly broken the convention with this start
pack so that I can easily export all of these
different things though some of these things
are in different folders. right? You've got
start packs scripts and then you've got script
up in the assets and that might drive you
a bit nuts;
But. it's actually pretty cool because we
have multiple ways of categorising the same
thing and if you want to see all of your scripts
in one place which might be what you're hankering
after click over here in the top right of
assets on the search by type box button and
then click under script; and then look that's
going to aggregate all of your scripts in
one place. So actually organising by something
but the type in these folders is a good idea
because you can already show everything of
a type over here. we could see all materials
for instance and that will pull materials
from both this textures folder and from the
start pack. you get the idea?
So you think you've seen that before but there's
another tip for you. OK so to create this
render texture for you go to assets. go to
create. and then go down to render texture
- there you go. Assets / create / render texture.
Boom. there it is. and I'm going to call it
top camera. not going to bother with the space
in this case. there it is. looks a bit funny
but that's because nothing is streaming into
it. Don't worry about the settings for now.
let's just leave them default unless we want
to change anything which we don't right now.
Fantastic. so we have a texture ready for
the camera to render into. What I want you
to do now is to actually create this "top
down” camera. so I want you to create and
position a top view camera. put the camera
above the pins looking down. make the pins
fill about 80% of its view. set the target
texture to the TopCamera.renderTexture that
we just created and test that the game still
runs. You won't see any difference but just
make sure that your camera - your main camera
- still works. Go ahead. pause the video.
and do that now.
So welcome back. let's pop back into Unity
and figure out how to do this. So you need
to create yourself a new camera. now where
is that? It's in Gameobject / camera there
so do that. now I'm going to pop mine at the
top. and I'm going to call it top camera.
OK? There it is. OK now we need to position
this camera in the right place so. it's a
question of getting it over the pins. Well
one easy way to do that is to set its z distance
to 1829 wasn't it? Should be right over the
top of the pins and then we're going to need
to go into the rotate tool in the top left
here and point it downwards.
Now what's happening? How come this camera
isn't showing anything? Well. because it's
at a y position of -80. let's try putting
it at 100. one metre above. Ahh. more like
it. There it is. above. and you look in the
camera preview we're starting to get there
now. Obviously it needs to move back a little
bit further than that and so on. Now. do we
want it to be a perspective camera? Well that's
a good question. I'm not sure that I do want
it to be a perspective camera because it's
a bit weird. Let's try an orthographic camera.
Oh. kind of does the thing apart from of course
it is in completely the wrong scale now.
So let's move it up and that's not going to
help; why doesn't it help when you move an
orthographic camera upwards. anybody know?
Well that's because it has no perspective.
you can only adjust it by adjusting its size.
here you go. So make the camera orthographic
I suggest. move it back in z and rotate it
until it has a 90 degree rotation. so it's
an orthographic camera that's looking directly
down. then use the z co-ordinate. there you
go. You see. and then adjust the size.
So what I want you to adjust in this camera
is projection to orthographic. adjust the
size until about 80% of the screen is filled
with pins. Adjust the rotation so that it's
x rotation of 90 i.e. pointing straight down
on top of the pins. Z position wants to be
roughly in the middle of the pins. that's
going to be around about the 1870 mark. calculate
it precisely if you want; x = 0 would make
sense and then y well that doesn't actually
matter very much so let's put it a couple
of metres above; as long as it's above it
doesn't matter because it's an orthographic
camera you see how it's got a square projection
box?
It kind of looks like it's not above the pins
there but if you come to the right angle in
3D. practicing your movement. it actually
is right above the pins. Fantastic so we've
achieved the first bit of what we wanted to
do. what I also said I wanted you to do was
render out to a target texture because look.
notice right now if you try and play the game
it's all very well but where the hell's my
main camera gone? Why can't I see the main
camera? Well. you may try going to the main
camera and setting a tag of main camera - you'll
find it won't work.
You could disable the top camera sure. now
your game's back to normal but now your camera
doesn't work. I think you'll find what you
need to do to get this working is to get the
target texture rendering out to the top camera.
So this top camera here now no longer renders
to the game view but renders into your target
texture. Now your game gets its main camera
view back but this top - this target texture
is being rendered into. We just have to trust
that for now because we can't see the texture
just yet. that's going to come up in just
a second.
OK so let's make this camera - this top camera
render texture have somewhere to render to.
So I'm going to start by helping you to create
the user interface. and then I'm going to
challenge you to finish that but off. So what
do we start with? Well we need a UI canvas
to start with and that's your overall UI canvas.
so you may as well just leave it default.
Canvas and remember that it comes with an
event system so that's there ready to go.
now we're going to use a screen space camera
canvas this time. which means that it's relative
to the camera. it stays with the camera. You'll
see how that manifests in a moment.
So we have a screen space camera canvas like
that and it's sitting over here. which is
a bit of an odd position but we'll worry about
that in a moment. Before we can really see
what the camera is doing we need to create
ourselves within that a panel; we're going
to have a left panel which is going to be
the pins and the number of pins standing and
then the right panel on the right hand side
in perspective that shows us how our scores
are doing and all that. So create yourself
a panel and call it left panel. So at this
stage you should have a UI canvas with a left
panel subbed to it.
Then you can shrink down that left panel a
little bit by using the UI gripper tool like
this. and see the effect we're having in the
game window. You see how I have a panel on
the left hand side there? Now we can perfect
that later but that's a good start. If I am
to play the game. you see how that panel stays
with the ball? Cool we'll leave the grey cast
to this panel just for now. because that is
going to let us know where it is and then
we'll have another panel. we may as well do
it right now. called imaginatively right panel;
and I might just call the canvas UI canvas
so UI canvas with a right panel and a left
panel. Let's remove this right panel using
the UI gripper tool to the right there and
have a look at the game again.
So on the left I'm going to have a top-down
view of the pin and various other things and
on the right I'm going to have my scoring
system so you might want the left panel to
be wider than that - taller rather and the
right panel to also be taller. We'll make
the sizes equal later when we tweak the user
interface but you get the idea. Perfect so
it's not interfering with your view but it
is there waiting. Right so I've got a challenge
for you then now that we've set up the UI
I want you to do something. and here it is.
OK so here's the challenge for you. I want
you to set up the camera view user interface.
Create a game object UI raw image. position
it on the UI left panel. set the texture to
TopCamera.renderTexture and test that you
can see that top-down view inside. Have a
go. persist until you get this working if
you can. We want on the left hand panel to
see a permanent view of the top-down camera
when you hit the pins you should be able to
see it from above. Have a go. good luck. and
I'll see you in a moment.
Welcome back. so let's make this thing work.
Fantastic. so I said in the left panel we
needed to create ourselves a UI raw image
so let's do that and child it to the left
panel. There it is. now I'm going to pop mine
something like this. top of the left panel.
again we'll tweak all this later. I love these
UI tools. you see how they're helping us snap
etc.? I'm going to call it top view. there.
so I've called it top view and I've got a
raw image already and the texture I want is
the top camera texture so let's just drop
that in. Now push play.
So cool. look at this unity five feature watch
this. wow look. top down view of the pins
falling. What do you want? How cool is that?
OK so congratulations on getting this far
with the video. I hope that you're pleased
with the progress I certainly am. and we'll
look forward to seeing you shortly.