Welcome back. in this video we're going to
be improving the scaling of our User Interface.
So we will add a new UI panel. ready for a
swipe gesture. We will be launching our ball
either with a mouse or of your finger on a
touch device. We will set the scaling and
anchors for our UI panels and then make sure
that it all scales well. So over in our project
at the moment we have a UI like this where
we have a screen space overlay User interface
here and now it specifically doesn't align
with the world space because it is rendered
by the camera right over the top of everything
like that;
but you'll notice that if you maximise on
play and then you play your game ignore the
movement of the ball for a minute. what we're
interested in is these panels. You see they're
kind of ugly and they move around pretty randomly
and if I expand to the right this right panel
it's not sticking to the side of the screen;
it's kind of a mess. right? So. let's get
this sorted. The first thing that we're going
to do before we do anything else is add a
third panel to the system. So click on your
UI canvas. go to your game object / UI menu
and then add a new panel; that's what you're
looking for. game object / UI panel.
Perfect. so that adds another panel to the
User interface. Now this is going to be called
the touch input panel like that and I'm going
to put it to the top. just indicate to myself
that this wants to be top layer. Now it has
an image and it needs to keep an image with
it otherwise the event system won't pick up
our mouse movements in the subsequent lectures.
but what we want to do with this image is
actually remove this image so we have an image
script but no image; OK? Then you can set
your alpha to completely transparent. you
see the difference in the background there?
If we have fully alpha'd then we have white;
then of course we're not going to be able
to see through it. if we have 0 alpha then
we can see perfectly through that panel. So
this touch input panel there is in the next
section. in the next video. is going to be
used to detect the position of our mouse clicks
wherever we click on the screen and allow
us to have the right type of interface. So
that's that bit. Now what we need to start
doing is looking at the way that these panels
work. So let's start with the left panel.
The left panel if you use your 't' key or
your user interface control tool. you can
see that it's snapped to the left hand side
at the moment. of the game space;
but what it's not doing is scaling appropriately.
So let's start to get it to do that. Drag
this user interface so that it's about a third
of the width of the screen. being aware that
it depends on how your current screen is set
up. it depends how big your game window is;
because your game window is floating with
your scene window; but take about a third
of the screen. something like that. Make sure
that it's snapping to the background appropriately.
you could set the left and top positions to
zero. OK. perfect. now what we need to look
at is the anchors. so if you click on this
little icon here. what we actually want you
to do is stretch like that.
We want it to stretch on the left hand side.
Try that setting there. stretch attach to
the left. Go to the game window. leave maximise
on play on. hit play and then try dragging.
You see how that left panel is now sticking
to the left a lot better than it was before?
Perfect. OK so within the left panel we now
have a top view. and again that top view we
need to give a similar treatment to. There
it is inside the panel. it needs to be smaller
than it currently is. and we want it to stick.
something like that. and we want it stuck
to what. to the left hand side? Well I don't
know. try. Try anchoring it to the left. for
example with this setting here in your anchor
presets;
then go into your game and have a play. It's
OK. it disappears off the top if the thing's
too small. so this is what I want you to do
now. I want you to play with those settings
for the left panel and for the right panel
so that when you rescale the game window then
they work how you want them to for your game.
OK? That's what I want you to do now. So pause
the video and play with your UI anchoring.
and get to know what these buttons and controls
do. Don't worry about getting them perfect
now. we need to do a lot of tweaking later
when we actually put some things in here but
for now let's just get this roughly scaling
how we want it.
OK so go ahead and do that right now. OK.
welcome back. so I just want to make sure
that the main elements like the touch input
scales properly. Another way to do it is to
drag your inspector around because this will
change the size of your game window. So the
touch input seems to work. the left panel
as we rescale is working OK. it's not perfect
but we'll make it better later and the right
panel is kind of OK as well. let's try it
the other way. Ah they're working much better.
right and when we let go of the drag you see
how they’re re-scaling? Much better.
OK the only problem that I have is that my
top down view isn't quite anchoring how I
want it so let's choose a different anchor
maybe a top left anchor. let's see if that's
better for the top-down camera view. Yes.
much better look at that. Oops. I didn't need
the console there... great. that's much better.
Fantastic. so now we're ready to start getting
the game ready for touch input basically so
I'm going to turn off my maximise on play
and we'll be able to play in here eventually.
dragging in the middle but with the confidence
that if we rescale our screen that these panels
will work. so as a recap for this lesson what
we've done is we've gone through each of our
elements in the UI canvas and we've worked
on the anchors button. and it's a question
of how things scale and what they stick to
so that's what I want you to explore and play
with.
As I say get it sort of 80% right right now.
don't aim for 100% because we're going to
revisiting this once these panels are actually
fully populated with. there's going to be
a counter down here for how many pins are
standing. there'll be some control buttons
here for restarting the game. and on the right
hand side we'll have the score system basically
showing you which player is playing and what
the current frame scores and total scores
are. So that's the general plan for the game
and the whole screen will respond as a user
interface swipe input.
You could argue that this game might be better
as a portrait game. most bowling games are
portrait on the iPhones just because of the
nature and the shape of their lane but I'm
going to be a bit different here because I
quite like having a portrait style centre
section for the game and then a user interface
on the left and right; also it'll build better
for the web that way.
So congratulations on getting this far in
this video and I look forward to seeing you
=======
Welcome back, in this video we're going to
be improving the scaling of our User Interface.
So we will add a new UI panel, ready for a
swipe gesture. We will be launching our ball
either with a mouse or of your finger on a
touch device. We will set the scaling and
anchors for our UI panels and then make sure
that it all scales well. So over in our project
at the moment we have a UI like this where
we have a screen space overlay User interface
here and now it specifically doesn't align
with the world space because it is rendered
by the camera right over the top of everything
like that;
but you'll notice that if you maximise on
play and then you play your game ignore the
movement of the ball for a minute, what we're
interested in is these panels. You see they're
kind of ugly and they move around pretty randomly
and if I expand to the right this right panel
it's not sticking to the side of the screen;
it's kind of a mess, right? So, let's get
this sorted. The first thing that we're going
to do before we do anything else is add a
third panel to the system. So click on your
UI canvas, go to your game object / UI menu
and then add a new panel; that's what you're
looking for, game object / UI panel.
Perfect, so that adds another panel to the
User interface. Now this is going to be called
the touch input panel like that and I'm going
to put it to the top, just indicate to myself
that this wants to be top layer. Now it has
an image and it needs to keep an image with
it otherwise the event system won't pick up
our mouse movements in the subsequent lectures,
but what we want to do with this image is
actually remove this image so we have an image
script but no image; OK? Then you can set
your alpha to completely transparent, you
see the difference in the background there?
If we have fully alpha'd then we have white;
then of course we're not going to be able
to see through it, if we have 0 alpha then
we can see perfectly through that panel. So
this touch input panel there is in the next
section, in the next video, is going to be
used to detect the position of our mouse clicks
wherever we click on the screen and allow
us to have the right type of interface. So
that's that bit. Now what we need to start
doing is looking at the way that these panels
work. So let's start with the left panel.
The left panel if you use your 't' key or
your user interface control tool, you can
see that it's snapped to the left hand side
at the moment, of the game space;
but what it's not doing is scaling appropriately.
So let's start to get it to do that. Drag
this user interface so that it's about a third
of the width of the screen, being aware that
it depends on how your current screen is set
up, it depends how big your game window is;
because your game window is floating with
your scene window; but take about a third
of the screen, something like that. Make sure
that it's snapping to the background appropriately,
you could set the left and top positions to
zero. OK, perfect, now what we need to look
at is the anchors, so if you click on this
little icon here, what we actually want you
to do is stretch like that.
We want it to stretch on the left hand side.
Try that setting there, stretch attach to
the left. Go to the game window, leave maximise
on play on, hit play and then try dragging.
You see how that left panel is now sticking
to the left a lot better than it was before?
Perfect. OK so within the left panel we now
have a top view, and again that top view we
need to give a similar treatment to. There
it is inside the panel, it needs to be smaller
than it currently is, and we want it to stick,
something like that, and we want it stuck
to what, to the left hand side? Well I don't
know, try. Try anchoring it to the left, for
example with this setting here in your anchor
presets;
then go into your game and have a play. It's
OK, it disappears off the top if the thing's
too small, so this is what I want you to do
now. I want you to play with those settings
for the left panel and for the right panel
so that when you rescale the game window then
they work how you want them to for your game.
OK? That's what I want you to do now. So pause
the video and play with your UI anchoring,
and get to know what these buttons and controls
do. Don't worry about getting them perfect
now, we need to do a lot of tweaking later
when we actually put some things in here but
for now let's just get this roughly scaling
how we want it.
OK so go ahead and do that right now. OK,
welcome back, so I just want to make sure
that the main elements like the touch input
scales properly. Another way to do it is to
drag your inspector around because this will
change the size of your game window. So the
touch input seems to work, the left panel
as we rescale is working OK, it's not perfect
but we'll make it better later and the right
panel is kind of OK as well, let's try it
the other way. Ah they're working much better,
right and when we let go of the drag you see
how they’re re-scaling? Much better.
OK the only problem that I have is that my
top down view isn't quite anchoring how I
want it so let's choose a different anchor
maybe a top left anchor, let's see if that's
better for the top-down camera view. Yes,
much better look at that. Oops, I didn't need
the console there... great, that's much better.
Fantastic, so now we're ready to start getting
the game ready for touch input basically so
I'm going to turn off my maximise on play
and we'll be able to play in here eventually,
dragging in the middle but with the confidence
that if we rescale our screen that these panels
will work, so as a recap for this lesson what
we've done is we've gone through each of our
elements in the UI canvas and we've worked
on the anchors button, and it's a question
of how things scale and what they stick to
so that's what I want you to explore and play
with.
As I say get it sort of 80% right right now,
don't aim for 100% because we're going to
revisiting this once these panels are actually
fully populated with, there's going to be
a counter down here for how many pins are
standing, there'll be some control buttons
here for restarting the game, and on the right
hand side we'll have the score system basically
showing you which player is playing and what
the current frame scores and total scores
are. So that's the general plan for the game
and the whole screen will respond as a user
interface swipe input.
You could argue that this game might be better
as a portrait game, most bowling games are
portrait on the iPhones just because of the
nature and the shape of their lane but I'm
going to be a bit different here because I
quite like having a portrait style centre
section for the game and then a user interface
on the left and right; also it'll build better
for the web that way.
So congratulations on getting this far in
this video and I look forward to seeing you
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1:Unity/Section8/BM12 Improve UI scaling.srt
soon.