Welcome back, so now we're going to add some
arrows so we can nudge the start position
of the ball. We'll add another UI panel at
the bottom of the screen; ensure that this
panel occludes the touch input panel, so that
we are either moving left or right or we are
starting our drag so there's no confusion;
add two arrows for moving the ball left and
right and write a simple method to allow this
moving of the ball only at the start. So let's
start off with this UI panel, I'll get you
going and then I'd like you to tweak it and
finish it.
So to reinforce our learning here around these
panels, I'm going to put another panel here
at the bottom. So let's take a look here at
our UI. First I'm noticing that my left hand
panel here is not snapped into the space here
so if I just drag I can snap to the bottom
like that that's great. So while I'm here
this would be a good time to make sure that
both panels are the same width, so let's say
a hundred and eighty pixels, and if you see
a really weird figure like this, something
with an e minus six that means ten to the
minus six; 0.000006 that's tiny. Basically
that means zero so set it to zero, same as
the top position.
Now if it won't actually snap to zero that's
fine but I just want to let you know what
this e means in here. It's a tiny number,
it's called standard form. So 180 pixels,
0, that's fine, and let's again snap that
to the right. Alright, so we're ready to put
another panel in here. So UI canvas, gameobject,
UI and panel, that's what we're trying to
do right there like that and there comes a
big panel. Now as long as you're in this UI
edit mode or the 't' key you're going to be
able to move and snap this UI panel to the
bottom here.
I love the way that the UI system works, so
let's double click on it. That'll focus it
and we'll be able to take a little more of
a look. So great, we have that panel there
let's call it arrows and now the order in
the hierarchy we will talk about in a minute.
I'm going to put it under touch input but
this is going to affect what gets clicked
first so let's get the rest of that general
structure right and then we'll worry about
that. So if you look in your assets pack in
your start pack then you will find that I
have updated the start pack recently and you
will find that if you go to Import package
/ custom package and then point it to the
start pack then anything that's not already
in it will show up like this and there'll
be an arrow.png.
So go ahead and import that arrow from the
start pack and then if you look at that arrow
let's take a look, how's it come in has it
come in as a sprite or a texture for you?
Well whatever it has come in as we want it
to be a sprite 2D and UI sprite under the
texture type. So just set that there, that's
great. Now so we have arrows, what we want
to do on the arrows panel is have two images,
left and right, maybe here and here for these
two different arrows. So create a sub-object,
gameobject / UI / image like that and if it
doesn't already sub itself to arrows then
drag it under arrows. Call one of them right
and then the image itself you can see it here,
it has the wrong sprite so give it the arrow
sprite.
We're nearly there, we need this to be inside
this panel and sensibly sized so let's double
click to focus on it, careful of the pivot
point drag the right thing, the whole thing
that's it. We're actually going to put mine
around here now, in terms of positioning these
arrows left and right if you click on them
and hold down shift as it says here there's
set pivot we want the pivot to be central
because that way this position in x if you
look in the inspector is the number of pixels
from this centre point. So let's say it's
50 pixels from the centre point, something
like that.
That means that when we put the left arrow
in which I'm going to do by duplicating the
right arrow and calling one left - now as
a hint we can use a negative x scale - a scale
of minus 1 like we did in glitch garden to
turn that arrow around then we rough drag
it to where we want it to be; but because
our pivot point is central we can actually
precisely position it by just saying minus
fifty there. I hope that that makes sense.
The final thing that we can do with both the
left and the right element there is make them
scale like this.
Stretch in both x and y and the effect that
that will have is to, when you click play
and look at this game window, let's maximise
on play actually, we want to make sure that
this bottom panel is behaving itself so as
far as I'm concerned that is not behaving
itself right now, you see how big these arrows
are and how this bottom panel is the wrong
size? There you go, started behaving now,
but this is going to be your challenge. I'm
going to do it after the challenge, but your
challenge is to finish off setting up the
UI panel because again, no good just watching
me right?
So get the arrows panel finished. Get scaling
how you want it; set anchor and pivot points.
Wire up to a method in the drag start script
called move start to a particular place so
the signature is MoveStart(float xNudge) and
that method in DragStart.cs should only log
to the console for now the position that you
are going to be moving to. Don't actually
do anything else with it and then ensure that
this doesn't conflict with your swipe gesture
when you click on an arrow you should be logging
MoveStart right or MoveStart left.
So before you do that challenge just let me
show you what I mean by that; we're going
to have an event system, again on our arrows
panel, and then; sorry on each of our left
and right arrows we're going to have a new
event system, remember how we had that before,
event trigger and then that's going to call
a method on drag start - on the ball and set
an amount to nudge left or right, maybe positive
five on the right arrow and negative five
on the left arrow or something, that's what
I mean by that. That's what I want you to
finish setting up now, is the arrows panel,
but without actually writing the rest of the
MoveStart method. Pause the video, have ago
at that now, and see if you can get it logging
out plus five and minus five when you click
the arrows.
OK welcome back, so let's take a look at what's
up with this panel. So back in the scene view
firstly the arrows panel itself, how is it
stretching and scaling versus how do we want
it to stretch and scale? Well I think that
we want it to be tied to the bottom of the
screen and stretching like so, you see this
one here? I think that that's the stretching
mode that we want, let's take a look. Now
the panel is looking half sensible. The panel
itself is fine, you see the panel working
nicely? What aren’t working nicely right
now are the arrows inside that panel.
So they look OK at this scale, just about,
but they don't look so clever at other scales.
So what's going on with our arrows? It's just
a question of working out what their scaling
rules are. So we had them stretching, but
is stretching doing the trick? Is that working
how we want them to? Maybe not, maybe they
just need to be relative to the centre. It's
a question of experimenting with these things.
Before I fine adjust them let's take a look
at that and see if that behaves better; yeah
I would say that that is better.
Yeah so the arrows just need a fine adjustment
of size and shape. So we've settled on an
anchor of centre for the left and right arrows.
So I'm just going to resize these arrows a
little bit like this, I may as well remember
the width and the height, or I can just copy
the component values once I'm happy with it
so I could put this one here for example,
copy component I could go to the left arrow,
paste component values, when I do that of
course it's going to sit right on top of this
component arrow so I need to make the two
changes. Minus one for the x scale to switch
it round, and then of course the x position
also needs to be minus compared to the centre.
So there's an example of how you get perfectly
positioned thingies. Cool so now on our ball
remember we have a DragLaunch script. I said
we wanted a new method called move start so
public void MoveStart (float amount) now it's
not going to do the move for now, it's just
going to Debug.Log ball moved and then add
in the amount. That's what I said we should
do in the challenge. SO you make a public
void MoveStart taking in a number of pixels
to move which means that our right arrow can
have added to it an event trigger just like
we did before;
and when we say pointer down it's going to
look at the ball, find its DragLaunch method
and call MoveStart with, say, five pixels
right. Fantastic, now we do the same thing
with the left. Now we could just copy this
component again, paste the component onto
the left arrow and just set the drag movement
to minus five. Let's see what happens now.
A couple of things that we need to check.
Firstly is that clicking down here doesn't
start the drag, good it doesn't and secondly
is ball moved five and ball moved minus five.
That works. Now, one word of warning, if your
arrows element was above your touch input
element in the canvas now look what happens.
You see? It's preferentially, it's assuming
you're clicking the arrows element so you
actually want the thing that you want above
above in the hierarchy. So the arrows want
to sit over the touch input so slightly confusingly
it's below it in the hierarchy, that's just
the default way that it sorts. So it'll be
read from the bottom up this list if you like.
So there's no 3 dimensional functionality
of that, you can't see it in 3D - well you
could move things around in 3D but the reliable
way is to get the hierarchy order correct.
So now we can g plus five and minus five.
Fantastic I hope that makes sense, we now
have a signal that allows us to nudge our
ball and a nicely scaling UI - that's another
challenge for you; get the start position
working. Approach it however you like but
the goal is to be able to drag or nudge the
ball left and right; only allow moving before
the ball is launched so we're going to have
to have some indication - some flag - to say
that the ball is not launched or is in play;
and clamp the ball within the lane width,
so when we click those arrows left and right
we want to make sure that that ball can't
leave the lane.
So go ahead, pause the video, and get the
rest of that working now. OK welcome back.
So we've done quite well. We've got DragLaunch
here, we know how much we're moving it so
why don't we go ahead and do it? Ball.transform
now there's a useful method here called translate
and then we can say new Vector3 amount comma
zero comma zero; and if you look up that method
in Unity's docs you'll see that it just translates
this transform without making an intermediate
method or intermediate variable. So let's
take a look and see if this works.
There you go. Now you might want to change
those five pixels to something else but that's
fine now. If we try dragging from here nothing
happens, if we drag from off that bottom bar
it works but we can nudge while we're in play
which is no good. So we need to supress the
nudging when we are in play. Now, this is
where we have to think about responsibility.
Who is responsible? Which object? Is it the
ball or the DragLaunch that's responsible
for knowing whether the ball is in play? Well
I would suggest that it's a private property
of the ball called inPlay and at start it
is false.
OK, or you could make it a public property
of inPlay and query it here so you have a
few decisions about how you talk to each other;
you either make this MoveStart method - you
could put it onto the ball and say is it OK
for something to move the ball? Well I would
say actually that it is OK to have a public
MoveStart on the ball; it's kind of a moveStart
request because the ball is going to ignore
it if it's in play. So that might be the simplest
thing rather than having component to component
communication is that our UI talks directly
to the ball, that we change our mind.
Another option is that our DragLaunch calls
a method on the ball but that's a little bit
around the houses. Another option is that
we have a public ball in play that we can
read from the DragLaunch script. I don't know
which way you want to do it, it's really the
flick of a coin, there are consequences to
doing it each way; want to make sure that
things are singularly responsible for what
they are doing, but I think that as the DragLaunch
script already launches the ball I think that
there's no harm in it also moving the start
position.
So I'm going to go down the public ball inPlay
= false route. So now from the outside of
the ball we can see if it's in play or not
which I think it reasonable. We started off
as not in play and then of course on launch
the first thing that we do is say in Play
= true. Now on a subsequent launch we'll have
to add more code to this but let's see how
it goes, we can always refactor later. The
key here now is that on DragLaunch we only
do this if not in play. Now I always put a
space after my exclamation mark because it's
really hard to see an exclamation mark otherwise.
The other way that you could write this is
if inPlay == false but that's a bit of a weird
thing to do but it reads more clearly, you
can actually see that I'm saying if it's not
in play. So I think in this case that I'm
going to do that but bear in mind you would
normally just go exclamation mark in play
like that. But you see that that's very easy
to miss that exclamation mark even if we put
a space, even if we put two spaces. Two spaces
does it, if not in play. You get the idea,
there are two options. That or ball.inPlay
== false. I'm going to stick with this for
now.
There's always lots of ways of doing things.
So only if the ball is not in play do we do
this. Let's see if that's helped. Now we can
nudge but if we flick and then try and do
it... well OK my flick was a bit weird then,
let's just do a standard kind of flick down
there and then try and nudge and it won't.
Perfect! So a lot of talking, a lot of doing
but look we've got extra UI elements now that
automatically scale as the screen space changes
and, you know not perfectly but there's a
finite size of these arrows, if the screen
space is too small then obviously it's going
to break down but it works pretty well.
We've got the idea of all of these elements
kind of sticking together, and we have a simple
way of moving the ball left and right. Now
you may have said why don't we drag the ball?
Well you can only do one type of drag. You're
either dragging the ball to launch it or you're
dragging it to move it. If you have two types
of drags then that's really confusing. So
you could drag maybe with two fingers but
why make it that complicated? I think in this
instance, you know in a real bowling lane
you kind of stand or you start on a particular
marker with your feet, so setting this as
a kind of one off is fine;
and then all the skill is in dragging in the
correct way. Now bear in mind that this touch
system right now is nothing to do with the
lane. If I start here and I want it to go
straight down the lane or slightly right I
have to say go from here to just slightly
right of that above so I need to do something
like that. So it's actually pretty skill based
which I quite like. So there you go, we have
the full control system that we need for the
ball at the moment except spin, and we'll
deal with spin in a subsequent video. So congratulations
on getting this far, if you did all the challenges.
I hope that the code makes sense for you,
we've decided to leave the movement in DragLaunch
just because it's already responsible for
everything to do with dragging and launching
the ball and the only change that we've made
to the ball is a public Boolean to say that
it's in play or not. As a general note Boolean
flags like this mean that there's a design
issue so use them carefully, don't use too
many Boolean flags, we'll show you lots of
other options later. OK, cool, see you soon.