Hey hey hey welcome back. So now we're going
to talk about working around nested prefabs.
Why are we going to talk about that? Well.
let's take a look. So we have this animation
happening right now. remember the swiper comes
down and wipes away all of the pins which
could include pins that have fallen over and
some of the pins could have been standing;
and you know half way through a bowling game
you want to clear away pins doing a tidy;
clear away pins that have fallen over but
lift up pins that are still standing. Now
at the moment this system is just going to
swipe everything out of the way.
So there are two approaches for differentiating
between pins that are still standing and pins
that aren’t. One would be to bring some
physical object down into the scene. Some
sort of rig that attaches just like a pinsetter
in a bowling game that attaches to the top
of the pins and lifts that ones that are still
standing up. That's an option. but we're going
to need to count the number of pins anyway
using code for the scoring. so we may as well
write some code to detect the pins that are
standing. So the first bit of code needs to
sit on the pin itself. It's a bit of code
that determines for a given pin whether it's
vertical or not vertical.
So this point brings us to talking about prefabs
because take a look at this. Click on prefabs
in your assets. and maybe open up pins in
your hierarchy. Now stop the game playing.
the reason that you can't see any pins right
now is that they've all fallen off to infinity.
Perfect. So there's your assembly of pins
and it’s full of ten pins but they’re
not your bowling pin prefab. We have a pins
assembly here full of pins and then we have
a bowling pin prefab and these guys unfortunately
are now nested prefabs. They are not this
bowling pin prefab inside of there. in fact
you can prove that by just deleting your actual
bowling pin prefab. Yep. delete it.
Why? Because we never want two places for
things. Look if you went in to what you thought
was the sole place for the mass of the bowling
pin and maybe made it 10 kg here look inside
the pin assembly. still 1.53. this guy is
not linked to these guys. delete it. OK. you
got the point. Now that that's deleted how
do we add something common to all of these
pins? Well. there are lots of solutions to
nested prefabs but in this case we've only
got 10 pins so a simple solution is this.
Select all pins in a pin assembly. We're not
selecting the guys up here because these are
linked to this prefab assembly. so we want
to select the thing in assets and then add
a new script - call it pin. Simple as that.
Now every one of these guys has a pin script
on it now. and that's a valid way to do it
when you only have 10 things. Just remember
in future that if you want to change the mass
or drag or any of the properties of the pins
you need to change all of them by selecting
all of them. you cannot simply do it by changing
a prefab I'm afraid. OK. now we have a pin
script available let's look at what we're
going to be doing in this lecture. We've talked
about how unity does not support nested prefabs.
I've warned you that the pins in the pins
assembly are unlinked. Now. we're going to
add. well we have already added a pin.cs script
to the right places.
So we need to talk about a method called transform.euler
angles which we're going to use to determine
if the pins are upright. then we’re going
to write the necessary code to determine that
the pins are standing. Cool. so I'll start
you off on this script. on this journey. and
then you can finish off yourself. So back
in Unity let's go into that pin script. which
is the same script on all of the pins inside
the pin assembly. So the pin script is like
a prefab. it's a script that you only have
to edit ion one place. there's silver lining
in this no nested prefab mess. OK. so here
we go. We have now the pin.cs script and what
we're going to want to do here is make this
have a couple of methods and a couple of properties.
So let me show you what your challenge is.
So your challenge is to detect if the pins
are standing; I want you to add a public float
standing threshold to this pins.cs that's
going to be a floating point number in degrees
of our threshold beyond which if they're further
away from the vertical than that then they're
no longer standing. We want a method called
public bool that's going to return true if
the transform is rotated less from the threshold
than vertical and it returns false otherwise.
You get the idea? We have a property that
the designer can tweak to do with the standing
threshold - how upright they need to be 0
and then we have a method that we can call
from the outside that asks if the pin is standing.
So go ahead. pause the video and see if you
can write this code right now especially given
the hint that I gave you about the transform.eulerangles.
OK welcome back. let's take a look at how
to get this done then. So into your pin script.
so firstly I told you how to do the first
bit. I absolutely gave it to you on a plate.
we said that it was going to be public float
standing threshold. Perfect. now do you give
this a value now. good question? If you do
give it a value here like three degrees then
that’s a good starting point for your designer
but remember that anything that is done in
the inspector over-rides this and that can
be confusing.
Let's take a look. Go into one of the pins
and because it' linked to the pin prefab array
you will find that it does have a script on
it and it has a standing threshold of three.
Another warning for you here. if you were
to change say this pin’s threshold to five
a couple of things - it goes bold. it's different
to the standard value - to the prefab value
- doesn't mean that it's different to the
script value. it's different to the value
here in this prefab but of course pin 6 is
still 3 degrees. and all of the pins in here
are still at 3 degrees. So slightly awkwardly
for your designer or for you with your designer
hat on what you really need to be doing is
selecting all of these and if you need to
change it to say 5 degrees then do it there.
Now all of these guys will be 5 degrees. OK
but bear in mind the one you change before
is bold you're going to need to revert it
back to the prefab if you want it to always
keep the same value. So this is a bit messy
now. we need to make sure that anything that
we change about pins we need to change by
selecting all of the pins in the prefab array.
and remember that this 5 degree is what over-write
whatever's in your code. But having a sensible
starting point is probably a good idea for
your designer. Great. OK. so the next thing
that we're going to do is to write a method.
alright?
and we gave you the signature of that method
so let's just get on and write it. It's going
to be called public. because we want to be
able to call it from the outside. bool because
it returns a Boolean. IsStanding capitalised
like this because we're good and like to write
nice code. So. how are we going to do this?
Well. firstly we need to get some simple representation
of the rotation of the pin so how are we going
to do that? Well. why don't we try printing
transform.rotation for a start? For a given
pin alright?
Now it’s going to print it for all of these
pins so that’s going to create a bit of
a mess for you in your console but that’s
OK for now we can do things about that in
a minute. Look. we have an error. Not all
code paths return a value. So now because
it's is a method of signature bool. we need
to return something so let’s just return
true. Click play. let's look at the console
what do we get out. Absolutely nothing so
why are we getting nothing out? Good question.
because we're never calling the IsStanding
method so if you call it from update or even
so we don't make a mess just call it from
start. Here we go. so call isStanding pops
up here. prints out the rotation.
Let's look at it. what do we get. Oh. we get
a 0.0.0 thingy. Ok. well you'd think that
that's OK wouldn't you? But. let's take a
look at a pin. let's rotate it by a known
amount by say the z axis. say 5 degrees OK.
so that's rotated 5 degrees in z. pin number
one. Now let's play the game. Let's find the
odd one out. and you'll notice that there
is no odd one out. how come’s that? Now
let's make sure that we're looking at the
right pins. so what you can do here of course
is just prefix name pin which will tell you
the name of the object plus the transform.
let's try that. so now we get the name of
the pin in front; bowling pin one. hmm yet
I'm sure that at the start. if we look at
it carefully. if we pause and play.
Look at bowling pin one. it's definitely got
some rotation in the z axis. 5 degrees. there
it is; and yet it's printed here to say it
has no rotation. why what's going on there?
Well. if you were to look at the docs of rotation
you would find that rotation is stored as
something called a quaternion and they are
horrible complex number based thingies that
we don't need to dig into the details of right
now. What I can tell you is that there's a
nice method called eulerAngles that looks
like that .eulerAngles and that will turn
it into a comprehensible vector. Let's try
again.
Play. pause and look. 0.0.5 x. y. z. 5 degree
rotation was the offset we gave this pin.
there it is matching that. OK? Perfect. so
just to convince you. if we tilted it say
30 degrees in the x axis and played and paused
there it is. 30x. 0y. 0z perfect. so that's
the method that we need. dot eulerAngles is
what we need here. so that gives us the rotation
in comprehensible angles of our pin. So why
not just capture that? That's a useful thing
to have in a variable. Vector3 and then what
shall we call it? Let's call it something
like rotation in Euler or it could be just
rotation but just to stress the point I'll
call it rotation in Euler equals that thing
there. OK which we just discovered by logging
and we know we're happy. OK now we have some
more code to write.
Let's think about what the departure point
from x and the departure from vertical in
z is. why x and z go ahead and look at the
pin again. it's the x axis that is this way.
sorry the z axis is that tilt there and the
x axis is this tilt here. we're not interested
in rotation around the y axis. pins only fall
over when they go into x or z. OK. so we need
x and z's departure from the vertical. So
what is the departure in x? So let's go float.
tiltInX now what does that equal? Well let’s
just try saying rotationInEuler.x and see
how that goes. and while we're here let's
boldly do the same thing for z. and why don't
we just print tiltInX plus - concatenate the
two together - plus tiltInZ.
OK let's see what we get out of this. 0.0.0.
fine which is what you'd expect because none
of these pins are tilted. let's tilt this.
what is this. 8 in x and 12ish in z let's
see what we get now.
Now what it's doing is a literal plus here
coming out of this tilt in x and tilt in y
are actually floats. so we're getting a literal
plus going on here so if we actually put a
string in the middle of this then now this
whole operator should evaluate to a string.
let's see what happens there.
Better. we get 351.5 degrees and 347.2 degrees.
So what's all that about? Well. we've departed
from the - well there's it's rotation. it's
just said that rotating a negative in the
x. so like saying that 8 degrees rotation
in x is a bit like the same as -352 in x Ok
so if we say 10 and 20 let's see what result
we get. 10 and 20 yeah? So that's fine. we
are now reading its departure from vertical
and because my pins are vertically orientated
when they are at 0.0.0 transform rotation
then these figures are correct that’s cool.
We have our tiltInX and tiltInY. so but how
about if it were tilted the other way? Well.
how about if it was tilted negative like this?
Then we're going to have a negative tilt but
we don't care which way it's tilted. any tilt's
a tilt. So what you can use is something called
Mathf.abs like this and what that will do
for you is it will return the absolute value.
So minus 3 becomes the same as 3. OK? If I
can spell Mathf properly. Perfect. so now
we have a couple of values if we watch them
where even if it's tilted in the negative
x look at the value we get out. we get 348.53
in this case. which is a bit odd so let's
go minus 10 instead. see what we get now.
350. you see how 350 degrees. i.e. ten less
than 360 is the same as -10 so that may catch
us out but that's OK 350 is still a huge tilt.
what I think we need to do is look at the
logic next and then debug from there. So we're
basically saying that if the tiltInX is less
than the tilt threshold. or the standingThreshold
&&which is a logical and. the tiltInZ is less
than the standingThreshold; my autocomplete
has temporarily given up. then we would return
true. i.e. the pin is standing. else we return
false.
Now every frame let's just print for a given
pin whether it's standing or not. So print
name plus isStanding and that should evaluate
to a string plus a Boolean which will then
print out as a string. i.e. true or false.
let's try it. I have a build error. so where
is my build error. let's take a look. Standing
threshold. so I spelt standingThreshold so
now when we run. and we've corrected all of
our errors you can see now at the start pin
one was not considered to be standing but
the rest of them were which is ideal. it's
great.
So I'm going to go ahead and leave pin one
standing upright now at the start. and then
what I'm going to do is just change this call
to IsStanding from the start to update so
that it updates every frame; so there we are
we're calling IsStanding every update. let's
see what happens. If I collapse the console
what's happening? See. we're getting a load
of changes now. that's good. So that's encouraging.
we're starting off with all of the pins logging
here to IsStanding is true and very quickly
we're starting to get some of them logging
as false and eventually all of them are logging
out to the false and all of the true lines
are stopped.
So that looks pretty encouraging to me. Let's
also try bowling the ball down the lane. a
little bit. now if you want that swiper to
stop by the way then you just go in to your
animator for your lane swiper. and this transition
here just turn has exit time off then it will
no longer do that. So it sits in idle the
whole time. So let's see. where's the console?
If by the way you want to see this console
more clearly you could always just bring it
over on the right here. or you can see the
full height of it; and if you clear the console
and play. and leave it on collapse. we get
quite a clear indication.
We had a few pins briefly saying that they
were out of threshold for some reason but
now they're all settled down to correct and
true. and standing. now let's try firing the
ball. see if I can actually get a hit. Oh
at least hit one. there you go so which pin
number was that? That was pin number ten.
Which is no longer logging true. it's now
logging false. Great. It looks on the surface
like the standing code is working. Let's take
a look at it. make sure we understand it.
we grab the EulerAngles. we grab the absolute
value of their rotation in x and z and then
we say that if the absolute value is less
than the threshold. whatever it's set to.
remembering that that's over-ridden in the
inspector. then the thing is no longer standing.
Final thing that I'm going to do is to make
sure that it's the same for all of them in
the inspector. to be absolutely sure you need
to select all of your pins. set the value
here. but that doesn't guarantee it because
your actual instantiated pins here in the
scene in your case. the ones that started
here. may have a different value. Later we
won't have pins in the scene in the start.
we will always instantiate them. Then we know
that we're getting the fresh values off these
prefabs but otherwise you may need to go through
here and check your standing threshold in
the hierarchy.
Cool. so quite a complex lecture but I hope
that you understand why. how we can detect
these pins standing vertically now and see
you soon.