Hey guys and girls, just a quick video from me
to say, well done and carry on! I
know that at this stage in the course, these videos are quite long
and the topic is quite complete, but please bear with us,
I'm trying to keep these as concise as I can. There's
just a lot to cover and you're about to dive into
a sequence of two videos, that cover basically the same
thing, because it's quite a large lump. But after another five
or six videos, the average lecture length is going to start
dropping again and the going will get a little bit easier. So
literally, I've just dived in to break up this large section of
long videos and say, well done! This is great
stuff you're learning here! I'm seeing the results in the discussions,
please persists with it. If you're really struggling,
remember there's always the strategy of
just overviewing the content, kind of rushing through it or just watching
it the first time and then coming back and doing it,
filling in every bit of detail. Remember, you can overview,
then in view to all the details, and then, review.
I certainly have had a tendency, in the past, to want to read a book from the beginning
to end, like you'd read a novel so you don't ruin it,
but of course, with learning it's actually better
sometimes to overview the map, like you would do
the outside of a jigsaw puzzle, before you go in and fill in
the details. So, do just watch some videos without doing anything,
if you feel like a break and then come back, or just plow on, but either way,
congratulate yourself! You're doing great! And I'll see you back in the
videos!