Welcome back fine people. So this video is
all about detecting that the pins have settled.
In this video we're going to use the PinSetter's
trigger collider to detect the ball, we're
only going to start counting upright pins
when the ball enters that box, we're going
to detect when pins have stopped wobbling
and then update the pin count display to green
and we're going to have an instance variable
on the PinSetter.cs script called lastStandingCount
and we're going to set lastStandingCount to
-1 when they've settled.
Now some of you programmers are going to wince
when I do this and I somewhat agree with you,
minus one is not an ideal way of doing things
because we are encoding semantic information
in arbitrary numbers that we've picked but
it does make for the rest of the code being
relatively simple and I want to show you this
as both a solution and a warning. So let's
start by just taking a look at where we are.
We currently have the display count - firstly
it's always updating so if the wind were to
blow right now and the pins wobbled this thing
would change.
What I want to happen is for the display to
only start updating when the ball's in the
box and then I also want it to detect when
the balls have stopped wobbling - these three
guys that are still standing here - and to
actually settle on a value of say three. So
that's the objective of this video, let's
get ahead and do it. But, of course in our
standard style it's going to be your job to
get this going. So I want you to add to the
PinSetter.cs script, set the pin count to
red when the ball enters the box; the PinSetter.cs
script is attached to an object called PinSetter
and it has a collider on it with a trigger.
So use that to set that text to red; the Pin
Count. Secondly, set the ballEnteredBox instance
- well we don't have one yet so I want you
to create a ballEnteredBox instance variable
which is a variable at the top of PinSetter.cs
and set that to true when the ball enters
the box, and then destroy pins when they leave
the box as well. This is a new way of creating
a shredder, this is a shredder where things
get destroyed on exit.
So have a go at all that, see if you can get
that working. You'll know it’s working simply
because the pin count will go red the moment
the ball enters the end of the play space
and you will also see the pins when they fly
out of the box disappearing. So have a go,
see how you get on. Are you waiting for me
to carry on or are you pausing the video?
I'm sure that you're pausing the video by
now. Fantastic, so let's get on with this
and write some code shall we?
Let's go into PinSetter firstly and intercept
our message. So the message is going to be
passed when a trigger happens - of course
you know this by now is the void OnTriggerEnter
we'll go with first. Now you get no help with
this so you must spell it properly and then
on a trigger enter we get a collider not a
collision right? Because triggers are specifically
disabling collisions and there you go. So
OnTriggerEnter collider collider now it's
always with these triggers and things a good
idea to start by just printing to the console.
So just trigger will do for now. This is the
sort of log entry you want to remove quite
quickly but let's just do that. Now while
I'm here by the way this top camera, I said
earlier that we could arrange it into the
PinSetter which is in turn in the lane, is
it worth it? Is that complexity, three levels
of hierarchy worth it? No. So if you make
a mistake like that just reverse it, I'm going
to put Top camera right back at the top, and
now when I click on PinSetter I don't get
the ugly camera gizmos. OK? Fine, so there's
the PinSetter. It has a collider on it, it
is a box collider and it is a trigger collider
crucially. So what should happen in theory
when the ball gets into that box is, well,
we're getting trigger, trigger, trigger trigger
triggered all the time. Why are we getting
eleven triggers? Ten may make sense, why eleven?
Not sure why it's eleven, oh yes I am, I know
why it's eleven.
Why is it eleven? OK we've got eleven collisions
because if you look at the end of the play
space we've got eleven things in it, ten pins
and a swiper, and it's collided with all of
them. So first thing that we want to do is
to create some differentiation. We want to
say well actually we only care about this
trigger when we actually hit a ball. So how
are we going to do that? Well I am going to
break it down for you. We're going to say
that the gameObject, which is the thing that
we hit and it could be anything = collider
that's passed into this message dot gameObject,
so we take the gameObject off this collider
here, that's passed in by the engine, we take
it, we look at its gameObject component assign
it to a variable here and store it.
It's a gameObject. Fantastic, so now we can
say, actually let's put a comment, ball enters
play box. OK fantastic. Now we can say if
thingHit.GetComponent() now, if that
succeeds then this whole method here will
return true because yes, I've found a ball.
OK so only in this case do we print triggered
and actually triggered is too generic now
so we want to say Ball entered box or something
like that. Fantastic. Let's test that logic,
let's make sure that we now differentiate
and we only get a trigger when the ball has
entered the box.
So firstly at the start, if we were clearing
on play - so let's just clear the console
- start again, make sure your clear on play
is on otherwise you'll be seeing previous
error messages and believing that you haven't
fixed them. Perfect, so there's no triggers
going on right now, we there are but none
of them are of type ball, where the ball is
intersecting, so we're not getting any logs
and this is kind of building the code from
the inside out. OK Iaunched the ball a little
slow but in a moment, watch the console, Is
it going to make it?
Yeah, ball entered box, perfect. Alright?
So we are now detecting that the ball enters
the box. Always a good plan to do that before
you start writing the actual code. So I said
that we wanted a ballEnteredBox = true instance
variable, of course ballEnteredBox doesn't
exist yet, so let's go to the top and make
it a... shall we make it public or private?
Hmm I'm going to make it private, I don't
really want things from the outside to be
able to change it. If in doubt, make things
private. You can always make things public
later.
It's a bool, b double o l and it's called
ball, b a l l entered box so we have a Boolean
which is the ball entered the box and by default
when we declare it is should be false because
it hasn't entered the box yet. Fantastic so
when we hit the ball, we said that the ball
entered the box is true, that's the first
thing that we wanted to do, and the other
thing is we want to make this standingDisplay.color,
we can go straight to the colour because this
standingDisplay is a piece of text so we can
go straight to colour = color, by the way
how would you know that? Well you'd hit the
dot and you'd start typing color and you'd
realise it was there and you'd have a go.
Or if you were somewhat more systematic you
would look at the documents for the text type.
Either way equals color.red, comme ça. Perfect.
Shall we have a go? See what it does? Then
we'll go back and show you the code in a minute
in case I went too fast for you. No! Don't
go off the edge, gutter ball! I think it's
going to work, red, and nine, perfect. So
this is a tentative value of nine and that's
exactly what we wanted there. So that's the
code that I used to achieve that result, relatively
simple. Cool, let's go back to the challenge
slide and just have a look.
I also said we want to destroy the pins when
they leave the box. That's the bottom element
of that challenge. So how are we going to
do that? Well, let's use the void OnTriggerExit,
again do we need the collider? Because we
can intercept on trigger exit like that. If
you don't need the collider don't use the
collider but we do need the collider because
we need to know that it's a pin that has left
so let's take the collider, it's going to
give it to us but you don't have to every
time, and let's do exactly the same thing.
It's not really a thing hit in this case but
we can still use this line and we can just
call it thing left instead of thing hit right?
Because it's not hitting anything. So what
has left this box? Well, if thingLeft.GetComponent()
so it
the thing that left. Cool, hey? I love it
when code reads like English, like Hannibal
from the A-Team I love it when a plan comes
together, well I love it when code reads like
English, I'm just sad like that,
OK let's see if it works, I'm going to have
to bowl straight this time. Let's have a go,
I'm going to have to knock the pins with some
velocity otherwise the pins will never leave
the play space. Was that any good? Maybe,
I'll start again. I'm clearly not skilled
enough at my own game yet. No! See it's quite
interesting because the faster you try and
drag it the harder it is to be accurate which
is exactly what we want.
We hit the pins, boom, now watch them carefully,
do they disappear? Not really, I'm not really
seeing them disappear, I'm not feeling it,
so what's going wrong there? OK the pins are
not being destroyed, now, guess what I didn't
do this time? I didn't break it down, did
I? I didn't for example do any logs here.
So start at the higher level let's just go
print something left, and make sure the OnTriggerExit
is even happening. So let's do that now. So
I gave you the advice of using logs, and then
I didn't take my own advice and then I paid
the consequences, OK so something left, and
it looks like the number of things that are
leaving are about the number of pins, right?
So there're five things left standing and
six things have left, five plus six is eleven,
a little bit confusing but that's about right.
So let's take a look and see whether or not
it is detecting that Pins have left so it's
no longer a log saying something, it's a log
saying that pin has left, and is there a problem
with this? If thingLeft.GetComponent
- seems alright. So let's see what's wrong.
Typical kind of debugging that you need to
do as you go along of course. So here comes
the ball with its dodgy football texture and...
No pins are leaving. Great So good time to
pause the game and have a look what's going
on here. This pin for example has definitely
left this bounding box right? So what is this
thing out here? Is it of type pin?
Well, this thing here is, the whole bowling
pin, yeah that's OK it just happens to intercept
my click on the render, so this is the bowling
pin, and it is of type pin because it has
a pin component and it has definitely left
the bowling pin box so let's look at this
pin's collider here you go does it have a
collider? Now there so let's look at the sub-element
it does but it's not a trigger. OK, so is
the message even going to get called in the
instance of the pin, well yes it is, so what's
the problem? We have an issue here, what's
going on? Have a think about it yourself before
I tell you the solution to that.
Well one simple solution could be if we look
for the component on the thing that left then
the thing that left is this collider object
here which actually doesn't have a pin component
on it. That would be a reasonable guess, so
is there a GetComponent method that is a bit
like GetComponent that also looks in the parents
or something? GetComponentsInParent how about
that? How about if we said that any pin components
in the parent of this thing. Let's see if
that works. Build it, so I get an error that
I cannot convert a pin array to a bool which
is fair enough - now there are two ways out
of this problem and I know which one I prefer.
One way is the make it more complex way and
to start looking through this array of components
that we have found in the parent of this thing
here, where are we back in the scene, in the
game, OK in this pin six guy that we were
looking at - he had a sub-element. Oh my god
this is confusing now right, or, there's another
way of solving it which is to simplify our
way out of the problem? Wouldn't that be nicer?
So the problem we've got with all of these
pins is that they're a bit too hierarchical,
we have a bowling pin which is a transform,
a rigidbody and a pin script; but we also
have a separate collider element on it which
has a collider mesh filter that we need and
a mesh collider that's OK but we don't even
need that mesh filter, we just don't need
it, you only need the collider with its mesh,
so you could simplify a pin like that.
You could look at the render component and
say well do we need the pin render mesh, well
yes we are going to need that but why couldn't
that pin render mesh be on the top level of
the pin, let's try it. I'm going to work on
pin 6 I'm going to copy the pin render component
and put it at the top level. Paste component
as new. OK, well that seemed to work, I'll
move it up I like my scripts at the bottom.
So now let's take off the render component
from the sub object so the pin's still rendering
that's fine so how about if we took it a step
further and say, well actually do we even
need the mesh renderer?
Well copy the component, go to the top level
object, paste the component in, maybe move
it up, it still seems to have all the materials,
how about if we got rid of the whole pin render
sub component. That's pretty cool apart from
it hasn't worked, and that's because the transform
of this pin has now rotated itself through
90 degrees you see, so now we have a discrepancy.
Well let's continue this, let's simplify the
hell out of these pins. So let's take the
collider component off as well and put it
at the top level of the pin.
So you are going for a slightly different
architecture, let's simplify things. OK so
now you have the collider so you don't need
the collider subcomponent. Look at bowling
pin six, isn't that prettier? So what does
bowling pin six need to do? Well it needs
to be rotated through the x axis by probably
90 degrees. This may affect your isPinStanding
script but pin six otherwise looks like it's
in pretty good shape and it's a much simpler
object, look at it. Even though it's got more
components on it it has no hierarchy - so
now when our script says well, am I a pin,
well it is a pin because the collider is the
thing that's passing the message and attached
to the very same object is a pin.
So it's got more components on it but it's
got exactly what it needs. It has a rigidbody,
a rendered, a mesh renderer, a mesh that gives
it its shape a renderer that draws it and
the same for a mesh collider that can all
be done in one; it has a mesh collider and
here is the mesh. You see how much simpler
that is? So I really like that, I think that
the simplification of the pins. So go ahead
and simplify one of your pins now I think
that that's a great plan, and then we need
of course to duplicate that pin through to
the rest of the array.
So we're slightly redoing some work here but
so what? We've got a better architecture here,
it's going to be a lot easier to use in fact
what's going to be the easiest way of duplicating
this pin into all of the others? How would
you do that? Well given that I've got all
of the transforms I think that what I would
be doing here is copying the transform component
of pin one, deleting pin one altogether, duplicating
pin six and then the only difference is that
we want to paste values in there - perfect
and then rename to pin 1.
So I'm going to just whip through and do that
for all the pins now. I know that this is
the second or third time that we've been through
all the pins but this is what we need to do
sometimes, we need to keep iterating until
the design is as simple as possible. It's
worth the effort in my opinion. So I'm going
to speed up a little bit while I do that now.
So I'm literally just going through all of
the pins here one at a time copying their
transforms. A few things to notice, when you
copy the transform for some reason at the
moment it's not copying the x rotation so
I'm having to reset to minus 90.
The second thing to notice is that if there
isn't already a bowling pin with a higher
number then it will automatically renumber.
So if I duplicate pin four it will make pin
five provided there isn't already a pin five
there, so that's a useful thing to notice.
Now if there are many more pins that this
then of course we'd do all of this in script
or find a different way but when it's just
ten items it's perfectly reasonable to just
do it by hand so for the last couple of pins
I'm just going to leave them flat on the side
and reset their transforms en masse for the
last three.
OK so we've got all of our pins simplified
like crazy. Cool, let's have a look and see
what happens now. So back in the code of course
we no longer need this components in parents,
we just need to go back to a simple GetComponent
because, let me recap why, because the collider
is on the object and the object itself is
of type pin as it has a pin script attached.
So we've simplified our way out of the problem.
Yes it's taken some time and effort but it's
always worth the time and effort to simplify
your way out of a problem.
So let's take a look now and see what happens.
Boom, they're getting destroyed. You see the
pins on the left there got destroyed? And
you can see them disappearing here in the
hierarchy. Perfect, so that was well worth
the effort in my opinion. So, that means that
our code now is pretty much identical for
the two OnTriggerExit and OnTriggerEnter methods
and we're following exactly the same pattern
in both cases, that's much better than doing
some weird thing with the rays here just because
we previously decided to make these compound
objects - be willing to go back on your decisions.
Now, is the standing code still working? That
is my question, because we have rotated those
pin prefabs through 90 degrees so let's just
see if the standing count still works properly.
I suspect that it won't and that we'll need
to just modify our standing code on the pin
a little bit to take account of the fact that
in the x direction we are rotated 90 degrees.
0 you see, it thinks that none of them are
standing and the reason for that is that if
you go over to your pin and you look here
then we have a tiltInX and a tiltInZ well
the tilt in, if we go to the rotation part
of it, the tiltInZ if we look here's the pin,
here's its new rotation parameters.
So what's happened is that the pins now all
have a 270 degree offset in the x. So why
don't we just say 270 - x let's see if that
works. So start playing, ten are standing
now, scroll to the end and if it does work
I'll show you the code and leave that on the
screen at the end of the lecture. Boom, count
is working. Fantastic. So here's the code
that achieved the desired effect and we'll
carry on with this in the next video.