Hey so welcome to the second part of this
video. Let's take a little look at our game
and see where we are. So we're in a pretty
cool situation where the standing counter
doesn't even start to update until the ball
is in this virtual bounding box down the end
here. this pinsetter box. When that happens.
as soon as it enters this green box we get
a count. and actually all of the pins are
knocked down there. Also we've arranged for
the pins to destroy themselves as soon as
they go outside of this box. The ball doesn't
but that's OK because we can just move the
ball back to the start. but we don't want
pins drifting around our scene and indeed
they're not.
In fact I think that we could even go into
Scene view here and do a sneaky movement of
a pin and I think. you see? The moment that
it gets outside the bounding box that method
gets called and off it goes. Pretty cool.
hey? So you could just let the pin fall off
the edge and the moment it falls out the box
it gets destroyed. Fantastic. so that's all
working. What isn't working yet is we cannot
detect when the pins have settled yet. What
do I mean by settled? Well there are some
instances in which it's going to be tricky
for me to get the game into this state but
there are some instances in which the pins
wobble around for a while.
Let's see if I can make one of these happen.
Otherwise I think that you get the idea. that
we hit the pins and they don't decisively
stand up or fall down but they wobble for
a while. let's see if there're some wobblers
now. Erm... not really. but you can imagine
that this guy on the left could have ended
up wobbling around and we need at some point
to just draw a line and say well it's either
standing or it's not so we can progress the
game play. So what we're going to do in this
second half of the video is the bottom three
items of this checklist that we saw before.
We're going to detect when the pins have stopped
wobbling. we're going to use three seconds
as the time-out. We'll update the pin count
display to green when that happens to say
yeah I'm confident about the number and then
inside our method we're going to update our
last standing count to -1 when they've settled
and that's a little bit nasty but we'll talk
about the pros and cons as I've said before
of doing that. OK cool. so let's get on with
the coding now. So we're going to be inside
our pin setter script and what we're going
to be wanting to do is write a few more methods
inside this PinSetter script.
Alright? So before we get going let me help
you off the ground. We're going to want a
public - I think - int so that other things
from the outside can say well how many. what's
the state of the pins. and it's called a last
standing count. Or I'm going to call it that.
and I'm going to initialise it to minus 1
which indicates that actually nothing's fallen
over yet. the pins are in a default state
that - they are as they were before. So it's
not a definite number of pins standing and
-1 well. OK it's nasty because we are encoding
non-numeric information in a specialised number.
but it does make our code short and any other
solution that I've come up with. or Brice
has come up with with me. does actually make
things a little bit more complicated so you
always want to go for the shortest code possible
and I like this solution in this particular
case.
Alright? So we're going to need that. The
other thing that you're going to need in here
is you're going to need a private float to
keep track of the last change time. OK so
private float lastChangeTime which is going
to keep track of when the count number actually
last updated; and the final thing that I'll
be alluding to we've already got here we have
a private bool ballEnteredBox - bool ballEnteredBox.
you see bool ball? Fantastic so I'm going
to group my public and private variables together
I like doing that. with a little bit of a
space so I can at a glance look and say here
are my public. here are my private.
Fantastic. so that's the outline. we're also
going to be writing at least another couple
of methods. One's going to be a check standing
method so I'll write the outline of it now
of course you're going to be writing the actual
code but we have a void CheckStanding method
here and what is this going to do? It's basically
going to update the standing count. or more
specifically the last standing count. and
what else is the CheckStanding method going
to need to do? It's also going to call a new
method called PinsHaveSettled when they have.
So there's a little bit of written pseudo-code
for you.
So. another method then we're going to be
writing in the challenge which is void PinsHaveSettled.
So this is a new approach to programming we're
just kind of going from the outside in. we're
writing the methods first; and then in here
we're going to do various things we'll talk
about in the challenge. The final thing to
say is when are we calling these methods?
Well from update. so I'm actually going to
move them up the function a little bit. right
under the update like so; because what I like
to be able to do is if I'm calling something
in Update I like to be able to see it on the
same screen and what I'm going to be calling
is I'm going to be calling CountStanding on
every single update if the ball has entered
the box.
So I'll leave you to do that. so we're going
to check if ball has entered box. in fact
you know what? I'm going to do that for you.
I'm going to give you a leg up. This bit is
so much just writing it as you say it that
I'm going to do it for you. So. if this flag.
this ballEnteredBox flag is set to true. so
if the ball has entered the box. then I want
to every single frame. because we're in the
Update loop. I want to check the standing
count. OK? And if you don't like the name
of Check Standing then rename it. Check Standing
Count. I'm going to leave it as CheckStanding
for now.
So after the ball has entered the box we run
this method which updates the standing count
and eventually calls pins have settled if
they've settled. So that gives you the structure
that you need in order for it to do the challenge.
and then remember the private and public variables
I've created are here if you want to pause
the video and take a look you're welcome.
So let's put you into the challenge now and
see if you can fill out the bodies of those
methods. So here's the challenge in question.
Number one if ballEnteredBox then call CheckStanding().
I've done that for you! Aren't I nice. aren't
I kind. but you're not off the hook yet. you
now need to wait for the standing count to
stop changing for three seconds. I've given
you all the tools that you need to do that.
all the variables. but I want you to write
that code. When pins settle call PinsHaveSettled()
and then all we're going to do on PinsHaveSettled
for now is just update the display to green.
So go ahead. pause the video. have a good
look at the code and see if you can fill it
in and do that challenge right now please.
OK so welcome back. let's get that code written
shall we? It's all about the code. so why
don't we dive in and write it? Starting with
let's say the CheckStanding method. well let's
make a variable inside this method called
current standing which is just an integer
and it is the count standing so at the beginning
the first time we come into this check standing
to see how many are standing we just call
that CountStanding method and get the latest
count. and store it in a variable.
Fine. then what? Well. just write some English.
If current standing is not equal to - and
notice the not - lastStandingCount. Now on
the first iteration it will not be equal to
the last standing count of course because
we initialised it to -1. so the first time
around current standing will not be equal
to -1. So if that's the case whenever the
current Standing count when we came in to
this method is not equal to the last one which
is an instance variable at a wider scope up
here. then we say lastChangeTime = Time.time.
You can look up Time.time but it's the time
since the game started.
So we log when the last change happened. we
update the last standing count. to whatever
it was when we came in to the method here.
and we return. we get out of here. we're done.
OK. If this wasn't to happen. i.e. if we have
the same count we had last time this frame
- remember this is all being called from update.
once the ball enters the box this gets called
every update. Every single frame it goes "has
the count changed?". if it has then it skips
this - look it's a not equals to.
So if it has changed then we come down here
and we say right. float. settleTime = 3 seconds.
How long to wait to consider pins settled.
Fine. now. if I'm going to put in a couple
of brackets for us. Time. and I'm going to
close the couple of brackets as well. it's
always good to close your brackets as soon
as you've opened them. so if Time.time - lastChangeTime
- so if it's been is another way of saying
that in English. if it's been more than this
settle threshold. or settle time. i.e. if
it's been more than 3 seconds yeah. in English.
if last change more than 3 seconds ago.
Now this comment will go out of sync if you
change this variable but OK. then we call
pins have settled. Do you get it? Can you
see how that works? We go into CheckStanding.
we jump out of it if there hasn't been a change
but if there has been a change then provided
that that change was more than 3 seconds ago
we call pins have settled and finally a call
to this method. Great. so all I said that
we needed to do within PinsHaveSettled was
set the standing display to its colour to
Color.green for now. Now is there anything
else that you want to do? Well yes. I think
that it would make sense to set the last standing
count back to this special reserve of -1 thing.
if basically indicates a new frame.
It means we're starting afresh. OK because
the pins have settled. so what it really indicates
is it indicates that pins have settled and
ball not back in box. so it basically means
a new frame. OK. later we'll be doing things
like Ball.reset which we don't have at the
moment and we also probably while we're here
want to be saying actually. the ball has not
entered the box any more. So where we have
this ballEnteredBox flag. that wants to go
to false. So when the pins have settled we
want to send the StandingCount back to its
default value of -1. we say that the ball
has no longer entered the box in this part
of the game and the colour goes green.
Cool. so that's going a little bit outside
the call of duty of the challenge so don't
worry at all if you needed a little bit of
help here. Let's see how this works. Indeed
if it works. So. oops. we have the black number
at the moment which means that it's not being
updated it's kind of idle. I'm having challenges
with even playing my own game... come on you
must get down the end! I'm going to have to
find a way to make this easier. I could just
get better at it. It's always a... a bit of
a break while you watch me fumble.
Here you go. so no updates at all until you
get inside the bounding box. boom it goes
red saying it's a tentative value. it waits
for the pins to settle. none of them are wobbling
so after three seconds it goes green. Great.
let's watch that once more; let's see if we
can get some wobbling pins so that we actually
get the desired effect. A sip of tea while
we wait. 10. 9. 7. 1. 0. you see that one
wobbling? 0. it's decided it's zero and actually
it's right. Now we won't optimise this time
until we've finished optimising the physics.
We're going to shortly be back to the point
where we're going to want to play with the
physics but I wanted to leave the physics
until now because you can tell that all of
this stuff will depend on the physics parameters.
and to some extent vice versa I wanted to
get all of this in place before we started
to work any harder on the physics. but we
basically have now all of the code that we
need to determine how many pins are actually
standing. The final thing that we're going
to need to do is to actually reset the ball
back to the beginning of the lane.
So moving into our PinSetter.cs let's lay
the foundations for the ability to reset the
ball. So firstly the PinSetter is going to
need to know about the ball. right? It'll
need to talk to it. So we're going to need
a private Ball ball. simple as that. With
a small b. a variable has a small letter;
and then where are we going to find that ball?
Well let's go find the ball. small b. it's
really wanting to give me a capital b here.
ah it's because I've misspelt private. OK
so a little lesson here. I've misspelt private
and then the auto-complete I'm fighting. so
if you're fighting the auto-complete in an
unexpected situation then it's probably because
of something like this.
If I spell private right here then it understands
that I want to find a variable and it allows
me to use a small letter because it's not
looking for a type any more. and then I can
say ball and everything is working. right?
GameObject.FindObjectOfType. there's only
one ball in the scene. We can actually move
this ball rather than reinstantiating it in
this case. There's two ways of dealing with
objects. you can either move them or reinstantiate
them. Generally it's more efficient to move
them than reinstantiate them but it depends
on the situation.
In this game we're doing both; we are destroying
and reinstantiating pins but we are moving
the ball. Performance is not an issue in this
game. the way it's running at the moment.
OK so we have found this ball and what I'm
going to want to do on when the pins have
settled is I'm going to want to reset this
ball immediately. So ball.Reset. now it doesn't
have a reset method yet. but let's pretend
if does. It's going to be red for now. let's
go into the ball script. and just at least
log out that that has happened so that we
know that we're getting to this.
So let's have a launch script. we've already
got a launch method rather in the ball script.
let's have now a public void. returns nothing.
reset. which resets the ball. And for now
we're just going to Debug.Log resetting ball
so that we know that we are getting to this
point in our code. OK now over in PinSetter
that code will go not red. i.e. black and
when the pins have settled then reset will
be called. Let's just check that works before
we finally make the reset happen. So we swipe
along. hope that we actually hit something.
keep an eye on our console. and what should
happen is that it goes red now. starts counting.
any wobbles are taken a count of. after three
seconds of no changes in this number it goes
green.
Pin left. we can delete that. log resetting
ball pin left. OK. I'm going to delete the
pin left log but we've got the resetting ball.
That's what we needed. So pin left log entry
from PinSetter.cs has gone around about line
67 on mine. Now the final thing to do is to
go back to our ball and to give it the ability
to be reset. So here's your challenge. Write
Reset() in Ball.cs. Create and manage a public
bool inPlay; so from the outside we can say
Ball.inPlay and it will tell us whether it's
in play or not. Capture the ball's start position
in the start function.
Reset the ball's position to the start when
we call the reset method - everything now
indented on this slide is what the reset method
does. It resets the position to the start
that we captured above; it sets the velocity
and angular velocity back to zero. and prevents
the ball from falling before a second launch.
You'll see what I mean when you get there.
So the basic objective is to be able to launch
the ball more than once in a row. to have
a second swipe at the pins. So pause the video
and have a go at doing that for yourself now.
Go on. please pause it. don't just be a passenger.
I'm sorry if you've done every single challenge
judiciously. you know that I'm going to keep
bugging people who haven't. OK. fantastic.
so let's get on and make that little bit work.
So we have a reset method here. resetting
ball. we can leave that log entry in - it's
the sort of log entry that's actually quite
helpful. I said that we wanted an in play.
Well we already have an in play flag here.
so let's set it at this point. inPlay = false
right? If you are resetting the ball then
it's no longer in play.
Now in the start we need to capture the position
of the ball. right? So how are we going to
do that? Well I'm going to create myself an
instance variable called ballStartPos so where's
that going to be? It's going to be up here.
it's going to be private. it's going to be
a Vector3 and it's going to be called ballStartPos.
there it is. On start I'm going to say ballStartPos
equals transform.position because we're in
the ball script here right. we're just capturing
the transform position of a ball at the start
so if your designer moves it it will just
store a new position in the variable. Fine
with me.
So how are we going to do the reset? So we
say that inPlay is not true any more. we make
the transform.position = ballStartPos. the
exact reverse of what we did in the start
method. we will say my RigidBody now - we
need access to the RigidBody of the ball now
in order to be able to play with this angular
momentum and its velocity. If we don't do
that then the ball is going to continue moving.
Let's try it and see what happens if we don't
do this. So we take one swipe at the pins.
there they go. and when it's determined that
they've settled the ball should reset back
to the beginning - boom.
Now what's happening? Resetting ball. where
is the ball? You see it's kind of just careering
off. and that's because it didn't have its
position and velocity stopped. So we're going
to need access to the RigidBody inside of
this Ball. So this is slightly new in Unity
5 because you need to explicitly go and get
the RigidBody now so. we have a private RigidBody
myRigidBody which is the ball's RigidBody
there. On the start we go and find that. so
that's simple enough. We just say myRigidBody
= GetComponent RigidBody. you're going to
have to do a lot of this in Unity 5. they've
decoupled things for us.
Which is generally good news but it does mean
you have to write a little bit more code.
So you've got the RigidBody now. and now that
you've got that you can simply come down here
and say myRigidBody.velocity = initialVelocity.
Ah. oops. well we don't have an initial velocity.
Well. what do we want the initial velocity
to be on the reset? Well. 0. So we don't need
an initial velocity. we need Vector3.zero.
We’ve reset the ball it wants no velocity.
and similarly with the angular velocity. What
do we want that to be? Well it's also a vector3.zero
if you looked at the docs then you'd find
that it takes a standard vector3;
and the final thing that we need to do well
if you look here we said RigidBody.useGravity;
ah. now look. RigidBody and myRigidBody. what's
that all about? Well look what I've done.
I've done this whole RigidBody thing twice.
so that's going to reinforce the difference
in Unity 5 isn't it? But it's completely un-necessary
so use the RigidBody you already had. you
see this line is identical to this line. you
may have been wondering why on earth's he
creating another RigidBody we already had
one. You're quite right; I'm just going to
slightly change the code to reflect that.
OK. fantastic. so just updating the spelling
as I go to sort this mess out. there we go.
So because we on launch said we want to use
gravity. on reset we want to stop using gravity
and that should stop the ball falling down.
Let's take a look. So let's fire the ball.
please hit a pin. Actually it doesn't matter
whether it hits a pin for this test. It's
gone into the bounding box that's the important
thing. Fantastic. So. resetting ball. that's
happening. Now. what's happened? Camera hasn't
followed it back. The ball is back at the
start but the main camera. if you look either
in the game view or in the scene you can see
that the main camera hasn't followed it.
Why not. where's the main camera? Back down
at the end here. Hmm. strange. So. how's the
main camera controlled? With the camera control
script. What's the problem? See if you can
see the problem. it's right in here. I can
see it now. So let me put you out of your
misery. the camera control is stopping moving
the camera when the camera's transform is
less than or equal to 1829. As soon as the
camera goes past 1829. which it is now. then
where is it. Is it there now? Yeah I've stopped
the game. but you would have noticed the main
camera was past 1829 in the z then it's got
no chance of recovering. So how about if we
did it based on the ball?
ball.transform.position - all the time that
the ball is at the end of the play space then
we follow it. Let's try that. see if that's
any better; and that's a typical bug that
you may come across and the obvious place
to look was the camera controller because
it's a camera control problem. it shows that
we've named things right. When it's settled
we can get back to the beginning and look.
no gravity and we can bowl again. Woohoo!
We have the objective for this lesson. we
have multiple bowls. we have a pin count and
we're making wonderful progress.
Of course we're going to need to deal with
things like it rolling off the edge we can
do that by either putting invisible walls
or a variety of different ways of dealing
with that but not in this video. it's plenty
long enough. congratulations in getting this
=======
Hey so welcome to the second part of this
video. Let's take a little look at our game
and see where we are. So we're in a pretty
cool situation where the standing counter
doesn't even start to update until the ball
is in this virtual bounding box down the end
here, this pinsetter box. When that happens,
as soon as it enters this green box we get
a count, and actually all of the pins are
knocked down there. Also we've arranged for
the pins to destroy themselves as soon as
they go outside of this box. The ball doesn't
but that's OK because we can just move the
ball back to the start, but we don't want
pins drifting around our scene and indeed
they're not.
In fact I think that we could even go into
Scene view here and do a sneaky movement of
a pin and I think, you see? The moment that
it gets outside the bounding box that method
gets called and off it goes. Pretty cool,
hey? So you could just let the pin fall off
the edge and the moment it falls out the box
it gets destroyed. Fantastic, so that's all
working. What isn't working yet is we cannot
detect when the pins have settled yet. What
do I mean by settled? Well there are some
instances in which it's going to be tricky
for me to get the game into this state but
there are some instances in which the pins
wobble around for a while.
Let's see if I can make one of these happen.
Otherwise I think that you get the idea, that
we hit the pins and they don't decisively
stand up or fall down but they wobble for
a while, let's see if there're some wobblers
now. Erm... not really, but you can imagine
that this guy on the left could have ended
up wobbling around and we need at some point
to just draw a line and say well it's either
standing or it's not so we can progress the
game play. So what we're going to do in this
second half of the video is the bottom three
items of this checklist that we saw before.
We're going to detect when the pins have stopped
wobbling, we're going to use three seconds
as the time-out. We'll update the pin count
display to green when that happens to say
yeah I'm confident about the number and then
inside our method we're going to update our
last standing count to -1 when they've settled
and that's a little bit nasty but we'll talk
about the pros and cons as I've said before
of doing that. OK cool, so let's get on with
the coding now. So we're going to be inside
our pin setter script and what we're going
to be wanting to do is write a few more methods
inside this PinSetter script.
Alright? So before we get going let me help
you off the ground. We're going to want a
public - I think - int so that other things
from the outside can say well how many, what's
the state of the pins, and it's called a last
standing count. Or I'm going to call it that,
and I'm going to initialise it to minus 1
which indicates that actually nothing's fallen
over yet, the pins are in a default state
that - they are as they were before. So it's
not a definite number of pins standing and
-1 well, OK it's nasty because we are encoding
non-numeric information in a specialised number,
but it does make our code short and any other
solution that I've come up with, or Brice
has come up with with me, does actually make
things a little bit more complicated so you
always want to go for the shortest code possible
and I like this solution in this particular
case.
Alright? So we're going to need that. The
other thing that you're going to need in here
is you're going to need a private float to
keep track of the last change time. OK so
private float lastChangeTime which is going
to keep track of when the count number actually
last updated; and the final thing that I'll
be alluding to we've already got here we have
a private bool ballEnteredBox - bool ballEnteredBox,
you see bool ball? Fantastic so I'm going
to group my public and private variables together
I like doing that, with a little bit of a
space so I can at a glance look and say here
are my public, here are my private.
Fantastic, so that's the outline, we're also
going to be writing at least another couple
of methods. One's going to be a check standing
method so I'll write the outline of it now
of course you're going to be writing the actual
code but we have a void CheckStanding method
here and what is this going to do? It's basically
going to update the standing count, or more
specifically the last standing count, and
what else is the CheckStanding method going
to need to do? It's also going to call a new
method called PinsHaveSettled when they have.
So there's a little bit of written pseudo-code
for you.
So, another method then we're going to be
writing in the challenge which is void PinsHaveSettled.
So this is a new approach to programming we're
just kind of going from the outside in, we're
writing the methods first; and then in here
we're going to do various things we'll talk
about in the challenge. The final thing to
say is when are we calling these methods?
Well from update, so I'm actually going to
move them up the function a little bit, right
under the update like so; because what I like
to be able to do is if I'm calling something
in Update I like to be able to see it on the
same screen and what I'm going to be calling
is I'm going to be calling CountStanding on
every single update if the ball has entered
the box.
So I'll leave you to do that, so we're going
to check if ball has entered box, in fact
you know what? I'm going to do that for you.
I'm going to give you a leg up. This bit is
so much just writing it as you say it that
I'm going to do it for you. So, if this flag,
this ballEnteredBox flag is set to true, so
if the ball has entered the box, then I want
to every single frame, because we're in the
Update loop, I want to check the standing
count. OK? And if you don't like the name
of Check Standing then rename it, Check Standing
Count, I'm going to leave it as CheckStanding
for now.
So after the ball has entered the box we run
this method which updates the standing count
and eventually calls pins have settled if
they've settled. So that gives you the structure
that you need in order for it to do the challenge,
and then remember the private and public variables
I've created are here if you want to pause
the video and take a look you're welcome.
So let's put you into the challenge now and
see if you can fill out the bodies of those
methods. So here's the challenge in question.
Number one if ballEnteredBox then call CheckStanding(),
I've done that for you! Aren't I nice, aren't
I kind, but you're not off the hook yet, you
now need to wait for the standing count to
stop changing for three seconds. I've given
you all the tools that you need to do that,
all the variables, but I want you to write
that code. When pins settle call PinsHaveSettled()
and then all we're going to do on PinsHaveSettled
for now is just update the display to green.
So go ahead, pause the video, have a good
look at the code and see if you can fill it
in and do that challenge right now please.
OK so welcome back, let's get that code written
shall we? It's all about the code, so why
don't we dive in and write it? Starting with
let's say the CheckStanding method, well let's
make a variable inside this method called
current standing which is just an integer
and it is the count standing so at the beginning
the first time we come into this check standing
to see how many are standing we just call
that CountStanding method and get the latest
count, and store it in a variable.
Fine, then what? Well, just write some English.
If current standing is not equal to - and
notice the not - lastStandingCount. Now on
the first iteration it will not be equal to
the last standing count of course because
we initialised it to -1, so the first time
around current standing will not be equal
to -1. So if that's the case whenever the
current Standing count when we came in to
this method is not equal to the last one which
is an instance variable at a wider scope up
here, then we say lastChangeTime = Time.time.
You can look up Time.time but it's the time
since the game started.
So we log when the last change happened, we
update the last standing count, to whatever
it was when we came in to the method here,
and we return, we get out of here, we're done,
OK. If this wasn't to happen, i.e. if we have
the same count we had last time this frame
- remember this is all being called from update,
once the ball enters the box this gets called
every update. Every single frame it goes "has
the count changed?", if it has then it skips
this - look it's a not equals to.
So if it has changed then we come down here
and we say right, float, settleTime = 3 seconds.
How long to wait to consider pins settled.
Fine, now, if I'm going to put in a couple
of brackets for us, Time, and I'm going to
close the couple of brackets as well, it's
always good to close your brackets as soon
as you've opened them, so if Time.time - lastChangeTime
- so if it's been is another way of saying
that in English, if it's been more than this
settle threshold, or settle time, i.e. if
it's been more than 3 seconds yeah, in English,
if last change more than 3 seconds ago.
Now this comment will go out of sync if you
change this variable but OK, then we call
pins have settled. Do you get it? Can you
see how that works? We go into CheckStanding,
we jump out of it if there hasn't been a change
but if there has been a change then provided
that that change was more than 3 seconds ago
we call pins have settled and finally a call
to this method. Great, so all I said that
we needed to do within PinsHaveSettled was
set the standing display to its colour to
Color.green for now. Now is there anything
else that you want to do? Well yes, I think
that it would make sense to set the last standing
count back to this special reserve of -1 thing,
if basically indicates a new frame.
It means we're starting afresh, OK because
the pins have settled, so what it really indicates
is it indicates that pins have settled and
ball not back in box, so it basically means
a new frame. OK, later we'll be doing things
like Ball.reset which we don't have at the
moment and we also probably while we're here
want to be saying actually, the ball has not
entered the box any more. So where we have
this ballEnteredBox flag, that wants to go
to false. So when the pins have settled we
want to send the StandingCount back to its
default value of -1, we say that the ball
has no longer entered the box in this part
of the game and the colour goes green.
Cool, so that's going a little bit outside
the call of duty of the challenge so don't
worry at all if you needed a little bit of
help here. Let's see how this works. Indeed
if it works. So, oops, we have the black number
at the moment which means that it's not being
updated it's kind of idle. I'm having challenges
with even playing my own game... come on you
must get down the end! I'm going to have to
find a way to make this easier. I could just
get better at it. It's always a... a bit of
a break while you watch me fumble.
Here you go, so no updates at all until you
get inside the bounding box, boom it goes
red saying it's a tentative value, it waits
for the pins to settle, none of them are wobbling
so after three seconds it goes green. Great,
let's watch that once more; let's see if we
can get some wobbling pins so that we actually
get the desired effect. A sip of tea while
we wait. 10, 9, 7, 1, 0, you see that one
wobbling? 0, it's decided it's zero and actually
it's right. Now we won't optimise this time
until we've finished optimising the physics.
We're going to shortly be back to the point
where we're going to want to play with the
physics but I wanted to leave the physics
until now because you can tell that all of
this stuff will depend on the physics parameters,
and to some extent vice versa I wanted to
get all of this in place before we started
to work any harder on the physics, but we
basically have now all of the code that we
need to determine how many pins are actually
standing. The final thing that we're going
to need to do is to actually reset the ball
back to the beginning of the lane.
So moving into our PinSetter.cs let's lay
the foundations for the ability to reset the
ball. So firstly the PinSetter is going to
need to know about the ball, right? It'll
need to talk to it. So we're going to need
a private Ball ball, simple as that. With
a small b, a variable has a small letter;
and then where are we going to find that ball?
Well let's go find the ball, small b, it's
really wanting to give me a capital b here,
ah it's because I've misspelt private, OK
so a little lesson here, I've misspelt private
and then the auto-complete I'm fighting, so
if you're fighting the auto-complete in an
unexpected situation then it's probably because
of something like this.
If I spell private right here then it understands
that I want to find a variable and it allows
me to use a small letter because it's not
looking for a type any more, and then I can
say ball and everything is working, right?
GameObject.FindObjectOfType, there's only
one ball in the scene. We can actually move
this ball rather than reinstantiating it in
this case. There's two ways of dealing with
objects, you can either move them or reinstantiate
them. Generally it's more efficient to move
them than reinstantiate them but it depends
on the situation.
In this game we're doing both; we are destroying
and reinstantiating pins but we are moving
the ball. Performance is not an issue in this
game, the way it's running at the moment.
OK so we have found this ball and what I'm
going to want to do on when the pins have
settled is I'm going to want to reset this
ball immediately. So ball.Reset, now it doesn't
have a reset method yet, but let's pretend
if does. It's going to be red for now, let's
go into the ball script, and just at least
log out that that has happened so that we
know that we're getting to this.
So let's have a launch script, we've already
got a launch method rather in the ball script,
let's have now a public void, returns nothing,
reset, which resets the ball. And for now
we're just going to Debug.Log resetting ball
so that we know that we are getting to this
point in our code. OK now over in PinSetter
that code will go not red, i.e. black and
when the pins have settled then reset will
be called. Let's just check that works before
we finally make the reset happen. So we swipe
along, hope that we actually hit something,
keep an eye on our console, and what should
happen is that it goes red now, starts counting,
any wobbles are taken a count of, after three
seconds of no changes in this number it goes
green.
Pin left, we can delete that, log resetting
ball pin left. OK. I'm going to delete the
pin left log but we've got the resetting ball.
That's what we needed. So pin left log entry
from PinSetter.cs has gone around about line
67 on mine. Now the final thing to do is to
go back to our ball and to give it the ability
to be reset. So here's your challenge. Write
Reset() in Ball.cs. Create and manage a public
bool inPlay; so from the outside we can say
Ball.inPlay and it will tell us whether it's
in play or not. Capture the ball's start position
in the start function.
Reset the ball's position to the start when
we call the reset method - everything now
indented on this slide is what the reset method
does. It resets the position to the start
that we captured above; it sets the velocity
and angular velocity back to zero, and prevents
the ball from falling before a second launch.
You'll see what I mean when you get there.
So the basic objective is to be able to launch
the ball more than once in a row, to have
a second swipe at the pins. So pause the video
and have a go at doing that for yourself now.
Go on, please pause it, don't just be a passenger.
I'm sorry if you've done every single challenge
judiciously, you know that I'm going to keep
bugging people who haven't. OK, fantastic,
so let's get on and make that little bit work.
So we have a reset method here, resetting
ball, we can leave that log entry in - it's
the sort of log entry that's actually quite
helpful. I said that we wanted an in play.
Well we already have an in play flag here,
so let's set it at this point. inPlay = false
right? If you are resetting the ball then
it's no longer in play.
Now in the start we need to capture the position
of the ball, right? So how are we going to
do that? Well I'm going to create myself an
instance variable called ballStartPos so where's
that going to be? It's going to be up here,
it's going to be private, it's going to be
a Vector3 and it's going to be called ballStartPos,
there it is. On start I'm going to say ballStartPos
equals transform.position because we're in
the ball script here right, we're just capturing
the transform position of a ball at the start
so if your designer moves it it will just
store a new position in the variable. Fine
with me.
So how are we going to do the reset? So we
say that inPlay is not true any more, we make
the transform.position = ballStartPos, the
exact reverse of what we did in the start
method, we will say my RigidBody now - we
need access to the RigidBody of the ball now
in order to be able to play with this angular
momentum and its velocity. If we don't do
that then the ball is going to continue moving.
Let's try it and see what happens if we don't
do this. So we take one swipe at the pins,
there they go, and when it's determined that
they've settled the ball should reset back
to the beginning - boom.
Now what's happening? Resetting ball, where
is the ball? You see it's kind of just careering
off, and that's because it didn't have its
position and velocity stopped. So we're going
to need access to the RigidBody inside of
this Ball. So this is slightly new in Unity
5 because you need to explicitly go and get
the RigidBody now so, we have a private RigidBody
myRigidBody which is the ball's RigidBody
there. On the start we go and find that, so
that's simple enough. We just say myRigidBody
= GetComponent RigidBody, you're going to
have to do a lot of this in Unity 5, they've
decoupled things for us.
Which is generally good news but it does mean
you have to write a little bit more code.
So you've got the RigidBody now, and now that
you've got that you can simply come down here
and say myRigidBody.velocity = initialVelocity.
Ah, oops, well we don't have an initial velocity.
Well, what do we want the initial velocity
to be on the reset? Well, 0. So we don't need
an initial velocity, we need Vector3.zero.
Weve reset the ball it wants no velocity,
and similarly with the angular velocity. What
do we want that to be? Well it's also a vector3.zero
if you looked at the docs then you'd find
that it takes a standard vector3;
and the final thing that we need to do well
if you look here we said RigidBody.useGravity;
ah, now look, RigidBody and myRigidBody, what's
that all about? Well look what I've done,
I've done this whole RigidBody thing twice,
so that's going to reinforce the difference
in Unity 5 isn't it? But it's completely un-necessary
so use the RigidBody you already had, you
see this line is identical to this line, you
may have been wondering why on earth's he
creating another RigidBody we already had
one. You're quite right; I'm just going to
slightly change the code to reflect that.
OK, fantastic, so just updating the spelling
as I go to sort this mess out, there we go.
So because we on launch said we want to use
gravity, on reset we want to stop using gravity
and that should stop the ball falling down.
Let's take a look. So let's fire the ball,
please hit a pin. Actually it doesn't matter
whether it hits a pin for this test. It's
gone into the bounding box that's the important
thing. Fantastic. So, resetting ball, that's
happening. Now, what's happened? Camera hasn't
followed it back. The ball is back at the
start but the main camera, if you look either
in the game view or in the scene you can see
that the main camera hasn't followed it.
Why not, where's the main camera? Back down
at the end here. Hmm, strange. So, how's the
main camera controlled? With the camera control
script. What's the problem? See if you can
see the problem, it's right in here. I can
see it now. So let me put you out of your
misery, the camera control is stopping moving
the camera when the camera's transform is
less than or equal to 1829. As soon as the
camera goes past 1829, which it is now, then
where is it. Is it there now? Yeah I've stopped
the game, but you would have noticed the main
camera was past 1829 in the z then it's got
no chance of recovering. So how about if we
did it based on the ball?
ball.transform.position - all the time that
the ball is at the end of the play space then
we follow it. Let's try that, see if that's
any better; and that's a typical bug that
you may come across and the obvious place
to look was the camera controller because
it's a camera control problem, it shows that
we've named things right. When it's settled
we can get back to the beginning and look,
no gravity and we can bowl again. Woohoo!
We have the objective for this lesson, we
have multiple bowls, we have a pin count and
we're making wonderful progress.
Of course we're going to need to deal with
things like it rolling off the edge we can
do that by either putting invisible walls
or a variety of different ways of dealing
with that but not in this video, it's plenty
long enough, congratulations in getting this
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1:Unity/Section8/BM19 Detecting Pins have settled 2.srt
far and I'll see you in the next adventure.