welcome back so we're finally ready to
return to the topic of animator substate
machines and default States and all that
sort of thing so if you remember we
broke off when we were in the middle of
building this animation system because
even though we could animate the motion
of the Swiper we weren't able to
determine which of the pins were
standing in order to raise them up so we
had a little sidetrack. did several
several videos where we produced some
great code that's allowed us now to
determine how many pins are standing and
there is the standing count that we've
just built so what we need to do moving
forward I'm gonna give you an overview
of everything that's coming now but this
is a couple of videos dealing with
roughly the same thing so in this
particular video we're going to overview how the tidy
and the reset work modify the
architecture of the game a little bit
and the hierarchy learn more about sub
state machines learn about default
transitions while we're there and then
we'll actually set up our tidy and our
reset sub states and there'll be a couple of
challenges for you and then in the video
after this one we will be creating some
animator helper scripts for raising and
lowering pins so those two kind of go
together but it's going to be too much
for one video and at the end of this we'll
have a fantastic animation controller
that will be responsible for both moving
the Swiper with a nice motion and also
for calling script that is going to
raise and lower these pins based on
whether they're standing so let's crack
on and get on with that so the first
thing to do is to talk about the
architecture of the game so the moment
I've got it set up like this I have a
PinSetter which is just a box collider
and a script and we have that as a
separate component to the Swiper
but actually if you think about it the
Swiper is part of the PinSetter
arrangements so I'm gonna move the PinSetter
to the top level of my hierarchy you
notice nothing changes it's just how it's
organized and then I'm gonna sub the swiper to the PinSetter so we end
up in this arrangement here so now when
you click on the PinSetter you get both
the PinSetter and its part which is the
swiper selected. Great.
so that's the first architectural change
I wanna make. The next architectural
change i wanna talk about is the fact
that at the moment the animation controller
and the animator are attached to the
Swiper well that was fine all the time
that the Swiper was the only animation that
was going on but now we want to actually
be able to lift the pins from script so we
have a swipe motion and we absolutely
want to keep that swipe motion that
motion that we've come up with that goes
out and back is absolutely fine but the
Swiper animation controller is no longer
a swiper animation controller at all. In fact
we may as well just delete it's actually gonna be a
PinSetter animation controller so let's
delete the swiper animation controller and
the Swipe the animator from the swiper
doesn't need one at all what we're going to
create a whole new animator and
animation controller at this level on
the PinSetter so add an animator to the
PinSetter for me and create yourself a
new animation controller and call it PinSetter. We're just going to start afresh and then
make sure that that PinSetter animation controller is attached to the PinSetter
Fantastic. There it is I'm gonna move my script to the bottom because I'm obsessive like that.
Great so let's start laying out this PinSetter animation controller so I'm gonna do
the top-level part of this diagram for
you and then I'm going to ask you to
play with the sub-state machine and to
organize that so while you're in the
animator bear in mind you can hold down
the Alt key to scroll around and in
Unity 5 it looks a little bit different
to before we have an any state node an
exit node and an entry notes so let's
start looking at how this works. What I'm
going to want is a tidy substate machine
and a reset substate machine. Because they do
slightly different things but they reuse
some things so we have a reset just be careful
with your renaming and a tidy. I'll put tidy
at the top I dunno why. I just feel like it
so what the idea is that we're gonna be
sitting by default in an idle states so we're
also going to need that idle state let's
generate the idle state now so this is a
state. not a sub-state machine and it's
called idle and it's made itself the
default state for this level so we're at
the top level the base layer of the
animator when we come into this base
layer from anywhere which includes from
the tidy level which is like a folder
we've just gone down into a folder then the
default transition is into idle which is
fine we don't need a motion on idle
because there's nothing to move around
the scene so that's all we need to do
there and then we're gonna have two
different sub state machines one is
going to be tidy which is going to lift
up the pins swipe the Swiper with that
motion we've created and then put the
pins back down on the bed before
returning back up to this level and
sitting back in the idle state and then
we're also gonna have a reset substate
machine which will do something
slightly different it's just gonna swipe
away everything. instantiate a new set of
pins and put them in place. So slightly
different behaviors for these two
sub-machine so the sub machines are just
basically like a folder they're a way of
going in here and saying what do I want
to happen within this sub-state and you
have very similar looking apart from we have an up to base layer which takes us
back to the top
Fantastic so it is time now for your
first challenge which is to set up your
tidy animation I want you to create the
tidy substate and it inner states. I've
already made the tidy sub-state in my
case. Set up the tidy trigger parameter
which is going to be what takes us from
the idle state into this sub state
machine and include all the following steps so what's gonna
happen at the end of this is you click
playing your game you'll be looping
around the idle state until you tick on
the tidy trigger parameter which would
take us into this sub state machine will
go through an empty raise. swipe lower
and exit. None of those things need to do
anything at the moment
although you're welcome to attach the swipe motion to the swipe state if you wish
but once it just passes through here and back
up to the top level and starts looping
round tidy.
idle again you're in good shape so let's
get that sub-state machine working now
Pause the video and set it up. OK welcome
back so let's make this stuff happen shall we?
Firstly I'm gonna make the transition
into the tidy substate machine there is
and I need to make that parameter so it's
on the left hand side slightly different
in Unity 5. add a trigger parameter
and I'm going to call it tidy trigger
Now the reason in unity four point X I
used to
suffix everything with trigger is because
it wasn't at all clear in the parameters
list whether we were dealing with a bool
or a trigger. In this case it actually is
if I put the bool in we now in Unity 5
have a square checkbox whereas triggers
have a round but for momentum because we have momentum I'm gonna continue to use
a trigger suffix at least for the moment.
So there is our transition from idle we
need to add the condition which is
OnTidyTrigger. let's check it works.
Sometimes these animators are a little bit
tricky so it's not working right now
idle is not doing anything so what's
wrong let's check the PinSetter. it has
an animation controller on it.
Fantastic let's I can remove has exit time from this transition because we
want the transition to happen the moment
that the tidy trigger happens. so let's
see if it works now without has exit time
yes it does look. We're looping around
idle and the moment I hit tidy trigger
then we go into the sub-state machine and
back out but it's so quick you can't see
it. So let's make the return transition
like that and go into the sub-state
machine to edit it so what have we got? Well
we said we had a raise pins. that was the first state. Now you can either create I'm
going to do the raise this way I'm
going to create an actual state with no
motion and then later we'll probably
have to create a motion I'm going to do
the lower a different way and the Swipe
so here's the Swipe how are we gonna get the
swipe into here?
Well we already have a motion for swipe
so we may as well just create the state
for swipe like so and
attach it to the existing motion and
make the transition. Fantastic and then
finally I'll show you a slightly
different way of doing things let's
click onto the PinSetter. onto the
animation and then you have a list of
motions here so far we only have the
swipe motion. remember that motion we
created. How about if you create a new clip
in here. what does that do? Pop it in your
animations folder. you can always choose it from here if you need to I'm talking about
assets / animations and let's call this one
lower. So now what's happened if we
scroll around we should be able to find in
one of our state machine diagrams
probably at the base layer there you go
it's created lower at the base layer and
that's the problem is not gone where we
want it can we drag it into that
lower layer? Yes we can but we have to drag around so this is an alternative and
what you've actually created here is two
things. you've created an animation state
here and you've created an associated
clip so if we inspect lower you'll see it
has a lower motion clip;
raise does not have a motion clip. well
we're going to need a motion clip for
raise later so why don't we just create one now just several ways of doing this. So we create
an animation we call it raise it's just
gonna be a script call by the way this
thing but we still need it and let's
attach it. So several ways of doing it
but it's really important we dig into
this like this so you can understand
what's going on under the behind the
scenes when you start creating things
you understand the difference between a clip and the motion; well the motion and the clip
are the same thing but I want you to
understand the difference between an
animation state and the associated
motion that's the main thing to learn
from this. OK so once we've lowered we
are going to exit this sub state
machine. So we come into the substate machine. raise. swipe. lower exit and that's just fine
swipe has a motion but raise and lower
don't do anything yet
that's absolutely fine. so let's try
it. Let's see what happens. We loop around
the idle state. we trigger the parameter.
Boom. It goes into the machine it's doing
the animation if you look down the end
of the play space and here in the swipe
and then it goes to lower and then it exits back up to the top level. Look at that isn't
that wonderful.
The only other thing you might want to
watch out for is that your default state
in this sub state machine and your entry
so at the moment what's the default
state what's the entry point you can
right-click and say set as layer default
state but you don't need to because what's
happening the flow that's happening is
we're coming into entry. raise. swipe lower. The thing that you do want to be aware
of is if you hadn't already created this
transition over here from idle to tidy
let's remove it and try putting in again
it's going to be different now. Find it. now make the
transition from idle to tidy look what
happens I can't just make it. I've got to make a
choice it's saying do I want to jump
into a specific state or do I want to
just link to the state machine
called tidy. Well I want to link to the state
machine called tidy. really important it would
be really strange and and and dangerous
to be linking directly into a sub-state
of tidy. Sure. there are instances when you would want to do that but the whole point in
our case of putting all these things in
the tidy sub-machine is that it deals
with the sequence of events so link
to the state machine itself and then in
tidy we determine what happens. So have a
little browse around all that. make sure that
makes sense to you and make sure you
understand what's going on here. So why
did we jump then for example when I just
played straight across because I didn't
put a parameter in. Yeah we need a tidy trigger and no exit time so now
we loop we trigger we go.
Fantastic. alright so you get the idea
there now your turn
so back over to you I want you to set up
your reset animation create a reset
substate machine set up a reset
trigger and just include the following
steps again. swipe. renew and lower
you can use the swipe motion on swipe
but renew create yourself a new motion
for renew but obviously don't do
anything with it yet and then lower you
can reuse and this is one of the
beauties of using the sub-state machines
like this how you can reuse the lower
clip that we used before
OK so swipe. use the existing motion. renew. create a new motion. lower. use the existing
motion
Go ahead and set that sub state machine
up now make sure it works in the same
way as the other one did. Awesome. welcome back so
let's do this thing let's make this
other sub state machine so I will this
time I'll do the transition later let's
just set up the sub states. So what is the
first thing you do when you reset? Well
if you look at the challenge it was to
swipe. renew and then lower so let's
start by swiping. So it's a new state
because it's part of this new state
machine so we swipe first with motion
what well with the swipe motion.
Fantastic now next state. We are going to
renew this is a new thing this is going
to create new pins.
There it is. Now you see somewhere. if you try and name something and it
starts putting numbers on the end it's
because you already have that thing
named so I already have this thing named
renew I just made a mistake so be aware
of that. If you see it starting to increment
numbers it's because it's trying to
prevent duplication of names. You can
have swipe here and in a different
substate machines swipe swipe no
problem; in fact it would make sense but
within a state machine or sub state
machine you cannot have two different
states with the same name which kind of
makes sense. So that's renew and then the
final one is lower which is a different
state because it's in a different state
machine but it's going to use the same
motion which currently doesn't do
anything it's going to call a script later.
Now we need to make ourselves a renew
motion let's do that; and again this
motion is just gonna be a call out to a
script. There it is and attach it. you get the idea. Hopefully this is really burning in your
understanding of this animator. It's a
fantastically powerful general state
machine and you can use it by the way
don't tell anybody I said this but you
could use it almost to program your game
you can build in game logic in fact we
are building in game logic right here
aren't we we're determining the game
execution flow diagrammatically and the
diagram is actually going to to run and
make the game and it's a bit like a
blueprint over in Unreal this is; we
can do some of that sort of stuff over here
in Unity.
So pretty cool so I've just made default
transitions between these. it just means it
does its thing and moves on. Nothing to
configure on the transitions; what we do
need finally is the transition from idle
to reset - again that annoying menu pops
up but it's a really important menu; do we want to jump into a sub-state no
no. no no no
we know the dangers of that now ok so
we just dive straight into the sub-state
machine itself and let the sub-state
machine handle what's going on
remember to transition back. So we're nearly there. but we need a parameter so here we go
It's going to be called reset trigger and this transition's condition is that it's
reset trigger
OK. fantastic let's try it and see if it
works. We're sitting in idle. we get a reset
trigger coming from a script or a
UI button or from wherever. from the gods
above what happens boom we swipe. it's
working. it's
taking as long as it takes we go into
renewing which does nothing lowering
which does nothing and we come back out.
Awesome let's do a tidy trigger. We raise. we swipe. I don't know about you but this is
really satisfying this is exciting. this
is programming with diagrams that is
perfect for an idiot like me because
then I don't have to think about the code. I
can just program with a diagram. how
cool is that? I think it's cool. anyway if
you don't think it's cool then you're a heathen and I'm sorry to
say so but anyway right
we're done we're done we have made
fantastic progress we have sub state
machines working we have a little widget.
it looks like Knight Rider that's why
I like it so much look at that. That idle
state blue bar looks like Knight Rider
that's what's so cool about it I've
realized why i like it so much now
anyway guys nuff said I see in the next
video.