Hey, fantastic students, welcome back. Now we're gonna be calling some animator
helper scripts to raise and lower our
pins so in this video we'll be adding
temporary UI buttons for reset and
tidy,
later those things will be done by the
scoring system. We'll be writing a raise
pins method to lift up all the standing
pins. We'll write a lower pins method to
lower them down again and then we'll
test it all works so back over in Unity
first I want to note that I have updated
my version of Unity I'm currently on
5.01 f1 so you wanna be at least that
version by the time you're watching this
video you might well be on a much
later version. No problem. Another thing I
want to say is that if when you first
install unity you like me
renamed your unity folder to unity 5. Your
unity 5 folder to unity 5, then that may
cause you a problem because when you
come to patch unity it's not gonna like
that and it's going to try to reinstall
in a unity folder for a rather than a unity
five so my recommendation is that you
keep unity four point six if you wanna
keep it in a folder called unity 4.6
that you keep unity five in a folder
just called unity so that it patches
properly. Fantastic, but that was an aside
So the first thing we want to do is to
create a couple of buttons here, tidy and reset that we
can click on and they're going to have
exactly the same effect as us clicking
these animation state triggers in here so
that's the first objective for this
video is simply that you can click on
tidy trigger and it will have exactly
the same effect. Now if like you me
your animator has stalled, it's not running
then I would suggest you go to this
transition from idle and remove your
tidy trigger condition and just re-add it
and see if that fixes it
often does for me that doesn't work try
cycling this has exit time toggle box
out of play mode, and if that still doesn't fix it try turning auto live link off and back
on again and hopefully your animator
will start springing into life. So even
though I patched unity I'm still finding
minor problems with this but I find that
if you just change some things that it
will suddenly start working so what
we're trying to do is we're trying to put UI
buttons that simply do the same as
clicking these buttons here in the
animator just as a piece of testing
harness. So let's go ahead and just do
that first because there's nothing to prevent us
so your challenge of course add two
buttons to your UI, connect them to the
PinSetter game object and work out how
to trigger the animation states now be
careful because the UI system will have
something called reset trigger and it's got
nothing to do with our reset trigger so
take a look around see if you can work
out how it works
read the docs if necessary but just play
with things and see if you can get it
working
great-great-great so welcome back I'm
not going to spend too much time on how
to do UI buttons right because we've done
this a billion times or at least once
before so let's just quickly put a
UI button on the panel here make sure
that it's subbed to the left panel
gonna call it tidy and gonna resize it
because I know how to party and stick it
well just leave it there right in the
centre why not, go to its text element
which is a sub-object here and just call it
tidy. If I can type... perfect here we go, tidy
now that we've got a template duplicate
that whole thing never renamed the
objects so I'm going to call that one tidy, that one
reset rushing through this because I
hope you done it lots of times and
change the text to reset and then we've
just got two buttons on top of each
other so that should do it reset tidy it
doesn't matter which order they're in. Fantastic so
now tying it up to the animator how do we
do that? Well we need to go and pick an object
so on click, so we click the Reset button, we go down to the button script component
on click Add an object. Now what are we
gonna find? Well, it's the PinSetter we want
to talk to so find the PinSetter. Now what's
the function well we can talk to the
animator but beware it's reset trigger
either takes a string or an int and it's
nothing to do with our reset trigger, we just
happened to name it the same thing. What we
actually want to do is set a trigger. What
resetting a trigger does is kind of un-set the trigger so I know triggers unset
themselves when they finish doing their
job but reset trigger would override that and do
it immediately. We want to set a
trigger and we're gonna do with a string
rather than an index. So we're setting a
trigger in this case called reset trigger.
OK? I'm actually quite glad there's a naming clash because it makes you think
carefully about what's going on and the
distinction so let's just test that, let's
click reset and see if it has the same
effect as clicking reset down here click
reset on your UI and it did
perfect it's triggered the animator. Fantastic so we're pretty confident that
tidy will work the same way right
search for PinSetter. Choose the
animator to set a trigger by a string
called tidy trigger. Now beware when you
do this you've now got information in two
places. Yuck. You have a tidy trigger here and a tidy trigger here so if you rename this object
you're gonna break these buttons but
these buttons are temporary anyway later
the scoring system which is gonna be all on
the right hand side over here will be
responsible for making the decision
about whether we are resetting or
tidying but that's a little further down
the road so let's test that tidy button
boom that works. Great so now we need to
get something in place for actually calling
into the raise and lower script. So where
is the raise pins and lower pins
information going to be? Where are we gonna call a method. Well it's the PinSetter's
job surely to raise and lower pins. So
let's go to the PinSetter and lay the
foundations for your coding challenge.
When it decides to open. Come on PinSetter
Here you come. Sounds like a dog doesn't it? So firstly if we're gonna raise and lower pins by a
certain amount in y why do we give in y, by y I mean the y direction why don't we
give the designer or the designer part of
you control over that
distanceToRaise and make it I don't
know 0.4, 40 centimetres? Well
done if you spotted the error there so
this is a post-edit to the video Dondi has
helpfully pointed out that if you you
try and use nought point four as your
distance to raise then it's not gonna
work very well because of course we've
decided for this game to make our world
units represent one centimeter rather
than one meter so no point to have a
centimeter is only four millimeters and
that's not gonna be far enough so you
need to be using a value here of forty
we will fix it later in the course but
please just set this value to 40 now
either in the script or over in the inspector
which will override the value in the
script. Good luck. Is that enough well I don't know let's go have a look at the PinSetter, and
look at the swiper - there it is, maybe scroll around a little bit. How tall is this guy? He is
25 centimetres tall so if we take a pin
and we move it up forty centimeters
should be plenty of room for the swiper to get underneath. Great so that seems like a
reasonable instance variable to use
distanceToRaise and that's what we're
going to do in our method which is going
to be called raise pins and lower pins so
create yourself two new methods void public actually because we want access from outside, void
RaisePins like so and this is going to raise
standing pins only by the distance we
just talked about. Fantastic and then make
another method called LowerPins. Hopefully you can
see where I'm going with this and that's
going to put the pins back down on the
ground fantastic. So I'm gonna put a
couple of log entries in now just to get
it all tied up and then you're gonna
write RaisePins and LowerPins
Debug.Log raising pins, cryptically enough
and what do you think I'm gonna put in
this other method what log entry
can you guess
Fantastic so we're lowering the pins
there so now that we have those Log entries
we can do the final tying up in our
animator so raise pins does have a
motion we created a motion if you didn't
make one now click onto the PinSetter in
the animator and go to the raise motion for
a start and click the event button of
course so were adding a raise
event. Now it will list all methods on
all scripts that are on PinSetter and
everything below it, which is why we made that architectural change. One of those is raise
pins. Let's make sure that that method
actually does get called. Nowfor it to
be called a few things need to be in
place; this raise state must have a motion
and the motion must have an event
trigger on it. Now let's see if that's
enough to make it work. So looking at the
console now which we can do we don't need to
look into the animator we know that if
we do a tidy for instance that one of the things
it would need to do is a raise. So click your tidy button
and it's not logging out. OK so that's
strange why is this event not being
called try setting it at a non-zero time. It doesn't have to raise the pins
immediately try after say point three of
a second, see how get on then. So here we
are you can look at the animator if you
want and use this tidy trigger button. We
do a raise now what does the console say
raising pins better so that the knack
here is to make sure that your event is
at a non-zero time. Events  that are precisely zero
time doesn't like it
alright cool so let's do the same for
the lower states. Just create yourself
an event, link it to lower pins put it in a
non-zero time and then we're good to go
So is there anything else left in the
animator we need to deal with?
We have raising, swiping, lowering. Let's
look at the other state machine... renewing
we need to renew the pins as well; well
why not pop over to the PinSetter and
write that method while we're here. Public void RenewPins and makes new pins in fact you
don't even need a comment because why
not just log a comment effectively
works as both a log entry and a comment
doesn't it? Unless you wanna say more the y
say more about the Y like the
standing pins only that's good enough so
I want you to do the same thing for the renew now
the renew motion needs to do exactly the same thing have an event method I'm gonna put
it at point of a second and I'm gonna
renew pins. Fan-diddly-an-tastic. So
let's check all this works look at your
console try a tidy. Raising pins, swiping
you can see happening there and then
lowering pins. Won-diddly-on-derful. OK let's start
again and try it with a reset. So a reset does what it swipes. Yep we can see it swiping and
then it renews the pins and it lowers
them. Awesome. Of course, it doesn't do it yet because we haven't quite
written the code to do it yet and guess who's going to be writing the code. So
now we have laid the foundations you are
going to be able to write that code so
guess what type of slide I'm about to
put up on the screen. A challenge slide
of course and here it is. Finish raise
pins and lower pins flesh out these two
methods in PinSetter.cs Create two
temporary UI buttons tidy and reset
aren't I kind I've done that for you; and test
that the game is now fully playable
basically if the tidy and reset work
properly then the game should be
playable at the end of it so good luck
with that challenge.
Of course there'll be no scoring but it should work. OK, you ready? Ready to see the solution or do you need more
missing the solution
time you get the idea by now you pause
the video right? If you need more time. OK, fantastic so let's go
into these scripts and take a look and
see what we gonna do
firstly how's raise pins gonna work?
Well in simple terms it's gonna iterate
over all the pins and see if
they're standing and lift them up if they
are now you might say isn't that a bit
slow, well maybe it's a bit slow this
remember this countStanding thing we did
that happens every single frame and it
does a GameObject find objects of type Pin? and you might think every frame it's
looking for every single pin. Isn't that
slow? Well maybe it's slow but you know
what I'm gonna show you something really
briefly as a bonus in Unity 5 you don't
need to guess, watch this. Play the game, go to window and profiler. First
introduction to profile not really teaching it here but it's a quick aside for you OK?
Now type PinSetter in this search box and
you can see that the PinSetter's update
loop is taking less than a millisecond at the moment. You might say
well let's ok but it doesn't start
really doing anything until the ball
gets down the end of the game; down the
end of the play space and this figure
starts updating true, let's do that, go
back to your performance profiler while
it's running and watch how long this
PinSetter update script's taken to run. Still negligible anything less than sort
of 10 milliseconds for us at the moment
is fine. This is taking point one of a millisecond. A
milliseconds a thousandth of a second so
I 10,000 or 20,000th of a second is taking
no time to do that
find find all objects so don't worry
about it so sometimes we think things
are going to be slow they aren't and now
with the profiler we can start to look
at that and we'll introduce the profiler more
love more and more now that it's in
unity five. Cool, so I'm just gonna do
this the easy way not worrying about
performance of the methods that I'm using. So how are we gonna raise the pins
well we're just gonna borrow some
information from down here actually from
the count standing for each pin. It's
very much like that and if we use this
many more times we may refactor it
but in for each pin if it's standing so
we want to raise the pin so the pins
transform; now you could go dot translate
that's an easier way of doing things, and
what's that gonna take a Vector3 so
we construct the Vector3 right in
here it's gonna have zero in the
x-direction its gonna have distance to
raise in the y direction and zero in the
z direction
Oh, that's quite exciting does that work is
that really gonna raise the pins well no
Because I've gone and put the code in the lower pins but who cares you copy and paste it into
there so raise pins is simply going to iterate an entire pins array; again don't stress about the
speed of this I've just show you it takes 20 thousandths of a second and we're only doing it
once, so just let's have a look and see
if it works. What we're wanting to happen is
that when we do a tidy for example we
raise the pins and it's raised most of
the pins, has it raised them up? Let's just have a look and see what happened there tidy...
So what is happening here let's look at
the end of the scene and click the tidy 7
pins disappear 3 pins fall back down.
Interesting, so we know why they're
falling down; they're  falling down because of
gravity but why on earth do 7 pins disappear and
only three raise up? Well, i could just
solve it for you or, you know what I'm
gonna do I'm going to ask you to find
the bug.
maybe there's more than one in the
system so save your work before you
start fiddling if you're using code
control here then take a snapshot
because in my experience when you start
trying to resolve bugs you mess around with things
a lot and that's fine and that's great
but if you are not using code
control then just save your Unity Project
Just close Unity is the
safest way zip up the whole folder and
say before bug finding or something in a zip folder.
If you're using code repository take
a snapshot in your repo and say
about to squash this bug or something
like that then see if you can work out
what the hell's is going on here. I can
tell you that there's at least one; at
least two different simultaneous weird
things going on as I can guess what's
happening here and then thirdly we will
address the debugging; I'll change that slide,
strategy in the next video so
congratulations - not congratulations but good luck with
finding that bug and I'll see you in the next video.