Hey guys and girls. welcome back!
So. we have some bugs! So. in this video we're going to learn a bit
more about Transform.Translate(). use the
Step Button to slow things down. talk about the perils
of moving Static Colliders. how
default animation blends can cause issues. and
also warning you about moving motion clips around. which
is another thing that caused our bug. So. let's take a look at these things.
one at a time. and see where our problems
have been caused. Let's start by reminding ourselves
what the problem is. The problem is that. when you click Tidy
in the game
state here. you see the way the pins disappear? Let's get
the pins up. on the left hand side here. So you
play the game. hit the Tidy trigger. and a
bunch of pins disappear. If we go down and look at the Scene View.
you've only got two or three pins left. And
what's going on? So. firstly my pins
are not lifting. so let's deal with that element first. If you go to
your PinSetter Script
and take a look at the
"(Raising pins") method. I have said transform.Translate
and then I put in a Vector3. but let's look at the
docs for Transform.Translate. just for a moment.
You'll notice something in the docs. the Transform
.Translate. which is this.
"If relativeTo is left out or
set to Space.Self the
movement is applied relative to the transform's local axes."
So. this thing here is defaulting to
a transform. relative to the local axes
of the pin. rather than
the global axes of the game. And we want to move this thing
up. in the global Y space. so we need to just
add in a comma space dot world.
So. let's just do that. On the end of your translate
function. you can put in .Space.World);
And that should make it reliably move up. in the global
Y direction. in the game's general Y direction. Let's just
take a look at that first bit. and make sure that over in this
Scene View. the pins rise up. They do! You can see that they are
raised up there. in the very beginning. Let's just check it again.
Click play. the pins do raise
up. OK. sure they fall down again. but we'll deal with all that
in a moment. So. that was the lesson about
the Transform.Translate. but I still want to know why these pins
are disappearing. so here's another trick for you. Let's
go to the Animator. turn off your trigger for a sec. play the game.
go and have a look down at the
end. and then. pause the game.
You can set your trigger off. even in Pause Mode.
and I'm going to look at my PinSetter here.
Do you remember the Pin Setter Box over here? It has a Box Collider
on it. the Pin Setter. So. let's
start stepping through and see what happens.
Now. if for some
reason your Box Collider is not showing. mine is off in the Gizmos
for some reason. you're welcome to turn it back on. I'd like you to
be able to see your Box Collider. I'm not sure how my ended up off.
So. as I step through frame by frame here. watch what happens! Ahh.
those back pins disappear out the end of the Box Collider.
and then they get destroyed by that OnTrigger
Exit Script. So. this
moving step by step is incredibly useful for spotting that
sort of thing. Now. of course there are two issues here. One is
why is the whole Box Collider moving? And the other
is. why are the pins being destroyed. when it goes out the back?
Well. they're being destroyed. when it goes out the back. simply
because the code tells them to be destroyed. If you look at your
PinSetter code. you have an OnTriggerExit.
and it says if a pin leaves the collider.
then destroy it. Also. we shouldn't really be
moving this collider. because it is a Static Collider.
If you'll remember back to your Collider Interaction Matrix.
it's just a Static Collider. because it has no Rigidbody on it.
We don't want to be moving those. So.
why are we moving them? Well. we're moving it because
when we took our motion. that was attached to the Swiper
and renamed it PinSetter. it was a
motion that was just effecting the transform. Remember the
motion here is just effecting the transform of the thing
it was attached to. It used to be attached to the PinSetter. it's now
up to the Swiper rather. it's now attached to the PinSetter. so it's
moving the entire PinSetter. Now. because the Swiper
is a child object of the PinSetter. they are all moving together
in that same animation sequence. Let's watch them do it. You see that.
So. that'a a bit weird right? And that's
a little bit weird that that's doing that. and that's what's causing the bug.
So. a warning about moving animation clips
around. How do we fix it? Well. good question!
There's two ways you could fix it. You could either remake your animation. which is what
I'm going to suggest. because it's going to produce the most fundamental solution.
The problem here is that we're animating now the wrong
thing; we're animating the whole PinSetter. rather than just the Swiper
inside it. so I'm going to suggest doing that. There are other
ways around this. Of course. you could on this Animator
here. say to the Box Collider. you could turn it off
but that's just adding complexity. Turning the Box
Collider off. at the start of the animation. and then.
turning it on again is a bit nasty. it's
adding complexity to try and solve the problem. Whenever you're doing
that. you're making things worse. really. So. if you can
bite the bullet and redo this animation. which I'll do in a moment. then that's
always going to be a better way of doing things. But I want to show you one
more potential problem with this as well. which also makes it quite hard to
debug. Watch this! If you look at the transition
in the tidy substate.
from Raise to Swipe. you'll notice that by default over here
in the Inspector it has a blend.
What that means is that. it... Oh. let me just try
and get it back on the screen. There we go! It has this blend. it
spends a little bit of time both in Raise and Swipe.
and of course. it doesn't trigger that piece of code
to raise the pins. until very near the
end of the Raise motion.
And have a look at the Raise motion. where it is at the end of it. it
is just a call to a piece of script. So.
let's watch what happens step by step again.
when we trigger. So. let's to through...
I have to start again.
So. start with your trigger off. pause the game.
look at the scene. maybe get the
PinSetter on the screen. play the game.
and then. we've already done the trigger. so I'm going to go to the top
level. Step
through the Idle state. until... I'll just redo
the trigger. just in case I forgot it. Step through the Idle state
until it's finished. Here you go! So we're going through Raise now.
Raise raise. Now look. you see the Swipe
motion. you see this blue line going down the
transition here. It's saying there's a blend in progress. and
even before the Raise has finished or even
triggered. look the thing is moving! The box is moving.
so we delete the back pins.
Then. we're raising up and then because gravity is
on. the pins fall down. So. hopefully you can
understand all of those different things. interactions. that are going
on there. So. we'll fix it in just a moment. but I just want to put the
problem back on the screen for you. so you can understand.
So. we decided to use Transform.Translate() and that's fine!
Of course. you could have said Transform.position +=
in a vector. That would have worked fine. If you are going to use
Transform.Translate() be aware of that last parameter. and make your
decision about whether you're moving in world space or relative to the
object. Number two. using the Step button to
slow things down. Incredibly helpful. you can do it at any time.
You can pause the game and go through one frame at a time. really handy.
Number three. the perils of moving those
Static Colliders. So. we don't want to move a Static Collider.
Unity doesn't expect Static Colliders like that
PinSetter Box to be moving. so don't move them.
Number four. how default animation blends can cause issues.
So. if you were wondering why
the Swipe motion was starting to
happen. before even the Raise happened. that's because
of the blend. the Animation State Blend. And by default you'll have
those blends in there. to try and make animations smooth. but if
you're calling functions from script and you have a blend in
place. it can cause problems. And be careful
about moving your motion clips around. because otherwise. you're going to have to do what we
ought to do now. which is just redo this animation.
The animation. in my case. wasn't great anyway. I'm very sorry if you spend a
lot of time on your animation. I want to use this as
a warning to you about the difficulty. actually. of copying an animation.
because I don't know a way of getting this animation
in here. from the Swipe motion
of the pin. I don't know how to get these keyframes.
and I have had a good look. there are some tools that'll do it.
But I don't know any standard way in Unity of taking all these keyframes and applying
them to what we need it to be applied to now.
which is the Swiper's transform. of course .position.
That's the thing that we need to be adding to this. We need to
dig in and add very similar keyframes to the Swiper.
So. you can do it just by inspection. of course. but you're
not going to easily be able to do it by copying
and pasting. even in the curves. Some people seem to have had some luck;
I can't make it work reliably enough to teach it. So. what I'm
going to do is. I'm just going to delete all of the properties that
move the PinSetter's position and just leave
the sub-object. Swiper. and just reanimate. I'm just going to delete
all the keyframes and just reanimate. There's not a huge amount of value
in there. in my case. So. what I'm going to
do is just go in. in the Recording Mode of the Animator.
you're hopefully getting quite used to now. and I am
going to start putting my keyframes in. So. my first keyframe is going
to be at say half a second. something like that.
Remember. you can zoom in by holding down Alt and
rolling the mouse wheel.
So. it's something like. this time I'm going to put in a keyframe.
and just go ahead now. really quickly. and rebuild that animation.
So obviously. I've sped up the video
again here. I'm going to make more and more use of that technique. as we go
through the course. so that we can get some leverage on
your time. when it's repetitive things like this.
So. we're just going ahead and reproducing a very similar
animation. to before. by moving the object
around in this Record Mode of the Animator.
and then placing our keyframes and their positions.
as we go. And then. I'm making sure
that the Swiper comes back. I'm using the Inspector
occasionally. to look at the Z position of
the Swiper. so that we return to the same
horizontal position. before moving up vertically.
And then finally. to smooth out
the motion. I'm going to be taking a look at the curves.
so that the Swiper doesn't go through the floor. So. by
holding down Alt and scrolling around or double clicking.
if you're not sure. you should get to the curves. Look for your
Y curve. and you can get a really nice motion.
OK welcome back! So. we've got a pretty cool looking
Swipe motion. going on there now. which is fantastic! And
we're back to where we want to be. with the simplest possible solution.
which was redoing the PinSetter's
animation motion. for the
Swipe motion and we're digging into the
swiper. OK fantastic! So.
that's working nicely now. Now. what we need to do. or what
you need to do is just get these Raise and Lower pins methods finished off.
So. it's going to be a challenge for you now. Let's go ahead and do that!
Refactor Raise and LowerPins(). Enter Pin.cs.
We don't really want it in the PinSetter. there's enough stuff in the PinSetter.
Now. let's move some of the responsibility over to the
pin itself. So. move RaisePins()
and LoverPins() into Pin.cs. Rename them Raise() and Lower(). because
the context now tells you what they do.
Create a distToRaise. at the top of the Pin.cs
class. which is going to be a property that tells us how
high we need to raise them. It will depend on the height of the pins mainly.
And disable and re-enable
gravity as necessary. during the animation sequence.
so that the pins don't fall. And just test that the whole lot works
together. properly for me. So go ahead. pause the video! See if you can get
all this. Tidy and Reset. finished off and working
properly. now that we've solved the bugs.
OK great! Fantastic!
Welcome back! So. let's go ahead and do this refactoring. It's always a good
thing to be refactoring. when you think that you need to.
So. I'm going from Pinsetter to Pin. so I may as well rearrange
my tabs at the top. so I know what I'm doing.
And just take a look. So. where have we got
RaisePins and LowerPins here?
Well. we already have a RaisePins and LowerPins
in PinSetter. Now. you're going to need to leave the RaisePins
and LowePins methods there. of course. because otherwise the
Animator will not be able to make the calls to them
because an Animator can only call scripts that are on the object
or sub objects. But we're just going to make them a very thin
pass through. So. rather than saying
if the pin is standing. do all this.
we'll take that responsibility and put it
over in the pin here. So.
over in the pin. let's go to the bottom and pop that code in
and then. wrap it in a public...
Yes it does need to be public; public Raise ()
and it's void. it doesn't send anything back. Public
void Raise () and then.
we need to just change that code up a little bit. so it's no longer if (pin.
IsStanding(). because we are in the context now of the pin.
so it's just (IsStanding(). Again. we don't need the pin
.transform.Translate. distanceToRaise...
...distToRaise. Just stick
with my example. and then. at the top of the method
we are going to go public float
distToRaise = I'm going to give it a default of 40 centimeters.
It's about right for this size of pin.
So. if it's standing raise it. that's fine!
That's done right! If it's standing raise it. that's simple.
And let's have another method. which is public
Lower () and is void. I keep forgetting the
return types tonight. So fantastic! There you
go! So. we're just going to lower them. regardless.
We're just going to transform.Translate it downwards. in world
space. by minus the distance. which
is why I'm using a variable because we can change the same thing in two places.
Great! So. we also said that we
wanted to turn the gravity
off of all of the pins. in question. So.
let's not do that here. because we...
Do we have access to the Rigidbody? Yes. we do! OK.
because we already have access to the Rigidbody and the pin. let's go ahead
and do that. So. it's going to simply a case of going say. rigidBody
.gravity or use gravity
= false; So. we turn gravity
off and raise it up. and then. when we lower it down. we put gravity back
on at the end. So. we put it down on the floor and turn gravity back
on. And that's how we stop the pins from falling.
Cool! So.
there's my code
for the raise and lower. inside the pins. and then. all I need to do
over in the PinSetter. when I raise. I say for each
pin just pin.Raise();
Just showing you how you can move
code around all you like and just change the API.
and don't be afraid to refactor and do this. So. pin
.lower. Oops. small p. Ah.
OK. so with LowerPins of course. I've got to do the same thing. roughly the same
same thing. I just need to
iterate through like this. and pin.Lower ();
So. one other thing is. it's not just raising them. it's raising
them if standing.
So. I'm actually going to change my suggestion from the challenge. having
done it. and just make this method on Pin.cs. Raise if
Standing (). because that's what it actually does.
OK. let's try all this and see how we get on.
So. the main thing to be concerned about is. what happens
when we click the Tidy trigger? Does it work?
Hmm. sort of. the Raise isn't happening.
Now. that's probably just because we've been playing around
with the names of our methods and it's disconnected.
Raise and lets just check Lower. while
we're here. LowerPins().
OK. so I'm a bit concerned that
this thing is called Raise. Go back to your code. make sure...
Ah OK! RaisePins ()
OK. just get your name in right. Now. when you change your
method name. back in the Animator. you probably
find you're going to need to reconnect that.
Yep you are. OK fantastic!
So hopefully now. with any luck when we're looking
down at the end and we go through our various animation
triggers it'll work. Tidy trigger! Raises!
The animation happens like that. the Swipe happens all the way to the back
and it drops them down. Beautiful! Let's try the Reset! We
are not raising in the Reset. What's happening
there? Well. you're not supposed to Raise
it in the Reset. That's absolutely fine! Yeah. the Reset is
not yet instantiating new pins. but that will be for another video.
All I want to do to finish this one off is to bowl the ball down
and have a few standing pins. before I Tidy.
And then. I am done for this video. and we'll talk about instantiating
new pins and what else we need to do.
in terms of tidying up in the next video. So. let's just check
that the Tidy actually really works properly now.
[Ball Sound Effect in Background]
Here it comes! So. the pin counting
is working. that's fantastic! Let's hit Tidy! Oh. it's
gone to the Start. That's absolutely fine! And let's hit Tidy now.
That's great. because we've actually got a couple of pins
to swipe out of the way. at least one. Lift up.
swipe the remaining pin. it comes back. and
drops them down. Look at that! Beautiful! Beautiful! Beautiful! Beautiful!
So. that's good enough for this video. You've done really well.
and we will polish off all of this
and do a little bit of code refactoring. in the next video.
before moving on to different things like physics. And then
Eventually. we'll swing all the way around to the scoring system. So. good progress
and we'll see you soon!