Welcome back again fine people; so in
this video we're going to be talking
about refactoring your code; we'll touch
on the single responsibility principle
which is a part of a wider framework of
SOLID which you can read all about
through the Wikipedia article on single
responsibility here and then by linking
up to SOLID if you choose to over here.
So with single responsibility in mind
let's go through now before we move on
to the final phase of this game and do a
little bit of refactoring. So firstly I
want to just go to the main camera; I
want to go to through all the game objects basically
have a quick look at them and I also
want to go through all the scripts and have a
quick look at them so the main camera
well one thing I'd like to do in the
main camera set a different skybox on
this main camera because I'm gonna make
it like a space bowling game. So add a
component to the main camera called a skybox
and then under custom Sky box
point it into your start pack that we
gave you the beginning of the section
and choose stars 1024. So now in game view
you have a starry spacey bowling game
which is what we're going to converge towards
anything else about this main camera
that needs tidying up right now I'm
happy we have no disconnected objects so
I'm gonna move on; top camera's working just
fine as well. The Pinsetter. how's  that
looking for us? Again i'm looking for any
disconnected objects or anything in here
this glaringly obviously wrong no fine. so
move on
lane so the lane has been restructured
so that it has a floor and a separate
collider under the floor just make sure
that the top level of your floor and your
collider are the same and that your collider is nice and deep and then as far as
I'm concerned that is absolutely fine
for now you may want to put a different
physics material on this floor. so here I
have a default physics material in fact
I'm gonna make a folder for this right
now
physics materials and  put the default in it. You may want
to separate floor material. if you do
that you can attach it to the floor and
play with the properties of the floor
material I'm gonna leave that to you to
make it more or less slippery or however
you want it but that's looking fine
the directional light is inside the lane
that's a little bit spooky a little bit
strange so we goona be happy with that? Or shall we pull it out? I'm gonna pull it out right to the
top and also do we want three levels of
hierarchy we don't really need it we
can just call this collider floor
collider and it doesn't need to be sub to
it
ok so you can see how it's very easy to
reflect your hierarchy. Looking better
the UI canvas is all fine and working
fine; the pins good one thing to check
with the pins is are they still connected
your prefabs here they're blue so they
should be that's good we have an event
system the event system is part of the
UI. I'm gonna put that above the UI just to remind me that it's part of the UI and then the ball itself
is connected to a prefab. Good so no
problems that are glaringly obvious over
there now let's look at our scripts and
think about refactoring. Ball. what is the
ball doing for us and is it singularly
responsible for being a ball? Well it has
a launch velocity which kind of makes
sense and it has a Boolean. a public
Boolean that talks about whether it's in
play so these are both properties of the
ball and I'm happy enough with that. Then
it has some private methods less
important that they are right but the
question is are these things
sensible helper variables or private
variables and for the class? Well. I
think they are we its start position.
access to its RigidBody and access to
its AudioSource so all perfectly reasonable.
So let's zoom out a little bit again in
our mind and think what are the public
methods of this guy now? I don't really
care what happens in start it just
does some set up stuff but is it
reasonable to say there's a public
method to launch a ball with a velocity
and a public method to reset the ball. I
think it is so I think the ball class at
the moment looks reasonable so I'm happy
with it I don't need to move any code
around let's move on and look at the
camera controller. It's incredibly simple
you point it to a ball. it privately keeps
track of an offset and it keeps the
camera behind the ball until you get to
1829 which is the end position. You could
publicly expose this 1829 as a stock
position if you wanted to I'm hard
coding it in
in this case I'm happy enough with the
camera control script. DragLlaunch. So
DragLaunch is specifically for balls so
indeed it requires the ball component
so I might want to rename DragLaunch tp
BallDragLaunch just so it's super
clear that it won't work on other things
it's very much a specialist script to
talk to Balls. It has no public
members and does it need all of
these private members. are they sensible. well I
think they are. that's all fine and again
I have no issues with this. Let's look at
your public methods is it reasonable for
a drag script to have a move start?
Well yes that's what these buttons do
remember at the start here we start
playing the game these left and right
buttons nudge left and right move
start reasonable. Then we have a public
drag start method so what's that about
where's that being called from? Well that's
going to be called because of a mouse
event from the UI and I think that that's fine
that there's a drag start and a drag end and
then the drag end is responsible for
actually launching the ball so I think
this is ok a BallDragLaunch script is
responsible for drag launching a ball.I
think that's reasonable so no changes
needed there. Pin. Now is this Pin
thing reasonable. Is it reasonable to
have a standing threshold for a pin I
think so. it's to do with the geometry of
the pin it's a property of the pin the
distance to raise the pin it's a moot point
whether this should go here with the pin
or the Pinsetter. You could argue it should
be the pin because it depends how big the
pin is. you could argue should be with the
Pinsetter because it's a property of how
the Pinsetter operates. so I'm leaving
here for now and then we have a private
RigidBody. So now let's look at your
public methods. we have an isStanding we
can ask a pin if it's standing. I think
that's fine we can raise it if it's
standing and we can lower it from the
outside reasonable architecture. Good so so
far we're just confirming that our
architecture makes sense. Pinsetter lot of
public properties are they all sensible?
This last standing count being minus one
that's the ugliest bit of arco
but it's nice and concise and I'm gonna
leave it like this for now but I accept
that this is not great what the hell
does minus one mean good question you
could use different data structures but
you'd end up writing more code to make
it read nicer so you'd have more code
that reads more nicely the trick is
that the less code the better so I'm
going to leave that. The Pinsetter needs to
update the standing display it needs to
know the distance to raise now we have a
duplication. This is talking about a
distance to raise in here and the pin is
talking about the distance to raise as
well so I'm not happy having distance to
raise in both the Pinsetter and the pin.
so my first question would be do we use
it in Pinsetter? Find it.
where's the second instance. we don't use
it anymore we've already refactored it out.
Raise pins only by distance to raise. so
we can take that comment away and we can
take the distance to raise away from the
Pinsetter OK so it's one place or the
other it's in pins. Awesome. does it need the pin
set yes it needs to know what is going
to reinstantiate. Okay and then privately
it has some variables. we won't worry about that
if it works. What are the public methods would
be my next question raising pins is that a
Pinsetter's job yes lowering them is that it's job. yes renewing them yes. Check
standing
maybe. counting them it's basically
counting the number of pins. so is check
standing a good name?
Well what is it actually doing? It's
counting it's updating the standing count
that's what this method actually does. So.
but it also goes in and does something
with the pins being settled you see so
this this is the first bit of
code that is slippery. I don't really
like the way this reads because it does
more than just check standing doesn't it? It
updates the standing count and if
they've settled it deals with the pins
having settled so you couldtry. let's
try renaming. use the refactor tool. Check
standing. check standing what do we call it
update standing count. update standing
count and settle that's a massive
method name but at least it tells you
more about what it does. I'm gonna leave
it like that for now just  the
idea is you need to know exactly what it
does. so is it reasonable for Pinsetter to
update the standing count and settle the
pins yes ok and that's a private method
so we're less worried about it in a way the
reason we're more concerned about public
methods and public variables is because
that's the API into this class; what you
can see from the outside is it's it's
variables here and its methods and then
the dirty way that you actually get the
job done is less important but still
important than the fact that the
communication between things is correct
so I think all of this looks ok the Pinsetter
is doing some stuff with collisions
here which strictly our shredders really
a shredders job how we could have a
separate game object called a shredder and
then make that do the destruction here
if you wanted to. For the sake of showing
you how to refactor let's just pull this
bit out of Pinsetter into a shredder
script and then I'm gonna leave you to
go through all of your code and make
sure that you're happy with it's
structure. So what I'm gonna do is I'm
gonna go to the pin setter over here and
I'm gonna say well okay that's fine but
it's also going to act as a shredder. So let's add
a new component called shredder
you don't need a different; you don't necessarily need a
different collider but we need a different
behavior. Put the shredder script in
there and then let's go to the Pinsetter
and pull out this code here which
purely shreds things. OK. and then put that
in your newly found shredder script and
make sure that it works so back to the
Pinsetter OnTriggerEnter is very much a Pinsetter
job because this has to do with
keeping track of whether the ball enters
the box and updating the standing
display but the shredding was very much
nothing to do with the Pinsetter so now
this Pinsetter box collider and the game
object has a shredder component to it let's just
check that things work now that we've
done all this this refactor so go into
your game. bowl your bowl. So on the ball the problem
is that we have renamed our script from
ball from DragLaunch to BallDragLaunch so we need
to reconnect that script one of the
dangers of refactoring which is why it's important to
test regularly. Now you'll also probably
find that your touch input panel is now
no longer properly connected. so you need
to go and find your DragStart method
and your DragEnd Methods. OK
Fantastic now that that's all reconnected
let's just make sure that all these
changes still result in a working game
particularly at the dragging and
launching and that the pins actually get
shredded when they leave this box so
watch your pin disappearing off the side
and make sure it gets shredded. there you go.
that's working and then reset let's
check that the reset cycle works properly so
they get swiped out the way and
reinstantiated and then drop down. Great. so that's
working much more nicely for us now so
that's the spirit of the refactoring
making sure that each item is singularly
responsible for what it is doing of
course your challenge now becomes to
save your current working state on your
game go through all of your methods add
your comments in when you add comments
it's so that you're explaining why
you're doing something not what you're
doing what you're doing should be
completely clear from the code. Move code
between classes if required like we did
with the shredder and regularly as you're
doing this test that everything works. So
I've already done mine. I want you now
to go and refactor your code to your
satisfaction so you know that if you
came back in six to nine months you
could still follow your own work. So go
ahead and do that now; and I will
see you in the next video because this
one is over. See ya!