Hey welcome back guys. so I think it's
about time that we find out about how
scoring works in ten pin bowling and
draw ourselves an object communication diagram
to work out how the Pinsetter and the
scorekeeper or whatever we decide to
call it talk to each other. At the moment
in our project we have not ideal physics
certainly my project doesn't have
ideal physics but I'm getting bored of
playing with the physics and of clicking
these reset and tidy buttons and I want some
code to decide whether it's time to
reset or tidy. The challenge with that of
course is that we need to solve the
whole problem of scoring in ten pin
bowling in order to do that because
whether we lay down new pins or tidy
what's there entirely depends on what we
scored what we scored last time where we
are in the game and lots of different
factors so we really need to start
attacking that problem now and then
we'll loop around at the end of this
section when we start adding in user
interface and savings scores to disk
and then we'll worry about the final
tweaks if you wanna go ahead and tweak
your physics and tweak the way it behaves now
go ahead but I would rather do that once
the game is automatically resetting and
tidying. Sso the theme of all of this is
to understand scoring in ten pin bowling.
So firstly where can you find out about
it? Well I found quite useful YouTube
video here I suggest you go and look at
that it's called how to keep score in
bowling score in bowling by Steven
Anderson and he basically goes through
in this video and takes you step-by-step
through the process of the scoring
system and he shows you here for
instance if you bowl an eight in the
first bowl of the first frame and then
that little line means a spare. it means
that you have bowled all ten in the two
strike in the two bowls so now we have a
score of 10 in the first frame which
means we don't know the first frame
score yet and so on
Now he's gonna walk you through that I
really recommend you spend the four and
a half minutes watching that because
it's a very cogent and step-by-step
example. we'll also be using freeze-frame
from this later on in the development to
help us make sure that the scoring is
going right so that's one place you can
find out about scoring and other places
you can go to are Wikipedia and help
yourself get off to sleep at night by
reading the overly detailed but
very concise. well not concise at all
but very complete
indication of how scoring works here on
Wikipedia or you can have an adventure
and learn with the computer with us and
not even get too into it now and
just solve the challenges as they come
along however you like you may already
know all about ten pin bowling scoring
so you just need an overview right now I
would watch that video and then what we're
gonna do is I'm going to ask you to draw
an object communication diagram fact I'm
going to ask you to do that in just a
moment; before we do that let's just look
at our Pinsetter script and remind
yourself of the main functionality of it.
So it raises pins. it lowers pins. it
renews pins etc
count standing pins but it doesn't have
at the moment anyway for the reset or
the tidy to be called from anywhere but
the animator of these buttons we need
something that can call a reset and a
tidy so I think that the Pinsetter is
going to talk to a new class which is
going to be called the scorekeeper or
the score card or the scoremaster
maybe the best word and the question is
how they gonna talk to each other so if
we just had a scoremaster and a Pinsetter
what would the communication be between them
Well that's your challenge. I want you to draw a
couple of boxes on a bit of paper for
Pinsetter and scoremaster. I want you to
draw lines for the API calls that you
want to set up between them; i.e.
what methods are called. When you decide
what messages will be passed what public
properties if any you need. and mentally
just rehearse how it's gonna work
what's the PinSetter gonna say to the
scoremaster in order to have a sensible
communication between the two of them
here about what's going on and when the
resets and tidy needs doing. Now this
doesn't have to be perfect if you
haven't a clue what to do just draw
something down and try and get into the
habit of when you're not sure about the
way your top-level design works draw a
diagram that's all I'm trying to do here
is enforce a habit of drawing a diagram at
least have a go we have covered these in
previous sections and see how you get on
so welcome back. This is what we've got. we have a very
simple API for the score master class
I've defined a public enum well. we're going to
be defining a public enum called action
which means we can explicitly say
whether or not we should be tidying or
resetting so we tidy every single bowl
even if we have a gutter ball. because even
if the ball has gone flying down the
side it may have just clipped a pin on
the end and dislodged it so we always do
a tidy;
sometimes we do a full reset depending
on where we are in the game and the
frame list thing that we're passing back
which I'll show you in a moment we'll grow
as the game progresses so the PinSetter
has the option to call a method called
public Action Roll (int pins) on
scoremaster so that's a method inside
scoremaster and what it does is it
passes back an action which is either reset or tidy
and it takes in a number of pins so it
just says I've rolled  3 pins and it says what I
do next and Scoremaster goes well reset or
you tidy depends where you are in the
frame and the other thing that you can
do from the outside of school master is
you can get a frame list back from it
a list of integers of frames but only
completed frames only frames where the
score is known now as we go through or
if you watch that YouTube video you 'llknow
what I mean by that.
It's basically the concept that while
you're scoring in bowling sometimes you
don't know for a while what the score is
gonna be so here if we bowl an eight and
then a two giving us a spare or 10 in
the first frame we don't know what the
score of this frame is yet because it
depends on what we got here in this box
once that score comes in we now know
that it's ten plus a bonus of seven which
is 17. OK so we don't know the result of
every frame immediately so our frame
list is going to grow only as we get
finalized results coming into it that's
the way we're going to approach it
that's the way I'm going to approach it
for this test driven development so
that's it really that's a quick overview
of the architecture our job is going to
be to write the ScoreMaster.cs
and the approach we gonna use is test
driven development because that allows
us to write the code in a way that
always complies with our rules and if you
try and do without test driven
development I think you'd find it tricky so
we're going to use test driven development. It's also
an incredibly useful tool in your arsenal
for your ways of creating games so see you
in the next video when we'll get cracking with
it