Hey, welcome back. In this video we're gonna be making your
first test pass. So we're going to set up
ActionMaster.cs as a new class;
write our first real test code; code the
solution until the test passes and then
we'll refactor. So let's dive into unity
and recap where we are just briefly; so
the game is fine, it's doing ok it's a kind of space
bowling games a few issues like if the
ball falls of the space it doesn't
trigger anything yet we'll sort that out
a little bit later but for now our main
focus is just to get the class that
can work out whether we should be
resetting or tidying written and I'm
gonna call that class ActionMaster
because it's about the action that we do
after a certain number of pins fall
So we'll make a new class ActionMaster, a  new
script called ActionMaster go ahead and
do that now yourself and then open that
up for me so that you've got your action
master brand new empty script available
to you
fan tastic then the other thing we need
to do is go over to our editor folder and
where we had this thing called
scoremaster test I want you to rename
that instead of scoremaster test use
the refactor tool, so click on the name of
the class and do the refactor command or
control + r and call it
actionMaster test because I've had a
bit of a change of name decision we're
going to focus only on getting the right
reset tidy end game next player whatever
message back for now we're not going to
worry about adding up the frame totals
in the scoresheet so you'll see what I
mean as we go along I like to have my
test code first and then my actual
production code to the right of it, it reminds
me that it is test driven development we
start by writing the test and then we move
from left to right in the Western
convention. Fantastic so we already have
a very basic test setup it doesn't talk
to anything else it just passes and you
remember that over in Unity we have here
this passing tests running remember also
this little drop down at the top right
over here and click Run on
compile I find that that turns itself off
sometimes so occasionally you wanna go check
that still on it just saves you clicking
the run all button every time you make a change
to a script. OK fantastic so let's
firstly as per our red green refactor
loop let's start off we need to make
something red we need to make a test
fail so let's do that first let's make
sure that the first thing is a a test
failure. So let's write a test and let's
call it public void now I'm gonna
prefix these T01 for test one just because it
will appear nicely in the list we could
prefix passing test T 00 you'll
see that they just sort in this list
over in Unity then by alphabetical order
quite nicely making them very easy
reference back to the code so it doesn't
really matter what we do as a first test
but for example we know that if you
bowled a strike in the first in the
first instance then what you would want
to receive back is an end turn message
it's it's a new message if you think
about it but we'll enumerate all
the messages in a moment but let's just
call this test first strike first one
strike may be the simplest one strike
returns end turn
so if you bowl a strike in the first bowl
then it's the end of your turn
OK so that's what we are asserting is
we're going to want to happen so
first strike returns end turn so this is
where we use assert dot
are equal; we're going to use that a lot - put your
brackets and your semicolon in right at
the beginning now what
well we're gonna want an enum; we're gonna want
short code access to the enums here that
come back from action master so we are
going to need to set up these enums over
in action master so even though it's test
driven development the problem we're
gonna have if we try and write a test
here we're gonna have two issues we want to
say something like end turn equals well it
isn't even going to let me write end turn easily
because it doesn't exist it doesn't
recognize it but imagine I've written end
turn and then I also call let's say
action master AM for action master or I
could just call it action master . again
I'm going to struggle with the
autocomplete here
actionMaster . bowl ten. so that's the
idea; I'm calling the bowl method on
action Master but I'm getting a lot of red
here and it's because it doesn't recognize end
turn and it doesn't recognize action master
dot bowl. So you do you can consider this
your first bit of red if you like it's
not a failing tests but the way this
test system works you have to go to
action master and at least make this
statement make sense so how we gonna do
that we're going to create a method over
in action master called bowl so public
bowl int pins now what does it return it
returns an action so something of type
action. Now be careful because action is
already built in or words very similar
to action are built-in terms inside your
environment so we're OK with action but
be aware that your auto complete has
other things similar to action just be
aware of that so what are we gonna use
we need to define an enum so we can make
it public so they can get to it from the
outside it's in enum enumerated list
it's called action and let's put in our
curly braces straight away I like to put it
all in one line in this case so that we know
where we're putting them. So what are the
possible return states? Regardless of what
our design diagram said before let's
think about it carefully now
well one thing is a tidy; one thing
is a reset so what's the difference between a
tidy and a recent remember that the tidy
lifts the pins up put's them down again, reset
creates new pins altogether.
We've also got end turn which means
that my turn is over we need to switch
to the other player so you will normally
have end turns you'll only do reset in the
13th in the final frame rather when you
do for instance a striking and you get
awarded an extra go then you'll
get a reset on your turn
normally it would be end turn which means
do a reset but switch control to the other
player and the other factor we can have
his end game so you could enumerate
these all yourself by thinking it through
now or another approach would be just
put in all you need for now and build
this list as you go because I know where
we're going with this I'm gonna put them
all in but strictly to pass this test all
you're going to need is the end turn. Now
why are all of these in capitals and this little
guy in lowercase? Well I'm gonna make a
shortcut in this test fixture here to
this end turn as a variable. So once I've
defined it over here in the action
master class I use capitals just as a
convention for these enumerated states
what I'm going to do over in action master is just make myself a shortcut to that
and you can do that as a mini-challenge if you
want. I want you to write a single line that gives you
a private shortcut to something called
end turn spelt like this
by talk by looking into the action
master and assigning it to a variable
have a quick go at that have at least
a think about what that would entail its
a micro challenge; just pause the video and have a go
So we're talking about a private action master we need to
look into that class dot action so
that's the type action master dot action
is of type enum end turn and then it just
equals action master dot action . and then
it's listed so rather than having to
write action master dot action dot end turn
need to be careful to choose the right one
every single time I want to access it in
these test classes I can now just say
end turn so now end turn isn't red. The
other thing that's red is the bowl, why's the
bowl red? I dunno actually why bowl's red,
let's try building it's red because Bowl
will not compile because not all code
paths return a value. Well, here's a
here's a simple cheat for us, to get this test
to pass we just need this to return end turn
so why not just return action dot end turn now
style point here a a strategy point is
it a good idea to write a test like this
that is going to
immediately pass because we're just
returning blindly something like end turn?
Well that's pure test driven development
if you go too far down this route of
being like obstinate about the code you
write you're gonna cause yourself problems
so it would be better if we really
thought about the minimum behavior we
can specify here but for the moment for
the sake of showing you the process
let's just do this but rather than end
turn what's the problem with me doing end
turn well remember red green refactor
we're still trying to get to a red
failing tests and end turn will pass so
I'm gonna use tidy just to make sure the
first test fails seem to be crazy but i
wanna show you the loop. So, over here now
let's have a look.
Action Master does not exist in the current
context so why does action master not
exist because we haven't created it
right we've gotta in the test harness
we've got to instantiate an instance of
the action master so later we'll refactor
this out when we've got lots of tests but
for now we just want a single action
master action master equals new action
master. OK, like that and we're going to
need the brackets to access the
default constructor of action master
which is our class that we have created
now what's the default constructor what
am I talking about
Well when you make a new instance of a
class then certain things have to get
set up but in Unity here we don't have
access to that so let's see what happens
when we try and do this, when we just try
and say make a new action Master. This
is just like making a new vector or
anything else in Unity when we try and
play the game now we should be getting an
error he go we're trying to create or
at least a warning. A monobehavior using
the new keyword this is not allowed and
then it goes on. So, go back to your script
action master all of the scripts you've
written so far have had a colon mono
behavior they've inherited from mono
behavior which is why when we from the
outside here do something like action
master the instance .
look at all this stuff broadcast message
cancel invoke, all this stuff that's
because it's inheriting from monobehavior
we don't need it to inherit from mono
behaviour, this is a pure new class we're
creating. So in your actionMaster.cs just take
off the colon mono behaviorand we're
defining a plain vanilla class with no
inheritance now if you are over here
and you looked at the action master
instance in another script and you say
dot look at that, it now only comes
with bowl which is a method that we defined
and just a few other generic methods
equals get hash code etcetera
alright pretty cool, so now you stripped it down
to a really basic action master and then
back in Unity when we play the game we
don't get any complaints about trying to
create new mono behaviours. Fantastic
so let's run our tests. Test one
fails well why because it is expecting
an end tern and you're getting a tidy.
Let's look at our code so we've done the
red bit now we're trying to make it
green
well in this case green is quite simple.
We bowled a 10, we've sent in a 10 here
and what we want to be returning in that
case when our first bowl is a
10 is that we want to be returning a
action . end turn but let's not just say
return action dot turn cause that's kinda
silly that's going to return in turn on
every single bowl regardless of how
many pins we drop 0, 1, 2, 3, 4 whatever that's
a bit nuts right? That's not good coding
so let's at least just code the
special case right let's code the special
case let's make it work and I'm gonna
let you do that actually, as a challenge so I've
got you this far this would pass but I
don't like it, I want you to wrap this in
an if statement that codes the
special case of the pins equating 10. So
that is your relatively simple challenge
here write the simplest code that makes
the test pass, no refactoring at this
stage and just make something work in
the actionMaster.cs. So go ahead
and do that little bit of a challenge now.
OK, so let's take a look at this. So
obviously this is the simplest code that
would make it pass but it's too generic
it's it's just wrong it's obviously
wrong we don't always return an
end turn action regardless the number of
pins, so in my mind that doesn't count
that's gonna take you down an awkward
path but if you said if pins equals 10
then end turn that's enough to pass this
test and I'm happy that that is
enough to pass this test a little bit
later we'll put some guard code at the top of
this method above in here that make sure
that the pins passed in is not less than
zero or more than 10 but for now if
pins equals 10 return en turn, let's try
running that test if we come back over
here, as long as your code will build which
it won't why doesn't the code build
because this method must return an
action. Now the compiler is noticing
well it will only return an action if pins equals
10 but who said pins was going to
equal ten? Yeah so what we gonna do in the
cases in this case what're you
gonna do to make sure the compiler's
happy could you go return null for now
well you're not going to be able to do
that and here is why; try it cannot convert null
because it's a value type you can't
a null is a pointer and you can't
return a null for a value type you could
if it was a list for example if this
return value is a list you could return
null but you can't do it for a value type
like this anyway that's not good
practice, why are we returning null? Why don't
we just deal with this case right now
this code, this line I'm about to put in will
move down to the bottom of the script as
we add more special cases above but this
is a good plan I would throw this going
to throw a new unity exception. Why are we
throwing exceptions rather debug logging
because it's much more powerful and it
will actually be satisfied that requires
requirement the compiler that we are
returning something even though it's not a
return value it can see if we ever
get here they gonna throw an exception
in its gonna say something like not sure
what action to return now when we finish
writing this class I would hope we never
get here right we're gonna put lots more
specialist behavior; other behavior here and
maybe we'll put other behavior above as well
depending on the order of things but I
would hope that we would never get to
this at the end but for now we will get
to this in some of our test and it
convinces the compiler that we always
return something or we always do
something and this is fine this is a
perfectly valid approach we already have
the I don't know what to do exception so
let's try now. Come back over here. Now
watch the little whirligig down the
bottom of your window when that finishes
whirligigging it'll run the tests if
you've got this checkbox checked if not
click Run all and it passes. Awesome. So
congratulations you have just gone red
to green and now it's a question of do
we need to refactor this code. Is there
anything else we can do in this code to
improve it or refactor it while we're here well,
in the spirit of throwing an exception
if we don't know what action to return
why don't we throw, do one more guard
condition and you can do this I want you
to write a bit of code that says if
the pins are less than zero or more than
10 then throw another exception and this
one is going to say invalid pin count or
something so go ahead and make another
exception at the top of this class right
now for pins is less than 0 or more than 10
I hope you'r not expecting a challenge slide
this is just a silly in line microchallenge
go ahead and do it... awesome
ok, so we need an if statement clearly if pins is
so if you close your brackets and all
your whirligigs, then you'll be in
good shape, yep so if pins, i'll get there
in the end, is less than 10 or remember
double standy-uppy-whatsits, pins, and I
don't mean less than 10 do I, I mean less
than zero if it's less than 0 or if it's
excuse me more than 10 then what are we
gonna do well I'm gonna put it in a single
line here because I want it to be just a
single check line and that's ok you can
interrupt your if statement it's the
same as doing this; throw new unity
exception invalid pins like that and you
can just delete back and make it a
single line that's ok it's up to you you
know this is C#, these curly
braces and the semicolons; you know the curly
braces represent a code block the
semicolon tells it where the end of the
statement is. You're OK to do it on a single
line if you want to like this I like the
look of that. We come in to the bowl; we
check that we've got valid input parameters, guard
code at the start there. We write some behavior, we
write some more behavior we write some
more behavior and then if we don't know
what to do we throw an exception. Alright,
so red green refactor remember? We went
red, we wrote code, just this code basically
and this cold here that was green that
made us green we passed the test we're
refactoring now you can only refactor
code that has green passing tests; it's not
refactoring if you have failing test it's
coding
We're refactoring now because we're trying to make
this code have exactly; pass all the same tests
basically and have the same behaviour as before. So
let's see if it does, just switching to
Unity interface should do this when the
whirligig stops you get passing test the
behaviour the same so that is a valid
refactor we've just added this line which
is a useful guard code. So a lot of words
said there, deep breath. A lot of stuff
learned you may be thinking well I wrote
more test code than the actual code and
that's fine and in this type of problem
you will and honestly this type of
problem is exactly the sort of problem
you want to throw test driven development at and let's
just let this unfold and see the beauty
of it and I hope you fall in love with
it as much as I do. So, see you soon.