Welcome back! So, the title of this video
is "Red > Green > Refactor". We're going to go through
a few more TDD loops. We're going to remind
you of the Red > Green > Refactor sequence.
Be strict with yourself, build the descipline
of doing things in that order, Red > Green  > Refactor.
Save a version, snapshot regularly, especially when
you either get a new... ...somewhere in the loop anyway, just
maybe after you've refactored is a good time to save a version
snapshot. Before you start again, save a version of your file,
use your code management, whatever you like, and remember to have fun.
This will be a brain ache, all of this. It's supposed to be, if
it's a brain ache it's good. It doesn't matter if this
part of this section takes you several days. That's absolutely
fine, it's going to worth all the effort in the end. It's a fantastic
new technique for you. So, I'm going to do a few loops
or at least a loop or two, and then, I will get you to do a
challenge of writing and passing your own test.
Cool! So, get your ActionMasterTest script and your
ActionMasterScript open, for me,
and then, let's start to talk about
what else we need to be testing
here. Yep, so what else do we need to be testing?
So, one strike returns
Enter and that's fine. What would be another valid test? Well,
we could just test that...
We could just test... Well, you know on that YouTube video, the first thing
bowls as an 8 I think, so
8Bowl8
Returns... Now, what should you return, if you
just bowl and 8? Well, this just a Tidy
right, because you need to have another bowl.
So, Bowl8ReturnsTidy (). Now, you could say why don't we test everything
from a 0 to 9? Well, you could
but really
we just want to go for a specific, to keep things
simple for now. Alright, so in this test the first thing we need to do
is ActionMaster. ActionMaster equals a new ActionMaster.
So, remember the rule about refactoring,
the first couple of times you do something just duplicate
the code. When it comes to doing it a third time, you need to refactor
out, so we'll do that in the next loop. OK, but for now let's just get
used to writing tests. Assert.
be careful with a certain asset. Assert.AreEqual ()
easy if you do your brackets first. so
What's the deal here? Well, we want a
Tidy to come back, when we bowl an 8, so it's very similar to this, but
we need a Tidy. So, let's just do exactly what we
did up here. I'll just write it out,
rather than copying and pasting: private ActionMaster.
Action tidy
= ActionMaster.Action.Tidy;
It's just a shortcut, it's just a variable, instance variable access
to everything. Cool! So, we want to say that Tidy
is equal to actionmaster,
the instance, .Bowl(8);
OK, save that code!
OK, you get the idea? We're just saying that an 8 leads to a Tidy.
Very clear. And we have a test name
that says what it does and it has a prefix. How many
zeros? Well, it depends on how many tests you plan on writing. I think 99 is going to be
enough. I think we'd all be bored if we do more
than that! [Laughs] So, wait for the whirligig to finish. Ah, it fails!
Now, it fails this time, not
with a Return type but with a not sure what action to,
and if you expand it out, return.
OK perfect! So, what's happened here then? This is good
we're in red. Let's keep track of where we are. Not green,
not refactor, but red. We're in red, that's what we want
to do. We want to force ourselves to improve our code, by making
a failing test. So, what's happening? We're passing 8 in here,
it's not less than 0 more than 10, so we pass through this
exception. It's not equal to 10,
so we pass through that, and then, you get straight to
the throw exception. So, the first question is, do
we want to put our code here or here?
Well, if you bowl a strike on the first
turn, you need to immediately return an Enter, so we need to
check for that first. So, I think it's down here we're going to
put our behavior, in the second block. And then,
we need to think about what happens. Why are we going
to return a Tidy here? Well,
we're always going to return a Tidy on the first
bowl of a frame, so you could say
in pseudo code, at least in a comment: "If
first bowl of frame".
That would be one simple way to put it, right?  If it's
the first bowl of the frame, then
we "return the Action
.Tidy;".
OK, so that's it in pseudo code! So,
how do you know that it's the first bowl of the frame? This is
the minimal code we can write here, we can't always return Action
.Tidy, because we know it's going to be wrong in a bunch of cases.
So, how are we going to know it's the first bowl of the
frame? Well, we're going to need something else, at the top
here. We're going to need to have access to
some idea of where we are in the frame now, at this
stage. So, what I'm going to do is I'm going to
set myself up a public int [] array,
array of integers. I'm just going to call it bowls. It's the
bowls, you know 0, 1, 1, 0, 10,
8, whatever. And it's a new
int array of [21] integers.
OK, that's fine! And I'm also
going to create myself, and this is all private. Sorry, they're both
private, because they don't need to be seen from
the outside, they're just for this class;
int bowl, which is the bowl number, and we're going to start with
that number at 1, because
it's just natural. We think of bowl = 1 as bowl 1
in normal human terms. Be aware though, of course, that any array
index starts at 0, so bowl is going to be used as an array
index. We're going to have bowls square bracket bowl,
but beware that arrays start at 1, OK
0 rather. So, just be aware of that, but I think this reads
nicer. So, now that we have an array
and a bowl number, we actually
don't even need the array. I tell you what, I've gone too far
here. The idea of Test Driven Development is that you
only write code you need to pass the test. We do not need this
array of bowls. I'm going to just comment it,
because it's code that I know I'm going to write later.
So, I'm going to comment that out temporarily, because I know I'm going to need it
soon, but I do need a bowl, because I need some
way of starting to track whether I'm at the beginning or the end of a frame.
So, if bowl = 1
then how could we keep
track of whether we're at the beginning of a frame
or in the middle of a frame?
Well, let's take a look at this. We could say
if (bowl %
2. What does that mean? Well, that's mod! Go
look up what mod or remainder means, OK.
bowl % 2 if that =
0, so if the remainder of dividing
the bowl number by 2 is 0,
then what do we have?
Well then, we are
at the end of a frame,
in that case. Have a think about it.
OK, so if bowl 1 is the first bowl,  bowl
2 is the second bowl. That's the end of a
frame. The remainder of divided 2 by 2 is 0; bowl
3 and then bowl 4 would be the end of the next frame.
Again, you divide it by 2, you get 0
remainder. So, if it's the end of the frame,
what do we do? Well, it doesn't matter for now,
because we are
trying to write code for if it's
not the end of the frame. So, what would the correlate to this
be? Well, that it's not equal to 0
or that it's equal to 1 either way, but I'm
just going to say that if it's that the bowl,
the mod of bowl, 2 is not 0,
then we are "Mid frame
(or something else...
caught above or last frame,
which we will catch above.
"Other behavior here, e.g. last frame."
So, let's just focus on this bit. If
the remainder of dividing the bowl number by 2 is not 0, if there's
something left over when you do that, then we must be mid
frame or possibly the last frame. We'll deal with that later.
So, we are trying to write code, just
to make this pass. We just want Tidy to come
back, when we bowl an 8, but we want to do it in a way that's
reasonably general, without writing more
code than we need. We need something to keep hold
of the bowl number. You could argue you don't
even need that for now. You could just say, if
pins equals 8 return Tidy,
but you know that that code is wrong, so
don't write it if you know it's wrong. This is about the
minimal structure I can think of writing, where we can detect that.
Actually, the reason it's Tidy is because it's the first
bowl of a frame. Now, we're pretty much there.
We return Action.Tidy;
and get rid of these comments.
OK, so this kind of
reads for itself doesn't it? We come in and we do it...
We come in, we do a check of validity.
We later will probably deal with things like the last frame or other
stuff. We say that if it's a strike,
you'll always return an EndTurn, and if
it is mid frame, then
you return the Tidy, but we're not incrementing our bowl number.
We need to increment our bowl number, if you
think about it. Alright, so if you get
a strike, then
how do you increment your bowl number? Well, you always go forward two.
We skip one, don't we, we go forward two.
And if you get a Tidy, then
we go forward one.
Now, we don't need to write anymore code for them,
for the moment. We don't even need to do the Strike one,
but while we're thinking about it, that make sense alright.
I would rather... Well, I need to increment your
bowl number, before you return, otherwise
you've left the method. So, that's an important thing, nothing gets executed
after the return. So, does that code make
sense to you now. Take a look at it!
Let's try it! Let's see if it works! So, we were red, we had a failing
test over here. Let's go back, wait for the whirligig.
Green! Cool!
Now, we could refactor if we needed to,
but I think we've written pretty cool code. So, in this
case, we don't need to. I slightly
jumped to a elegant solution there,
without struggling. I did struggle when I first wrote
this code. I want to show you nice ways of thinking,
but what we're going to do now is let you be messy and then let me be
messy. So, now is your challenge! Your challenge is
to write one test of your own, write a single test of your
own. Anything relating to correct return types.
Ensure it leads to the need to write new code.
Write the new code, until the test passes.
Refactor and recheck all the tests passed.
So go ahead, pause the video, and write your first
new test now, that makes you write new code, and then,
make it pass.
OK welcome back! So now, red! We need to create
a red. Get back in your test code. Let's create a new test
condition, that we are pretty sure is going to
fail, right. That's the idea of what we're doing now.
So, what test
should we write next, that we know is going to fail?
Well, what would happen, if for instance, we bowled two
strikes in a row? What would it do at the moment? We go
strike, strike, 10, 10. What should we do after
two strikes in a row? Well, it
should be
near the end of your turn, and that's what
would happen. So, there's no point in writing that test, because every
time we get a strike, it doesn't enter. So,
how about when we get a spare? Why don't we do something
to do with a spare, just to make sure that we
can understand how we handle spares, right.
So, why don't we just throw a spare, in the beginning
and make sure that the turn ends. So, maybe we bowl a
2 then an 8, and then what happens? Yeah, let's
do that! That's exactly, actually, as per the YouTube
example. So, let's go ahead!
Write a [Test], public
void test 03
Bowl28...
That's OK, because they're all single digits
in here. No we're not! Actually, 2
ah 28 will do, it's pretty explicit. Returns,
now what should 28 return?
It should return EndTurn, right? Because
28 is leading to a spare. This is a
spare.
Bowl28SpareReturnsEndTurn ().
OK now, now we're duplicating ActionMaster too much
OK. So, I'm going to show you a special way
of refactoring this out, in this test code.
Go to the top of your test code,
and you could access now a special annotation
called [SetUp]. if you start typing S you'll see it.
And that tells it that you want this to run, every single time a test runs.
OK, now you make yourself a method. You call it what you like, but I'm just going to
call it Setup (), because I like calling a kettle a kettle or
anything what it is. So, there's
your Setup () method. Now, what's your Setup going to do? It's simply going
to do this. ActionMaster
blah blah blah. So, take that out of both of both of your
methods. Out of test 10 in my case...
Sorry test 1 and test 2,
and put it in your Setup (). Now, the only difference is, no
good having a locally scoped variable here, is it. We can't
see ActionMaster, the variable, outside of this method.
So, instead of having it
locally scoped like that, we're going to declare it
up at the top level, as a private
member variable. OK.
So, let's just go private
ActionMaster actionMaster; and here we don't need to type,
you just set the actionMaster to a
new actionMaster, and then, all of the tests that run will have access
to actionMaster. So, go ahead and do that now. Add in
ActionMaster actionMaster; at the top, as a private instance variable.
Declare it here in your Setup ().
It's a bit like in your Start () method right, but this happens every time
a test runs, it's different to Start (). Then, you don't
need it in your tests! Your tests can be one liners! How cool is that!
OK, so now asserting that we
get an EndTurn coming out of here,
is relatively easy , we already have an endTurn variable.
So, be careful
asserting the bowling 2 is the endTurn,
is the second thing you need to do, but the first thing
we do is we take this actionMaster, that we've not got access to due to the
setup and we bowl a 2.
We bowl a 2 and we don't care what comes back in this instance,
we're already pretty confident that's going to be
right. It's just going to Tidy like an 8.
And then, we assert that on the return
that we get a Tidy back. Now, you
could put two assertions in one test, if you wanted
to. You could say Assert.AreEqual.
And you could say that we want a
Tidy to come back, the first time.
and an endTurn, sorry, to come back the second time. If you
want to do that, with an 8 being bowled there,
you're welcome to. It's not necessary to do
two assertations in the same test, but if you do,
and I'm going to leave it like this, the test system will tell you which
of them has failed, if either. So, let's see that in action!
Right, Assert, a Bowl (8), and then a Bowl
(2), and now, you're looking
to try and get to red. Let's go over here, let the test run.
Good it fails! Good
it fails! It's weird but that's the idea of Test Driven Development!
We want it to fail, we want to force ourselve to write new code.
OK, it's failed in that it said
I don't know what action to return.
OK, now the annoying thing about
that is that, we don't know which of these to assertions failed, which is
why I said we're probably better off stripping that out
and just having it
bowl an 8. And then, we Assert that the
second bowl returns and endTurn. So, do that! Just
strip it back to the code I'm showing you there, and go back and run the tests
again. Then, we can be sure that the error we get, yes is on the second
assertion. So, it is having a problem
with the endTurn. So why? That's fine, we're in
red. Now, let's go make it green. Well, in what
general circumstance do we want to endTurn?
Do we need to talk about a special case
of a strike, or is a strike just like any other frame
where two bowls happen? Well, we always want to end a bowl frame
after two bowls, right? Apart from the last frame, we'll
deal with the last frame, up here.
So, can you guess what code I'm going to put in here now?
Well, I'm just going to say that else if the
(bowl mod % divide
and see what the remainder, however you want to call it, does ==
0, then do something.
Now, what are we going to do in
that instance? Well, I'm going to put a comment
in, to say that it's the "End of frame", because it is
an even now frame number. It's like
bowl number 2 or bowl number 4 or bowl number 6.
You divide any of those number by 2 here
and look at the remainder and it'll always be 0.
What do we do in that case? Well firstly, let's get our increments right. Let's just
increment our bowl. It's that we're moving on to the next bowl
and we return Action.what?
EndTurn yep,
so the system knows to move to the next player. Does that make
sense? On odd frames we do that, and on uneven
frames we do that. Let's try it!
Woo hoo! [Laughs]
And the test passes! And that rediculously high pitch excited
noise is perfectly allowed, when you have a test pass! Red >
Green > Refactor! Look at your code. Does it need refactoring?
Well, my code looks quite nice,
I think it does anyway. You might want to comment, at this stage. You might want to
do something else, but it looks pretty good. Now
again, I'm going straight to pretty good code,
because I've thought about this a lot. I've rehearsed this a lot. I've even written the code
before. In your case, you're quite likely to
have it pretty minging, to use a technical code term rather,
code at this point. That's fine, if
it's minging. This is you're opportunity now, to refactor
and continually go back here and rerun the tests,
making sure that you take it from ugly and working
to pretty and working. That's worth writing down!
You want to go from ugly and working
to pretty
and working. OK, that's what your goal is! [Laughs]
So go ahead, refactor your code now, and
congratulations! You seem to be getting into the swing of Test
Driven Development, and I shall see you some more soon!