Isn't this fun? in this video we're gonna be
finishing our control code. In fact I'm
going to challenge you to finish the
control code. I want you to go through
the red green factor loop strictly. Focus
your failing tests on the edge cases on
awkward situations like the last frame
for example. Keep your actionMaster.cs
code looking clean but only do that
at the refactor step; stop when you're
confident it's done, and then why not challenge the
community to write a failing test? Paste
your action.Master.cs code into
pastebin or something like that,
share it into the discussions and say
hey guys I think this does it, can
you guys write me a failing test; and then your
fellow students can try and write a
failing test, paste that back to you via
pastebin or similar, or with a short test
it'll probably be fine to paste straight
into the discussions and then have a
little battle between you and see if you
can settle on the nicest possible action
master dot cs code. I'm going to do my
best but I'll be interested to see what
you guys can come up with also this same
challenge applies to our code my code
just try and write a failing test to
make our staff fail. This only applies to
whether it's returning the right status
of course in terms of tidy reset
etcetera
so go ahead pause the video, if this
takes you two days then it takes you two
days it's fine
this is a major thing in a way
especially if you've never done test
driven development before,  you need to get
your head round it so struggle with it
and then try and succeed. There isn't
that much more code to write in action
master dot cs, it's only a handful of
lines you could probably only add 10 more
lines so I suggest you think really
carefully about how the last frame is
handled. I suggest you be very careful
about indexes if you ever write bowls
open square bracket and then a number
rather than a variable then be careful
about what that number is because what
we're calling bowls is in human terms
counting from 1 and if you ever do a
direct access of the member in an array
then you are of course starting counting
from 0. So a couple of gotchas there have a
go, really give it a go see if you can get this code
stable so that we can control
automatically the reset tidy
next player and game. Go ahead, see you soon.
OK, welcome back I don't know how long it's been
for you it could be minutes it could have
been days and days is fine, if you really
struggled then hopefully you learned
something or you're at your wits end and you
need our help either way we are here to
help so let's go over to actionmaster to
the to the Unity Project and just recap
what tests we've got so far; so far we're
doing pretty well we have just a few
basic test but actually the code that
we've written for action master is fairly
general it seems to handle most odd and
even; well most in the middle frames here
but it's pretty glaringly obvious
looking at this code is it's not gonna
handle the last frame properly there's just
nothing in here to tell it what the
special rules are in the last frame. So
let's try and write some tests that
break the last frame. Firstly let's just
think about how the last frame works so
here I've got listed the frame before
last so bowls 17 and 18 counting from 1;
and then the last frame is bowls 19, 20 and
possibly 21. So let's take the top case for a
minute. In the top case we bowled 1, 1, we
bowl 1 and then 1 in nineteen and twenty so
no Bowl 21 is awarded because we have
not scored enough we need to have scored 10
or more in bowls 19 and 20 to be awarded a
extra bowl so the game will end at bowl
20 and there'll be no bowl 21
allowed. So the second case down we bowl
a spare on the 20th bowl, so at that
point we do get awarded a 21, it's a
question mark as we don't yet know what
the score's gonna be and we need to
issue a reset at poll twenty here
because it's not the end of the game, and
the other kind of special case I can
think of is where you bowl a strike on
bowl 19; and what that does is it awards a bowl 21 because you always get the next
two bowls to add up to a strike you do a
reset though immediately at bowl nineteen
and you do do a  bowl 20, now you may
actually bowl a nothing at bowl 20 which
is why I've put a dash in for a 0, or a gutterball, and if you bowl a zero at bowl 20 then you
still get a bowl 21 is what I'm
trying to get across
Cool, so let's think about what our tests could
be for that so back into MonoDevelop
into ActionMaster test what test could
be write to start putting some pressure
on this last frame so one test we could
write is as follows test and I'm going
to call it public void test what number
are we on? 5, check reset at strike in last frame
so we're going to do a strike in the
last frame just like the slide I drew for
you a moment ago we are going to go to
the bottom case first because it's just a
weird one I want to get off my mind and
that is one one strike ok so firstly we
need to populate the early game so how
we gonna do that well there's lots of
ways we could do this but why don't we
just use a for each loop and a explicit
list of rolls do that in this case let's
take an array of integers rolls and
let's just write a general array now, which you use curly braces for like that and
let's just specify them 11 and then 11
again and we're just gonna do 11 all the way through.
When I've got five I think I just copy so I
don't go nuts and then take one away so
I need nine pairs here
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9 pairs of rolls will take me up
to bowl number 18 here, at the end of that array
which you can see coming in on the
bottom left on this diagram 1 1. 1 1 are
these two here ok so that gets us to
this point all we need of course a for
each loop to iterate through this now
because they're all ones you could just
put one in the for each loop, but i wanna show
you a more general simple way of, you know
you can change any of these numbers now
very easily, it's very explicit so for each int
roll in rolls, what are we gonna do? Well,  we're gonna
ActionMaster dot bowl the roll - Bowl
the role there you go, so that's just gonna
issue a bowl this many times of one
Fine. So the actual magic kind of happens here this is
where we do a strike here so we're gonna just
do the strike straight inside the assert
statement as before
Assert.AreEqual, and then we are actually gonna
call SM dot bowl and we want a reset
back so reset is what we expect to come
back
Now, why does it not have access to reset?
Because we haven't declared a reset at
the top so give yourself a instance of
reset just to make things short; just a short
cut to reset perfect now when you try
and say are equal to reset it will be
there and then where's that gonna come from
where's the value reset gonna come from?
from a method call to action master dot
bowl with a number of 10 in our case, a strike.
Alright, so we have their 18 ones and
then a strikes again back to the slide 8
in the bottom case 18 ones and then a
strike now what we want to come back
from that is a reset so we're trying to
get red green refactor let's go to unity
see what happens. Run the tests or wait
for your whirligig to finish and it'll
do itself I just need to fix
check here but look we get an end turn and
it wants a reset so is not awarding us
this last frame that's the problem so
let me firstly fix the spelling error
in check there you go so we don't want a
what happened, let's have a look at the results. Click
on your test it says expected a reset
and it got an end turn so if you look into your
code, your actual production code why is it
giving an end turn, because the condition
is simply this its if pins equal 10 then
increment the bowl two and return
end turn. Well that's not right in this case we
need to put the other behavior above
that we need to catch it before that. We
have a slightly more special case, so
what is our special case?
Well look at our diagram, be as general as
we can but without doing any more than
we need to to pass this test so what do we
need to do to make this pass? The basic
issue is that if bowls 19 and 20 are 10
or more
then we're allowed a last frame then bowl
21 is awarded. So if bowls 19 and 20 are
greater than or equal to 10 then we award a last frame. OK so that's one way
of looking at it. So let's just write the
simplest code we can really if the
bowl number is greater than or equal to
19, so if we're in that last frame then what
do we do? Do we just end the game well
it depends if let's do a bit of wishful
coding if we're in the last frame  bowl number's greater than or equal to 19 and bowl 21 has been awarded
we'll write that method in minute then what do we do?
That's the question. Well then you
increment the bowl index one and you
return a reset which is what we're after
In fact that's the case that we're
trying to code for we don't need to
write any more than this if we're in the
last frame and Bowl 21 has been awarded
then we need to reset so we can keep
playing the game so finally how do we
calculate bowl 21 awarded? Well let's just
write ourself a boolean method down the
bottom here a nice simple private bool
action Ball 21 awarded; doesn't need
to take any parameters it can just look
straight to the Bowl array and then how do
we know whether bowl 21 has been awarded
now be careful this is where you need to
remember that arrays
start counting at zero. Quite important
OK, so how we gonna do it? Well we're gonna return
one very simple way of writing this is
return what bowls 19, but be careful
it's not 19 is it it's bowl 19 but
you need to take one off it so you could
do it right in there bowls 19
plus bowls 20 but take the one off because
arrays are awkward and then if thats greater
or equal to 10 then you get your bowl
twenty-one awarded
OK but we don't have any concept of the
bowls, nothing is storing the bowls yet so
in order to be able to determine whether bowl
21 is awarded we do need to start
storing the actual bowl numbers so we're
gonna need an array of bowls up here
remember we started writing that before,
I did in line 7 now it's time to bring
dust that off a 21 index size array of
integers called bowls so 21 bowls is a
maximum we could ever have.
If we bowl a strike then we'll
enter it as ten comma zero so that we always have
21 bowls. So now we have a bowls array there we
need to make sure that every time we
bowl anything provided there's not an
error that we insert the bowl we just
did so
bowls, and then we need again because of the 0-basing
of this index bowl minus one equals pins
so the pinfall comes in and you put it in the
array at position bowl minus one
because of the way arrays count so if we
do that every time that we get a valid
bowl, so if it's invalid we just jump out; if we do
that every time I get a valid bowl then
down here we should be to say bowl 21 is
awarded provided the bowl 19 + bowl
20 is greater than equal to 10 and
if bowl 21 is awarded and we're in the last frame
then increment 1 and reset, let's try it.
Waiting for the whirligig
there you go it's passed. Fantastic now I've
kind of jumped to a nice solution, of
course I've rehearsed this; what you're
allowed to do is make much more of a
mess than this and then refactor and
tidy your code as you go of course ok
fine so what else could go wrong in the
last frame, let's think of any other tests how
about if we bowled a spare in the last
frame back to the slide for a minute, so the
situation we're testing now is the
middle one, just making sure that if we get a
1 then a 9 in 19 and 20, 9 is drawn as a forward slash
because it's a convention on a scorecard
for a spare then the same behavior, we
should get bowl 21 awarded and a reset
so let's just take a look and see if
that works, firstly we need to write the
code now we can use a leg up from the
last test no harm in copying and pasting
test code so this case we roll all of
these guys the difference here is we're
just gonna go action master dot roll or
bowl a five and then we're going to
bowl say another five or if we want to
be consistent with our slide then 1 and then 9
gives you the same thing so we're gonna
bowl all these then a 1 and a 9 just like the slide
instance in the middle there.
OK so let's do that let's see how that
test goes, so you compile your code and to
our delight over unity the test passes.
Fantastic so what else do we need to do
well I think we need to deal with the
end game now. If you look in here in the
code and you do a find command or control
- f on tidy then you see the code
contains a tidy output
a reset, an end turn but not an end game
yet. So it's tempting just to kind of come
in here and try to write the end game
conditions but let's not do that, let's write
the failing tests to make sure that the
end game actually happens. So why don't
we use the YouTube video that we had a
few slides ago and use its data as a
test game that would be quite fun wouldn't
it make sure that that runs properly so
let's make a new test here which is
public void test 07 YouTube rolls in end
game. OK so we've got a load of rolls
there on that YouTube video it may make
sense if you're ever gonna link off to web
content like that to a) remember that may
disappear and b) maybe to put the URL
you could pop the URL
of the YouTube video from the earlier
slides into your code if you wanted to
for reference but I'm just gonna put
the roll array which I've pre-typed here
so you don't have to get bored stiff now
do you need to initialize it? No you
can just say that int roll array equals
that thing there and that's exactly the
rolls from the YouTube video, and what
does that end up with that ends up with a
nine. So we get an eight and a two which is
a spare than a 9 on the end. We need to
take the 9 off because we need to
actually do some assertations on that.
So it's doing a simple for each loop
again through all the YouTube rolls like that
and then on the last one we going to
assert
are equal; now do we even have a shortcut
for the endgame? We probably don't yet
No we don't so let's make the short
cut at the top here
OK, fantastic now you've got a shortcut
now we're going to assert that the
endgame is equal when we call action
master dot bowl on a number what was
it? 9 for the last one I believe so
okay regardless if we bowl a nine here
we should be doing an end game so
compile and test, or compile and run let's see what
happens and of course we get a reset
but we wanted an end game so why are we
getting a reset at the end here?
Well you look at the code then bowl 21
has been awarded so it just does a reset
so we need to intercept this above there in
this case or below here so let's think
about it we gonna say beforehand or
after well we actually are in the
situation where it's bowl number 20.... 1 isn't
it it's bowl number 21 and whenever it's
bowl number 21 it's an end game so if
the bowl equals 21 then you simply
you're done
turn action . endgame. It's always the case if
you get as far as 21 let's try and
see if that makes the test pass. Here it
goes yes no maybe. Yes it makes the test
pass. Awesome, so great that's working what
else could go wrong? Well how about
if you... were at bowl
20 but there was no Bowl 21 awarded so
look at the slide for a minute
imagine we're at bowl 20 but no bowl 21 is
awarded that top case well let's just
code that in so game ends at bowl 20 could be
the test name. So let's make a new one
I'm gonna take it from here because it's
very very similar to that test; but I'm going to remember
to change the name this time. So it's
test number eight and Bowl ends at; game
ends at bowl 20. So we're gonna roll
123456789 so that's eighteen times; we may as well roll
once more in here and then if we
rolled a 1 at the end there we should get
an end game. Again from the slide it is
this situation at the top
now we want an end game and no bowl 21
awarded. Let's see what happens. Back to
Unity, let it whirligig, and it gets an end turn but you
should be getting an endgame ok so how
do we make that test pass? And it
should be pretty much the last one I
think. Well where's the situation here?
It's not at bowl twenty-one cause
we're only on bowl 20. So we are on bowl greater than
or equal to 19 but in this case we're
bowled greater than or equal to 19 or
specifically we're on bowl 20 and 21 was not
awarded so else if bowl equals 20 and
not bowl 21 awarded; so bowl 21 is
not awarded then it's the end of the
game right?
try it. OK so I'm getting this time
I'm no getting a failing test I'm getting
code not compiling so what have I done?
Splodge b to build there and it's just
that I never called bowl twenty-one
awarded; I should never put the braces in
the brackets in so I never called the
method so let's try now. Awesome, so the game is
at bowl 20 so let's take a look at this. Do we
think we're done? I think we could be
done. I think that we are saying that we
check the validity of the pins, we store the
pin fall if the pinfall is valid. If it's
bowl 21 it's always the end of
the game otherwise if it's bowl 19 and
bowl 21 has been awarded or rather if
it's bowl 19 or above, so we're at the beginning
of the last frame and Bowl 21 has been
awarded we go ahead and reset otherwise
if it's bowl 20 and bowl 21 hasn't
been awarded then we end the game. Fair enough
so this is all this whole thing here is
handling handle last frame special cases
otherwise in general if you bowl a
strike you end the turn and if you're mid-
frame you tidy and if you're end-frame
you end turn. If you're not sure what to do you
get an exception we haven't had one of
those for a while but let's leave it in
there and then your logic for Bowl 21
awarded is if bowl 19 plus 20 is greater than or equal to 10. I like it I think it
feels right. So at this point I'm going to
throw it out the gauntlet to you guys to
say if can you make my tests fail. So
if you use exactly my code then can you
make my tests fail that would be your
challenge right now what I'll do is
attach my current state of action
master dot cs and actionMaster tests
dot cs to this lecture under the
resources so that you can download them
and put them in a project if you want to
and then try and write a failing test
for us and if you can do that then
please stick it in the discussions in
the comments and we'll improve the
section and the code. Meanwhile I'm gonna
crack on with the physics and the
control systems. See you soon.