Welcome back, so thank you very much to
Daryl Kempthorne who has posted in the
discussions of the course while I was
moving house but he's found a failing
test. So he says that I think that in
the last frame that if you roll a
strike on bowl 19 and don't knock over
all the pins on bowl 20 then we should have
a tidy. It sounds right. At the moment
we're getting a reset not a tidy
Fantastic so I think that Daryl's failing test is something like this we
come into the last frame we bowl a
strike but then on bowl twenty we are not
knocking down all of the pins and I
think is quite rightly saying that it
should be a tidy not a reset, so what I
want you to do in a single challenge
right now is to write test and make it
write a test and make it pass, so red
your gonna write the test for Daryl's failing
condition which I'll leave on the screen
in a moment
green you're gonna write the code to
make that test pass, and then you're going to
refactor to make it pretty. So I'm gonna
move over to Daryl's
condition and then I want you to pause the
video and try and write the test for
this condition and then try and make
the test pass this condition so go ahead
pause the video and do that now
OK welcome back, so the condition I'm
going to use is the one on the slide I
gave you so this slide here we're gonna
set up 18 rolls of say one and
then a strike and a 5. We'll see what we get.
So back in our - I need to put a marker in my video here,
I could have made a small mistake - it's ok.
So back over in Unity we need to go to our
editor folder remember because our tests are
over in the editor folder and then bring
up your action master test . cs script
So we need to make a condition which is
19 ones and then a 10 and then
a 5. So let's just take this previous
test, paste your code, increment the
number. I'm going to credit Daryl so it's
going to be a Daryl Bowl 20 test let me
get 2, 4, 6, 8, 10, 12, 14, 16, 18, 18 loads of 1,
let me check the slide now; and then a 10 and then a 5. So we get a
strike there and then a five and then
what we should be getting when we bowl a
the five so the 5 goes down here, be
careful where you put that the bowl that
we want to interrogate the
action on is here so we've got to this
ten relating back to the slide that is
here, this X in column 19 so that's bowl number
19, and then bowl number 20
becomes five so let's bowl 5 there and what it
should be giving it is a tidy. OK, so
that's the test let's go into unity, run
the test, see what it says. Failed. Now let's
just check it's failing for the right
reason it was expecting a tidy and it's
getting a reset so that's exactly the
fail condition that Daryl suggested.
So well done if you got that far you
have written a test that matches a
condition that is given in plain English
that's very useful if for example one of
your play testers says to you
blah blah blah is happening if they give
you a sufficiently specific example of
what's going wrong you could always
write a test to represent what they've
said immediately which is pretty cool. So
now your next job of course is to
to make that test pass. Now Daryl
actually gave us some code he gave us an
example piece of code, he put that on
PasteBin so what I'm gonna do is I'm
gonna start off by using his code
because he's gone to the trouble of
writing it why not? So here it is in Paste
bin and what he's done is he's made an
extra check inside Bowl 20 that says if
all pins are knocked down slightly
differently worded then reset otherwise
Bowl 21 is awarded and then he's got
this method here that says AreAllPinsKnockedDown
well I would call that all pins are
knocked down. So let's try it, it's slightly
strange, it says that if bowl 19 + bowl 20
mod 10 is zero. So to my eye that means that if
bowl 19 + ball 20 equals 10 or 20 then we're going to end up with zero
Well I'm not sure that's gonna get the perfect result
in all cases but let's give it a go and
see what happens now.
Bearing in mind we only need to make
this particular test pass. So let's take
Daryl's code and pop it in and see what
happens.
so we need to go into unity of course and
go and find your action master . cs
script and then I'll put this helper
method on the bottom that Daryl has
given us but I will just rename Are All Pins
Knocked Down to just All Pins Are Knowcked Down
because it just works better for my
brain and then we'll go up here where he
has this code; we have this code here if
bowl is greater than or equal to 19 and
bowl 21 awarded Daryl is saying
if bowl is 20 then do all this; he's got different
logic here so we could just take all of this
code and say well he thinks that this
code is better for the last frame
special case so that would be fine I
mean I'm quite confident to paste that
last frame special case in, leaving my
comment where it was
and of course renaming my method - his
method to my method name bowl 21
awarded I'm just gonna check that the
indentation is right and it looks ok so
it looks like a reasonably good code so
a number of pins... I think we used pins so
let's see if Daryl's code just
slots in - slightly new technique for you
here, just taking somebody else's code and
popping it in this is where test driven
developing really comes to its own
because if Daryl's code works then all these
previous tests should pass as well so
I'm pretty confident in his solution
even though it looks different to mine
all the previous test just passed and his
condition has passed so as long as we
understand how his code works I'm pretty
happy. Cool so that's good progress now
the next question would be is that
covering everything? Can I now in this in
this to and fro of failing tests can we
find a condition that his code fails in?
Well let's take a look, how about this one here.
How about if we were to bowl a strike
and then a zero on bowl twenty I think
that should give you a tidy myself
because if you do a gutterball on Bowl
20, then you just need to tidy you don't
need to do a complete reset no new pins
needed so let's try coding that
condition in. Pretty much like the last
one but bowl 20 is a 0. So I did a test
script
Test your code, I love cutting and pasting.
Cutting and pasting works well with test
driven development is not ideal in most
situations but here it's good. Ben' s
bowl 20 test and it's very similar to
before but instead of bowling a 5 we're bowling a 0 and
I think we should still get a tidy let's
see what happens now; build your code over
to unity let the tests run, wait for the
whirligig down the bottom right ah Bens
Bowl 20 test does not pass. Now I'm
pretty sure that that should have passed
so of course we need to fix that. What's
going on? I think what's going on is
when Daryl says well if bowl 19 and 20
here mod 10 equals 0 I think that that
the problem is that that's catching the
case when 19 + 20 equals 10 so I think
he needed just some simpler code that
said if 19 + 20 equals 10
then that's all pins are knocked down so let's think what
that means, let's look at the slide if
19 + 20 equals 10 it should be a
tidy, how about if 19 + 20 was equal to 20?
2 strikes then it should be a reset. So yeah
if it's that the only special case is that
all pins are knocked down in both bowls 19 and
20 so actually I think I'm going to rename  this
method to I dunno, 2 strikes last
frame, something like that, and let's try
that code, let's see how that goes
so I'm excluding the case where bowl
19 plus 20 equals 10 that I
just put in that test let's see if that
works for this test and all previous
tests and it doesn't look I made a much
older tests fail I was expecting a tidy
beginning of reset on test 6, so let's go
look at test 6 and see why I've broken test six
check reset at spare in last frame so if
we do this lot, then we bowl a 1 and a 9 we
should be getting a reset, OK, so bowls
number
2, 4, 6 so that's Bowl 18, so bowl 19 + 20 equals 10
in this case and
yeah okay so we're not catching that
case either so I can see the spirit of
what Daryl was trying to do when he
was saying let's take the sum of
19 and 20 and a mod it with
10 and say if that equals 0, if the remainder's
0 then you get this previous
tests passing the one that just failed
number six will pass because it will
catch the case where the two equal 10
but my bowl 20 test still doesn't pass
and I'm pretty confident that my
test is a valid test, that if we bowl
this sequence here 10 and then a zero
that we should get a tidy so over to you
how are you gonna write the code to make
that work so pause the video and have a
go at making that work right now please.
OK, recording seems to be working so let's
take a look at
this back in action master we need to
just code in the special case to start
with, it doesn't matter if our code is ugly and
the special case is where bowl number
well, let's look at the slide it's always worth
having a visual representation in front
of you so bowl number 19 is
a 10 but bowl number 20 isn't now
the question is do we do this check
before or after this two strikes last
frame check? Well it's difficult to tell
with that name two strikes last frame so
let's rename it again until we get a
name that really resonates at this
method doesn't really tell you whether
it's two strikes last frame it just
tells you whether, well it it tells
you whether bowl 19 + 20 is 10 or 20
ridiculous method name but we'll go with
that because it's clear so if bowl 19 + 20
is 10 or 20 we may as well have put
this code to be honest straight in here
in fact you know what such a ridiculous
method name that I'm actually just gonna
put this code; I'm gonna refractor this code right
up into the if statement 'cause that is
a stupid method name, that's just too
specific you may as well just write the
code at that point right so if bowl - may as well just be explicit here - so if bowl 19 +
bowl 20, the modulus equal 0 so there's no
remainder now you can actually see what
that does and of course we don't need
this method down the bottom here anymore
I'm only doing this so I can work out
where to put my new if statement, above this
or below it.
OK, so we've got an unexpected symbol and
that's because of a closed bracket. Great, so
that compiles now, so we're saying let's
recap where we were the condition we're
looking to catch is when nineteen equals
10 but twenty doesn't so this condition
here would trigger for nineteen it was 10
and 20 doesn't
in the 20 equals 0 condition because bowl nineteen
being 10 plus 20 being 0 would be 10 for this
statement here
Take a modulus with 10 you get zero so
this will trigger wrongly we want to
tidy so what we gonna do is we gonna put
our new code above this so we're gonna
say very explicitly - let's borrow this - if
bowl 19 equals 10 and bowls 20 -1
because arrays start at 0 is not equal to 10
then we do a action dot tidy. This is my
special case and then when you just put an
else in front of the if and of course
our closing brackets. So this is my
special case, if 19 is ten and bowl 20
isn't 10 return a tidy otherwise if
bowl 19 + Bowl 20 is 10 yadda yadda we just
want to make sure this works don't try
and refactor now, we're just trying to
make the test pass, so build your script go
back into Unity see if test passes. It
doesn't because it breaks test six so
reset at spare in last frame now gets
broken presumably because of my code
here.
Interesting, so how about we say that
actually the special case is not that bowl
20 equals 10 but very specifically that ball 20 equal s 0,
let's try that. I'm not allowed to refactor
here I'm just going to try and get the
code working so that all the tests pass
No so check reset at spare at
last frame is still failing so let's see
what the conditions of that test are, now
it's quite common that you end up going
back and having previous tests fail so
we bowl a bunch of ones and then a one and a nine, so it's
sending back a reset. We're expecting a reset
but we're getting a tidy so it looks like
our new code is returning a tidy in
this case if bowl 19 = 10 and bowl 20 = 0 and that's not
the test. This test says bowl 19 is 1, and
bowl 20 is 9. OK that's interesting so
why are we getting a tidy. Let's go look
at the results again over here just
re-run the test just to be sure, yes so
test six is saying it's expecting a tidy
but it's getting a reset so where could
it be getting the reset from? Probably
this condition here... does bowl 19 +bowl 20 in
the case of test 6 equal 10 yes it does, you see
so this special case that Daryl's
written, I think it may be too general
I think that we want to say if 19 +
Bowl 20 equals 10, let's see how that goes. Great,
now all tests passed. So we're saying
we're saying the following then that
makes all the tests pass I'm quite happy
with that, if 19 is 10 and bowl
20 is 0 then we tidy, otherwise if you
add them together and they equal 10 we reset. OK
I think that's ok and I'm not sure we
can make it too much simpler than that,
so I'm gonna go ahead and leave the code
like that now if you can see refactor of
this code that makes it even simpler
sure go ahead and share in the
discussions and furthermore if you can
find any more
tests that are going to fail go ahead and share in
the discussions I want to involve the
community in the production of this part
of the course by the time you comment I
will be further ahead with the course
but I'll be sure to add any of these
things and mop it up at the end. So for
now this is my solution and all the
tests are passing and in the next video
we're going to start cracking on with
making sure we get rid of these nasty
buttons over here and getting the rest
of the game working well. So see you soon