Hey, so we're gonna talk about the bug reporting
cycle right now so a brief overview of a
possible TDD bug reporting cycle
creating relevant tests from user bug
reports and a bit about sticking to the
TDD discipline. So here's a possible bug
reporting cycle, a very simple cycle so
you're... imagine we have released our game
now and it's out there in the wild and
there're some issues and so your user
submits a bug report so you are gonna be
all three of the bold people here the QA
and both developers as an indie
developer, but in a larger company you
may have quality assurance verify this
bug is valid and can be reproduced. They
may then pass it on to developer one who
writes a failing test; who passes it on to
developer two who writes code to make the test
pass and then maybe the user is informed,
something like that. So let's just take
the example of a couple of our very
helpful students who have found some
more failing tests or bugs so the
first discipline is to be able to turn a bug
report like this into a test that
actually tests for the symptoms of the
problem so Nathan quite rightly
points out the following problem and I'll
just let you read that for a moment, Iwon't read it
out to you so pause the video and read
that if you wish
ok so basically he's pointing out an
issue but the issue is probably even
more helpful than you would get from a
user because it's looking behind the
scenes into the code and talking about
how we increment the bowl index and of
course that doesn't directly result in a
testable symptom so we need to make a
test, in fact you need to make a test to
test the symptoms of this problem within
the scope of what we're doing at the
moment because remember we're still just
writing the action master, we're still
just writing a system that needs to
correctly tell the PinSetter whether to
end the turn, to
tidy, to reset etcetera so you need to
make a test that makes this problem that
Nathan's talking about manifest in a
failing test. So that's a slightly
different skill for you, it's making
something testable. OK so go ahead and
write that failing test for Nathan's test
now. Welcome back so now with our test
designer's hat on let's start
thinking about how we would make a test
that's going to fail, to exhibit the
symptoms of this problem so let's focus
on the first row of this diagram what
Nathan is saying is that we bowled a 0
then a ten, and the bowl pointer gets
incremented two, which is wrong, and let's
just look at the code that does that for a
second if we look over in action master
to show you the offending code. What's
happening is that we handle the last frame
here and then immediately say
well if pins is 10, increment
the bowl twice and return end turn. Well the
problem with that is we get pins equals
10 on bowl two, we increment bowl index
twice and return end turn so that's not
right because look what happens if we
write the following tests we bowl 0,
now I'm looking at the second row we bowl 0,
10 and then a five look where the five
goes the five goes in the wrong place,
it goes in the second slot of the second
frame and then the system will wrongly return a
tidy. What we want to happen when we
bowl a 0, a 10 and a five and then, say, a 1 is that
on that one we want an end turn. So the bottom
case is our test if we bowl 0, 10 5, 1 we
should get an end turn but I think at the
moment our code will give it tidy which
is our failing test. So let's do that let's
just write the test 0, 10, 5, 1. Relatively
simple so over in action master test
gonna call it in my case test 11 you
just increment your test number if you
want to do things like this you don't
have to give them names it's only the
reason I put this number here by the way
is just over in unity it keeps them
sorted in the order we wrote them down
it just makes it easy to find
Nathan Bowl index test. How's that. Nathan
bowl index test and what we said we were
gonna bowl was a 0 then a 10,  then a 5 and then
we were going to assert that when we bowl
say a one - is that what I said in my slide?
yeah 0, 10, 5, 1... 0, 10, 5, when we bowl a 1 here we assert that what
we should be getting is an end turn. Let's try it
Compile your code now I've missed
something a semicolon there. Fantastic
Now back into Unity and the whirligig goes round
in the bottom right Nathan bowl index test
expected end turn got tidy. Perfect, so we
have a failing test; red green
refactor we have a red. So let's go into
the green condition. How do we fix the
code to make it work? Well again
Nathan suggested a solution to this but
you need to think about the solution for
your code because it's going to be
different in your code. So let's look in
the code, this lot here
handles frame special cases
put my tongue back in there. So we've got our special
frame handling now the problem is this
line here this is the one that causes
the issue so let's think about what this
code does here so what does mid frame mean?
We're taking the modulus and we're
saying well it's not really mid frame is
it is this is first bowl of frames one to nine
and this is the first frist... and this is
second bowl of frames one to nine so on
the second bowl of frames one to nine we always increment one and end turn but on the first bowl of frames one to nine we
don't always do this do we? It depends on
the pins per this logic up here so
what we want to do is we want to say that
if pins is 10
then we do this stuff here, that's where we
want that
else we increment one and return tidy. We
just have done logic in slightly the
wrong place but I think this is a
solution so let's get rid of that, we
moved  it inside the if statement, we said if
we are in the first bowl of flames 1 to 9,
strictly this isn't necessarily actually
the first ball of flames one to nine is it because
there are other instances where this
modulus may equal 0 so im just gonna say
first bowl of frame, second bowl of frame
but anyway if we're in the first bowl of the
frame and the pins is equal to 10 then we
do the increment 2 and end turn,
otherwise we only increment one and tidy.
Let's try it before we get too excited.
The great thing about this test is all these
previous tests need to pass as well, green
red green refactor so we've done red,
we've done green let's see if we need to
refactor well actually think this is
pretty clear.
We've gone straight to clear code. Now
if you've kind of hacked it in here or you
think that you need to refactor then go
ahead and do that. You could maybe take
all this out and say handle first bowl of
frame or something but I don't think
it's necessary I think this reads ok so
fantastic that is that one done now
let's see there's another bug report
We're going to work the next one
the opposite way round in this case
we're putting our hat on as if we are
developer two, let's go back to the slide
remember the first time with Nathan's
test we acted as QA and developer one
and developer two and we wrote the test
ourselves well as QA we kind of
verified the test, we wrote the test and
then we wrote the solution
now what we're gonna do with Nathan's, sorry
with Dondi's issue is he's actually
we're pretending we're developer two. He's
actually written a failing test and we're
gonna take it from there so if we go to
this slide here then Dondi has told us
that this test fails, so it's Dondi
10th frame Turkey which is fine and he
rolls all this stuff gets us into the
last frame and then rolls
strike strike and then strike and it
should be end game. OK so if he's written us
a test then lets going to stick it
straight in our code now a couple ways you
can do this you should be able to copy and
paste this from the slide deck if you've
got it as a PDF. Alternatively if you're
online on your device click on that link
and it'll bring up a Gist which is a
nice easy way, an alternative to pastebin
possibly a more solid way of sharing your
code and you'll be able to copy and paste the
code from that Gist there so let's go and actually take the test, it's a
perfectly valid system this take
somebody else's test slot it right into
your code; in my case I'm going to just
increment my test number in front just for
my reference and let's go ahead and go
back into unity and run all the tests. Look
Dondi10thframeturkey expected a
reset you got a tidy. That doesn't sound
right I thought that we were expecting
Oh OK, so we don't even get the reset
here. So Dondi's doing three tests,
he's doing testing this is reset this is
reset and this is endgame. So it's three
tests in one which is kind of ok, it
would be easier to tackle this if we did
it 1 action at a time we could split
this into three tests but let's see if we can
find what the problem is. Now Dondi has
also suggested what the problem may be
and he suggested that when we are
handling the last frame here instead of
being saying that we are definitely on
Bowl 19 let's say that we are on bowl
greater than or equal to 19. Let's just
try that solution and see if it makes
the test pass. No harm in cheating like
this, no harm in saying well you know
somebody's given us a hint there you go and
that seems to make not only Dondi's
test pass which I wouldn't be too
confident is not just a hack but all the
previous tests as well so we've gone red
green now let's refactor let's make sure
this makes sense so handle the
last frame so certainly Bowl 19 and above is
the last frame but this first if
statement only catches the case where
we have a strike. So then we do a reset
That's fine and then it's saying what else
if bowl equals 20, then what do we do that's all fine. So how come are we getting an end game on Bowl 21?
I'm not sure why we're getting ever
getting... Aha, because that's the
first thing we catch great so it kind of
makes sense we get an end game on Bowl
20, if all of the above conditions aren't
met or always on bowl 21. Great, so what
that seems to be doing is it seems to be
catching all three of these tests in one
go making sure that we get reset reset
endgame. Perfect so you might now be
slightly losing confidence in the
solidity of your solution even though
we're adding more and more tests. One
thing I certainly feel at this stage is
well that's all very well but every time
we add another test and feel more
confident about our code because yet
another test is fail... passed we also
feel more and more that there's going to
be more tests that could come along that
will fail
well that's true so how could you really
button this up? At some point you need to
ship your product and be willing to
change it if a user does report a bug
but in the case of say a bowling game or
you're making a deal making an ASIC, an
Application Specific Integrated Circuit
maybe your coding for that
and it's gonna be millions of pounds
spent on the structure of that or
something like that some cases you know
your shrink wrapping your game you
really just don't want major bugs. How
do you know that this is
working? Well you can never really prove
it in in the aviation industry you have
to make software that's really really
tightly and proven to be working but
here in in the game industry you know
that you have to be willing to patch
your game if there is a bug, as Brice says,
there will be bugs in the game the
question is do they interfere with the
user experience. So how we gonna just
make ourselves feel more confident? Well
one thing you could do is you could go
to the rules of bowling if you can find
them written out sufficiently clearly
and just make sure that there is a test
for every rule of bowling, so at the moment
we have only 12 tests and we're probably
not covering all cases. What we have done
here is we've actually developed these
tests in a pretty cool way with the
community. So we've got a lot of students on
the course and they are willing to try
and make failing tests so I'm going to
continue this way actually,
I'm gonna say throw it back to the
community and see if from this video you can
make any more
failing tests so eventually nobody will
be able to find a valid
failing test, I mean anybody can make a
failing tests right but you gotta have a
failing test that is actually valid in terms
of the rules of bowling. So guys back over
to you try and make yet another failing
test because I am feeling pretty
confident about this code but I'm very
happy to accept there could be more
issues with it
OK so congratulations on following this
video and we'll see you soon.