So welcome back, it's time to wire up our
action master to the rest of our game
regardless of whether we think we're
completely finished with the action
master testing we can still wire it to
the rest of the game because the API the
interface between the action master and
the rest of the game isn't going to
change its a very simple API is just
that bowl method. So we're going to
connect PinSetter.cs to action
master.cs; refactor PinSetter.cs
to report pinfall; currently it
reports the number of standing pins it
doesn't actually know how many pins have
fallen connect PinSetter.cs
to the animator aswell; remove the
tidy and reset test buttons and ensure
our game controls itself now. So the
first thing to do is to refactor PinSettter.cs
so that it understands the
concept of the pinfall that it's going
to need to call the bowl method, so work
out how to do that you're going to need
to help PinSetter.cs
understand how many pins have fallen in
a given bowl rather than just how many
are standing at the end
go ahead, pause the video, see if you can take on
that challenge yourself. OK, welcome
back so this is how I'm gonna take that
on I'm gonna suggest that in PinSetter
we need to have some concept of last
settled count and what does that start as? 10
So  in the beginning our last settled count
is 10 pins because we have 10 pins just
standing there with the very very
beginning of the game, after that it's up
to the code below to maintain the state
of that variable. So when do we update
last settled count and what is last settled
count? Well you do it when the pins
have settled right right here at the top
of pins have settled we need to think
about updating this last settled count
so what is going to be the code for that?
Well we need to ultimately end up with a
pinfall, so let's make an integer for
PinFall and that will be the last
settled count minus we'll do a count
standing right now. So imagine we've
knocked down one pin, we count nine pins
standing so 10-9 is one so our PinFall is
one. We knocked down one pin makes sense
then we need to update this last settled
count, that's the time to do it, so the last settled
count simply equals the count standing.
OK we're calling count standing twice, who
cares it's pretty quick
OK so that's it really in terms of
getting a last settled count variable
that actually works do we want to make
sure that works I think we do print last
settled count. Now I think we've actually
possibly got too many print statements
going on now so I'm going to look for
print in my code and also debug.Log
as we seem to use them pretty interchangeably
I hit too many keys tehre, that was fun. OK let's try again
debug log raising pins yeah we don't
need raising pins anymore what else don't
we need? Just one of renewing pins, don't need that. Just trying to keep my log tidy.
Ok, cool so when they settled we gonna print
or I'll use Debug.Log, doesn't really make much difference
last settled down let's make sure it
works firstly back into unity see if
that concept works. So let's bowl a ball, see what we get.
Clonk. How many have we
knocked down? Actually don't want to knock all
of them down. What did we get? One, that's not right
that's not right that's the number of
standing pins OK I'm going to get rid of the resetting ball debug log, I missed that and try and
work out what's wrong with our code so
where did this one come from it came
from this line debug.Log settlecount
I'm logginf the long thing, I should be logging PinFall. OK so I want
to see what the pinfall is not the last
settled count. Try again, so one actually
was the last settled count at that point in the code that's
correct. That
was the last count of the settled pins. Which is kind of
what last settled count means. wow I'm too good at
getting strikes. So anyway we should get a
pinfall of 10 we do. okay so, let's just start
again and bowl another another bowl;
and actually we could of course use test
driven development for this as well
if you wanted to but we're not doing
that right now just to keep things
simple keep one set of tests going at a
time and then I'm going to restrict the
test to making sure that the scoring
and the reset and the action master all work
properly
Let's just do one more kind of playtesting
test. Everything's a bit weird and slow
I'm gonna leave my game like this I
quite like it being spacey like this you
might want to change all your physics
parameters. So are they gonna settle let's see
them settle, it should settle on 3, 3 and it
was a pinfall of seven cool so we now
know the PinFall which is helpful so why
don't we try and find out what the
action is going to be for that we're
gonna need an action master. Privately we
need  an action master, it's a base class and
we're going to call it am for action
master so we've got ourselves in action
master available now so we may as well
go straight ahead when we when the pin
settle and rather that just logging the
pinfall we could log action master lower
the instance dot bowl and then the PinFall
and see what we get back; and we should
be very close now, what have I done wrong?
Missing closing bracket - we should be
very close now to a situation where the
machine can actually control itself but
let's just take one step at a time and
try actually instantiating an action
master and calling it, see what we get. So If I was to
Bowl this is whatever that's going to
end up being... gonna be a nothing or a 9 I'm
guessing it's gonna be a 9. Well a 1. So I bowled
1, I should get a tidy here and I get an
object reference not set to an instance
of an object
What's wrong? So it doesn't understand
this action master and that's because I
never actually create a new action
master I need to construct an action
master so when I declare it up here I
define it but I don't declare it I need
to say new action master with some curly
brackets and that will use a default
constructor for action master we don't
actually specify any constructor in here
but we also just don't need to. So you
need when you declare; when you define
it to add on this, to make a
declaration and to actually create
an Action Master. Let's try again now that we
are actually creating an instance of an
action master. previously we declared it but we did
not actually instantiate it, let's see what
happens now
tidy perfect, we're getting a tidy back. So
let's rig it up, let's rig this guy up
to the animator which means we need
access to the animator
so let's go find an animator private
animator animator. OK so let's go find
the animator in start, simple enough
actually why don't you do some of this?
why don't we give you a bit more of a challenge
to do rather than just watching me
coding/ Why don't you connect the PinSetter
to the animator? You thought you were going to get away
with a free ride then, just watching me
code doesn't teach you very much at all.
You doing it does so connect PinSetter to
animated, get PinSetter directly
triggering the animator, check it works
and remove the UI test buttons. Let's go
ahead and get this guy finished. OK
welcome back so where was I? I was
finding an animator animator equals
get component, what am I gonna say? Animator.
Simple enough, it's a method it needs the squigglies, we're good to go.
OK so once we have an animator, then down
in our pins have settled we don't need
to log this out any more. We get the
pinfall and the last settled count and
then something else is gonna happen in
here. So we want firstly to capture the
action so it's an action master dot action
that's the enum, or the type, so this is
the type action master dot action and
we're going to call it action
equals and then we make the single
method call in this in this pins have
settled method action master dot bowl
pinfall, just like the Print statement. So
now this action will contain the result
of action master; what actionmaster thinks
we should do next.
Do we need to log this? You could
log it if you wanted to, I think it
would not do any harm to log it again
even though I just removed that log entry
Debug.Log the actual action so this is
gonna behave just like it did a moment
ago but we have access now to a variable
called action that we can start doing iffy
things with. Not iffy but iffy - you know what I mean.
Action if action equals action master dot
action tdot tidy - capital A for faction
master because we're talking about the
enum that is a type declared in action
master. So action master dot action dot tidy
what do we do if we have a tidy? Well you
want to go to the animator that we just
found, we want to set the trigger and it
wants to be the tidy trigger right? Now
if you're not sure what the name of the
trigger was remember where to find it in
Unity, you go to the PinSetter you probably
bring out your animation layout if
you've got one if you haven't then you're
gonna need to add in an animator
or animation rather easily confused window
and then you click on there and
then we look at the triggers which will
be parameters tidy trigger reset trigger
oK so that's right you need to click the
animator and then you look and you see
your triggers under the parameters there
so it's tidy trigger and reset trigger. So if
we get a tidy back we trigger tidy well
let's try it. Let's try and bowl something
that makes a tidy happen shall we?
So that is... well, hitting
1 pin would do it. We also need to deal
with gutter balls, we need to deal with gutter
balls in a moment. OK, I hit a pin so I
won't deal with a gutter ball right now, so we
get a one and then what do we get? A tidy
and there goes the machine we didn't
have to hit the tidy button. That's pretty
cool in fact it means we can delete the
tidy button right now because I think
that's the only instance in which we
well if we get a tidy it's doing it for
us we don't need to hit the button so
there goes the tidy button, what's next well
let's get the rest of this finished
off, it's relatively simple now. We just
need to enumerate through the different
possible actions so else if and then
we're going to have a very similar
statement I like to write my braces all
first and I know they're right; and then if
the action equals action master dot
what will we go for next, end turn? It doesn't
really matter really, let's just deal with the
end turn next. What are you gonna do on an end
turn? Well actually as far as the PinSetter's
concerned we just need to trigger a
reset don't we? For now we don't have any more
nuanced system than that. In fact I'll
probably restrict this game to a single
player game anyway and leave you as a
challenge to make it multiplayer. It's just
extra coding you don't need to watch
So if you have an end then you do a reset
trigger now we can copy this else if here
I'll just copy that differently if you copy
an else if correctly like that, there you go
then you can just paste it so what else have we got?
We've got a possible reset coming
back, what do you do with a reset? You
also do a reset you could have used an
or there but I'm not using an or, and
then the final thing that you might get
back is an end game and we don't
actually know how to handle an end game
yet so what we gonna do if we don't know
how to handle an end game? Why don't we
throw new unity exception" don't know how
to handle end game yet" and then we have
an exception with a badly spelled No
oK so that's that lets take a look at
how this actually pans out now. So let's
boldly remove this reset button, and make
sure you remove it
not in play mode, rookie error. OK let's have a go.
Kind of doing play testing as you go here
Gutter ball now, what happens? Tidy yeah that's
correct, no PinFall, we don't really know what
the PinFall is. Let's find out what the
PinFall is, I'm just gonna go back into
my code and log out the PinFall, so
where we debug log action why don't we
also put the PinFall
Cool. So I'm just logging out the pinfall and the
action just for fun really. OK let's try it,
a bit of play testing as we go... what have we got? Pinfall 10 tidy is what I'd expect, oh end turn rather.
yeah that's right, look at that cool; and
the machines doing a reset down the bottom
there and it's the end of the turn but
it's a single player game for now so let's
play again. So you're doing some
play testing as you go, it's perfectly
valid, good time to do it
knocked one pin down - it's very much space bowling isn't it? Look at that, pinfall 0, invalid pins, Unity exception error
So we get an exception error first when
we try and call the bowl, so where does
this happen? Here probably and then we
log the PinFall, so I'm just gonna move this
log statement up just above the action
master in case it ever happens again but
before... no we can't move it above because we don't
know the Pinfall at this point yes the
action at this point but the point is
what's going on here we're getting a
PinFall of 0 we didn't have a PinFall of 0
so ok perhaps this is because we're
calling count standing twice and maybe
one of his pins was wobbling. It's a bit
dangerous to call count standing twice
so why don't I just do a little bit of a
refactor here, so why don't I say int standing
equals count standing and then actually
use that variable thee - simple, simple
change but then we're not calling count
standing twice at two very slightly
different times during which the pins
may have wobbled around their center and
maybe standing in one instance and not
standing in another let's see if that's
the problem
It's gonna be difficult to test of course and
not something we can super easily write a
test for because this is to do with physics
probably probably, it may have some more
systematic error let's find out.
So here we've knocked down what, 5 pins
something like that so we should get a
PinFall 5 tidy which we do, tidies the
pins, now let's see what we have, it would be nice to knock one down
with this, are we gonna clip this guy in the end?
Missed. Pinfall 0, End turn. Yeah, 5, 0 tidy end turn. That's working nicely. I'm going to  keep playing for a
moment, see if I see if I can find any
bugs in this, because basically we're
done if this works then we are done in
terms of the control of the machine the
final thing we need to do is change up
our UI and get scoring working. Oh look,
hold on
pinfall one yet I see four pins standing,
definitely wasn't a pinfall of one there.
Something is going wrong with the way
that this pin fall is calculated. So one
of my ways of tackling this will be to
temporarily make public the last settled
count and I'll put in a TODO to make private
again and what I'm going to do is I'm
gonna play the game looking at the
PinSetter's last settled count over here in
the inspector here. So let's start afresh,
keep an eye on the last settled count,
make sure that's right because
something is going wrong with this PinFall
and the last settled count. Now this is
where, once you've done test driven
development this is where you really
start to appreciate it because having to
get the right test conditions to
form the bug here is a pain in the butt
right so Pinfall of 0, last settled count is 10
that sounds right to me. Lsat settled count is still 10, it hasn't updated
yet so PinFall of 6 and last settled
count of four, and now you see of course
the last settled count should be 10 now so
this is where we're gonna get our problem
we're not resetting the last settled
count when we do a reset, let's try it. That's
going to be the problem. Now I bet we'll
have a weird issue. Yep we have a weird
issue. OK that's not particularly
surprising it's because we're not, as I say,
we're not resetting the last settled count.
So you see the approach there was to
expose in the inspector the thing that
you suspect is causing the problem and
then to make sure that you can see it's
value live so whenever we do a
reset in the animator we need to set the
last settled count back to 10. So here we
just need to say last settled count equals 10
and the same here and you could refactor
this so that you don't repeat code but
it's fine So now whilst we still have that
variable exposed let's just play again and
make sure that the second frame behaves
properly, last settled count is 10 it was
set by the declaration at the top, we get
a pinfall of 7 and we should have a tidy
at this stage; beautiful I love this
machine working on its own it feels kind
of exciting ok now I missed which is
fine it's a perfectly valid bowl
so I missed, I get a zero so PinFall 0, end
turn yeah that looks right, swipes away
the pins really cool, feels like it's got a
mind of its own it knows the rules of
bowling. So all that hard work that we did which I
think was hard work with the with the
test driven development of the action
master starting to pay off; we're still
not guaranteed the action masters working
perfectly but this gives us a load of
other opportunities to test it; so yeah we
dropped 7 pins there the last settled count is.. sorry 3
pins last settled count is 7, try and hit a... I
did actually want to hit something but at this point
okay now this has set up perfectly for
the next video, at this point I've gone
off a gutter ball before I hit my
collider box at the end, remember we
have this PinSetter collider, what
happened here is my ball went off the
side of the track before hitting this
collider and it's now lost in space, if I
click on the ball it's somewhere deep deep
deep down below the play space falling
away forever so let's sort that out in
the next video, and yeah, I'll see you there