Hey. welcome to the third part of this
section so we're gonna be talking
about creating a testable architecture
now we'll be taking the time to refactor
our code because we need to step back and
think about the strategy for a moment
while we're talking about strategy I'm
going to share some of my thoughts on
being your own boss. we will then take a
look at our current architecture. decide
on a target architecture and then talk
about keeping our current tests in place.
So firstly let's just talk for a second
about taking the time to refactor.
Refactoring is all part of the journey
the way that we are teaching you to make
games and you are going to want to
continually make progress but also
continually refactor at the same time so
if you're spending too much time in
planning it's time to get coding and if
you're spending too much time in coding
it's time to get planning the key is to
know when it's worth refactoring and
when it's not and actually in this
section we gonna see examples of when
it's worth it like now it's definitely
worth considering our architecture
before we move forward and start trying
to tackle scores you'll see why in a
moment and we're also going to see an
instance where it's not worth
refactoring any further so that'll
happen when we do some work on the
action master you'll see that we'll get
to a point where we could make some
improvements so that the code read more nicely
but it wouldn't actually add any value
to do so so it's a question of whether
or not the refactoring adds value
another thing to consider is are you
stuck: if your stuck it's worth it. If you
can't move forward clearly. you're not
quite sure. you're scratching your head then
it's probably better to take some action
in the form of some strategic work so briefly
I'd like to share with you some of my ideas
about being your own boss.
Think about the fact that you if you're
working on your own wear two hats at
least. One is your boss telling you what
to do and the other is the worker obeying
the boss. Now my thoughts are that
neither can improve if the lines are
blurred. What I mean by that is that if you
set out to tell yourself that you're
gonna do
certain things. for example we are going
to choose a target architecture in a
moment. we're going to decide how we
gonna make the game in the next in the
next like sprint. If you then don't obey
your own rules and start questioning your
own judgment once you get into worker bee mode
then how are you ever gonna get any good at
telling yourself what to do the boss
inside you won't be any goodm it's very hard to
become a good boss if you have
delinquent staff and vice versa if you
don't do what the boss says then you are
never going to be particularly satisfied
in your work so I think it's worth
making the mental separation. it takes
discipline but it's worth it. It's making
worth making the mental separation
between when you're telling yourself
what to do which is what we gonna be
thinking about in this video. we're
standing back and doing some strategy
and then once you've committed to a
reasonable course of action that's not
gonna take too long you know it's going
to take days or hours or days rather
than weeks or months then go ahead and
get on with it without too much review
without too much questioning and then
come back and reap the consequences of
your actions and review your decision
after that that's just a a good habit to
get into. I think. But if you don't then share
in the discussions I'd like to hear your
thoughts.
Anyway let's talk about the code now so
our current architecture is something
like this and we're gonna show the bits
that are relevant so we have a mono
behavior called the lane box and that sends
a ball out signal over to the PinSetter
which sends a single pin fall number;
some number between 0 and 10 to
the action master and the action master
has an array of integers called bowls
and I put it in red because it's a bit
dodgy. for want of a better word. that the
action master is storing the state and
that int array of the bowls or the
PinFalls is is the state of the game. is
the main thing that determines what
state the game's in and we'll see why in
a moment that the action must is probably not
the best place to keep that. that's why I made it
red
The other thing to note is that action
master is a base class which does not
inherit from mono behavior and one of the good
things about it we could pop action
master into any bowling game and it
should work fine.
It also makes it very testable. we can
construct new action masters in our test
scripts and work on fresh action masters
and make sure it behave so it's good
that action must as a base class that
part of this architecture is ok. Then the
next thing that happens is that action master
returns an action to the PinSetter. that's
our enum. The PinSetter then passes that
action on to the animator now at this
point the PinSetter is starting to look a
bit like a manager. it's doing more than
just setting pins right? It's talking to
the action master and then it's talking to
the Animator. it's coordinating it's kind of
got a bit big for its boots right now
and then the animator replies with
things like raise or lower the pins
coordinating with the PinSetter. So that
coordination between the animator and
the PinSetter. the animator doing what
it's best at like the Swipe motion and
the PinSetter doing what it's best at like
raising and lowering pins. that's all fine I
just don't like the fact that PinSetter
is acting like a manager or a
coordinator here. and finally the PinSetter
sends reset commands to the ball;
again really we're stretching the
definition of a PinSetter here. Far too
thin and the problem with this
architecture is what happens now when we
want to start introducing a scoring
system how are we gonna do it? So there's
lots of places you could potentially put
a scoring system. you could try and
modify action master to deal with frame
scores. By a scoring system by the way
I'm talking about what are the frame
scores. So when we bowl a 1 and a 4
then we know that that frame has scored
1 + 4 which equals 5. So who's going to be
responsible for that? Well I'm tempted
not to mess around too much with action
master right now. it's a reasonably long
class and it does its job I don't want to break
it. So how would we move forward then
bolting on scoring systems well it would've been
messy and this diagonal just looks messy so
let me propose a target architecture
it's going to entail some refactoring
and that's fine and you're going to have
to refactor some tests as well and
that's fine and this is real coding here
what we haven't done is coded a perfect
solution and then
and then walked you through that perfect
solution as that really doesn't help you
learn anything. What we're trying to do
here is show you the tactics and the
strategy of building a game and how you
do get into situations where you need to
stand back and we'll stand back together
and so if you think of it that we are
you know are you on a guided tour of game
development here or are we teaching you
to be game developers? Well I like to
think that we are teaching you to be
game developers which means that you get
all the warts and all and we have to
make these refactors and strategic
decisions so join us in the journey and
be stronger for it. So the target
architecture that I propose is a pin
counter. Call it a pin counter. stick it on the
lane box and its job is purely to count
the pins and to send the pinfall to the
game manager. Now I want to move state
out of the action master make action
master stateless and have a list of pins
a list not an array
probably of pins here in game manager.
and game manager does keep the state so
then game manager will send pin falls -
plural here - gonna send all of the
pinfalls that've currently happened in this
game as a list to action master. Why a list?
Rather than an array? Because the length of
the list will vary as the game goes on
and if we send an array. array has to be
fixed length because it's a value type
and if it's fixed length then we have to
somehow try and then pass with that how far
into it action master should look. it's a hassle. Let's
just talk about a list. So the game
manager could pass a list of pinfalls to the
action master which will again return an
action. So we may send six different
Pinfalls in and the action would go ok.
based on that and based on the last
pinfall and all the history this is what
you need to do next
The game manager could then pass that
action on to the PinSetter stroke
animator those two work together very
similarly to how they do now I just put
them in a single box and the game
manager would then be responsible for
resetting the ball; pulling that
functionality out of the PinSetter seems
to make a lot more sense to me and then
moving forward to bolt on the score
which is of course the task in hand I
suggest something like this: that the game
manager also passes its list of Pinfalls
to a scoremaster and the scoremaster
can pass back a set of frame scores. It
can say okay so you've bowled one.
two. and then three then you know that
the first frame has a score of. well
three and because it's the one plus the
two but you but you don't know the score
for the third frame; for the second
frame yet because you have one and two
which is the first frame which adds up to 3
and tehn you bowl a 3. and you don't know the score of this frame yet because
the frame hasn't closed yet and there
are plenty of other situations in which
we the frame score is not finalized for
instance when you keep bowling strikes
we don't yet know the frames score. So
let's make scoremaster
a stateless thing it doesn't need to
store any state that given a set of
PinFalls. whether they're 5. 5. 5. 5. or
strike strike strike whatever they are
it just returns all of the possible
frame scores that can be known at this
stage so if you send it 5. 5. 5. 5. then initially on the
first two 5s at this stage you do not have
any frame scores because you don't know
the spare bonus yet; then you bowl another five and you
know at this stage that the first
frames score is 15; 10 for the two 5s plus the 5 for
the spare bonus and then when you bowl
your second five then you still only
have a single element in your list you
do not know what's in that empty box yet
because you need to wait for the next
bowl so that's an example of how the
timing needs to work we need the code to
return the correct list of frames the
bottom row of numbers in this diagram at
the right time for us; does that make sense and
we can create and test this scoremaster
thing completely independently of the
action master; we create a whole new set of tests
for scoremaster and build that up. make
sure that works keep it stateless in
fact we'll probably even make its main
method a static so that it's absolutely
stateless so there are no instances of
it any more there's just one; and it's just a
function basically you just pass in a list of Pin falls
and back comes the frame score the same
as the action master the newly refactored
action master; and you may say well
hang on aren't the action master and the
score master gonna have very similar
coding? Well we don't know yet we just
don't know yet maybe I have a hunch they
will have quite similar code they both
need to have concepts of frames and
and spares and strikes and things but we
don't want to break action master right now
action master's pretty well defined
it's got a good set of tests around it
and I want to show you a way that we can
move forward without having to break
what we've already got keeping all of
our tests in place so we'll build this
score master using test driven development
it'll be a base class and then it'll get the
scores and pass them onto a score
display that should then have a nice
simple job of just showing the scores on the
screen. however we do that. so that
architecture to me just looks better
maybe just cause the diagram symmetric
but maybe there's something in that
maybe the fact that this is simpler and
clearer and a cleaner said it flows is
actually a really good thing and it is
worth taking the time. Now this took me
some time to come up with but it's an
architecture that I'm happy to now
commit to trying. and later if score master
and action master end up being very
similar then we have an option we can
keep our tests in place and actually
merge those two together. so firstly we're
gonna need to refactor the action master
tests. we'll see that in the subsequent
videos because if we if we pass in a in
our target architecture here... there if we
pass in a list of PinFalls - plural to
action master that's a different API into
action master it used to be just
get a single bowl number now is getting a
whole list but we can minimally
disrupt action master and our test to
do that so we will need to refactor
the action master tests but
that will be fine; we will build a
score master using test driven
development. Later we will have the
option to merge those two classes the
action master and the score master
and if we do decide to merge them and I
don't know yet I actually. whilst recording
this video do not know whether we'll do that
it depends on overlap in code in various
other things but if we do decide to do
that then that merge would be protected
by two separate sets of tests we would
have a set of tests on action master and
a set of tests on score master and we
would make sure we can use those tests
to make to ensure the new
merged class call it bowl master maybe
actually works and and performs both of
the functions. There is unlikely to be a
benefit in merging these classes but
there may be. we may decide to. So that's it
really I just wanna leave you with a
diagram of the target infrastructure
it's like that so in your slide deck
you'll see all the builds of this
slide so as separate slides you get all
of these different builds each set of
arrows and boxes coming up on your on
your slides. so do take a look at the
section notes. it'll remind you the order that I built
that diagram and talk through it in do
digest this target architecture and if
you want a real challenge and your an experienced
coder then go ahead and don't even watch
any more of this section for a bit until you
get your game to this target
architecture. Now this is only a
challenge for the more advanced students
is not really reasonable to expect you
to do that on your own but if you think
you can then why not give yourself that
challenge? I'm not gonna put a challenge
slide up because frankly that's a big
pill to swallow but in doing this we're
gonna learn a lot. we can learn a lot
about keeping tests running we gonna be
learning a lot about segregation of
responsibility. we're gonna be learning a
lot about the value of refactoring and
you'll see that by the time we finish
this factor. refactor that the code will
be a lot cleaner. more easy to reason
about and it'll be worth the effort and
the pain
There'll possibly be a temptation for you at the
moment if you were doing this on your
own to plow ahead and to just try and
get the game finished and think will I'm
nearly there let's just plow ahead and
and and hack it together and you'll end
up with pretty ugly code you may get
stuck completely and I don't think
that's a good. I don't think that's a
good habit I think that taking time
to think about strategy means that when
you've done that when after this and you
after we've done this exercise of the
refactor you will be better at judging
strategy in the future and I think you
only get that judgment by taking the
time to set a precedent. say no we want
to make things with nice architecture
and we're going to do that if it takes
more time and cost a little bit more in
the in the early days it would be worth
it later when you come to update your
game. or you get bug reports for your live
game. or you just want to to build on
what you've already got and maybe create a new
game reusing some of your code all
of that stuff will be a lot easier if
you've taken the time as you go along to
get the architectur right and you'll
find that if you do that. and you set
that precedent
then you will automatically start to
pick a better architecture in the
beginning but right now you can't expect
to pick a perfect architecture because
you don't have enough experience to to
know exactly what the ideal architecture
is and that's what we're doing here with the
course. we're simulating your
learning journey and the fact that at
this point you're likely to need to make
an architectural change when
you're trying to put your games together
and I want to encourage you to to step
back and do that and to give you the
tools to step back and do that. So I'd
like to leave you with an outline for
this scoremaster script so just let me
set it up with you. Let's create
ourselves a C# script called
scoremaster and let's go take a quick
look at what the outline of this script
will be. I'm not going to do the whole
solution to you by any means that's going
to be in a different video. I just wanna talk
about lists and getting this set up. So.
start of the top. Firstly to use lists we're
gonna need something called systems.
system dot collections dot
generic which is the namespace that
contains the list data type Alright? So
then we'll be able to deal with lists. Then we
need to take the monobehavior
inheritance off. Remember I said that
score master. like action master was
going to be a base class. not inherit
from monobehaviour. The moment that we don't
inherit from monobehavior we cannot
then intercept the start or update message
because they won't be passed to us. because we are a base class. We are just nothing now
ok so there we are. a nice simple plain class
now I'm gonna write the signature of
this method so we have a public static
why static because I really want this
thing to be stateless we don't need
multiple score masters. in fact we
don't even need score master to hold any
state we're just gonna say to
score master give me back a list of
integers and this is the syntax for that
ok so generics format we're saying
produce a list and the type of list I
want you to produce is an integer. like that.
a bit like the GameObject dot find object
of type and that sort of thing and
I'm gonna call it score frames and then
I'm gonna pass in a list of integers
called rolls now how are we gona write that?
Same way. list of int like that and we pass in the rolls
ok so that's the outline of the only
method that we need bear in mind that
this score frames thing is going to
it's not gonna return cumulative scores
it's going to return individual scores for
each frame unlike a bowling score
card. You might want to write another method to
do the cumulative bit. calling this thing
many times but anyway I'll just finish
off with setting this up for you. you need a list of
integers like so I'm going to call it
frame list. You need a new list of
integers. you need to construct these things
Now if your list doesn't come up in blue it's
because you haven't importeded system dot
collections dot generic or you spelt it
wrong okay and then you have to use the
curly brackets because this new here is
a constructor.  we're constructing a new
empty list then you're gonna write some
code in here
your code here and then at the end you're
gonna return frame list. OK. sounds simple
right and it's got to do what we
discussed it's got to return the right
frame list every time you spit a list of
frames at it; completely stateless it
doesn't matter what the history of the
game is we can just always pass it a
list of rolls and it will return as a
list of currently calculable frames. Now
this took me more than two days to get the final code.
it was a real nightmare but great fun. I
learned a lot about test driven
development I got a solution that fits
in here in nineteen new lines in the
middle here. you made during the process
of trying to do this write hundreds of lines
and that's ok. We'll talk about that more
in a subsequent video meanwhile I'm
going to leave you with this slide which
just tells you a little bit about lists. so
using system dot collections dot generics
to use lists you need to import that new
namespace. the line you need is using
system.collections.generic
You define a list like that where T is the
type and there you go
so that's that there's my outline and if
you really want to challenge go and
refactor all of your code and write score
frames if you want a bit of a leg up. see
you in the next video.