So we've created the outline of our
score master class and before we move
on I just wanna tidy some things up,
teaching you how to create the
score master through test driven
development. It's going to be a fairly
large chunk and we need to re-
architecture all of our project but before
we worry about the code I just wanna
tidy up a load of other little things
about the way the game plays so in this
video we're gonna be removing some
unnecessary Unity testing folders to
make our project smaller, importing an
animated gif texture of jupiter as it
happens in my case; talking briefly about
quaternion.euler
and quaternion identity to iron a couple
bugs using a boolean flag to prevent
dragging of the ball once it's in play
and also briefly talking about using
Untinious, there's a new word
continuous dynamic collision detection.
So, let's dive in first I just want you
to change your ball's texture so at the
moment the texture, well if you're not
happy with it. I'm not happy with my
football so I'm gonna change it and what
I want you to do if you're not happy
with your texture is go ahead and
change your ball's texture. That's it, you could even
create your own texture in, well a texture is
a 2d thing of course but you could create
your own material or even your own bowling ball in
blender if you wanna go mad and you know
anything about Blender if you don't then
we've gotta course coming about it
super soon, just click on my face. OK,
welcome back so here we go I'm just
gonna quickly change that so am I gonna
do that? Well,
let's just go for say Jupiter, I think it would
be fun to bowl Jupiter wouldn't it? and dive
into images, I'll use the search tools to
look for something that I'm allowed to reuse, we've done all
this before there's a quite a large
image there, I'm looking at the resolution
as I hovered, there's a 1700 and odd by
600 image on Wikipedia now this is
an animated gif and only if we
import it as a standard texture it's only
going to import the first frame of that
and that's fine. I'm putting it in
straight into my textures folder in fact I'm
gonna put it somewhere slightly
different I'm gonna put it in this case
in the start pack under images because
it's an image and I want you to have it
available in case you want to use my Jupiter image
even though it's super easy to find one
with Wikipedia. The good thing about
stuff on Wikipedia you can be pretty
sure that its ok to use ok so over in Unity
because I put it in the start pack
folder under textures
images then it's there, and what I want to
do is to create a new material very
quickly. So, create a material... it's here somewhere
There you go, called
Jupiter and then the albedo which is
its base color and gonna set to jupiter
this is all your stuff you're very
familiar with now that I've got this
material I want to apply it to the ball
prefab so... Where's it's renderer? There, football. Instead of football we want Jupiter.
long list of things you can search in
your list that comes up on the screen
here for Jupiter - and it's done now we
have a Jupiter ball, now I may just want
to tweak the material just a little bit, it's a bit
too shiny for Jupiter probably I dunno, that's OK
smooth, that's too shiny, that's too dull
something like that little bit of
shininess and that will do, of course you can
play with this map and this texture
all day long but the point is I just
want a little bit better than it looked
before. Fantastic. While we're here in the
spirit of tying up I have a top camera
render texture here may as well go into
this texture folder just to tidy things up
Cool, alright and that's the first element
of this tidy up done, now what's next - we
were going to remove some unnecessary unity
testing folders, I've jumped the gun so that's
a simple thing
just if you look at the Unity test
folders structure here in your project
you'll find that there's quite a lot of size in
the examples in the integration test
framework folders. I'm just going to
delete examples and integration test
framework ok, so these two here examples integration test framework just delete
them
your unit testing stuff will still work
just fine its just gonna be a smaller
project now for that. Simples, ok so why are
we talking about quaternion dot euler
and quaternion identity because I want you
to reset the rotation of both the ball
and the pins so pins should be reset to
vertical when they're raised that's
because imagine they're slightly off
vertical; so we hit some pins may be off on
the side here they wobble around a bit,
now imagine that you get in a situation
where your pin, say maybe this guy here
is just slightly off vertical maybe it's
falling over but not quite got to our
threshold number of degrees and then the
script lifts this pin up and then maybe
it puts it back down again and it finishes
falling over which would look really silly
so we want the pins to reset to neutral
not necessarily
well vertical, they want to look vertical but
beware that
neutral for the pins if you look at them
at the start is 270 degrees rotation
in x 00 so for the pins you're gonna
need to reset their rotation to 270, 0, 0  the
other thing I want you to reset in the
same challenge is this ball, because if I
slide the ball off the side here it picks
up some rotation wherever it goes
whether it's off the side or down the end of
it, look it's got rotation now cuz we just
move it back here now when I use my left
and right buttons bug 'cause we're
translating the ball relative to its own
transforms it doesn't work right now
there's two solutions one is to
translate against global coordinates
global rather than local coordinates but
then it still looks funny but the ball
sitting it starting at this rotation so
what I'd rather be doing is just
resetting the Bulls rotation to 0, 0, 0 so it's
back like that every time you reset it
so that's your challenge, I want you to
reset both the pins to vertical and the ball
to neutral you're going to want to use probably quaternion identity for the pins and quaternion, sorry
quaternion.euler for the pins so you
can specify 270, 0, 0 and quaternion dot
identity for the ball which is the same
as quaternion.euler(0,0,0), just another way of saying the
same thing really ok go ahead and do
that challenge now please.
Cool so let's do it really.
firstly where we gonna do the pins?
Let's do the pins first so into scripts, into
scripts okay and then with the PinSetter
I believe is what did it. Is it? Or is it the pin
itself raise pins here we go, so when we raise pins
we want to go pin dot transform dot
rotation equals; now transform dot
rotation wants a quaternion so given
that this wants a quaternion, how we
gonna get a quaternion from euler angles?
well, what you do is you go quaternion.eluer
and there's a static method on
quaternion let me show you the
intellisense here
public static quaternion, and it takes
in a Vector3 in our case 270, 0, 0
and returns a quaternion that we don't
need to know how works for the moment. So
quaternion.euler 270 float 0
comma 0 should make the pin stand
upright shall we have a go? So
what I'm trying to do here's not bowl a
strike but hit something so is my raw
bowling talent gonna fail me here?
Yep, okay let's try again.
You know what, you should always focus on what.
When you focus on what you don't want you tend to
get it you know I don't want I don't
want all the pins to fall over what happens?
They all fall over. I don't want to hit that
lamp post now careering off the road so
focus on what you want I want some
pins left standing and they are and if
we go ahead in the scene view and look
this pin is now vertical and its
rotation when we inspect it will be
precisely what we want 270 it's picked up some
y rotation when it landed but but
that's ok
alright so they are resetting I believe
to 270, 0, 0 now, it wasn't very
convincing was it that argument so let's just try that
again. What we need to do is to see a pin
before the raise happens and then we need
to inspected it as the race happens.
Nuts, I keep knocking them all over look
I'm sure it's working. If you
find it isn't let me know but I doubt it
I doubt it isn't. OK cool so the other thing
we want to do is when the ball gets
reset we want to transform it or rotate it
so here we already transform dot
position it back to the start position
that's fine now we want to do
transform dot rotation equals now we
could go quaternion dot euler, 0, 0, 0 which is
fine and that's rotated it to 0 or we could
go quaternion dot identity which is basically the same thing. I'm gonna us that just for variety. Now what should
be happening is when I drag the ball
just slightly off to the side or
anywhere to be honest that's rubbish
because it didn't pick up any rotation
Let's try a different drag, down the lane spin spin
spin when it resets now rather than it
resetting to whatever rotation it was at
the time out it resets here and these
buttons work. That's cool.
Well actually I don't like my floor being
this color it just doesn't work for me
so I think what I'm gonna do is go into
my textures folder my floor and remove
the albedo map completely double click
it and say none, and then I'm gonna pick a base
color that is.. try black and see how it
looks in the game view... a slightly shiny
black should we try a slightly metallic
black, let's try that. Kind of spacey isn't it?
Strange and spacey that's perfect great
and there go the pins ok
fine in fact now we can use this
opportunity for a briefly pause the game
to inspect some of these pins so look they
have perfect rotation now that's good ok
what was the final thing I asked you to
do, if we look back it was using a boolean
flag to prevent that dragging oh and the
collision detection so fine, so what's this Boolean
flag to prevent dragging lark all about
then? Well look, there's another bug, thanks to Dondi
a friend of ours, one of our
students for noticing that if you drag
the ball and then drag again you can
modify it mid part that's rubbish so
challenge time what we want you to do is
prevent double dragging make sure that
you can't drag the ball once it's
launched and there's already a similar
solution in and I'm gonna leave you to
work out which script it's in. In one of the
scripts is already a similar solution.
So work out which script you need to work
on and then go ahead and make this
change you've already got the flag and
everything you need in there. OK cool, see
in a moment
OK, welcome back so which script are we
talking about first let's let's decide
on that well the dragging remember works
because you go to the touch input layer
of the UI canvas and it calls this ball
drag launch script remember that and
here is the ball drag launch script and it
does a drag start and a drag end message
that we can call from the UI but the
problem is we're not protecting with
something like this yet we need a if not
ball in play and I'm just going to wrap
that round both of the drag start and
the drag end OK so that's that bit and
then I'm going to do exactly the same
for the drag end. Oo the whole of that code just
gets completely ignored if the ball is
not in play
Telling you off for thinking about negatives a minute ago and now we're using negatives... just be aware about the
use of negatives both in life and in code.
Quite easy to miss those exclamation marks
isn't it? So now I bowl it and I try to
left and right and its staunchly ignores
me which is perfect
ok final thing is to do with collision
detection we have noticed or been
noticed... if you bowl straight and fast boom no
it didn't pass through the pins then but
the ball can pass through the pins
now one way to attack that is to go to
your prefabs, now you want to select all
your pins and you want to look down in
the collision detection part of
the rigid body and if you set that to
continuous dynamic then you can read in
the manual with the little blue button
about these different types of collision
detection it's a stronger type of
collision detection and if you
do that on the pins it will reduce the
chance that the ball passes through and if you do
it on the ball as well it will
significantly reduce the chance that the
ball passes through at the expense of
some performance as long as it's still
running OK for you then go ahead and set
continuous dynamic collision detection
on both the ball and the pins and it
should then not pass through. We're done,
we're tidied. Now we can enter a zone of code
where we're gonna be thinking about firstly
factoring everything and then we are
going to be focusing in on the
score master dot cs and how that is
going to work. So I'll see you in the next video.