Hey guys! So, we're going to continue to prepare ourselves
for the journey of making Score Master work.
We need to get to our target architecture.. Remember,
this target architecture that we built up?
A couple of lectures ago, we talked about the PinCounter
on the Lane Box, which is different to where it is now,
sending a pin forward to a Game Manager that doesn't exist at the
moment, which holds a list of pin falls,
and sends it across as a list of pin falls, to the
ActionMaster, which sends back an
action and so on. And then, we built out the rest of the architecture. So, let's just
focus on this bit for now, where we
refactor our ActionMaster,
so that it fits the new API. And we'll also
move on to refactor our code in general,
to suit the Single Responsibility Principle, so that
things to what things should do and not what they shouldn't,
which is my technical definition. OK cool! So, let's
get on with that, really. So, over
in ActionMaster, we need to change the whole API of ActionMaster,
which will of course break the ActionMaster
tests, over here in our Editor Folder, as well.
So, I'm going to have open just a couple of scripts. I'll close the rest.
ActionMasterTest, when we call in
to Bowl, we're no longer going to be calling Bowl,
we're going to be sending an entire list in.
First, let's refactor the ActionMaster,
and then, we will need to fix the test, by refactoring
them, so that it all works with a new API.
And guess who's doing it? Is it me? Is it you?
It is going to be, once we've gone past the target,
you! [Laughs] OK, we
want you to refactor ActionMaster.cs, still returning
an Action enum. Create a new static method, as
signatures in yellow below. Call your existing
Bowl method, as it is in ActionMaster, for each pin fall, just
go in a loop, and you
can use it for each loop with a list. And then the new API
passes a list of pin falls, so the method I want you to
write is public static Action NextAction
(List of  pinFalls), and I want that to loop around your bowl
and just return. This is what you do next, given all the pin
falls you've just given me, the very next thing to do is X and it's stateless.
It doesn't need to remember, the ActionMaster will
no longer need to remember anything, it can be completely amnesiac.
Once you've passed that set of pin falls, then it can forget about it,
which is one of the reasons I'm making it static. Because from the
outside then, we'll never even need to instantiate an ActionMaster.
We'll be able to just go, ActionMaster.NextAction.
That's ActionMaster with a capital A,
.NextAction from anywhere.
Pass it a list of pin falls, it tells us what to do next. You see that's pretty elegant?
We're no longer confusing...
We're no longer confusing where our state
is being store. That's what I'm trying to say. OK fantastic!
So, pause the video and have a crack at doing that now!
OK welcome back! So, here we are! Let's do the heavy
lifting. Firstly, we're going to need to use the System
.Collections.Generic; as we talked about before,
otherwise, you won't have any access to your list.
Fine fine fine! So now, I'm
going to make a new method, exactly the method I described in the challenge slide
here: public because we want it from the outside,
static because we want it to be stateless, Action
because it's going to return an Action, next Action.
And then, we're going to take in a list of integers
called pin falls.
Boosh. OK, so there is the definition!
Actually, we're going to make the Bowl method here
private, eventually as well, because we don't
need to be calling Bowl from the outside. In fact, let's be bold and do that
now. That's going to break our tests of course, but
that's OK, one of the things we need to do is refactor our tests.
We don't want to call Bowl directly. We're not sending single pins in anymore,
because if we do that then this class needs
to keep state, and we don't want this class to have to keep this
state, any longer than while it's just,
while it's running. Then, we have no confusion over whether the game state is
stored, it's going to be stored in this new Game Manager thing, remember that we're going to
create. OK fantastic! So,
how are we going to do this? What's going to be the code
here? So, in order to do this, we're going to need to have an
ActionMaster.
Because it's a static method,
which has no instantiation, it's not instantiated, so
we need to create ourselves an ActionMaster temporarily
so that we've got access to the Bowl.
OK, so then the action, we want to store the current action,
is a new action.
We just have to construct something.
OK, so we have an action, and then here's the
loop foreach.
We'll reason through this a bit more in a second, but for each integer pinFall
in pinFalls, what are we
going to do? Well, we're going to simply say
that the currentAction =
action master, this new thing we created, .Bowl
the (pinFall). So, we're just calling our own
method, action master .Bowl.
We have to create an ActionMaster
to get to that. If we didn't create an ActionMaster, we wouldn't be able to reference it,
from inside this static method. You can try it yourself and get all the
errors. You keep doing it until you run out of pinFalls, and when you've run out of pin
Falls, the current action will
be... Well, actually we
just return it, because we have what we need.
We just return currentAction. So, we keep
overwriting this current action, action variable, every single time
we call Bowl. Bowl spits back the Action and then,
when you run out of pinFalls what's left in currentAction
is the right thing. So, hopefully that makes
sense. Let's have a look at compelling this, see if we
get any problems. Ah hah! OK now, this is good! This is interesting!
So, under PinsHaveSettled () it's saying
that actionMaster.Bowl is inaccessible due
to its protection level,
and that's because we've made Bowl a private
method, over here in ActionMaster. So, in the spirit of not breaking
everything at once, I'm going to put Bowl
back to public, for the moment. I'm going to put myself a
TODO, which is easy to forget so be careful with those.
"Make private" we're going to be making it private
later. Now, when I build,
when it builds all the other scripts, they should continue to work. So for now,
this won't have changed anything right, because we just added a method that nobody
is calling. Let's just test our game still works. The purpose
of this is, I don't want to break everything in one go. I want to break things one at a
time, if I'm going to break things or improve things. OK, the game
appears to work fine, and that's because we've just added a method but
nothing calls it, and I haven't changed yet the
privacy of our Bowl method. OK
fantastic! So, if you've got this far, then you have done the
refactor you need to do on ActionMaster, but we don't
know it works. How on earth would we know that that's going to work? I mean it looks
OK, but how do we know it works? Well we don't really, so the next
thing you need to do is to refactor all the ActionMaster
tests, so that they apply
so they work with this new API. So,
the question becomes, what's different about the ActionMaster
tests, now that I've done what I've done? Well,
let's go and have a look! Over in ActionMasterTest...
I'm going to do this for you, rather than leaving it as a
challenge for you I think, because it's all a little bit new.
We actually aren't going to need to instantiate an ActionMaster. We've
made the method static, so we don't need an instance of it, we can just
call the method. You'll see that in a minute, but what we are going to
need is a list of integers, right here in the
tests. I'm going to just call it bowls or
better pinFalls.
Be consistent. OK, so we're going to need a list of
pinFalls. In the Setup, we do not need, anymore,
to have a Setup that tells
that creates an ActionMaster,
because we don't need an ActionMaster instance,
it's a static method we're going to be calling. But what we do need, is we need
this pinFalls array or pinFalls list, should I say,
to just be a new list of ints.
Now, when you construct a new list, you need to put the curly braces afterwards to call
the constructor. So, we have an empty list here, OK.
So, I've taken away the instantiation,
actually we don't need it. It's going to make our test a lot simpler.
Alright, so now what we need to do is, fix the tests
one at a time. What I suggest you do is, comment out every single test,
apart from the top one, the passing test. They've all got problems
anyway. They won't even compile at the moment,
and it's giving us a load of warnings, that we're not using things
which is fine. So, let's just go back! Remember
the Red > Green > Refactor loop now. Check your game runs.
It does! Go to the unit test and let's
run them all. In fact, I'm going to make sure Run on Compile is on. Good! the Passing
Test passes! OK, now it's a question of going through each of
these tests, one at a time, and getting them working for the refactored
tests. So firstly, we can't call actionMaster.Bowl,
it just doesn't make sense to call that anymore.
Why? Because we haven't instantiated an action
Master in our test, in the Setup () we never make one, and this is rehearsal
for when we use it in the game. We're not going to be making an
actionMaster instance. OK, we don't want it. So, what
are we going to call now? Well, we're going to need a
list of bowls instead, so we're just going to say
bowls.add. Remember in the Setup (), or
pinfalls rather. In the
Setup () here, we've made a pinFalls List,
every time we do a test. So, we're just going to say
setup .Add (10), which is going to make the equivalent
test for this, if we call ActionMaster, with a capital A,
because it's the class we're calling into now.
OK, ActionMaster has a static
method on it, called NextAction. That's beautiful! Trust me
it's beautiful! Honestly, I know it doesn't look it but it is! It's
beautiful because we can just pass in this
list of pinFalls. Have I spelled
pinFalls wrong somewhere? Pin falls
I don't think so OK! That's OK, I just have some Autocomplete error.
We can pass in the list of pinFalls to NextAction,
and it will spit back what we should be doing next, which
in this case is endTurn, if we bowl a strike.
And ActionMaster, we've not instantiated
it, we're calling it on the class. It's like calling Mathf.Clamp or Mathf
.PI. So,
we're not changing the state of ActionMaster. Action
Master will only be in existence while it does this calculation, then it will disappear.
So, we're keeping state away from the ActionMaster.
I like it and you'll see the beauty of it as we move on. Alright
cool, let's run the test. It passes! Fantastic!
Alright, let me do a couple more, then I'm going to whip through,
because it's going to be completely formulaic. So, we undo the next
test, because we want to go to red. It won't
compile, so we've got to make the test compile. Well,
it's exactly the same thing. We may as well copy this, actually.
We're bowling an 8, and we don't have to change the
test too much. In fact, it's almost a Tidy copy and replace.
I'll show you. So, Bowl (8), let's just check that works. It
will work, by the way, because we've just made a very simple
refactor. So, you expected an Enter and you got a Tidy,
and that's because when I carelessly
copied and pasted, I changed the test. So,
what's the sane and safe way of going through and changing
all these tests. It's enough of a hassle having to change these
tests anyway. Is
there a sane way of doing this? Well, for these early tests probably
not. I think it's worth just reasoning through here
that, we need to bowl 8, and then carefully
change this bit. It's worth copying and pasting this bit. ActionMaster
.NextAction (pinFalls) is going to be the same for everyone.
So, we add an 8 to the list, send it into the next action
system, and in a moment when it's finished compiling,
it will pass. OK next one! Let's try
the next one. Again, we're bowling an 8,
but now, this is where the API changes and I think it's a
lot more explicit. Let me give you another way of
writing these tests. A slightly more sensible way
is when you get to the array ones, or the ones that are a
list of multiple bowls. Why don't we do it like this.
Create an int [] array. Why an array? Just because it's an easy way of specifying
it. Call it rolls for now
or something, and then because with
an array... Because it's a value type you can at
at this point in your code, before it is even
compiled, you can specify the values 8, 2,
which is what test 4 was about right. And now,
you just pass in the pinFalls...
...dot what? Now, I want to turn pinFalls into a
list. I can't just say ToList,
or can I? [Sings] Do do do.
So this is backup... Why am I doing this? Because I can't easily
populate a list, without going .Add .Add. You know
.Add (8) .Add (2). Well, you can do that, but I'd rather
write it on one line with commas. So, if I
created a value type, an array
an integer array, then I can write it nicely on one
line, but I wish I had something called ToList.
[Laughs] Well, maybe my wish is
grantable, because if
I get the semicolons right, ToList doesn't exist,
but let me show you something. You come up here,
there's something very very handy for you, which we want to add.
Using System.Linq, L i n q,
that is a very useful
namespace. It has a load of things in it, and one of them is things operate on
lists and one of those things is ToList(). So now, we're just
literally sending it in a list of 8,
2, which we should get an EndTurn back from. Let's see if it works.
That's the last thing I need to tell you, before
you are ready to do it all yourself. So, it's expecting
an EndTurn. It got a Tidy, what have
I done wrong? So, bowl 2
8 spare. I've done around the wrong way! ;
so be careful you don't break your tests as we go here.
That's why I'm doing them one at a time, carefully.
And I need to be careful, because it's
rolls.ToList. I created something called rolls,
so that it's got a different name, and then I turn it into a list, going
into next action. I hope you're following this. I'm just playing
around with syntax, it's just a way of us getting this guy
in. OK, let's look at this type of test, and the rest of the tests
actually are all in that format! OK.
So, when you've already got a test in this rolls
format, then the difference is we
don't need the foreach loop here anymore.
All we need to do is go...
Got to get the right number of brackets.
All we need to do now, actually, is this. Paste
that in there. You see, because you're already forming an
int ray of rolls, and we just turn it into a list.
So, as long as I get the right number of closing braces, which is
three, then my test should run. Let's have a look.
Not quite, it was expecting
a Reset, it got an EndTurn, and that is because
what you need to be careful of is, previously,
we were doing a lot of rolls and then on the final role
we were checking against the action. What you need to do is
add that to your list, which is much more explicit of course, because
these are the rolls we're testing. Now,
when you paste that in, with the right number of end
brackets, it'll work because you've got the
final role in there. You see, watch.
OK cool! Let's do a couple more
together, and then, I'm just literally going to fast forward through it real quick.
So this one here, what you do is you look that we're adding a 1
and a 9, so what I'm going to do is go 1, 1, 9
on the end there. So, I've captured the Bowls that we had.
Then, I can paste in my code,
making sure there are three closed brackets, and I can delete
all that stuff in the middle there, build my code,
and test.
Now, it really is formulaic, because the rest of these are the same.
There's no new information to tell you now. Do one more.
So, I look at this
and I say, well what's
the Bowl that's missing in this list? It's 9. You see how our Bowl
list is much more sane now.. it's all of the bowls rather than
being split around. This is much nicer, it's stateless, it's just
generally better.
OK cool! So now,
I'm just going to whip through, so I shall see you on the other
side, because the pattern here is exactly the same.
So, I'll speed up the video and whip through! You go ahead now
and refactor the rest of your
tests, at the same time. And if you need some help, you can see what
I'm doing but it's the same thing.
This part of the Video is Being Shown on Fast Mode, for your convenience.
You may pause it or use Udemy's Slow Play Option, if you wish.
So, just slowing down for this one,
and here we test three things, at the same time,
and actually, the only one we really need to test is the
last one. So, I'm going to ditch two tests, but before I ditch the
two we do need to make sure that all of
the Bowls are put in. 10, 10, 10, and now I
can just paste in my static call
there and off we go and then
finally on the last one. So,
we just need a list.
So, here I'm going to do it the old way, at the top, where you just
add a pinFalls.Add.
And then we can... Or not...
No let's not, let's keep it consistent.
So, here and then
there's just a single 0,
and it should be endTurn.
OK, let's just check that
So notice that every single time, I was checking
that all the tests pass.
And this should be {0,
1} gives enter, not 0. Perfect!
OK, let's just check
and after a bit of a marathon, we have
refactored our ActionMaster, and we have refactored
all the ActionMaster tests. A huge amount of work but
I believe it's worth it, because now we are on track towards
the target archetecture that we are looking
for. So, in the next couple of videos, we'll be continuing to build out this architecture,
moving our PinCounter, creating our Game Manager.
But we've done this bit, we have created an
API, where we can call ActionMaster, with a list of pinfalls
and it returns an action, and we have kept all of the tests
working. So congratulations on this bit of the refactoring,
and I'll see you soon!