Stop. Refactor time. So it's time to do a
lot of refactoring, we're gonna create a
game manager with some state so what are we
gonna do? Correct a quick bug due to
incorrect responsibilities to do with
the pins you'll see that in a moment
Create game manager dots cs...
...anyway we're gonna create game
manager dot cs and Pin Counter dot cs
we'll weed our PinSetter.cs into
these new classes we'll then called the
static action master dot next action from
our game manager and repeatedly as we do
this test everything to make sure it
still works. So remember our target
architecture is something like that
not quite enough detail on this slide
necessarily for you to
verbosely go ahead and do it but I think
that it's worth a try, I think it's worth
you trying to do this refactor, but save
your work right now. Pause the video save
your work.
Take a proper backup of your unity
project; now if you're using version control
obviously just make a commit, if you
don't know what the hell I just said
just close Unity and take a zip
of your unity project folder because I
we're quite likely to break things before they get any
better, but sometimes we need to take a
step back in order to take two steps
forward this is gonna be worth it
because we have let the design drift and
I've let that happen rather than doing
it perfectly as I go along cuz it's
gonna happen to you, and your PinSetter
has got far too big for its own boots and
it needs to be put back in its place
over on the right there
tied up to the animator doing nothing
else but setting pins rather than trying
to pretty much control the game like
it does at the moment, so go ahead and have a
go at this refactor, you're allowed to
fail
you're allowed to succeed, don't worry
about actually updating any score
displays and don't worry about writing
scoremaster so both of those top boxes
are just for illustration and just see if
you can get the game working as it is
now but talking through a game manager
script and
see how you get on. You doing it? Or just waiting
for me? Hopefully you had a go and
hopefully you've either done it or you
have done some of it, or you got kind of
stuck and... whatever but as long as you
had to go then what I'm about to do will
make life simpler so firstly let's
squash a bug, so what I did a couple
of videos ago for you is I suggested
that we need to make sure that when we
reset our pins that... at least when we lift our
pins up during a tidy that
we reset their rotation... remember that?
Unfortunately that's causing a bit of a bug, I will
probably be able to see it right here if I focus on
the pins
well we didn't see it in this instance but
what happens is that even the pins that are
left on the floor jump upright,
which isn't very good. So the reason that
happens is that we put our code for
making the pin upright over here in the
PinSetter, now it's not the PinSetter's
responsibilities to do that the PinSetter
just calls the pin and says raise oif
standing. So I want you to take your line
of code that says Pin dot transform
dot rotation etc here from the PinSetter
just cut it, and then go over to the Pin
class and where it says raise if standing
pop it in there... it's almost the same apart
from we don't need pin dot because we're already
in the context of pin, so you take the
pin dot off, and build. So that's a
splodge + B from my point of view. So,
let's take a look. When we click Play Now
apart from the instances where you scrutinize
the pins as they reset
I'm hoping that the game will operate in
basically the same way so I switched to
scene view, let's watch the pins fall
over... hopefully not all of them... but at
least look they don't jump vertical now
they just tidy. OK, cool so that bug is
squashed and thank you very much to the
student who pointed that out. Right now
second thing we're going to do
everything. So, all we're going to do is to start
weeding out this PinSetter and pulling
out information that shouldn't be in
PinSetter and putting it where it
should be.
So let's start at the top of PinSetter
should PinSetter be dealing with the
display of the number of standing pins?
No, what should be dealing with the
Well the pin counter should be dealing
with the display of the number of standing
pins, that makes sense doesn't it?
it's the pin counter that's telling us how
many pins are standing, so let's move that
over to the pin counter if we have it, so
cut it have a look see if we have a pin
counter, we don't so let's make one I said
to put it on the lane box so go to the
lane box and add a new script now called
Pin Counter and later we'll get rid of the
lane box script and put it straight
into this Pin Counter as well
OK so tidy my scripts as usual, cool. I've moved
my prefabs to the wrong level...
OK, so the pin counter's gonna need access
to the Standing text sorry, flipping all over the
place. Here we go, now why is this text in
red? Because we don't have unity engine
dot UI, so let's pop that in. OK
let's try building, it's fine, we're going
to get errors down in PinSetter because
now PinSetter is trying to update the
display, so let's move all of this code
from the update loop in PinSetter over
to pin counter, that's fine, let's try
building now what do we get? It doesn't
have a count standing method well that's
true and we want count standing in fact
we want all of these bottom methods from
PinSetter, count standing, pins have
settled and update standing count and
settle, all of those want to be not in
the PinSetter, they're not about setting the
pins, they're about counting the number of
pins standing. Take all three of
those bottom methods, pop them over in
Pin counter and let's try building again.
OK so I've got an extra bracket and
that's because I took it from the
PinSetter, so simple things as you go
through. Just keeping your code going. Now
what we want to do is do as little
refactoring here as we can to get the game
running again
ok but the problem is that everything
kind of depends on everything so this
takes a certain amount of commitment to get
this working, because now that we've pulled
out all the pin counting stuff this is
saying well I don't know; that
the pin counter no longer knows whether
the ball is out of play. So whose job is it?
Whose responsibility is it to know about
the ball being out of play? well I actually
think that it is the responsibility of
the PinSetter, in fact all of these four
private variables here should be the
responsibility of the pin counter rather
not the PinSetter, theyre about counting
the pins so let's put all those in pin counter. So as a quick
recap, so far we've gone to pin setter
and we pulled out anything that's
clearly about counting the number of
standing pins and we put it in pin counter
Now I'm aware that we're a long way from
compiling code at the moment so let's
try and focus on getting this actually
compiling now as quickly as possible.
So we're not going to be calling
action master dot bowl anymore at all
it's gonna be a game manager thing so
let's just get rid of that line for now.
We can put it in a little bit later once
we have a game manager in place
ok so how about all this stuff? How about the actions?
Well it's not the pin counter that
should be doing the actions right? It is
the pin setter. So let's take the code
back from pin counter about all those
actions here in pins have settled that
stuff I just deleted... there... all the if
statements and let's just cut them out
and stick them back in the PinSetter, but
we're going to need to create a new method and that
new method is going to be called perform action.
OK, so let's just create public void
perform action and it's going to take in
something of type action master dot
action and we'll call that thing coming
in action; because the purpose of this
PinSetter is to augment the animator to do
the things that the animator can't do
for itself like lifting
the pins for example because it
doesn't know which ones to lift. So the
PinSetter is the thing that we want to
be calling saying OK go ahead PinSetter
and perform an action now in
collaboration with the animator get on
with these tidies and these resets and all that thing. OK
so it's all good but the last settled
count is clearly something that
shouldn't be here in the PinSetter
right so let's create a slightly
different API to the pin counter if the
pin counter is responsible for counting
pins it really in my mind ought to have a
simple new public method and that's the
reset so right here I'm gonna say public
void reset taking in nothing and then
that's simply going to; it's simply gonna
do what we do every time in PinSetter
set the last settled  count to 10; so
instead of last second count being set
up in PinSetter it's no longer a member of a
class we just; that's it, very simple method
right? It just resets the pin counter. Much
nicer.
So now where we see last settled count
equals 10, no we're going to want Pin Counter
whether or not we have an instance of it,
we haven't so better go find a Pin Counter
so we gonna need a private
pin counter pin counter
OK and then we're gonna need to find the
pin counter on the start; we don't need the ball
anywhere, not from the PinSetter's
perspective. The ball is going to be
handled by the game manager so let's
take that out; anything that's going to be handled by the game manager
let's just take it out we'll add it to
the game manager separately. So we need an animator
but we also need this pin counter thing so
let's go find it...
fairly standard stuff by now
OK so we found the pin counter which means
that down here I can now say pin counter
instance . reset
There does need to be an instance because the pin counter is stateful;
pin counter is in a particular state
at a particular time so we're not going
to define statics, we use
static when everything we're calling
is state-less like Mathf dot pi, it doesn't
affect Mathf, it doesn't affect pi asking
Mathf what pi is for example, alright? So
pin counter dot reset and we just call
it and then we use that same line here
in the last settled count. So much neater
API now. So what else isn't working? We
can't do a ball dot reset from pin counter...
well, good really. It's not the pin
counter's job to reset the ball is it?
Let's look at the slide. It's the game
manager's job to reset the ball because it
may not want to, because the scoremaster
may tell you that the game's over, or
the action master might tell you that the game's
over in which case the game manager is
responsible for saying ok, don't reset the
ball, so we don't want to be doing a ball reset here,
let's just take it. I'm also going to ditch my log thing
about the pin fall; ok will this build? Not
quite because ball out of play
equals false is still sitting here over
in our PinSetter; well it just shouldn't be
there, look at that code, it's horrible... set
ball out of play? Nasty, get rid of it,
get rid of the method, it's nothing to do with
Pin Setting. OK what does that break? It
breaks the lane box. Do we care? Not
really, the code in lane box is to
do with when you get an On Trigger
Exit remember of the lane box of
this thing here then we start counting
pins so I'm just gonna take that on
trigger exit method and I'm gonna pop it
on the new... into the pin counter
itself. Why not do this On Trigger Exit stuff
in the Pin counter? It doesn't matter where you do it I
think that messages should come quite
near the top of the class, so something
like this
on trigger exit collider collider and
then instead of saying PinSetter. ball
out of play we're right in the right
class and we don't have this horrible
set ball out of play we just say ball out
of play equals true. So to recap what
we've done there, the pin counter itself,
this thing that is attached to this
object is going to be doing the pin
counting and keeping state... keeping track
of whether the ball has left that box that's all
we're doing, so we no longer need the lane
box script, remove it and delete the
lane box script; we've merged lane box
into Pin counter. So what's going on
here the error's gone because we killed
the lane box script. Now lots of changes
right? Lots and lots of changes but the
code compiles which is a start. Now the
game won't run properly because we haven't got
a game manager in place but some things
will work let's see what works ok so we
can bowl the counting is not working
because the message is never getting passed
We have an object reference not
working
that's the standing display text let's
fix that so what needs the standing
display? The pin counter, where is it on
the lane box. There it is, it says I want
standing display so go to the UI canvas
in the left panel and you give it the text
Text? That's a nasty name let's rename that
while we're there. Standing count better
Just check that that association stayed, there it
did, perfect let's see how we do now. No
more red errors, she's good boom, the
standing display's updating the pins are
wobbling, the reason we're not getting
any resets or tidies is that we've kind of ripped the heart
out of this code so far we have not yet
put the heart back in which is the game
manager which is gonna hold the state of
the game and tie it all together. So without
further ado who let's create a game
manager. Here it is
game manager now I'm also going to
create a new empty GameObject up here
gonna call it game manager game space
manager just because... I don't know, it just
reads better
and let's put the game manager script on
it now it has a slightly different icon
there, just because game manager's a standard
name but that's fine, and let's go into
the game manager and make sure that we
well, write it basically so here's the game manager
let's take a look. So what's it going to need,
this game manager?
Well we said that it is going to be holding
the state of the game and most of the
state of the bowling game is in the the
list now why didn't list come up? Because
I haven't got the generic collection
built in so there comes the namespace.
Now when I try and write list bowls
equals new list of int like that and
remember your brackets for your constructor
and let's make it private. Cool, so now
we have a place to store state, isn't that wicked?
What else might it need? Well go back to your
diagram. I think it's going to be a PinSetter
and a ball but let's just take a look. So
it's at least for now gonna need access
to yes the PinSetter and the ball in terms
of game objects not - I'll go back to it - not
the action master because it's a base
class it's grey, we don't and it's not
only that it's a base class more importantly
it's a static. The methods in it are all
statics we do not need to instantiate an
action master we're just gonna call; we're
gonna pass it a list of pin falls and it's going to
give us an action and the same's gonna
happen in score master which is really cool
so we actually only need to create connect
the game manager to 2 unity game objects;
one is a private
PinSetter pinSetter; now notice at this
stage in the course we're tending to
connect objects through script rather
than messing around in the inspector.
It's just more solid and
also your designer or the designer
part of you does not want to change
these things, it would break your code so
there's no reason to try and do it in the inspector.
Alright so we'd better go find these things quite quickly
it's going to be pretty easy pin setter equals
GameObject dot find... god I'm going to get bored
of typing this type of
thing; as you're probably aware I could use some
shortcut keys but it wouldn't make your
life any easier; let's go find the ball Now how are we gonna find the ball? How do you
want to find the ball? There's lots of ways
you could find the ball but let's do it of type again.
Type's pretty strong, better
than using names as if you change the
type name then it'll follow. Cool so what's the
problem here? Just use objects of
type in both cases that's why it's
saying it can't convert an array. OK so
that's done. So we need a method in here
called bowl. The method that we call into
is bowl, I don't know if I put that on my
diagram I said pinfall, you pass the
pinfall but the way you pass the pinfall is you say
public void bowl and then int pin fall
Comme ca. Actually it's just reminded me, I'm sure I
spelt pinfall wrong somewhere just have
a quick look I can find it easily; maybe I
didn't, I thought that i spelt
Pinfall  funny earlier... if I find it I
find it so we have this method that bowl
and what we do is we just get this list
that we just created we just bowls . add
the number of pin falls that we just passed in,
so the number. So we add to the list, we then
need to call the action master . action
it's not calling anything, sorry, what I'm
doing is I'm just temporarily creating myself a variable
called next action it's of type action
master dot action which is an enum and here's
where we make the call will make it to
action master . and it's not one of
these so it's action master dot next action
what do I do next
given this pin fall... no no no no not given
the pinfall, given the list of bowls...OK?
given the list of bowls. So you call
it with all of the bowls and it gives
you a next action back, we could have
done this all in one line but this just
makes it easier I can now go
to the PinSetter instance because it's
stateful in the game and I can say
perform action it's all coming together,
next action get it and now we say ball dot
reset which we've got a method for
and that's it
How cool is that? See what's going on there?
So when when we call bowl to the game
manager it adds to its internal state
full list of polls it then says to the
action master what do I do next? Given all
of the bowls I've got my list, everything, what
do I do next and the action master goes
well at this stage in a game of
bowling you would do next action so then
you say cool, PinSetter go perform that
thing and then you reset the ball. How's that?
Let's take a butcher's hook. Of course it's
not gonna do anything because it is not
yet
tied into the pin counter so we do need
to quickly tie it in to the Pin Counter. How do we
do that? Well, we need a game
manager right so private game manager
game manager we're gonna go find it on
the start, that's why I left the start there; game
manager equals GameObject getting
bored of typing this stuff! Find object; not objects
of type game manager... fine and then
your squiggles; nearly there we just need
to come down and we need to make the
appropriate call in pins have settled
and it is just what I said in pseudocode
game manager dot bowl, let's compile... I
think the only other thing I want to do
over in PinSetter is remove the
ball line from the top of PinSetter because
we're no longer talking to the ball and I
think I think that's it
the final bold step we could make is we
could go to action master and we could
make this public method of action master
private, see if that works, it should because we're only
ever asking action master about a list
of bowls now, not an individual bowl and that
really will put the nail in the coffin if
you can
of your old API if you can make your bowl
method private and the game still works
like this it's done. Guys, rather than
spending any more time in this video
going through all of these scripts I'm
gonna just... I'm just gonna attach the
project to unity they're all here, and you
can go and have a look
go into Unity, go into resources, download
the project and you can see exactly what
I did if you couldn't follow the video
The refactor's done, we have a clear path
in front of us for a zen moment, we're
going to create score master and it's
going to be amazing!
So I'll see you soon.