You're either gonna love me or you're
going to hate me by the time you've finished
with this challenge. In this video there's
going to be an overview of the challenge
and the delight ahead, we're gonna find and move
our score master test dot cs into the editor
folder; temporarily disable our action
master tests; write a cumulative score in
score master and then set the challenge so
let's get all the kind of administrative
stuff out the way first and then I will
talk to you about the
the final thing the challenge OK? So over in
unity I've got a red red error coming up
now because between the videos all I've done
is I've popped a score master test dot cs
script into the tests part of the start
pack so it's not in your start pack
then you need to just go and re-download
the start packs from the assets at the very
beginning of this section, your section
assets because it's only in the latest
version of the start pack. OK so firstly
what's this all about why is there an error
Well the error is because tests need to
be in the editor folder because they run
in editor mode so drag from tests into
editor, right ok now that error goes away
second thing go into your score master
tests, take a look at it most of the tests are
commented out for now what you're going
to do is you're gonna go round uncommenting
these tests and building score master
but before you can do that we need to
do a couple of things firstly try and
compile code and you'll find it'll
work fine but if you were to uncomment
one of the bottom tests then you'll find
it won't work and that's because it's
making a call to something called
score master cumulative here and we
don't have a score cumulative method yet
so leave all your tests commented as
they were, it's just the top one I'm commenting.
Go into your score master that we have
created before and let's just create this
cumulative script so I'm gonna leave you
to do that as just a quick challenge
it's just a cumulative scorer, it's just gonna
keep calling score frames and then
keeping an internal track of the
cumulative score because remember that score frames
frames that the major challenge that we're
gonna create just returns the list of
frames scores it just doesn't add them
up so this is a simple loop and the
and the signature of this method is is
as follows its public static list of int,
score cumulative list of roles and it's just
going to make a call in to score frames
let me take you a step further if you
need me to before the challenge so that
you can see exactly what I'm going on
about and should be relatively easy for
you to warm up your coding; roll up your
coding sleeves and get warm so
remember this score frames; this is the
epic challenge writing that, I'll explained
why it's epic in a minute but for now let's
just get you the signature of this thing
sorted it's public static list of ints
score cumulative list - it's taking in
a list of ints - rolls OK? And I'm going
to describe what both of these methods
do in some comments this returns a list
of cumulative scores like a normal
scorecard and this method here is going
to return a list of individual frame scores
not like not cumulative ok now it turns
out it's easier, slightly easier I think
to write score frames than it is to write
the cumulative version of it although
frankly there's probably not alot in it
but I have done it this way, so as a
little challenge for you what I want you
to write here is a simple method that
calls into score frames regardless of
the fact we haven't written score frames
yet as many times as it needs to to make
a list of running totals. So hopefully you
understand now what the challenge is and
that's it; it's a little For Each loop, you can do this in about
less than ten lines of code, have a go, warm
up your coding
OK, so I'm just gonna tell you how I've done
that I'm gonna keep internal list of
integers called cumulative scores and it's
a new list of integers and then
eventually we're going to return just the job to
the bottom of method the cumulative
scores . OK, fine, but what are we gonna do in
between? Well it's a for each loop, and it's for each int
frame score in... now in what? In score
frames with the number of rolls now what's
that? That's a bit functional isn't it? What's going on there?
Well, when we call score frames with a
list of rolls, that has come into our
cumulative method we just pass it
straight in here to score frames, score
frames tells us what all the individual
frame scores are and now we just iterate
through them. Running total... have we got a running
total? No we need a running total don't we?
Simples... int running total better start at 0,
right? Cool, so running total + equals
frame score and there's only one more line. The other
line is what, cumulative totals
cumulative scores dot add, just add that to the list
the running total. OK see what we're
doing here? This is just providing a
wrapper that allows us our score master class
is going to have two ways of accessing it you
can either query for cumulative scores
or for individual scores. So it turns out when
you're building your test I find in the
beginning it was easier to... well let's do it
actually let's uncomment the first test
which is score master score frames and
its gonna pass in two bowls, two and
three and ist' expecting to get a
score of just five out - an actual frame
score you know, not a cumulative score,
which is of course the same with just one
frame and let's see what happens when we
go in and try and run our tests and we
get and I'm gonna set my run on compile
we get a failing test, good this is
where the challenge starts with this
failing tests now just before I set you
the challenge I'm going to go into my
action master test and I'm just gonna
comment out all the action master tests
just for speed and come back to unity
and run all your tests and it would just
mean, when it's finished compiling, that
you don't have to run all the action
master tests every time
OK we are there, we're at the frontier of something
that for me was absolutely epic writing
score master sorry writing the
score master, yes the score frames method
in here was completely epic for me at
one point my code had a hundred and
forty lines and it still didn't work and
these are the tests I went through
you've got exactly the same journey as
me as you start to uncomment these tests one
by one
I want you to strictly stick to the
red-green refactor loop and by the time
you get down to about test number twenty
one we'd hope that you have working
code and then after test number 21
I've labelled all the rest of these as
verification tests and they're golden copy
tests; these are actual scorecards if you
click on the URLs they'll take you to web
pages that will show you where I got it
from that one came from that site that
one came from this site
ok and it's it's kind of just tells you
the source but it's all written here, here
are the rolls, here the totals, and it's a
complete test. Starts off working on
individual scores then goes to cumulative, and the reason it was so epic for me is
that I got to a hundred and forty lines
in here right in here where my code is and
then I reduced it down to... I can't
remember how many to be honest with you
but I think eighteen yeah I added 18
lines in the end and I could not believe
that as I went from a hundred and forty
lines of code that just about worked
down to 18 lines of code that works, or
seems to work perfectly but it kept
working and it's so satisfying cos you
build it up you build it up as the tests
come and then you start deleting and
deleting and deleting code constantly
re-running your tests as you refactor and
it's incredible how powerful a solution
you can come up with and I'm really really
pleased with my solution now yours
doesn't have to be as short as 18 lines
I think mine is really pretty and
I'm very very pleased with myself for
doing it I nearly gave up I remember
sitting in the garden and nearly there
on the brink of solving it and then I thought
Oh my god no I've got a problem that is gonna
need me to start from the beginning and
instead of scrapping my code I just took yet
another version so a tip for you, take
lots of snapshots use version control
get source tree or something or just
take loads of zip files so that you can
go back anyway I sat there
thinking oh my god I'm gonna need to
start from the beginning but I went and had a bath
and in the bath I realised a simple
solution to the final problem that meant
that I really was nearly there and I
solved it and it worked. So your
challenge. Are you ready for it? Get
Score Master dot cs working. This took me two full
days. It may take you much more time than
that, it may take you a week don't spend
any longer than a week on it of like
full-time work and I mean a week of
full-time work, like 40 hours. Yes, spend up to
40 hours on this right because if you're
making progress and you're making more
and more tests pass it's worth it. If
you spend more than a week or so just
stop and and let me help you with the
solution because it's just not gelling
for you and I haven't taught you well
enough and it's not a failing, ok, but i
wanna give you the opportunity to have
that huge satisfaction ok and it may
take you a lot less time, it might just be I'm
rubbish and you could just take you hours, let's
see used the TDD test driven development
red green refactor loop strictly stick
to it's your friend. If lots of tests start
failing just undo the new test you
created revert your code to its previous
state and start again;
Uncomment the tests one at a time and go
for it, just start making it working
start with a small step you just need to
make it return five. You know if you
want to start in score master by just
saying; make a new list and just
return five that's fine because that
will make the test pass. If you get in a
situation where you just want to write
special cases again and again and again
and again for a while that's fine too
it'll help you spot patterns ok there's
no wrong here
just
get it done and do your very best... sorry
I've just made some mistakes in the code
ok just get it done so go ahead,
pause the video for up to a week and I'm
serious in a way I hope it's not easy
for you because it's so satisfying if
you struggle and struggle and struggle
and then this works, so good luck and I'll see you soon.