So. welcome back. I'm really looking
forward to showing you the adventure I
went on to get to the code that I
finally got to and then challenging you to
make your code even prettier and more
concise than what we came up with so in
this video
how we solve the scoring problem; a
reminder that it's the destination that
counts it really is here our code as I
said before went through some very
very very horrible states. I'll probably
even show you our repository in a moment
and you'll see how tests really
protect your refactoring. when we get to the
refactoring. So the overall goal is what
Einstein says is to make things as
simple as possible but not simpler - Good old Albert Einstein - so let me just show you something. I'm gonna
show you how round the houses we went -
if I open my bowl master repo history here
what this is every one of these
nodes here is a commit and you'll see
that to get to the bowling solution I
branched off here from the blue branch
which is our main production branch and
did a load and a load and a load and
a load and a load and a load and a load of work
and more and more and more and more and
more and more and nearly gave up at one
point and the code went from very little
to a lot and back down to very little
again so now we are back here I'm gonna
show you what that journey was for me
and I'm going to try and strike a
balance between taking you all round the houses
and going straight to the solution going
straight to the solution for you would
be pretty boring taking you down the
full journey that I went would be
frustrating so I think I'm going to try
and strike a balance that is appropriate
so let's get on with it
here we go open up unity I would suggest
you have your unit test panel
wider than usual cuz we're just doing
testing here and also make sure that your
action master tests are all greyed out
and we should be starting in a position
where this first test. 01. is
failing - perhaps you've already got all
of your tests passing that'd be fantastic
if you have. this would just act as a
recap for you but if you haven't and you need
some help then this is how we got there.
So firstly let's start with that first
test. What is the test? The tests on the
left and look at the test the test says
that if you roll two and three return a
list of just five. Well. I could be pretty
obstinate here I could say I don't want to
type frame list every time. frames just gonna
call frameless frames I could just say
frames dot add five and that would
actually make the test pass wouldn't it
and over in unity we can see the test
does pass so we've gone from red to
green now it's time to refactor now
clearly our code here is never going to
generalize right it's never gonna work
if all we do is return a single 5. For a start
this whole thing needs to be taking in a
list of rolls and iterating through the
list of rolls to produce a list of
frames. So let's try and do this
iteration now see if we can still keep
our test passing so about a for loop? For
int i. starting at 1 - we're gonna call bowl one
bowl one. provided that i is less than
rolls . count - so we don't
overrun the list that's coming in let's
step through in twos.. OK. we're gonna step
through in twos. let's try that. OK and when we
step through in twos rather than just adding
five we're going to add rolls i. minus one
plus rolls i. so what are we gonna be doing
each time is starting this i. this pointer
is going to point at the second bowl of
the frame all the time.
OK. so it's going to start off as i equals
one and that is roll one which is
because it's an array is the second roll
and then it'll go to i equals three
which is roll three which is the fourth so
it's looking at the second roll in each
frame every time. Let's see if that works
it's just adding together the two adjacent
ones. The ones I is currently pointing
out and the bowl before.
Cool. so we've had a refactor and this is
more likely to work now in a general
case than that other code which clearly
was never going to work with just a
five. OK. let's undo the next test and go
back into unity and see what happens
Let it compile... boosh. Now 2. 3. 4 is actually
working as well we're still just getting
a five which is fantastic so this idea
of jumping through in twos and adding
together the bowl and the previous bowl
seems to be working. Now this test isn't
driving any new development so strictly
it's a verification test but I'm gonna
leave it here just to keep the journey
simple for you guys rather than changing
the tests. I'm not gonna change anything about
these tests. I'm only gonna uncomment so
let's build again and doing the 2. 3. 4. 5. now
will this still stand up to scrutiny? Yes
it does actually so again this idea that
we iterate through in two is working
really well now you may well have gone
down a completely different route here
in fact you're even allowed to put if
statements in for every possible condition
and that's absolutely fine and then
eventually you'll spot patents and you
will start being able to generalise. In
fact that's how I got to this code. by
putting in if you know if you bowl 2. 3
then return a five and if you bowl
2.3.4.5 return 5. 9 - you can literally put every
special case in as long as at some
point you start to generalize and this is
the generalisation I made for this type
of frame so let's keep going and see
where this falls apart.
Build again 2. 3. 4. 5. 6. see what happens. and
that works! Fantastic. good. so so far
stepping through in twos. i's pointing
to here and then adds that these two
together and then i points to here. and adds these
two together; and then i goes outside of
the rolls list so it doesn't iterate a
third time so our loop just goes round
twice adding two and three and five and
four which gives you your five and your
nine. So that structure still works. awesome.
Again for you it may have driven you to
create more and more code. that's
absolutely fine because you can refactor
later. I just would take all day recording
this videos if we go that way. so let's go
back to unity and see what happens when
we try and do this test
It still passes. fantastic. and that's because
there's nothing that different about
this frame it's still not a spare or a
strike so it just adds up
Great ok. what's the next test? Should work as
well because there's nothing special
about the last frame what happens? It
still works fantastic so pretty good
general code I've stumbled across. The
reality is that that came out of days of work
and you may well struggle to get there
as quickly. Not a problem. here we go now
we're bowling a strike. Right now this really
shouldn't work because it doesn't know
that it should be delaying the
production of a frame score. let's see what
happens I suspected it'll fall over
horribly now. it must do - yes and what's
happening is you're getting an 11 out. which
should never happen. we should be getting
nothing out and the reason is it just
blindly starts with an index here. adds 10
one to 10 and you end up with an 11 which we
don't want. Great. so now we have a test
finally at test seven the way I'm doing things
we have a test that drives the need for
some new development. So how do we
protect this? How do we say we're iterating
through but we only want to do this
thing when what? Well when it's a
standard open frame right? So one way of
saying that is if... and I'm going to do my
braces. all of them now. I'm gonna put an if
statement in before I even write the
if statement I'm gonna remind myself what if
statement I'm trying to write - this is a
normal. what they call in bowling. open
frame meaning the sum of the two bowls
with less than 10 so how do you say that
well it's quite simple. you say rolls i minus
one. that's rolls i is less than 10 so a
normal open frame is when they sum
to less than 10 do that but if they
don't sum to less than 10 then we're
gonna get a different result. Let's see
what we get here. clearly the loop just
won't execute at all and I think that'll
make the test pass it does because now
it goes hang on the first two bowls are
more than 10 therefore I'm
just gonna do nothing. it just leaves the
loop. Great. so we passed. Do we need to
refactor?
Not yet. we don't have any tests forcing
us to refactor yet so we get another
test you can write it. your friend can write
it whatever ok cool so here we bowl a
1 and a 9. now they're equal to 10. what's going to happen? Let's see. Again it works because our
code says if the two bowls are less
than 10 do this otherwise do nothing. Cool.
let's carry on. See how this works? Again I
don't expect you to go straight to the
code that I've got. OK? You may have gone
significantly round the houses. Now.
what's going to happen here is it gonna
know to delay on the 5. 5? It should do
cuz they add up to 10 right? We just told
if they add up to 10 that you need to
skip and it does work.
Fantastic. so I have coding super powers
here just because I've spent a lot of
time in rehearsal. Most of the amazing
performances you see of course in real
life are people rehearsing beforehand. so
just remember that when you see
something that you think is great.
OK so here we go let's try again let's
try this spare bonus that can't work I
don't think. that we haven't told it
about speed bonuses - no ok it was
expecting a 13 but it got a six.
let's look at the test condition. So
where it was expecting a 13 it's
getting a 6. so how's it ending up getting
the six here?
Well what's happening is the code is
saying get these two. add them together make
a three
these two. add them together make an 8. these two. they equal 10 so let's just exit the loop so
then the i pointer goes to here. to the
second three. it adds these together and adds
it to the end of the list which is now
still just here. See what's happening? It's
just skipping over these and ignoring it
which is exactly what the code says to do.
it as only add something to the frames
if the total is less than 10 but it
keeps skipping ahead in twos. which is fine.
So is this a good strategy? Well we don't know
I mean I know it is because I know the
end code but if you don't know just
press on just keep going and we're only by
the way gonna go through this until we
get to verification tests then we'll stop
and take a break.
So how do we make it work then? Why is it
not working? Well it's not
working so we haven't told the code what
to do when the rolls do equal ten. so
put in a separate if statement. in fact you may as well
copy this one here if rolls equals 10 -
the sum of the two rolls equals 10 - then
what do we do? Well we frames dot add; what
do you add in this case? Well you just
add 10+  i+1 right? So you here at this
point. your i is here on this second
five. what do we score this frame? 10+ i+1
this guy here. Cool. hey? Alright so let's do
that and see if that works. By the way
I'm going to comment here and just say
spare. just because I think it's a clear
place to put that. Now let's see if
that's helped the code at all. it has but -
and this is a very common thing. it's broken
the previous two tests. So what we do
here? What do you what to
do to fix this so do we go back and try
to fix these tests? What state are we in?
Red. green. refactor? Well we just made
this test pass but we've made these fail so
here's the discipline. Go back. undo the
test you did - you just put in that caused
that problem. Revert for the moment your code
changes - you can comment them if you're
confident in them and then rebuild. let's
see where we are. You mustn't have multiple
tests failing. OK. now that these tests
are still passing let's refactor so that
they continue to pass even though we
have our new code in. so how about if we put
this spare handling code in. what happens?
These tests fail. 19 and this one. Now look carefully. the
reason is that there's an argument out
of range. so why on test 8 do we get an
argument out of range. let's have a look
what is test 8 provide. a 1 then a 9. so what
happens in the code it says do the sum
of the two rolls equal less than 10? No.
do hey equal 10? Well yes they do but it's
trying to add rolls i +1 when rolls
i +1 does not exist. at this stage it's
here and is trying to look at i +1; well
there is no i +1 from this standpoint
where we are now so we need to protect
against too much look ahead. So let's try
this if rolls . counts minus i. so you
take the count how many there are on the
list you take away where we are now in
the list and that needs to be at least
one we need a look ahead of at least 1. So if
the look ahead is less than one and
I'll put that in as a comment...
insufficient look ahead. then what we do?
Well one neat thing to do here is just
break out of the loop; just leave the loop
for this time round. We don't have enough
look ahead. don't even try and calculate
the spare bonus yeah? Get it? OK let's have a
look. see if it compiles. Well it compiles but
see if it works
beautiful now we don't have any argument
errors. and we have nothing in our lists
coming back because it dives out at this
point. Get it? Cool. so now we can undo the
test that caused us the problem before
rebuild and see what happen. Hopefully it'll just
pass... and it does it's calculating spare bonuses
fantastic it's carry on next
test. Build. and the other spare bonus
test where we've just got a few more bowls
that works ok let's keep going. Now strike
bonus can't work right because we
haven't told it
how to calculate strikes. great it
doesn't work. It's missing everything
well. by the looks of it. it's yes it's missing
everything cuz it's just got completely
flummoxed by this 10 here.
So. what's the easiest way to calculate
that strike bonus well. let's go have a look at
the code I think the code is quite easy
to reason about right now. So the first
question is do we need to think about
strike bonus before or after we think
about spare bonus? Well I think that we
need to think about it before the spare
bonus because 10. 0 is the same as 0. 10 as
far as this statement goes right these
things still sum up to ten whether or
not the sequence comes 10. 0 or 0. 10 but the
strike is just 10. 0. So what we do is we
say rolls i minus 1. yeah? Because remember
we are sitting here and the i pointer
will be sitting at the three right now
so we're talking about i minus one because remember
it goes ahead in twos so if rolls i
minus one equals 10 then we do something.
OK and in this case we have a strike.
What do we do in the case of a strike? Well
it's very very similar to this isn't it
with a strike you add ten plus the bowl
ahead plus two bowls ahead that's how a strike
bonus works isn't it and I could
simplify my code here by just saying
else if. OK. fantastic. so will that work
or do we still have a problem? Let's have
a look. It doesn't work and we get an
argument out of range why
well because we're stepping through in twos
remember. and then our code goes ahead
and tries to look at two a head when
a strike goes and messes things up
doesn't it because a strike is recorded
is just a single bowl and then it skips
it doesn't put a zero it just skips. so that's
irritating. how can we deal with that?
Well there's a pretty simple way of
dealing with it. The moment we realise
we're in a strike situation decrement i just
take it back one. the moment we identify
that we're in a strike situation here bring i
back to here to the 10 ok. see if that
works.
It does. perfect. ok so let's record what
we're doing. this is really important to
comment here because it's not it's not
obvious to somebody reading it so strike
frame has just one bowl for example
would be a useful comment
ok cool let's carry on. let's keep doing the
tests and see if we can break the code
again
strike bonus 3 so this is just a
different strike bonus and the code
handles it great so it becomes a
verification test. We just leave it
there cuz we're better to have more tests
than less. and the multi strikes works. nice.
So how about a different multi strikes?
Now this wasn't my journey. I wrote every
test for a reason to try and put
pressure on my code but now that I know
a better solution
this is working much more nicely so
gutter game. all zeros. it should get zero. does it?
Yep great so this code that we've
written now with a lot of rehearsal and
insight seems to be handling most of
what we're throwing at it. Good. let's test
all strikes I suspect we're gonna run
into problems with the last frame
shortly.
It's not yet. OK test immediate strike
bonus. Passes. great. OK let's have a look
at if it can handle a spare in the last
frame like this. 1. 9 in the last frame
surprisingly it does OK. can it handle a
strike in the last frame? I seem to
remember this. I definitely remember this
part. it won't handle it and it's a subtle
reason why. OK it does not handle
a strike in the last frame. and it's you get
an extra 38 on the end of the
list. why the hell does that happen? Let's
look at the code. What happens here is we
get 38 at the end. What's 38? It's 33 + 2 + 3. Or 33
plus 5 is 38 and what it's doing is
it's going round the loop once more adding
the 2 and the 3 to the previous frame
score. Why is it doing that? It's doing
that because the system has no way of
knowing that it's the last frame from
the inside from its point of view
it doesn't know; a game of bowling can
have as many as 13 bowls like this
or as few - sorry as few as 13 bowls
like this in a perfect game. or as many
as 21 bowls like this and the code
doesn't know whether we're in the last
frame and at this point I nearly gave up
I tell you I thought I've nearly got the
solution but now I'm stuffed now I've
gotta go back to the drawing board and
make this whole thing calculate based on
frames not rolls. oh my god. but I had
the wisdom to close my laptop and go and
have a bath. and in the bath I realised hang on.
there is a simple way of telling that we
are in the last frame. we are leaving a
breadcrumb and that bread crumb is the
frame list that we are creating behind
us. so why don't we simply say if frames
dot count equals 10. just get out of the
loop and it won't go around again
because by then the i will be too high.
If frame count is ten. get out of the
loop and what this does is it prevents
11th frame score. Without the apostrophe.
OK? Let's try it
Wonderful. and that fixes it. and I believe that's the
end of our test driving test from here
on i categorize it as verification and
we've got a lot of golden copies so I'm
gonna stop the video and in the next
video I'll talk about what's going on
there so well done following this so far
and I'll see you soon.