Hello, hello hello!
Golden copy testing what's all that about?
So we'll be telling you what golden
copies are; why they're useful for verification
testing; I'll be showing you the about
using the category name test
annotation; we will be using binary
search to find the failing tests;
necessary it won't be but still I tell
you and also commenting your code for
future readability and then finally
you're gonna share it as something really cool
and pretty into the discussions as the
pièce de resistance and I'm very very sorry
Brice for that French. OK, fantastic
so back over to unity, even if you
say it like that, and back into mono
develop, and
let's take a look at our code and our test,
here they are so bunch of verification
tests I'm gonna take the bold step of
undoing them all at the same time now if
they all pass that's great but what I
want to just tell you is if they didn't
all pass then what you could do to find
the ones that aren't is chop the
space in half like we did in number
wizard and then try the first half and then
try the second half and keep dividing
the space in half, you could do a binary search
if you had a lot of tests to find the
ones that are faliing. So that's one
thing I want to say and the other thing
is this is a useful tip, putting URLs in
here these URLs support the test so they
are... this is the evidence it is the link
the reference to where I got that test
data from. OK, and the other thing here is
this category annotation; it can go above or
below the word test, and let me show you what
it does, we build, it's just a way of
organizing your test once you've got
verification sorry annotations in like
that then this drop down at the top
right here lets you filter for things
with no annotations all things just with
the verification annotation and it
actually turns out that all of our
verification tests passed so that is
pretty cool
we've got full games in here; full  real
games with lots of weird things going on
and it all works. Well I'm pretty pleased
with that in fact I'm slightly smug
about my code and very pleased with it
so you can see what golden copies are
now they are just full examples of real
games. They're
not really very useful for driving your
development in the first place because
what tends to happen is they fail and
then it's not at all obvious why they
fail which is why we're building up the
solution one frame at a time we built
our tests up like one frame one
suggestion one week point at a time.
Anyway they're very useful for verification
testing like this and verification
testing is fantastic for protecting us
when we refactor. So if at this stage
if you've watched all this and your code is still
pretty big, and bloated, and ugly then what I want
you to do now is to use the fact that
all the tests are in place and go to
your code and try and get it as
concise as the code we've written and
really look through it and ask every
line is it necessary? You know, could I do
things more clearly? Do I use less than
or less than or equals? Particularly like
here: do we have rolls dot count -1 is
less than i? Less than or equal to 1? Or
or less than 2? I'm saying less than or equal to
one because it's one look ahead we need
so we need - and let's put it in the
comment ensure at least one look ahead
available.
OK and then comment - make sure that
your comment about why you're doing
things - why do we do this? To prevent the
11th frame. Do we need to; do we need to
comment here?
Normal open frame - not necessarily but I
think it's clear, I think it helps it
helps it helps clarify that this is a
normal frame in bowling so it's almost a
why but the what your code does I don't
think you should have to write it if
it's not clear this reads pretty clear
right you add together two rolls the
previous roll and next the current roll
and then here, what's going on here? Why
Do we break out? Wll this ensures that at least a look ahead is available. Fine. Here, this is a strike. Fine. This
why do we do this thing well because a
strike frame has just one bowl so we're
adjusting the iterator for that, that seems
to work really well.
Obvious what we're doing here. What are
we doing here?
well this is calculating the spare bonus
useful and there's not really anything
to be said about this line because it's
obvious by looking at these two lines
that they're kind of doing things right
there adding 10 plus the frame ahead and in the
case of a strike you get two frames
ahead and then you just return the
frames at the end, so that's my final
code I think I think it's bomb proof I
hope its bomb proof if you guys can
write a failing test against this code
- a valid failing test of course it's
very easy to write a failing tests you
write a test that doesn't make any sense -
but if you can write a test that is
valid and to show that my code here is not
scoring bowling properly I would love to
hear about it and I'd love to hear about it
as soon as possible so that I can fix it.
I'd really be quite sad if you find
one, because I'm very proud of this
piece of code for its simplicity and I
hope you realize after having gone
through the exercise of trying to get to
this point that it is quite hard to get
very condensed code out of this; even the
white space matters, it even makes a
difference if you do that or that; right
I like to drink things in logical groups
we come into the loop
hang on we'd better put in another comment in here,
we'd better say step... something like... I
think if I've got a longer comment I'll put
the comment above, so I'll say something
like frame index... was it a frame index or just a
bowl index or just an index? Let's just say an
index i points to second bowl of frame.
OK so that's another clarification. So
I converged on a strategy where we stepped
through the frames second bowl at a time,
that took a lot of time and effort and a
lot of refactoring so the strategy is
everything once this loop strategy is
correct the rest of it becomes a lot
easier. This I think could be improved, if
you can find a way to improve that I
don't like that line, the fact we have to
break out there but fundamentally i can't
see any other way at the moment of of
knowing that we are in the last frame
unless we look at the frame count so if
you can think of a neater way, great and
tell us, share in the discussions
and here we go into calculating a normal
open frame which seems to be obviously
correct then the next thing we must do
when we're going through with real-time scoring
is check we have enough look ahead and
abandon if we don't and that's what
gives us the scores at just the right
time and then we deal with strikes and
spares I think I don't need that strike
comment there because we talked about
strikes here I think I'm going to just
put strike and open in bold but as we
deal with open strike spare... spare bonus
fine. Great I can't refactor that code
anymore, I've got to the point where it's
as clean as it can be from my mind all
the comments lineup so let's talk about
beautifying your code. There it is, I
don't like nots, I don't like negatives, so
let's just take the not out of that and
any variables you want to change? I used
to use current list here instead of
frames but as Brice pointed out frames
or framelist is better, so once you've
converged on this code that you think is
as good as you can get it, let's do this
as a final challenge:
One, make your code as pretty as possible.
Two, the shorter it is, the easier it's going to be to
reason about. Number three, write comments
about why you do things. Number four, let the
code speak for itself
re: the what; it should be obvious what
it's doing and finally we're gonna make it
pretty using instacode dot es. So
go to that website; when you get there
paste in your method, your score frames
method, don't worry if it looks ugly
when you paste it. Tell it that is
dealing with c sharp in this box over
here, choose a theme I quite like fruity
and proceed. It's gonna do some magic... there it goes
now you've got pretty pretty pretty
pretty pretty looking code so scrolling
carefully, if you scroll inside the box it's
going to zoom, if you scroll outside of the box
it's going to pan the page. You can tilt
your code a little bit if you want, you
can choose whether you're rotating or
translating with buttons at the bottom
here so I could translate it here and then I
could go back to rotate... and what I want you
guys to do is make the prettiest
possible solution to this code you can.
Make a pretty thing here, looks like a
Polaroid image doesn't it?
Beauty in code question mark like that,
and then what I want you to do is to
share that in the course discussion so
once you've got it and you've got to the
zoom level you want, the rotation you
want, then you just come down you can
choose some other options here that you
can play with you publish... instant
hipsterization.
Here it is, and there's your code and you can
take that image, just save the image and once
you've got the image go to the course
discussions and just upload it into the
discussion saying here's my solution but
please do it like this. Please
over in the discussions, I'll just go over
to a discussions thread myself, start the
discussion with the word spoiler in
square brackets and capitals like
spoiler alert me to show you, because
you're going to be posting a potential
solution to a challenge that other
students are going to want, so do it
against this very lecture, so you'd be in
this very lecture itself, so let's go find
this lecture I think it's here already,
golden copy testing there you go. You know
how to paste to the discussions, by the
way if you've never posted to the
discussions now's the time do this
spoiler alert or something, or just spoiler,
my beautiful code and then say what you
wanna say and insert the instacode
image that we just created. I hope this is
the right one... always a bit dangerous going
into my downloads and uploading a random
image not quite knowing if it's the
right thing but it is there you go and
share that with the rest of the code
students ok and that's the final point
of this part of the section you have now
created great code for bowling scoring
and then we need to finish move on to
how to display that score, and there's a little bit
of trickery that needs to be done there
but it's not the responsibility of the
score master to do that, it's going to be
a score display class, and we've got a
few other little bits to tidy up in this
game but anyway, congratulations getting
this far, this is a huge feather in your...
cap? Something like that I don't know.
Anyway it's good news if you've got this
far,
see you soon.