Welcome back so I don't know about you
but I want to start seeing my scores in
this video we gonna rearrange your UI to
make space for the scores; create your
score board and then wire up your
score board. So I'm just gonna talk you
through my ideas here I've got a very
basic UI I think I don't need the right
panel so I'm going to ditch the right
panel and what I want to do is also
get the arrows in my case on to the left
panel. Now you can arrange your UI
however you like, you can even go be bold
and make it portrait if you want, which
may be even better for bowling but I'm
just gonna keep it simple and keep
the learning flowing so I have these
arrows I want him in the left panel so
I need to child into the left panel and then
it's just a question of getting in there
and snapping to the bottom like so I
might make them a little bit higher so
what've I got? 40 pixels high let's say and I
just need to check the scaling and
stretching and it's sticking to the
bottom and stretching. Cool, looks good
let's just check the game view and make
sure that once we release the mouse that
this guy scales sensibly. Yeah looks OK, so there we
go, we can still nudge in the same way if we
were to play the game. Still nudge in
exactly the same way it's just that we
made some room along the bottom of the
screen now for the scores so that's where
I'm going to pop them, so let's make ourselves
under the UI canvas or make yourself a
score panel, I'm going to challenge in a little
bit to actually fill it out with all of the
details but everyone is going to need at
least a score panel. So let's call it
scores. fantastic so there's the
scores panel, of course it's far too
big, it's across the entire top of the
UI so let's make it 40 pixels high
maybe, same as the other guy and then
snapped to the bottom and stretching
So again over in game view just rearrange
your game window to make sure that that
behaves. It does, Coolio. OK so now it's a
question of populating this so I'm going to
draw up one unit to help you out of frame
scores and bowls and then I'm going to
challenge you to populate it with the rest
so let's have a little bit of a think, a bit of
planning we've got 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6 roughly six
Unity game units along the bottom here
let's just see how that translates to
pixelsSo if I pop a single text box in
here and have a look. So if the left if
the left hand side of this, well let's look
at the center of the text box actually
here it said minus 300 pixels, here it's
at plus 300 pixels, I'm seeing that you
see the 300 there in between just to the
left of the thing I'm dragging so we're 300
pixels right 300 pixels left of that
center point so it's 600 pixels wide,
we've got 21 scores why don't we make it
twenty by twenty pixels? Let's try that
and I'm gonna go through font size
of 14 but i wanna make my text a lot
blacker than that, there you go. So let's
test it let's put a single character in
say I'm going to stick with six just for
fun and I think I want these characters
like that
centralized both vertically and
horizontally. Cool, so what I'm thinking
now is having a bunch of little kind of
duplets or triplets even where we
have bowl a, bowl b, just name these things up
as we go to there's bowl b, let me just zoom
in get into a line perfectly so bowl a, bowl
b, and what we're gonna do in a moment is
just duplicate all these guys but
but I'll challenge you in a moment to do
all this yourself, the point is create this
unit for yourself now and then obviously you're
going to do all the replication of the other units in a moment, so you're welcome to follow along with
this. Now this last guy, to make it look
good is a little bit challenging it's
gonna need up to three digits so the
question is how do you lay this out? Well
I'm just gonna pull its right hand side
in a little bit until these align, and
one way of checking their line is to use
a character like a one and just put
maybe 1, 1, 1 and they are pretty much aligned
or perfectly aligned? I would say
perfectly aligned. That's good, so the
triplet I've got looks something like
that, two boxes called Bowl a, bowl b I'm
struggling to name this a guy! Bowl a, bowl b
and score. OK so we have a triplet like that
now so to get it across remember your snap
settings I'm gonna set myself an x
snap of 50, why 50? Well look, if we select all these
three guys and then hold down command or
control on a PC and drag using the
transform tool what what happens at fifty... 50
100 150 200 and its just because these
Unity grid squares tie in
every, well they're obviously every 100
pixels so we're looking at how it works
so that's it you've got everything you
need now to duplicate this right across
and also modify the final frame so that
you have three bowls in there. So that's
your challenge for now it's just to finish
off the creation of this score board so
make space for up to 21 bowls that take single
characters, also ensure you have ten
frame score boxes and remember that
frame scores need to take up to three
digits. Go ahead, pause the video and get
your score board somewhere on your
screen and laid out now. Could be
the top, the bottom, down the side, however you like.
Welcome back so to keep this sane I'm
going to organize all of these score
blocks these triplets into frames so one
way to do that is to create yourself a
UI panel and then from that panel child it
to the scores, the panel is frame 0
1, zero because we know we're gonna have
nine... ten or more so therefore we need a
leading 0 for them to sort properly then
it doesn't need an image on it and it
doesn't need a canvas renderer on it
either it's basically the same as creating
an empty GameObject if we look at an empty game
object it's just a transform. If we look
at this guy it's just an empty Rect
transform so its screen space rather than
world space so frame 01 here now if we child
all these guys to... well actually before
you child them to frame 01 let's get
frame 01 positioned properly
where is it right now? What's its size?
Look at the size of it, it's massive it's crazy.
So that's because this position here is
relative to its parent, now its parent is
the score panel down there. So
obviously as a start we wanted 00 as a
starting point and then we
need to decide just how big it's gonna
be well it needs to be big enough to
just contain the scores, so
something like that. In fact I might even snap
it so it exactly contains the score
elements now this is not critical
really at all because all that matters
is that this whole thing this whole
frame here once you've subbed these three
text elements to it, that's what you need
to do you make your frame which is just
a rect transform you sub in your bowl
a bowl b and your score like that that
once you've got this frame it's just
important that you can move it around
and it's in a vaguely sensible position so
let's get another frame by clicking on
frame and duplicating look how helpful that is,
it's called it frame 02 and it's put
it below, and if I move this frame 02 whilst
holding down the command or control key,
with my snap setting set and make sure
your snap settings are set, and edit snap
settings and then you want a fifty in my
case I want 50 for the x value, and that will
apply to 50 pixels here in UI mode and
then what I want to do is I want to move
this guy but I want to move it by
snapping by 50 pixels, maybe easier to do
that using the transform tool and there
is. Now once I've got two next to each other
I just want to zoom out, say are they spaced
ok? Do they look ok? They look ok so let's
duplicate both of those to make four
and this is where we really get to see
our spacing so holding down Ctrl now is
the spacing reasonable? Well I don't know, let's look at
the game view, it's pretty good, we
can see what's going on. Good enough for
government work as they say. So, we have
four frames and now we really get some
leverage, because we just duplicate the
four frames hold down CTRL, move them
across, so we even can see what frame number we're
up to, it's really cool the way it renames
objects like this, hold down control and you've
now got ten frames. Let's go focus
on the final frame, it just needs a tweak
doesn't it so the frame itself is not
it's just not big enough so remember you need to be
in UI mode for this in order to make the
change to the to the panel, there it is, and that's
fine make a little bit bigger and then
these guys inside need to be moved
across a little bit and then we need
another score so let's put another score
in or another bowl should we say, then move them all a little bit round
and check they're in the frame... looks ok to
me. Move this guy frame score across and
how's that? That looks pretty good to me so
that's fine, now I just want to get a bit
of naming going on here, bowl B1 is a
bit odd that's the downside of it appending
numbers on the end so we want bowl c. So
look at the sanity of this we've got
scores which is just a panel of scores
there that we can collapse or expand in our hierarchy
and then we've got each frame and then the bowls
in each frame ; bowl a bowl b, like so bowl
a, bowl b, score, and that pattern just
repeats and in frame 10 - double click to
focus, or frame
bowl a, bowl b, bowl c, score. Awesome! So well then if
you got that far you have a set of
scores basically, which is which is great
Now you wanna move them en masse of
course you can select the whole lot and
just shift along a little bit, pretty easy
right?
so wherever you like that looks ok
check it in game view always, just make sure
it renders how you expect and I think
it's going to work
cool so that's the first challenge the
next challenge of course is we need this
score display script. At the moment we
don't have a script that's gonna be
responsible for displaying the score. Let's
just briefly revisit our architectural
diagram. So we've got the pin counter
sending the pinfall to the game master
that stores the game state as a list of
pins; sends that list of pin falls over to
the action master that sends an action back,
which controls the pin setter and resets the
ball. and sends it to score master which send
scores back now we haven't really defined
what scores is; it's two things it's a list
of frames, frame scores, which is fine and
the other thing is what do we do about
the bowls? Well we haven't quite decided
yet what we're gonna get out of here, or
what we gonna send at least to the score
display in terms of the bowls themselves.
It could be single characters, it could
be one long string, it could be a
list
although when you get a strike then there's
nothing, how's score display going to know to
skip a box? so this is an API we'll need to
think about next video but what we need
to do for now anyway is get score
display set up and ready to go and
connected to the relevant UI elements that we
just created so why don't you go ahead and do that
now write yourself a score display class
once you've written the score display
class
I want you to create an array of text in
it, wire all the scoreboard boxes to this
display manually in the inspector, drag them
across and just do the same for the frame
scores so that you have a score display
class that can actually write to all of
those texts elements that we just created. Go ahead, pause the video and do all that now please
whittle sticks welcome back, I'm not sure what whittle sticks are but I'm sure they're cool.
OK so I'm gonna make a class called cord, well,
score display even and then at the top
of that class I need a couple of things
they're just gonna be arrays both of them
because we have a finite and
predetermined number of text elements, so
when you've got a predetermined list of things then an array
seems like the sensible construct so I'm
gonna have a public text array, now text
doesn't exist of course you know about
this now, you need to be using Unity
engine . UI, so now the text type
will exist and I can validly create a
text array, public text text. OK now I
haven't given it a variable name so
let's call it rolls, or rolltexts and
let's have another one declare it on the
same line, frame texts and that just
makes it clear that they're texts ok and
they're public arrays of those things so
over in unity now if we decide to put our
score display script on something so
what would it make sense to put the
score display script on I think on the
scores object right? Because that's the
object that's responsible. Look what
we've got, we've got a roll texts and a
frame texts array. So the roll texts is
gonna be of size 21 and it's going to
be great fun to fill that in, let's just
go ahead and get it done, let's
just suck it up. A couple of ways you
could do that of course you can just
drag them straight from here or you
could click this button and then try and
find it in your assets list, not going
to be so easy to do though because we get
the repetition of the name and we don't
get the hierarchy so I recommend just
carefully dragging in bowl a, bowl b
frame two, bowl a... this is fun right? Now you
could say is there a better way to do
this? Of course there is, there's lots of ways you can
do everything in unity and you could use
the names programmatically but in terms
of you know it's one off right? There's 21 to
do, by the time you've moaned about it and
thought of a more automated way to do it you
could have just done it, in fact you get
your designer or your mom to do this bit.
I know that the developers out there
hate doing this type of repetitive task
and so do I but why create a framework
in this case for something more
complicated to do this? You say well in the future
I might have a game with 30 bowls, or three thousand well
deal with it then because by doing this
once or twice to get a feel for how long
things actually do take manually and you
can make a sensible judgment as to
whether it's worth automating now I
don't even know if I'm doing this right
bear in mind that arrays are index offset
+ 1 so the bowl numbers are gonna be
slightly wrong because they start counting at 0 but
I have done it right and there's the
nervousness can end. It looks like a, b and
then c are gonna slot in and I have
space for all 21 bowls; whether we use them
or not, well it depends how the game pans out
doesn't it? a, b, a, b, a, b, a, b... wicked okay and then we've also got
frame scores, so the hierarchies all opened wide
up I need to firstly allocate an
array of appropriate size, what is the
size? How many frame score texts are
there? 10 right, okay and then it's
literally just a question for each frame
of just going in, getting these guys, the
scores and you can common-sense check it
as you go making sure that it says
score score score score and yes I
know you're gonna hate me for doing this
manually... other ways of doing it, you
could use GameObject dot find objects of
type or tag and you could tag all these
guys and then you could name them and
write a script that goes through and looks
at the name but then if somebody messes up
the name in the hierarchy or your designer
goes in and does something then it all breaks... there's probably a thousand ways, do put in the discussions if you've
got a neat way of doing it but I think
for 20 odd items you're better off
just hard wiring it like this
whittle sticks. we're done. We now have
programmatic access to everything so
better check it I guess we better just
go to score display and just on start
just say roll texts
one let's say, zero, the first one
arrays start at 0, dot text, remember equals and
then let's just make it an x for strike
that's fine and why don't we set a
frame score frame texts, put the first
frame score 2, 0 remember though that it is a string
here because it's a text element. Run the
game
make sure that the first elements update
from the script boom X 0 and then everything
else is as we left it.
Good job guys, that's all fantastic the
only final thing you may want to do here
of course is all of your text elements
currently have funny spurious stuffs in
them like you've got scores and all the
rest of it test scores et cetera so you
probably want to empty all of these
elements here which of course we could
have done at the beginning but we needed
to see what was going on right and you
could always have your code just
initialize these that's another way, you
could just put nothing into all of these
boxes. I for the sake of it am just going
to go here and remove the text or put a
space in, and that has the effect of
clearing down the scoreboard, but
when we play the game the program can
now write to it. Cool, we have somewhere
to write our bowls and out frame scores to, I look
forward to seeing you for the
programming aspect of this in the next lecture.