So to prepare ourselves to write the
score display code we need to think a
little more carefully about static classes;
what it means to define a whole
class as static; the perils and
disadvantages and advantages of statics;
Why we're using statics here;
refactoring a class to be static and
then learning to accept other people's
code I'll talk to you about that in a moment. So
our target architecture. you've seen this
diagram quite often it's been changing
slowly but i wanna make another
distinction. Score master is a base class
but it is also potentially a static
class in fact go to score master now
and take a look at it and you'll find
that you can write the words static go
ahead and do that after public static
class. and if you do that you'll find it
doesn't complain and it builds just fine
because there are no member variables; if
you try to define member variables up
here - not gonna have it. it's going to
complain - and each of the methods are
static so that's what a static class
means. it just means that all the methods
are static and there are no member variables
so score master is already like that but
action master isn't yet. Action master's
not a static class and we can't be
completely confident that when we call
action master with a load of pin falls
that it isn't remembering something.
Let's go look at action master. you'll
see. There's action master. try and make that
static. Look what happens. It firstly
complains that we have a member variables.
or instance members. and secondly it
complains that this method here is not
static. So that's what it means to be a
static class. We've also got another method
I think here. that's not static. So I wanna
make action master static so that we can
be absolutely sure that it is stateless
and then we will have a better frame for
understanding how we're going to be
dealing with score display and how we're going to
be testing that as a monobehavior. So
reading around a little bit more about
statics. there's a nice long blog post there by
Tom Butler. It's from the PHP perspective
but it has some very useful points in it
and the summary is as follows: static
variables always introduce global state
which is bad. and static methods always
break encapsulation which is also bad
Statics should be avoided at all costs ok
so let's justify why we're using statics.
Firstly static variables always
introduce global state. I completely
agree. it is not helpful for us to be
introducing static variables
and global state so the whole point of
making sure that the list of pins was in
game manager was that there was no state
in school master or action master and
currently there could be state in action
master; it turns out the way that it runs
that state's cleared every time but we we
want to make that static. So absolutely. we
want to move away from that static...
globals are bad because we don't know
who's addressing them that's the problem
with globals. and then the second thing
that Tom Butler says here is that static
methods always break encapsulation which
means that things are all in one place;
well the reason we are breaking
encapsulation is cuz... it's to do with
the history here. we started off with
action master and we built a load of tests
around it and we got it working which
was a relief by breaking the the
concepts of the whole bowling system
down. We then created a score master with
a separate set of tests and it does have
a different looking behavior; action
master goes through in every single bowl
at a time score master jumps through
in twos adding up the frame so they do
behave differently; now they could arguably
be in the same class. and arguably they
could even be part of game manager but
they're not because of the way that we've
got here and i actually quite like the
fact we have short concise classes so
all that remains here to be sure that
we're using static sensibly is to make
sure that action master is a completely
static class. in that case we are both
treating score master and action master
as just pure functions so what I want to
do here is I want you to integrate the
action master I'm providing you in the
start pack from the start pack. it's called
action master two you're gonna need to save
your current action master to maybe
action master three or something like
that and go into action master two and
rename both the file and the class name; if you
want to you're welcome to refactor
action master two until it's beautiful if
you feel that you don't have ownership
over it I'm asking you to copy and paste
code here for the first time in the
course I think and I'm doing it on
purpose because sometimes you need to
let go of the idea that you fully follow
all of the code and if your action
master's protected by tests I think it's
fair to say let's bring in somebody
else's code ie ours for now. and just
trust it and use the tests to keep
the certainty that you need in your
mind so ensure the test pass and then if
you want to refactor it paste the results
of your code in pastebin
and he less lines the better. if it's still
readable. Personally I would leave
refactoring action master until the very
end of the project if you refactor it
at all so another lesson here is: Is it
worth refactoring it? Well if it works
maybe not but maybe you're compelled
like I am to refactor it I haven't done
so yet so the lesson here is accepting
somebody else's code so I just want you to
bring in my code. convince yourself that
it passes to start with and then if you
really can't stop yourself go ahead and
refactor it. otherwise leave it as it is and we'll move on.
OK so doing that is relatively
simple. firstly back in the old action
master you need to take the word static
off otherwise you'll be having errors. OK
so you have a start pack and in the start
back you have scripts and one of those
is called action master two so the way
I'm going to do this I'm gonna find my
original action master. I'm going to go into
it. I'm going to rename it using
command or control r. action master old
or something like that. and then I'm
gonna go to the one in scripts. pop it
into... from start pact scripts into just
scripts and then rename that one to...
from action master 2 to simply action  master
and that should just slot into place now. so
if you then re-enable your action
master tests by un-commenting them all
and then go back to Unity hopefully when
we run firstly we're looking for no
errors. that's good we have no errors. and
secondly we're looking to see that the
action master tests alll pass. They do. so
let's look at this code that we've provided
what's different about it?
well it's a lot shorter for a start. it's
only 40 lines instead of sixty odd so
that's a good thing. and it is now static
and all the member variables are gone
and it's a static method and it's a
relatively simple refactor. the
bulk of this logic is exactly the same.
we have an off by one difference in
these in these indexes and a few other
things are slightly different but what I'd
like you to do is consider just
accepting this code as is and if you're
nervous about any of its behavior why
not go to action master test and write a
test to see if your hunch is correct or
not if you think it's not behaving but
why don't you try and let go of the
implementation details of action master
just this time.
because sometimes it's very helpful
for you to be able to farm out the production
of a method. especially when it's
protected by tests and say well if it
works it works alright? and if you can't
stand to do that then go ahead and
refactor it making sure the test pass I
would love to see a tidier version of
action master I believe that we can get
action master a lot shorter than this I
think we can get it in about 10 lines in
here somehow cause we've certainly done
that with our score master and I've got a
feeling that score display will come out
shorter than this as well. if you want to
reflect this and maybe even contribute
to the course by pasting the result in
the discussions go ahead and when I
refactor action master the end of the
section. if I do that. then I will include
your code or credit you. So that's it. that's
a brief discussion of statics I want to
go back to the top level briefly and
explain why that's important it's
important because we want these action
masters and score masters to be
stateless. we want to make sure we're not
dealing with more than one version of
them and we want to make sure they have
no member variables so that's how we
make sure they're stateless and it
frames the discussion about how we're going
to test score display; we're going to
make a static method inside score
display in order to make sure that we
can test it nicely. So there's a big risk we're
overusing statics here but as long as we
understand what we doing. this is a really good
exercise in getting to understand when
to use statics and when not to use
statics. so that's the purpose of it OK
so have a little think. have a recap on
this video
make sure you understand what's going on
and what I'm gonna be doing in the next
couple of videos is actually setting us
up for a situation like this where if
you look at the top right of the diagram
we have a static format rolls. and then
we'll be able to test the static format rolls.
it'll return a string and that can then the
score display can simply read that and
we have a testable mono behavior
effectively. we're not quite testing whether
it puts things in the boxes but that's
going to be obvious from playtesting
So that's what we'll be doing next. see you soon.
=======
Kind: captions
Language: en
So to prepare ourselves to write the
score display code we need to think a
little more carefully about static classes;
what it means to define a whole
class as static; the perils and
disadvantages and advantages of statics;
Why we're using statics here;
refactoring a class to be static and
then learning to accept other people's
code I'll talk to you about that in a moment. So
our target architecture, you've seen this
diagram quite often it's been changing
slowly but i wanna make another
distinction. Score master is a base class
but it is also potentially a static
class in fact go to score master now
and take a look at it and you'll find
that you can write the words static go
ahead and do that after public static
class, and if you do that you'll find it
doesn't complain and it builds just fine
because there are no member variables; if
you try to define member variables up
here - not gonna have it, it's going to
complain - and each of the methods are
static so that's what a static class
means, it just means that all the methods
are static and there are no member variables
so score master is already like that but
action master isn't yet. Action master's
not a static class and we can't be
completely confident that when we call
action master with a load of pin falls
that it isn't remembering something.
Let's go look at action master, you'll
see. There's action master, try and make that
static. Look what happens. It firstly
complains that we have a member variables,
or instance members, and secondly it
complains that this method here is not
static. So that's what it means to be a
static class. We've also got another method
I think here, that's not static. So I wanna
make action master static so that we can
be absolutely sure that it is stateless
and then we will have a better frame for
understanding how we're going to be
dealing with score display and how we're going to
be testing that as a monobehavior. So
reading around a little bit more about
statics, there's a nice long blog post there by
Tom Butler. It's from the PHP perspective
but it has some very useful points in it
and the summary is as follows: static
variables always introduce global state
which is bad, and static methods always
break encapsulation which is also bad
Statics should be avoided at all costs ok
so let's justify why we're using statics.
Firstly static variables always
introduce global state. I completely
agree, it is not helpful for us to be
introducing static variables
and global state so the whole point of
making sure that the list of pins was in
game manager was that there was no state
in school master or action master and
currently there could be state in action
master; it turns out the way that it runs
that state's cleared every time but we we
want to make that static. So absolutely, we
want to move away from that static...
globals are bad because we don't know
who's addressing them that's the problem
with globals, and then the second thing
that Tom Butler says here is that static
methods always break encapsulation which
means that things are all in one place;
well the reason we are breaking
encapsulation is cuz... it's to do with
the history here, we started off with
action master and we built a load of tests
around it and we got it working which
was a relief by breaking the the
concepts of the whole bowling system
down. We then created a score master with
a separate set of tests and it does have
a different looking behavior; action
master goes through in every single bowl
at a time score master jumps through
in twos adding up the frame so they do
behave differently; now they could arguably
be in the same class, and arguably they
could even be part of game manager but
they're not because of the way that we've
got here and i actually quite like the
fact we have short concise classes so
all that remains here to be sure that
we're using static sensibly is to make
sure that action master is a completely
static class, in that case we are both
treating score master and action master
as just pure functions so what I want to
do here is I want you to integrate the
action master I'm providing you in the
start pack from the start pack, it's called
action master two you're gonna need to save
your current action master to maybe
action master three or something like
that and go into action master two and
rename both the file and the class name; if you
want to you're welcome to refactor
action master two until it's beautiful if
you feel that you don't have ownership
over it I'm asking you to copy and paste
code here for the first time in the
course I think and I'm doing it on
purpose because sometimes you need to
let go of the idea that you fully follow
all of the code and if your action
master's protected by tests I think it's
fair to say let's bring in somebody
else's code ie ours for now, and just
trust it and use the tests to keep
the certainty that you need in your
mind so ensure the test pass and then if
you want to refactor it paste the results
of your code in pastebin
and he less lines the better, if it's still
readable. Personally I would leave
refactoring action master until the very
end of the project if you refactor it
at all so another lesson here is: Is it
worth refactoring it? Well if it works
maybe not but maybe you're compelled
like I am to refactor it I haven't done
so yet so the lesson here is accepting
somebody else's code so I just want you to
bring in my code, convince yourself that
it passes to start with and then if you
really can't stop yourself go ahead and
refactor it, otherwise leave it as it is and we'll move on.
OK so doing that is relatively
simple, firstly back in the old action
master you need to take the word static
off otherwise you'll be having errors. OK
so you have a start pack and in the start
back you have scripts and one of those
is called action master two so the way
I'm going to do this I'm gonna find my
original action master, I'm going to go into
it, I'm going to rename it using
command or control r, action master old
or something like that, and then I'm
gonna go to the one in scripts, pop it
into... from start pact scripts into just
scripts and then rename that one to...
from action master 2 to simply action  master
and that should just slot into place now, so
if you then re-enable your action
master tests by un-commenting them all
and then go back to Unity hopefully when
we run firstly we're looking for no
errors, that's good we have no errors, and
secondly we're looking to see that the
action master tests alll pass. They do, so
let's look at this code that we've provided
what's different about it?
well it's a lot shorter for a start, it's
only 40 lines instead of sixty odd so
that's a good thing, and it is now static
and all the member variables are gone
and it's a static method and it's a
relatively simple refactor, the
bulk of this logic is exactly the same,
we have an off by one difference in
these in these indexes and a few other
things are slightly different but what I'd
like you to do is consider just
accepting this code as is and if you're
nervous about any of its behavior why
not go to action master test and write a
test to see if your hunch is correct or
not if you think it's not behaving but
why don't you try and let go of the
implementation details of action master
just this time.
because sometimes it's very helpful
for you to be able to farm out the production
of a method, especially when it's
protected by tests and say well if it
works it works alright? and if you can't
stand to do that then go ahead and
refactor it making sure the test pass I
would love to see a tidier version of
action master I believe that we can get
action master a lot shorter than this I
think we can get it in about 10 lines in
here somehow cause we've certainly done
that with our score master and I've got a
feeling that score display will come out
shorter than this as well, if you want to
reflect this and maybe even contribute
to the course by pasting the result in
the discussions go ahead and when I
refactor action master the end of the
section, if I do that, then I will include
your code or credit you. So that's it, that's
a brief discussion of statics I want to
go back to the top level briefly and
explain why that's important it's
important because we want these action
masters and score masters to be
stateless, we want to make sure we're not
dealing with more than one version of
them and we want to make sure they have
no member variables so that's how we
make sure they're stateless and it
frames the discussion about how we're going
to test score display; we're going to
make a static method inside score
display in order to make sure that we
can test it nicely. So there's a big risk we're
overusing statics here but as long as we
understand what we doing, this is a really good
exercise in getting to understand when
to use statics and when not to use
statics, so that's the purpose of it OK
so have a little think, have a recap on
this video
make sure you understand what's going on
and what I'm gonna be doing in the next
couple of videos is actually setting us
up for a situation like this where if
you look at the top right of the diagram
we have a static format rolls, and then
we'll be able to test the static format rolls,
it'll return a string and that can then the
score display can simply read that and
we have a testable mono behavior
effectively, we're not quite testing whether
it puts things in the boxes but that's
going to be obvious from playtesting
So that's what we'll be doing next, see you soon.
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1