Hey! Super useful video this one we're gonna
be finding out how to unit test mono
behaviour we'll firstly see why mono behavior
classes are hard to test, then create a
testable static helper method and then
create our testing structure preparing
you for the challenge ahead.
Cool, cool, so let's just dive in. This is what
we're aiming for,
we are wanting to pass a list of
frames and a list of rolls to the score
display and we want that score display
to be testable now it being a mono
behavior it's not very testable, you'll
see why in a second, but as an overview
what we're going to do is create a
static helper method called format rolls
that takes in rolls as an integer
somewhere between 13 and 21 different
rolls, depending on how the game pans out, and gives
you by the end of the game always 21
characters in a string which score
display can then just very basically step
through and stick in the right boxes.
Alright so let's firstly see why it's
tricky to build a mono behaviour that's
testable. So if we make our action, and go
ahead and do this, not action master but
score display test class and I would
suggest that you copy the top of
another test class including its first
test as a leg up and just use that as
the template, ok, and I'm just going to
make sure that works actually apart from you
need to be careful to rename the actual class
score display test and let's just see
over here; may as well run all on recompile
or at least run selected; boom and there
we go
wrong class... score display test passing test.
OK, so we have that now imagine that you
just have your score display class here
and in there we have fill roll car. Now I know
that fill roll card's not working properly but let's
just say that we want to call into this
so how are we gonna do that?
Well regardless of how it works let's just
put in a your code here. I'm actually gonna
just call it fill rolls because it's a
little bit simpler a name - don't rename
methods like that always rename methods
by clicking on them and holding down
Ctrl command r and then using the
refactor tool, and then the name will change
in other classes like over here in game
and it'll be very easy to forget that call
so always use the refactor tool. We don't need the start
or the update methods, so imagine that we're
wanting to just do build fill rolls
through test driven development; well we
do want to build fill rolls through test driven development so here we are over in the test system and we want
to make a test so test 01 is simply bowl one now what are we... how are we gonna do this? We need to
call score display fill rolls but it's
not a static so we have to instantiate
score display, so you may be tempted to
go score display sd for example equals
a new score display and then put some
brackets and try and instantiate it like that
the test will be ok, it'll complain that
it's never used but we could go score
display dot fill rolls and we could
pass in some - I don't know - new list of integers
like that some empty list
ok and as long as we have a semicolon on
the end that all looks ok and checks out
now we go over to unity and we try and
run it, and we even get the failing test
or in this case we get a passing test
because we haven't made an assertation
but regardless we get the following: you
were trying to create a mono behavior
using the new keyword this is not
allowed, and if you go into the error you can read more
mono behaviors can only be added using add
component alternatively your script can
inherit from a scriptable object or no
base class at all. Right so we've done
script inheriting from no base class at
all before but you'd be quite tempted
here to go down the route of trying to add
components and stuff, you might try and create a
GameObject instead of a score display
here and then you might try and build it up
like you would in the inspector and then add a
score display component to it and you'll
find your hierarchy starts filling up
with objects; no no no don't want to do it, you don't
want to try and directly test mono
behaviors like this, that's the whole
point of this lecture is to tell
you that that is a bit of a no-no
So that is not what we want to do. So
what we're gonna do is write an auxiliary method called
format rolls and that is gonna take in
the list of rolls and it is going to
return you a string and then each
character of the string is going to be a
one-to-one mapping with the boxes that
were gonna be entering the score into
these 21 boxes in our UI down here,
OK? So it's going to be a one-to-one
mapping between each of these bowl boxes
and the string that comes back from the
static format roles so that's how we're
gonna do things and then it's going to
be a hell of a lot easier to reason about
and to test so we need to make this
static string format roll, so go ahead
and do that now static, string is the
return type; format rolls
taking in this list of integers rolls
like this
okay and then how's format rolls going
to work? Well, that is the however many thousand
dollar question, actually your code that
you're gonna be writing in the test is
gonna go here so it's clearly going to
start with an empty string so we're gonna
have string output or something like
that, roll string output will do equals
some empty string and then we're
going to return the output at some point
right, but you are going to have to write that code in
the next video; but for now we need to
know had to call format rolls, so if
you're confident go ahead and make
format rolls now, it's only three lines, if
you're not then I'm going to do one more
thing for you to give you a very big leg
up which is I'm gonna write public void
fill frames now, which is going to take
in a list of integers called frames and
that's the method that's simply going to
go into the UI and pop into all of these frame
score boxes here; all of these guys down
there, the frame score so that's going to
be a pretty simple for loop; for int i equals 0 so in a for loop you define the iterator first
so it's integer i and it starts at zero
then a semicolon and then you go I is less
than what well its gonna be in this case
frames . count; however many
frames we can count less than, not less
than or equal to, and what you do each time you
iterate the i plus one and then what we do?
Well we go to frame texts. What are
frame texts? These are these guys down
here these frame texts, these ten things
So frame texts, which
we have available here we we pulled it in
publicly dot text remember we need to go
to the text element of that but it's not
gonna let us go to text until we say
which member, which element it's the i-th
element. Now we can go to it's dot text and
it's going to equal frames at the i-th
element, but frames at the i-th elements
an integer so we need to make it a
string. OK, where would we call fill
frames we'd call it from game manager
it will fill the rolls and it will also
go score display dot fill frames and
it'll pass in what? Well, its gonna pass
in the cumulative frame score isn't it? If you
remember look at a bowling card, bowling
scoring and just look at any card and you'll
see that the scores here on the frames
are cumulative, they're adding up. So we've got a
method for that that makes life very
easy, we have a static method called
score master dot score cumulative and then
all we need to pass into that is bowls. Now
I'm getting a bit fed up of bowls
and rolls being different so I'm gonna go
to the top of this method and
rename bowls to rolls, so we fill the
rolls which are these guys here the X, the 9,
the dash and then we fill the frames; and
in the score display there's the fill
frames film rolls isn't working yet so
let's get the fill rolls out line code
working and that's your challenge; and this
will make you stop and think about the
architecture I've just created so public void fill
rolls list of int, calls format roles
and iterates the return string should be
just three lines of code very similar to
what we've just written for fill frames. Have
a go, write that simple bit of code now
to iterate through the string and
put it in the right boxes and also you on
the other side.
Cool, welcome back, so I'm actually it's so similar to
this code that I'm nearly gonna cut
and paste it but we need to first start off
with a new output,so it's a string output
equals go get it from format rolls with
rolls, ok so go get the answer from
format rolls or we can just in line this
we might do that in a second so what's
the loop?
It's a very similar thing, for int i
equals zero, gonna be consistent with
my spacing, semicolon, i is less than what
well its gonna be the output dot count
the format rolls dot count, right? So output
. length, so cos we're going to be using
this twice who won't re-inline it, and
then we i plus plus don't we. OK so that's that
and then for each of these times we
access the roll text, remember what the
roll texts are they're these guys here on the
right, all these elements and then at element i
remember dot text equals what?
Well it equals the output or I don't like
output in two places like this in case we
get a scpe clash so I'm gonna rename it just
here to score string and then score
string at element i and then element i as a
character so it's toString. OK, so we've
pulled off the i-th character from the
score string that's come out, we've converted it
into a string and popped it straight in
the box. So this should work now apart
from the fact that obviously we won't
get any rolls, but we will get frames if
it's coded right, so if you've done it
right now and you've passed this
challenge then your frame scores will
update when we bowl but your roll
score card won't get because that's gonna
be the subject of the next video it's a
fairly major bit of TDD to make that
work unfortunately, because we have to translate
13 to 21 bowls into precisely 21 bowls.
So we bowl twice, we scored eight we
should get a frame score of 8, we do so it
looks like the frame's working and the
subject to the next video we'll get the
individual scores working so as a recap
for you cause there's quite a lot to think about
in this video we've understood why mono behavior
classes are hard to test the editor
tells you that you can't create them, you
can construct them with a new; if we do
start constructing objects then it's going to
start filling up your hierarchy with
editor time created rubbish, just don't
do it. We saw how to create a
testable static helper method that
string based method and then we've made
our testing structure... although have we,
let's have a look
score display test not quite yet, so let
me just get you prepared for the next
video's challenge by helping you with the
score display test. We're gonna do the same
thing as we did before, we're gonna say
there's an integer array of rolls and maybe
it just contains one in this case, and
then we're going to look at the string
which is the rolls string, and say well
that that must equal one in this case and
then we're going to go the assert are
equal rolls string comma what? Well, comma score display
dot format rolls, now why can't I see score
display dot format rolls? Because it's
not public
OK, score display dot format rolls passing in what? Rolls . to list, cos remember it needs a list; and that's a
great linq method that to list is coming
off linq here which is pretty handy
three closing braces and that is the
testing structure you're gonna need for all your
tests, you define your list of rolls just
like we did before in our score master
test, then you're gonna make your roll
string should be like 1,2
X, space, you know, 1, / whatever one character
per box that we're gonna fill it into and then
you'll always do this same line; so that's
the structure of your test, let's make sure that that
test fails which is where we want to
start, and many to run selected there you
go and that's a failing tests you get an
empty string and it's not surprising
because the helper method the format rolls does nothing. Cool, so in the next video I'm going to be
challenging you to do that, so if you want a break go
take a break and in the next
video it's going to be write format
rolls using test driven development
I'll see you soon.