Welcome back so in this video we're gonna
be designing our own tests and doing
test driven development in unity... again!
So  the context for this is we
have this bowling game here and we can
roll the ball and it counts the pins and
does the physics and stuff and what we
want it to do is fill out our scores as
we go and what we've done is we've made
ourselves a score display script and
because it's a mono behavior talking to
our UI text we've created an
auxiliary method called format roles
which basically takes in a list of rolls
somewhere between 13 and 21 rolls
depending on how the game pans out and
makes a string of ultimately 21 rolls
that fills out the boxes and we need to
put our code in there so we set up some
tests we've got the Unity test tools
infrastructure in we've got the right
name spaces in here we've told you it's a test
fixture we've made our first failing
test which is that if we roll a one.
and we pass it into format rolls as a string
we should just get a string of one back
and of course we get a failing test
which is exactly the right place to
start with
test driven development so I want you to
write format rolls. There's the signature.
we've already got it. write your own tests
as you go. you gotta design your own
tests now as you go. stick to the red-green
refactor loop.
remember to only test one thing at a time aim for
twenty lines or less of beautiful code
enjoy the process. and when you've finished
share in the discussions. but with a
spoiler in square brackets like that at the start
so we don't mess up the experience for
anybody else. So go ahead and enjoy doing
this and you should be able to make beautiful
code possibly even prettier than our
scoremaster code so pause the video. spend plenty
of time on this and really use it as
your final test driven development
exercise of this course.
Welcome back so let's get on with it. I
like when I'm doing test driven
development to have both my test script
and my actual script open just those
scripts so we'll have score display
test in the left
calling in to score display and I'd like
to be able to see the results of my test ok
fantastic so we want to make this test
pass. how are we gonna do it? Well we could
simply return 1. Why not do that in the first place?
Return one... we've got some unreachable
code but that's okay. we just want to make
this test pass and what we get? We get a
failure
let's see if we can make it pass there you go.
return one works fine ok so now it's... we've
gone red. we've gone green. it's time to refactor.
Clearly returning one sucks because
that's never going to work for future
cases. How can we be more general? Well we can
write the for loop that we're clearly gonna
need. we obviously have to iterate
through rolls so for i. int i equals zero.
going up to i is less than rolls dot
count. we're gonna iterate i and we're simply going to
say that output + equals rolls i dot to
string.
Alright so we're just gonna add to the
string whatever happens in this case not
enough code to pass all the tests of
course. but for this test that should do
it and we're only gonna have a single element
so it should just do exactly the same thing
but much much more general; let's test
the code. run selected. Wait 'til the
whirligig finishes. run the selected tests
and bowl... passes fantastic so on to the
second test what's a good second test
now well let's have a look what do we wanna
test next? Well I want to test that a
strike works - I wanna make it deal with
strikes so public void test 02 X
just as in a strike. nice and simple so
let's get the code laid out you can just copy and paste the text; in fact you may as well copy paste the entire
test if you bowl a 10 you want to get
an X so. red green refactor.
This should fail...
and it's failing there. ok. so we're getting
a 10 and that's not surprising because
our code says just return the string so
how we gonna deal with the special case
of a strike well we could just say if
rolls i equals 10 then we're going to
output + equals now what should it be? X or X and
a space actually our test is wrong it
should be X and a space. yeah. remember the
space because we skip a space. at least
until the last frame so X and space and else we output... what are we going to output? Just a number so
we're catching a special case here
of strike strike basically for now
that's it. we're just catching the strike. OK.
let's go ahead and run the tests; wait
for the whirligig to finish.
runs selected and the first one
OK we have array out of range indices.
and that's because I put a 1 instead
of an i in here. let's try again... run the
selected tests fantastic. so we get an
X. Passing. OK. great. so  let's move on to
another test. I'm going to duplicate the test
because it's by far the quickest way of getting the next test in; I'm going to iterate the test number
to test three. I like them to go in the
order that I wrote them. and I would like
to think that if I bowled a 1 then a 9 that I
get a strike. that's going to force me to
write new code. you wanna keep writing
stuff that forces you to write new
code I'm just going to change the name
of these. bowl X bowl 1. 9. OK. bowl 1. bowl 9 and what I
should be getting here now is a one dash
like that; let's save and run the test
run failed test is 1... rerun failed by the
way is one way of running tests that
failed before and that have not yet been
run so
it's expecting one slash. it gets 1. 9
not surprising our code doesn't know
anything about slashes; so how are we going
to deal with slashes. when are we gonna deal
with slashes? Well we need to decide if
there's a spare is it more... do we
decide that before or after we decide
about strikes? Well I'm gonna go for
before so if rolls I minus one isn't it
plus rolls i... now that's fine if
that equals 10 then you go ahead and
output your spare thing. so it's that. and I'll
just comment over here just line them all up
spare. that's kind of fine and then we can do an else if here. but my concern is that we won't have
enough look ahead in the very beginning
if we try running this I think the test
is gonna fail because we can't do rolls
i minus one when i equals zero; so let's
see what happens I think we're gonna get
an argument array failure - yeah here we go.
argument out of range exception. So what
I need to do is protect this spare check; in fact I want
my comment up here I want to protect
this spare check with a modulus operator. I
can say if the roll mod 2 equals 0.
and that - then we're on a spare so roll
mod 2 equals zero means that we
have an even. or do I mean roll or do I
mean i? Well that's a good question I
want to use the word roll. I want to talk
about the roll starting at roll one
then roll two; then roll three then roll four and
every time I get to an even roll like
this like roll two. roll four then I'm in
the second bowl of the frame and then I
want to go on and say okay. is it a spare?
So I need something that is a roll but I
want that to be the roll string or the
output dot
length plus one.
OK so my roll number is however much
output I've already created +1 so in the
beginning it'll start at 0. no string. So our
roll number one. it's a roll number
starting from zero. OK? Roll number
counting from 0 or box number if you
like; call it the box number. it's the score box
starting 1 to 21; the actual box you write it in.
OK so if that mod 2 if the roll - let's call
roll box actually - if box mod 2 is zero
then we must be on bowl roll number two
or roll number four or number six... an even
roll then we've got a spare. so let's try
that. Passed. fantastic ok so let's move
on and keep the plan going. let's take
another test... let's force in new
development here. what new development
could we force? How about if we did a 1 then a 9. then a 1
then we should get a 1. 9. 1... we should get a
1 / 1. that should drop out of the
existing test. more of a verification
test here. let's try... out of the existing code
should I say. Yep that works so that's not
actually driving any new developments so
what could we do that would definitely
drive some new development here? Well if we
look at our score display code and see
what it can currently handle. it can
handle a spare. how about a spare in the last
frame? That's gotta break it hasn't it? A spare
in frame 10? Let's see if we can get a
spare in frame 10 and see if that breaks
it. So I'll remove this 1. 9. 1 test because it
didn't drive any new development. and I'm
gonna go to spare in last frame and then
I'm going to have to put in a load of
one's here
carefully....
I think that's four. so that's four frames and if I
put in another comma I can get another
four frames so I'm on frame 8. frame 9 and then we
could go spare in the last frame
something like that so as long as my commas are in
the right place I've got 1. 2. 3. 4. 5. 6. 7. 8. 9 frames and
then a spare here and then a three. So
what should that be giving me in terms
of my rolls. it should be giving me [a lot of ones!]
spare three. Now is this
spare in the right... in the last frame gonna
work? I don't know let's find out.
Spare in the last frame like that does
work which is fantastic
OK. so maybe the pattern for spares is
always the same. I think that this is
general that even in the last frame
that's the case for a spare. How about if we had
a strike in the last frame. a strike in
frame 10? Let's change our tests and try
and break it with a strike in frame 10.
Strike in last frame so how about if I
go X and then well we can't do nine after... we
could do nine after. an X; X. 9. 3. So 10. 9. 3
that's fine then what we would expect to see is
an X but with no space. and then a nine
and you can't have a 9 then a 3 so it's gonna
have to be a nine and... say a one but
that's testing another concept so let's just
go 10. 1. 1. keep it simple X then we should
get X. 1. 1 without the space. Let's see
what happens. I'm pretty sure that our
code is going to put a space because
remember here we're putting X space. it
doesn't know about putting X without
a space so this is bound to fail which
will drive new development. Yep and is
doing exactly what we thought. it's giving
us one extra character. 22 instead of 21
and is putting a space. So now we need to
intercept the special case which is
where we are in the last frame
and we have a strike so that is here... else it... roll.
or box. we're calling it. if box number is
greater than or equal to nineteen so in
those last three 19. 20. 21 and rolls i is
10 in that case we have a strike in
frame 10 what do we do? Well. very similar
to before we just output an X but
without the space. OK? Make sense? And I
just need to make sure that I've got my
brackets right now I'm just
missing a open curlies there. Perfect now
let's go run the test wait 'til the
whirligig finishes meaning this code is
compiled and loaded into unity and strike
like in last frame is working.
Fantastic. so what other what other
situations do we have? Well have zeros
nothing here is putting in a zero right
so what happens if we just bowl 0 next
just see that breaks it. Test bowl 0.
and let's go right back to basics and just
bowl a zero; and what should we get when we bowl a zero? Well by the notation of bowling you want
to get a dash now that can't work because
there's nothing in our score display
that tells it to return a dash so we rerun a failed
and it gives you 0 rather than a dash... now
I've been lazy and I've been forgetting
to increment my test numbers... it's not vital
but I like to have them in order so I'm
just gonna do that now four and five and
that's fine so now our code needs to
deal with zero so what is the deal with
zeros well actually always you enter 0 for 0.
so why don't we just start with that. If rolls
i equals 0 then what we do? We simply
add to the output string a dash
and then we just need to turn this guy into
an else if. So either this happens. it's a
zero. and we may as well just say that we just say always enter 0 as dash. OK. fantastic I might take
out a few spaces in here and I'm trying
to get this spare to line up on the right
hand side but I think I'm gonna be lucky.
it's gonna be a bit too much to expect
that too so I may just have to accept a
little bit wider. It's only that
I've got my test showing on the right if
I made my mono develop a bit more sensible it
would be fine - there you go - so we got the 0
case. the the spare. the strike. the strike
without the space. and otherwise we just
enter it normally so what is the deal on
this last line. what's the comment? It's a
normal 1. 2. 9 bowl. something like that. So
and this guy here is strike in frame 1-9
1 to 9. this is spare anywhere. always enter a 0 as a 0.
and this is the score box. OK let's try it.
Let's see if that all works. Looking
pretty elegant. now of course I cheated
again. I have done lots of work to
prototype this code so that I can just
write it like this. Again I considered
writing a meandering video that would
take absolutely ages but it would bore
you stiff so what I actually did when I
created this code is I ended up making
much much messier code building more
tests actually than this... than I built here
and then constantly refactoring my code
back. alright. but I'm not gonna put you
through that pain. So what I've got now
is some verification tests now I'm not
gonna type of these out for you. I've got
six Golden copy verification tests
they're available in the action master
sorry in the score display tests
file that is available for you in
the start pack so you may have to rename
the class because I've so that you can
use it but this is available for you
score display test and also attach it to
this lecture. so here go the golden copy...
I'm going to leave a space and paste it in
so they're the same games as in the
previous test the same links I've just
written them out now. oh I've got a
score cumulative left in there. I don't want
that so I want golden copy 2. golden
copy 3 here you go. so I'll start the numbering at
1. 2 and you can see what they're doing 3 and golden copy 4 and I think you're only going to end up with 5
OK so you end up with 5 tests.
They're all golden copy tests. the strings are carefully
written out. the format is X space when you
get a strike and let's see if this
simple code passes all the golden copy
verification tests or not... Wow. it does
so I'm pretty happy with that result I
hope you are too and I'll see you in the
next video.