Hey guys! So.
here we're going to look at a couple of things. Firstly. kindly a couple
of our students have pointed out some bugs. So firstly.
this actually ins't a bug. but I want to make sure that it behaves properly. It's in our score display
test. I want to add a new test. because Ben Vasco said
if you bowl 0 pins on the first bowl of a frame
and 10 on the second bowl of a frame. it is actually a spare.
So. let's just make sure that. that is the case. So. I'm going to go down
and put in a new test. and I am going to call it
T06. And then. I'm just going to call it Bowl010.
So. if we bowl 0 then 10. what we should get out of it
is a nothing and then a spare forward slash. Let's see if we do.
So. save the script. Make sure it's saved. Back over into Unity
and let's let the tests run.
Now I need to rerun. Bowl 010 works! Fantastic!
OK. now the second thing I'm going to deal with is the fact that actually we have an invalid
test. If we look in our score display test again. at the bottom
we have this GoldenCopy 2of3. Look. if we go
1091 in the final frame. actually the last thing we should see is a
spare. not a 1. So. 9 and 1 together make
spare. OK. so let's see what happens if we try running that.
the code against that test. The test is actually wrong in this case.
Now we get a fail. and we get a fail because what our code is giving us is 91
and it should be giving us a 9 spare. So. a quick challenge for you. I won't even put up a slide.
Just fix that in the code if you can. So. go to the code for
ScoreDisplay and see if you can fix it.
OK welcome back! So. thank you very much
to Elijah I believe. who pointed out this problem for us
and solved it! What you need to do here is. this line is the offending
line. It's saying that a spare is when
box mod 2 is 0. but we have an exception on box 21.
because box mod 2 is not 0 and box 21 is that weird third frame.
So. what I'm going to do is just say box mod 2. take out a few spaces.
or box == 21.
I will probably just reduce the length of the comment.
OK. so in the case that we have box mod 2 is 0. which covers all the
frames apart from the last one. and then. the final frame our box is 21. Let's try that.
save it. back into Unity. let the whirligig
finish. and we still have a failing test. What's the
problem? Let me rerun. There you go. all passing! Fantastic!
OK. so that's two things sorted out. I want to tell you a final thing. I can't reproduce it for
you I'm afraid. I've tried. But when I came to this for the first time and I haven't used
this section for a little while. this project for a little while. none of my tests were running. In fact. none of the ticks
were even showing up. If that ever happens to you. here's what I did to fix it. So.
what I would suggest is that you quit your project.
you go find your project folder. which is here.
and delete everything in the root.
all of these solution and preferences files. and the Library folder.
leaving only Assets and ProjectSettings. I'm also leaving a readme file.
That may clear it on it's own. just clearing the caches. becaues what can happen
is. your version of Unity can get out of sync with the version of the Unity test tools.
If after importing and recompiling all of this stuff it still doesn't work.
then go to the Assets Store and I'll just tell you what to look out for.
It's a simple tweak. So. go to the Assets Store. which
is Windows. Asset Store. Remember what you need to search for.
for Unity test tools. It's Unity Test Tools.
When you search for that. make sure that you're seeing this one by Unity Technologies.
When you click on it. this for me says Import. but it might for you say
Upgrade. So. just go ahead. download. re-import it. and upgrade it. If it still
doesn't work or you get weird errors. clear those files again in your Unity folder.
The Library folder. so your
left with just Assets and ProjectSettings. these ones highlighted. Delete everything else
and try again. and that should clear the problem for you. OK. that's two bugs
sorted out. The code is even stronger. So. I hope you enjoyed this brief and simple video. and I will see you soon!