Hi guys and welcome to Glitch Garden. So firstly
thank you to the makers of Glitch which was
a game that didn't make it to market but they
made all their assets available to it.
Yeah it's fantastic right everything is available
to us and to you as well to use in your own
games if you want to move beyond just the
Glitch Garden for this time.
It's awesome because these sprite sheets that
we give you in this game don't take them for
granted. If you were to try and draw that
hand, you know frame by frame by hand... real
hassle so fantastic to have these assets and
animations you know we can focus on the coding
of it, on the structure, on the patterns so
what are they going to see that's new in Glitch
Garden
So lots of really cool stuff right we've kind
of met the animation framework in Laser Defender
now it's time to really put it through its paces
and use it to do key frame animation and flipbook
animation for your sprites so we're going
to show you a lot of things on how to make
sprite animations, how to use sprite sheets
to make your characters come to life and because
we're going to be using professional assets
from the Glitch game they're going to look
really sharp.
So the major the big teacher for this section
is really getting to grips with the animator
and the other things you're going to learn
- you're going to learn a lot more about how
to structure a slightly more complicated game;
how we use the component system and how things
talk to each other and how we need to be careful
about that so we can stay sane and the other
thing is that it's designed to be deployed
to mobile from the beginning so we straight
away start thinking about going to mobile
and we're constantly checking with ourselves
through the project that it's going to be
suitable for mobile and at the end we'll put
it on mobile.
Yeah we definitely want to be building games
for release on a platform so that we can get
to our players right our game isn't a game
until its being played and so we now want
to get mobile players to play Glitch Garden
Absolutely and of course it'll deploy to the
web so in the end you'll be sticking it on
GameBucket won't you? alright so let's get
stuck in, get it done, I'll be teaching this
one so see you soon.
Good luck and enjoy it.