So we're going to start a little differently
this time by making a splash screen. On the
free version of Unity there's a mandatory
splash screen that comes up as you can see
here on the left. Now these are screen shots
from Block Breaker running on my Android device
but the same would happen on the web and that
splash screen would stay up until the first
screen for example the start menu has finished
loading. So what we want to do is make our
own splash screen in between where we have
a nice big pretty image that lasts between
one and five seconds, maybe with some short
sound and then people can see that while the
start menu loads. It's also just good branding,
good practice and just looks better.
The other thing that's good about it is that
you can get away without having to check for
duplicate music players and the like if we
insert our music player on the splash screen
and then tell it not to destroy on load then
because we never revisit the splash screen
we never have to check for duplicate instances
and do any of that destroying business so
this is an alternative pattern for you.
So here are some resources for you - we've
used before Dafont.com, freesound.org, google
images but crucially glitchthegame.com - that's
where I'm going to get all my assets from
for this game.
Glitch is a game that failed and they've very
kindly put all of their art into the public
domain. So from here I'm going to use this
for my start scene at 1600 by 900. So here's
your challenge what I want you to do, I think
that you're ready for it, is to add a simple
UI image to a scene called splash; add a short
sound, five seconds or less. Again you can
get that from the Glitch website, there's
a couple there that work quite well.
Import a Start Scene from a previous project,
customise it if you like, the fonts and things
and then arrange for the start scene to load
after one to five seconds so what we want
is for the splash scene to come up with a
little bit of sound and then after between
one and five seconds I suggest about two and
a half then the start scene will load and
then that's it, you're done.
Don't worry about the scaling of that image
but I suggest that you use a 16:9 image.
So that's it, go ahead and enjoy the challenge.
Welcome back so, how am I going to do this?
I've downloaded the 1600 by 900 image, I'm
going to go quite quickly as we've scene quite
a lot of this before so I've saved the project
as Glitch Garden now in my case I accidentally
saved it as a 3D default project - I know
that because if I go to the layout and hit
default I end up in the 3D view. It doesn't
matter, it hardly changes anything you can
always just click 2D so that's fine, Glitch
Garden's the project name. I'm going to save
the scene - currently the scene is not saved
so I'm just going to call it... I'm actually
going to make a folder for it you can do that
in Finder here - underscore scenes - because
I like to tidy it into there and then I'm
going to call it 00 Splash. I'm going to start
using numbers in front of my scene names just
for simplicity.
Cool so here we have a splash scene. Insert
a UI image. Perfect. So there is our canvas
and our image. Canvas is th larger box, the
image is just a little square.
Right. Now we need to get the... Import a
new asset we need to get the image that we
found for Glitch in here. That's great so
we have an image now for me it's come in as
a texture, we want it as a sprite 2D and UI.
Because that's what the UI image is expecting.
Perfect. I'm not going to worry about pixels
per unit because this is a screen space canvas
we're going to be using.
Cool so here it is, there's the image I'll
leave it in the root for now it doesn't matter.
I'm going to apply my image changes, drag
the image sprite on; perfect. Now a couple
of things I do want to change on the image.
Well, only one actually, I want to preserve
the aspect ratio, there you go now the image
suddenly is no longer being stretched so preserve
aspect ratio and I'm going to click set native
size - Ooh much bigger.
Alright, cool so now we have an image that's
much bigger than our canvas if we look over
in the game preview, it's a bit weird but
that's OK at least we've got the full pixel
resolution of the image. If you go back up
to the canvas now we've got a few options.
What render mode do we want on the canvas?
Well it's still going to be screen space overlay
it's a UI, it's a User interface and it's
going to overlay the entire screen so we leave
that as it is.
Skip over the rest for the moment. OK the
canvas scaler. We're going to go for scale
with screen size. If the screen size is smaller
than 1600 by 900 we want the canvas to scale
down and vice versa so we're going to scale
with screen size as t UI scale mode.
The reference resolution is 1600 by 900 in
my case because that's the resolution of my
image. Ah we're getting closer now, if we
look over in the game scene, it's starting
to look a bit more sensible.
OK, now what's the screen match mode we're
going to be using here with this image? Well,
I'm going to leave this bit until another
video because there's quite a lot to think
about when it comes to match modes and all
the rest of it so I'm just going to scale
my image so it fits and stick it in the middle
of my canvas then over in the Game Scene it
looks OK. It's kind of what we're used to.
OK let's leave it at that, we'll revisit these
settings in a little bit.
Fantastic, so now we need to get it loading
a start menu. Or a start scene. So firstly
we don't have a start scene, let's go find
an appropriate start scene. I'm going to use
the Block breaker start scene because it's
the most similar to what I want to use here.
So I go to Block Breaker, I go and find Start
Menu here and I'm going to drag - just drag
it into the project. OK if we look at it,
saving changes to Splash, what have we got
on the Start Menu? So hitting play, it doesn't
look like we've got anything, but that's because
if you look at the title, subtitle et cetera
you'll find, and you can see the red error
down the bottom that there's no font on any
of the characters so this is a good time to
choose ourselves a font. So over to daFont,
I like funny Kid, over on daFont, I found
it by searching Kid in the search - here he
is, funny kid.
So I've downloaded that font, what I'm going
to do is just quickly import it. Let's make
ourselves a folder - let's be neat as we go
shall we? Fonts. Now as a quick aside, by
the way, you don't have to structure your
folders like this. Brice showed you an alternative
in Laser Defender which is he used entities
to group things and we may even change our
grouping later because even though scenes,
fonts, you know images is very clear it is
a bit of duplication with this feature that
Unity has up here which is that you can click
towards the top right of the assets and you
can say well show me all of my scenes or show
me all of my you know my textures or all of
my shaders or whatever. So rather than using,
say texture versus sprite, I'm going to just
say images in fact it's treating the two the
same but I'm not going to use this type search
at the moment, not until our assets get more
complicated. I just wanted to give you that
quick aside.
Anyway, fonts. What do I need to do I need
to import a new asset from my downloads and
I want to call it funny kid. Cool. Now if
I apply the Funny Kid font to all four of
those things and then double click on my start
menus so I can see it Ahh that looks a bit
better, it's got some style to it now. In
fact, why don't we go over to Glitch and get
ourselves from the downloads something we
can use as a background for the load scene;
what would work well?How about dark?How about
a dark style with a fox? I'm planning to use
the fox later.
Download full size fox. Glitch fox. Perfect.
Grab this fox and pop him into images. Great;
and I'm going to set this as the background
so UI image, same as before and I need to
set the fox as a Sprite and then I need to
push the fox backwards in the order of things
and I can do that by dragging it up here in
the inspector, to the top of the heirarchy,
and having dropped the Glitch fox image into
the sprite I have it in the background. Fantastic
so again we're going to preserve the aspect
ratio and then let's get it up to the full
size of the canvas like so again so scaling
issues we're not going to deal with in this
video because it's going to be too much for
one... video so let's not worry about that
for now I'm just going to move my text to
the left a little bit and left align it because
right aligned is frankly a little bit ugly;
so let's just left align and centre vertically
the text; now just kind of tweak all the components
now we'll talk about... as I say we'll talk
about how all this should fit on the canvas
later.
I'm just going to get it vaguely right now.
Great so we have something that looks like
a vaguely stylised start menu for this game.
How's that looking? Pretty cool now it says
Block Breaker, change it straight away the
moment you see that it's called Glitch Garden
in my case, call your game what you like.
It's spelt properly; and stop them pesky animals.
If English isn't your first language, stop
them pesky animals is terrible English so
well done if you spotted that but I don't
care.
OK, fantastic so leave these two elements
not overlapping and stop fannying around with
this screen for now so we have a start screen
which is the purpose of this bit. Let's now
go back to the splash screen which is the
one we're really focusing on, let's stick
a tiny bit of text in here, let's say Glitch
Garden; this looks incomplete so maybe just
take this Glitch Garden text component, paste
it in here; centralise... the font is correct
this colour is a bit weird I'll try black
on here... yeah or white. No, black. We'll
go for black and then we don't need the word
garden because it already says. Well, sorry
we don't need the word Glitch because it already
says it and then I'm just going to get the
UI element roughly showing us the space in
the image we want it to take up. It's just
as a guide line for ourself. Perfect that's
pretty good. Now, the only thing is the font
is rendering really ugly size-wise so I need
to turn its size up and then maybe reset the
scale here. We've inherited some weird scale
here. I want a one to one scale there we go;
that's better now I can resize it. So they're
the sort of things you're going to have to
fiddle around you're probably going to want
a one - one scale on your rect transform up
here; and then I'm going to use a hundred
on the font size; black, Glitch Garden - perfect
let's try this.
Glitch Garden, nice.
OK next thing we need - a tiny bit of sound.
Let's do that the easy way for now, let's
not worry about music managers and things
let's just go grab from the ringtones - under
the alerts for example you've got Game Loaded.
That sounds fine so I've downloaded it there
a moment ago; let's make myself a folder called
sounds, immediately bring in the sound asset
which is... what's it called die sound, game
loaded. Perfect. Make it not a 3D sound because
it's not a 3D game and then just drag it into
the heirarchy there and then just call it
Load sound. Play on awake, yup that's fine
so look, it's starting to come together. Wow
OK now what we need to do is make this oh
hold on... game loaded didn't save. Very easy
to do that by the way you want load sound
and then you have to hit return. Make sure
it changes in the heirarchy. Great, so final
thing we need to do is just get a level manager
in here; we don't have a level manager at
the moment. So make ourselves a scripts folder,
you get the plan. Go grab yourself a level
manager from another project; I'm going to
grab mine again from Block Breaker because
it's... I know it works alright . Not to say
that Brice's things won't work fine it's just
that I know it and I'm familiar with it. There
we go level manager dot cs. Let's go in there,
have a look at the level manager get rid of
anything to do with Brick Breakable counts
that's nothing to do with this game, OK we
don't even need the brick destroyed method.
now we want to modify this level manager a
little bit but before I modify it for this
well no, let's modify it straight away.
OK so I'm going to have a float - a public
float - auto load next level after... what
a long variable name do I get a long variable
name award here somehow and then what I'm
going to do is I'm going to go start - void
start of course because it doesn't return
anything and then I'm going to say Invoke,
OK and then I'm going to use the invoke method
- you can look up the docs for that - I'm
going to call load next level give it a string
it's a bit weird; after auto-load next level
time. OK; and then what's going to happen
is if I put a level manager into the scene
which I can - I need to make myself a game
Object, call it level manager. Make sure you
hit return, reset the transform we want all
our manager components at the origin, pop
it up the top and then pop a script on it.
Great OK now look it's got auto load next
level if I put two seconds watch this. Ah...
nearly there, it would be auto calling load
next level but look, it couldn't be loaded
because it's not in the build settings. That
old chestnut. Build settings, splash and start,
in they go, in the order we want them. I think
I'm going to rename start actually to 01A
start because what I want to do is reflect
this diagram that I showed you a little bit
better. All the things in the left hand column,
well splash is going to be 00, start and options
are going to be 01 and then we can go on from
there and worry about it after that.
So 01 Start, that's fine let's try again on
the splash screen. Great, OK it just loads
too quickly, so I'm going to make it three
seconds... cool so congratulations on getting
this far, you can now click start, you have
a splash screen, a nice sound, and it goes
across to the start menu. Awesome, we have
the start of a cool looking game. Congratulations
and I'll see you soon.