Hey guys I don't know about you but I'm feeling
really good about the way that this is coming
on now. it's really starting to pull together
as a proper game so. well I say a game. at
least a menu system for a game.
What I'd like to be able to do is create a
fade-in from the intro screen here I want
this to fade in not just bang but fade up
and we're going to be able to re-use that
fading functionality in other places. This
is about just finishing the polish of this
system. So what are we going to do in this
video?
We're going to add a nice fade-in to this
start scene. I'm going to give up completely
on trying to spell lose or loose properly
because it's just not working. we're going
to add a background image to the levels a
grass for our play scene and check that it
all flows really nicely before moving on.
OK so let's get on with that. So how are we
going to do fading? Well. sorry to say. you're
going to work it out. You're brave. you're
going to work it out. Have a go for yourself.
what I want you to do is make the start scene
fade in over a variable amount of time.
Try it your way. it's great learning to try
to see and explore the different ways. Use
google. think of ways of doing it. I'm going
to give you a couple of hints. I'll be using
a UI panel and adjusting its alpha and if
you're wondering where to place the script
then why not on that very panel. So there's
enough hints. enough ideas there why don't
you see if you can get the start scene fading
in over a couple of seconds?
Pause the video. have a good go at that now.
and when you're ready to see how I do it just
carry on.
OK welcome back so it's time for me to show
you how I'm going to achieve my fade. So we
go to the scene in question which is the start
scene; open up the canvas and let's add ourselves
a UI panel. Perfect. Where is that panel?
Well it's sitting right over the top of everything.
I'm going to go into my UI mode and literally
put this over the top of the entire canvas.
Like so.
There it is. That is my panel covering my
entire canvas. So. what am I going to do with
that panel. Well. let's set its colour to
black and its transparency to 255. its alpha
to 255 so fully opaque. Now you can't see
anything. Now where it is in the hierarchy
does that make a difference? Well it does
in the case of the UI elements so you are
going to want this at the very bottom of your
canvas like that.
So fantastic we have now a blank. useless
start screen but. this is the start state.
this is how we want to start and then we want
it to fade through. so it's the alpha that
we're going to be changing on this guy so
let's add a component. a script straight on
the panel itself and let's call it. well.
fade in. Maybe later we'll generalise this
a little more. make it a fade in/fade out
script but for now all it does is fade in
so we should call it fade in.
Scripts. organise the scripts into the scripts
folder. and let's take a look. So. how are
we going to achieve a fade in. Well. good
question. what would the public variable that
we need to expose be for a start? Well I suggest
that it's something to do with the amount
of time that it fades over right. so why don't
we start with a public float and what would
we call it? Have a think about the name. I'm
not just going to tell you the name for two
seconds. what would you call it? Naming is
everything. Well. FadeInTime. You could say
FadeInTime in seconds. so what are we going
to need in order to be able to control this?
Well. privately we're going to need to have
an image; that's a UI image.
Now why does image not come up in my list?
Because we need to import the UnityEngine.UI
namespace. Great. So now we can say private
image and it'll work; and what are we going
to call this image? Well. I'm going to call
it FadePanel. OK? Pretty unimaginatively.
You know. if it's a dog. call it a dog. If
it's a cat call it a cat. private. what else
do we need here? Well. we're going to need
a colour. Why? Because in C# you may have
noticed that often you need to pass methods
complete objects like you need to form your
vectors before you pass them in. In the same
way we need to fully form our colour before
we pass it into the panel.
So we're going to need a private colour. and
I'm going to call it currentColour. because
it's going to change every frame. right? Now
do I put a "u" in my colour? Oh here's a dilemma.
how long do we spend considering this. Unity
don't put a 'u' because they're heathens and
they're American. I'm English and I like 'u's
I'm going to leave it consistent with Unity.
how's that? I'm giving up the flag for the
sake of being consistent with that dodgy American
spelling.
So what do we start the colour with? We start
it with color.black so we don't necessarily
have to set it in the inspector because we
are initialising here. OK. that's fine so
on the Start. what are we going to do? We're
going to find that fade panel. Let's just
go back to Unity and make sure that we understand
what we're talking about. If you look at the
panel. I'm adding a script. I want to find
the actual image component - this bit - this
image script here and it's this colour that
I'm going to change and what I want to do
in script is have the effect of dragging this
alpha slider. you see?
As I drag it it starts to appear. Perfect.
so that's the control that I want from script.
So the way that I need to do that is I need
to get component image from within my script.
I'm getting another component off a different
component on the same gameObject and it's
of type image so fadePanel equals GetComponent.
and I'm going to use the chevron format type
image. and then it's a method so it needs
squigglies. Fantastic.
Alright. so on the update. what are we going
to say? Well basically. we do something when
Time.timeSinceLevelLoad OK time since level
loaded when that is less than the fade in
time then we do something. What are we going
to do? Well. put a comment in for the moment.
Fade in. Basically; and then what do we do
otherwise? Well. this is quite important.
Once that fade-in has finished we're going
to need to de-activate the panel. otherwise
you're not going to be able to click anything.
You see right now you wouldn't be able to
click any of these objects. We're going to
need to deactivate it which has the same effect
as clicking this tick.
So it will go from black through the alpha
over the period of two seconds. or however
long you set to white and then it will disable
so that we can click the buttons below and
it's out of the way. So that's the pattern
that we're going for. So else gameObject.SetActive
false. That's setting active false is unticking
this box effectively.
Cool. so now all we need to do is write the
fading code. Ah. come on. I've got to challenge
you to do this at this point. surely. How
about you write it? It's three lines. well
I've done it in three lines. and it's relatively
simple it involves the currentColour.a and
a bit of Time.DeltaTime and a bit of division
and stuffs. Have a go. see if you can write
this fade-in code and make it work. If you
can't. don't beat yourself up. just come straight
back and I'll show you how.
Awesome. so I'm going to define an intermediate
variable called alphaChange so we can see
what we're doing. So alphaChange is what?
Well. in this frame we need Time.DeltaTime
s that could be a few milliseconds. typically
it's going to be something like fifty milliseconds
or whatever. depends how fast the framerate
of the game is at the moment. Divided by fadeInTime.
yeah? So that's how much change we need this
frame. Time.DeltaTime over the fadeInTime.
So if it's a two second frame. and the fade
in time is two seconds. then you would have
a hundred percent alpha change. If the fade
in time was say two seconds but we had a tenth
of a second frame then we would have twenty.
we would only want a twentieth of the fade
to happen this frame. Does that make sense?
It's just the proportion of the fade that
we want to happen this frame.
Fine. so now we go currentColor.a we take
its alpha channel off and we reduce it by
the thing we just made. alphaChange. So we
reduce the alpha and then we set the fadePanel.color.
No we can't do it all in one step in C# unfortunately.
Equals currentColor. Anyway this reads really
nice and clear. So. hopefully. that works.
OK. let's have a go. I'm going to start on
my splash screen. Hang on. back to your start.
remember to set your parameter. Under your
panel here. and I'm going to call it fade
panel. Fade in time of how long shall we go
for? Well shall we try three seconds? The
same fade in as the fade out on the splash
screen? ie the delay on the splash screen?
Let's try.
Looks good. apart from my panel positioning
is wrong. So lets take a look at what's up
with our fade panel. Well. for me what's happened
is that when I first added the fade panel
it subtly came in as completely the wrong
type of image. It came in as a sliced image
so let's set it to simple. Before I do though.
the clue is here up in the size of the rect
transform. It's 283 by 19 pixels so that's
a bit weird. it's all sliced and stretched
let's just set it to a simple image. That's
starting to help. Now if we play with the
alpha for a second of this image. you'll see
that its got a kind of oval background and
that's because it's a background image. We
don't want an image so that's the second thing
to fix.
Now that option has gone away. Because there's
no image if you set the image then you get
the image type slice but as soon as we take
the image away there is no option any more
so we're much closer to where we want to be.
It kind of looked OK in the preview by luck
before but this is set up properly.
The final thing we want to do is actually
explicitly set the size of this image to the
1600 by 900 that we're talking about. It's
still not working. so why is that not working?
Well. you've got a little tiny element up
here and you've got a really strange position
you've got stretching set. you've got really
weird settings in this rect transform. Just
reset the rect transform. there you go. There
it is in the middle. now all we need to do
is set the 1600 by 900.
So they're the sort of things you may need
to go through and align the image. OK? So
if in doubt trying to add a simple panel like
this. reset your rect transform. set the resolution
explicitly and make sure there is no source
image. Now we're in business. let's have a
look.
So I reduced the music volume and delay so
it went through quickly. final thing of course
that I forgot to do was just to add the script
back - fade in script over I'm going to make
it two seconds. I think that three is too
long. let's try that for effect.
Whip through that. one. two and then it works.
Fantastic. let's try starting the game. So
where's my start button taking me. let's have
a quick look at that. Where's the start button
wired to? It's wired to start. Well we don't
want it wired to start. we want it wired to
02 level 01. Now. we have a problem here.
This is different to the prefab. the thing
is we've prefabbed a start button and it's
doing two different things. This start button
is taking us to level 1 and our prefab start
button which we use on the win screen and
the lose screen is taking us back to the start.
So why don't we change the name of one of
them? Why don't we just change this one on
the front scene here instead of being called
start. it's a play button now. OK? So play
button and it's not. it's nothing to do with
the prefab any more. So it would actually
be better to disconnect it from the prefab.
The easiest way to do that would be to duplicate
the options button. remove the play button
altogether and then just call it play button.
Because it's nothing to do with the prefab.
that's where the confusion is coming in.
OK so again. naming. So many issues around
naming. right? Play Game. and then simply
whip out the UI size. make sure that the play
game's script is wired to the right place.
which is 02 level 01. that's fine. Now lets
just try it all.
So wait for that fade to finish. play game
lose condition. you moose. start takes you
back here. play game win condition. you win.
Fantastic. So we have a nice simple fade script
that we can use on any UI image panel and
we can apply that same technique to any level.
We didn't quite get around to adding the grass
to the levels but that's fine. we'll do that
in a subsequent video. because we need to
think a little bit carefully about our scaling
mode for all of the levels and how we're going
to deal with that. congratulations on getting
this far. and I shall see you soon.