Hey guys Ben here! So firstly.
this video has been inserted after the main production of the course.
That's why we have a white background and slightly different production standards.
So. one of our students very kindly pointed out that we're
about to dive into Player Prefs. and we're going
to straight way modify it. So. why are we doing that? Well.
let me just give you a brief overview. Firstly. Player Prefs
are a piece of Persistent Storage. on your device.
Now. this is very abstracted. you don't need to worry about whether
it's an Xbox. a PlayStation. a telephone. a Mac. a PC.
or what it is. Always. when Unity is
running a game on it. there's a little bit of storage set aside
for Player Preferences. Now. this storage is unencrypted.
so if you use it for things like level unlocks. then a
wise hacker can very easily go into that Player Prefs
File. in the Hex Editor for example. and unlock levels for themselves.
so be aware of that. It's also very very slow to access. Now. by
very slow I mean measured in milliseconds.
not minutes or many seconds. but it's
slow to ba accessing this. certainly on a frame by frame basis
you don't want to be doing it. So. there are a couple of the downfalls of Player Prefs.
Now. the main one I'm addressing. with this wrapper that I'm creating
is the fact that it's very easy to throw things into the
Player Prefs Bucket and forget what you sent in there. If you
look at Unity's docs. you'll realize that you write
a Player Pref like this. You say. I want to set a
Bool a string... I'm sorry. not a Bool. A
float an integer or a string. For a start. there's only three data
types. float. integer. string. and you take one of those.
let's say a float. and you give it a key
a word. You say the. I don't know. the
player's speed is 1.3. So. you say player speed is the
key. and you put 1.3 in the bucket. Very very
well. but it's very easy to do
that. from lots of different scripts and not to know what you've got in your Player
Prefs. And if you check Unity's docs. you'll find that there's no way
of listing all of the different settings.
all of the different key value pairs. that you've
put into your Player Prefs. it's just not possible. The best you can
do is use the .HasKey method. to see if a given
key is there. That's pretty messy right. if you've got several scripts
writing into the Player Prefs. Or did I call it Player
Speed or Players' Speed? I can't remember! You've got to through
all of it's mess! So. that's why I'm trading a Wrapper
Class! That means that all of your rights. to the Player Prefs. go through a
series of Constants. that are defined at the top of a single
script. and that means that we've got a single. as I call it.
canonical place that we know that
all of the key value pairs that we want to work with. So. this will all come clear
as you go. So. we are slightly jumping in the deep end by
skipping over using naked Player Prefs. but don't worry.
using them on their own is really simple. You'll see the
lines of code in there. you just say write this
value with this key. But we're going to wrap it all up
more nicely than that. into our own Player Prefs Manager
static class. which will be right there when you  use your
auto-complete. ready to use. and it'll serve you well.
in the future. So good luck! This will all come clear in the next video.
and I'll see you soon!