Hey guys. welcome back. So in this video we're
going to set up our actual levels. So what
we have at the moment is just a win button
and a lose button loosely slapped down but
we need to think about the canvas for our
actual levels. So if you remember our splash
screen. that was a canvas of screen match
mode type shrink if you look at the canvas
scaler of your canvas on your splash screen
it's screen match mode is shrink. which means
that the canvas shrinks as teh game window
changes size.
That has the following effect: it means that
when your aspect ratio gets squarer. so say
we go from the 16:9 the big box you can see
down to the 4:3. the iPad style resolution
we lose the edges. and we talked about the
edges being a quiet zone. and that being OK
on this image. because there's nothing particularly
interesting happening and you don't really
notice you've lost it; but this is what we
want for our game as well. We actually want
for our level to have all the important gameplay
elements in the centre here. and then anything
that's irrelevant to the gameplay on the the
outside.
So firstly. we're going to need a grass texture
so let's go and grab ourselves a grass texture.
It's in the asset pack for this section. I
found it on the web. made a little bit of
a modification to it and there it is. So pop
your grass tile into your images folder but
crucially set your sprite mode - sorry the
texture type to texture up here in the inspector.
not to a sprite; because we want this thing
to repeat. So all the other default options
should be fine. and click apply.
So now you actually have a texture in here
rather than a sprite. Fantastic. I think that
this is the first time that you've probably
used a texture. Now lets go into the level
one scene. Now. what do we want to add to
use this? Well. click on the canvas and add
yourself a UI raw image rather than an image.
What's the difference? Well. you can click
on the book and it will tell you. take you
to the docs. but basically it takes in a texture.
That's the main thing. and it's better for
static images.
So if you pop the grass texture on there then
look what we have a little grass element.
Now before I do anything else I'm going to
reset the rect transform for this guy. we
had so much trouble before; and I'm also going
to set the width and height to 1600... and
not 16 million. or whatever that is. 1600.
struggling because the microphone is between
my face and the keyboard. There you go. 1600
by 900. great.
So that is our target size. that's fine. raw
image is not particularly useful. let's call
it grass. just grass and I'm going to put
it at the top of our canvas hierarchy so it's
behind the text. Now that it's where it is
we can see that our text is no longer on the
playing field so let's bring it in. let's
bring it even further remember that at 4:3
we still want t be able to see it. How do
we check that? Well we go over to game. we
set the aspect to 4:3 and make sure that we
can still see these things. Fine.
Alright so where's the canvas mode here? It's
on expand. we want it on shrink. Set it to
shrink. Better. Now. as you go from 4:3 to
16:9 you just lose the edges you see? So.
finally we need to tweak in the win condition
and the lose condition. Now if you want to
see them together you can detach your game
and have it next to the scene like this. you
may have a lot more room on your screen. I'm
very small here because of the screen resolution
that I'm using for recording.
Great. so now we can see the direct effect.
Great so as our aspect ratio for our device
gets wider. and it introduces more information
left and right but the core of the game is
4:3 is what we're going to be targetting.
So in the rest of the video we are going to:
well. we've covered the screen match mode.
We've covered the raw image and grass texture.
I've talked to you about quiet zones so now
I want you to set up the level with prefabs.
So I need you to scale. find out how to scale
that; or tile rather. that grass texture image
so that we have at least five rows and nine
columns at 4:3.
Make it fill the screen. we've kind of done
that. then once you're happy with your canvas.
once you're happy that you've got at least
five rows and nine columns at 4:3 I want you
to prefab the whole canvas and then replace
the canvasses on all three levels with the
prefabbed version. Now if we need to update
this first later then we can. by just changing
the prefab. Just check that it all scales
properly with the game window and flows through.
Have a go at that now.
Great. so the option that you're looking for
to make this grass scale is here. Let me just
go back to default layout. OK fine. Get my
canvas focussed and this is the option you're
looking for. go into the canvas. into the
grass and then it's width height here. You
can adjust these until you get what you need.
We need nine columns at 4:3. So actually maybe
I am better with my game detached so that
I can see what I'm getting. Aspect 4:3 and
keep changing the width until you get the
nine columns you're after 1. 2. 3. 4. 5. 6.
7. 8. 9 there's the nine at six we get nine
that's OK we may want to change that later.
no we need five high. we've only got three
high. so let's see where we go there.
1. 2. 3. 4. 5. 6 high. so maybe 3... 5 that's
OK there. Alright. that's OK. and we've still
got room along the bottom and the top for
a little bit of user interface so we have
our nine by five and a little bit of space
top and bottom for user interface. So that's
fine I've got UV rect settings of six and
three there. That's absolutely fine. that's
good news. So. what next? Well. the next thing
I'm seeing that I don't really like is that
there's a slight break in this texture. can
you see that there's a little horizontal line?
just a little thin horizontal line?
Well that's because my image has got a little
bit of mess on the bottom of it. If you go
into your favourite image editing program
- I'm going to use Preview but you might want
to use GIMP or some other PC program. All
I want you to do in your image is simply crop
the bottom pixel. The bottom single pixel
off that image. I'm leaving it this way rather
than giving you a perfect image because this
is exactly the sort of thing you're going
to need to do. I wanted you to see the effect
of having a slightly dodgy image.
OK. so if you do that and you reimport that
image into Unity... actually it's already
updated. which is good. You may not need to
reimport depending on where you make your
edit. If you've right-clicked on it and revealed.
or shown your file then it'll immediately
update look you see we don't have this problem
any more because we've taken this bottom pixel
off OK? And that grass playspace is looking
pretty cool now. Right. now I want to prefab
the canvas - the whole canvas is basically
set up how we want it. Prefab it. give it
a more meaningful name. Level Canvas. Right.
fantastic. and then what we finally want to
do is go through the levels and make sure
that all levels don't use this dodgy old canvas
they had but they use a nice. prefabbed level
canvas. Spelt correctly. and the great thing
about prefabs is that they'll all update when
we make a change.
So later when we inevitably decide that we
want to tweak our level canvas we only need
to tweak the prefab. There it is. just try
renaming it again. Canvas... pefect. Alright.
so now. if we look through our scenes. start
from the start screen. In fact we can't start
from the start scene. we must start from splash
so our persistent music comes through properly.
if we play the game we get to here. lose condition
you moose. rather than lose. back to start
play game. win condition so that's all fine
and then if we just have a quick preview through
our levels. level one level two. level three.
all our level canvasses are prefabbed so we're
in a great state here.
Just check that when you detach your win scene
that it works for aspect ratios from 4:3 through
3:2 all the way up to 16:9; and it does. So
we now have a play space that's just begging
for us to start sticking some animals and
some plants and just creating a battleground
here. so congratulations on getting this far.
the final thing we're going to do in the next
video is take a look at making the options
screen actually do something and talk to the
=======
Hey guys, welcome back. So in this video we're
going to set up our actual levels. So what
we have at the moment is just a win button
and a lose button loosely slapped down but
we need to think about the canvas for our
actual levels. So if you remember our splash
screen, that was a canvas of screen match
mode type shrink if you look at the canvas
scaler of your canvas on your splash screen
it's screen match mode is shrink, which means
that the canvas shrinks as teh game window
changes size.
That has the following effect: it means that
when your aspect ratio gets squarer, so say
we go from the 16:9 the big box you can see
down to the 4:3, the iPad style resolution
we lose the edges, and we talked about the
edges being a quiet zone, and that being OK
on this image, because there's nothing particularly
interesting happening and you don't really
notice you've lost it; but this is what we
want for our game as well. We actually want
for our level to have all the important gameplay
elements in the centre here, and then anything
that's irrelevant to the gameplay on the the
outside.
So firstly, we're going to need a grass texture
so let's go and grab ourselves a grass texture.
It's in the asset pack for this section, I
found it on the web, made a little bit of
a modification to it and there it is. So pop
your grass tile into your images folder but
crucially set your sprite mode - sorry the
texture type to texture up here in the inspector,
not to a sprite; because we want this thing
to repeat. So all the other default options
should be fine, and click apply.
So now you actually have a texture in here
rather than a sprite. Fantastic. I think that
this is the first time that you've probably
used a texture. Now lets go into the level
one scene. Now, what do we want to add to
use this? Well, click on the canvas and add
yourself a UI raw image rather than an image.
What's the difference? Well, you can click
on the book and it will tell you, take you
to the docs, but basically it takes in a texture.
That's the main thing, and it's better for
static images.
So if you pop the grass texture on there then
look what we have a little grass element.
Now before I do anything else I'm going to
reset the rect transform for this guy, we
had so much trouble before; and I'm also going
to set the width and height to 1600... and
not 16 million, or whatever that is. 1600,
struggling because the microphone is between
my face and the keyboard. There you go. 1600
by 900, great.
So that is our target size, that's fine, raw
image is not particularly useful, let's call
it grass, just grass and I'm going to put
it at the top of our canvas hierarchy so it's
behind the text. Now that it's where it is
we can see that our text is no longer on the
playing field so let's bring it in, let's
bring it even further remember that at 4:3
we still want t be able to see it. How do
we check that? Well we go over to game, we
set the aspect to 4:3 and make sure that we
can still see these things. Fine.
Alright so where's the canvas mode here? It's
on expand, we want it on shrink. Set it to
shrink. Better. Now, as you go from 4:3 to
16:9 you just lose the edges you see? So,
finally we need to tweak in the win condition
and the lose condition. Now if you want to
see them together you can detach your game
and have it next to the scene like this, you
may have a lot more room on your screen. I'm
very small here because of the screen resolution
that I'm using for recording.
Great, so now we can see the direct effect.
Great so as our aspect ratio for our device
gets wider, and it introduces more information
left and right but the core of the game is
4:3 is what we're going to be targetting.
So in the rest of the video we are going to:
well, we've covered the screen match mode.
We've covered the raw image and grass texture,
I've talked to you about quiet zones so now
I want you to set up the level with prefabs.
So I need you to scale, find out how to scale
that; or tile rather, that grass texture image
so that we have at least five rows and nine
columns at 4:3.
Make it fill the screen, we've kind of done
that, then once you're happy with your canvas,
once you're happy that you've got at least
five rows and nine columns at 4:3 I want you
to prefab the whole canvas and then replace
the canvasses on all three levels with the
prefabbed version. Now if we need to update
this first later then we can, by just changing
the prefab. Just check that it all scales
properly with the game window and flows through.
Have a go at that now.
Great, so the option that you're looking for
to make this grass scale is here. Let me just
go back to default layout. OK fine. Get my
canvas focussed and this is the option you're
looking for, go into the canvas, into the
grass and then it's width height here. You
can adjust these until you get what you need.
We need nine columns at 4:3. So actually maybe
I am better with my game detached so that
I can see what I'm getting. Aspect 4:3 and
keep changing the width until you get the
nine columns you're after 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6,
7, 8, 9 there's the nine at six we get nine
that's OK we may want to change that later,
no we need five high, we've only got three
high, so let's see where we go there.
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6 high, so maybe 3... 5 that's
OK there. Alright, that's OK, and we've still
got room along the bottom and the top for
a little bit of user interface so we have
our nine by five and a little bit of space
top and bottom for user interface. So that's
fine I've got UV rect settings of six and
three there. That's absolutely fine, that's
good news. So, what next? Well, the next thing
I'm seeing that I don't really like is that
there's a slight break in this texture, can
you see that there's a little horizontal line?
just a little thin horizontal line?
Well that's because my image has got a little
bit of mess on the bottom of it. If you go
into your favourite image editing program
- I'm going to use Preview but you might want
to use GIMP or some other PC program. All
I want you to do in your image is simply crop
the bottom pixel. The bottom single pixel
off that image. I'm leaving it this way rather
than giving you a perfect image because this
is exactly the sort of thing you're going
to need to do, I wanted you to see the effect
of having a slightly dodgy image.
OK, so if you do that and you reimport that
image into Unity... actually it's already
updated, which is good. You may not need to
reimport depending on where you make your
edit. If you've right-clicked on it and revealed,
or shown your file then it'll immediately
update look you see we don't have this problem
any more because we've taken this bottom pixel
off OK? And that grass playspace is looking
pretty cool now. Right, now I want to prefab
the canvas - the whole canvas is basically
set up how we want it. Prefab it, give it
a more meaningful name. Level Canvas. Right,
fantastic, and then what we finally want to
do is go through the levels and make sure
that all levels don't use this dodgy old canvas
they had but they use a nice, prefabbed level
canvas. Spelt correctly, and the great thing
about prefabs is that they'll all update when
we make a change.
So later when we inevitably decide that we
want to tweak our level canvas we only need
to tweak the prefab. There it is, just try
renaming it again. Canvas... pefect. Alright,
so now, if we look through our scenes, start
from the start screen. In fact we can't start
from the start scene, we must start from splash
so our persistent music comes through properly,
if we play the game we get to here, lose condition
you moose, rather than lose, back to start
play game, win condition so that's all fine
and then if we just have a quick preview through
our levels, level one level two, level three,
all our level canvasses are prefabbed so we're
in a great state here.
Just check that when you detach your win scene
that it works for aspect ratios from 4:3 through
3:2 all the way up to 16:9; and it does. So
we now have a play space that's just begging
for us to start sticking some animals and
some plants and just creating a battleground
here. so congratulations on getting this far,
the final thing we're going to do in the next
video is take a look at making the options
screen actually do something and talk to the
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1:Unity/Section7/GG10 Scaling Level Backgrounds.srt
player prefabs. See you soon.