So, in that last part of the video I was starting to make a real hash
of the coding, I think it was getting late in the day. So, I've split it into two now for you,
and I am just going to recap before we carry on, because that video is already 10 minutes long and
we've got plenty more to do. So, we're making a wrapper around the PlayerPrefs
so that we can centralize these keys, like the volume
keys, etc. so that we know what type of data we're putting into the PlayerPrefs. It also
allows us to check, when we set the Master Volume we can check that it's between 0 and 1 and make
sure that it doesn't go outside that range and that we can have a list of keys
inside the PlayerPrefsManager, that tell us exactly what we're actually storing
in Player Prefs, because there's no other way of knowing without trolling through your entire code base.
So it's centralizing the usage of PlayerPrefs. So that's pretty
cool! So, where we'd got to is, I had just written a setter to set the
Master Volume, and we were just writing a getter as well. So, in the next couple of minutes
I'll fumble through that code and then we will get it working and carry on.
So good luck, I hope you enjoy the rest of the video!
I'm doing something funny with my brackets here,
and what I'm doing is I'm putting my
semicolons in the wrong place. I'm sure you spotted that
before I did. Now, the issue I'm getting here
is it's saying I can't print the return value of SetMasterVolume,
because SetMasterVolume doesn't return anything. That's all fair enough.
Finally, we're there! We print the Master Volume, we set it, and
then, we print what we get again. Let's try it!
Look at the Console, we get 0, we set it to 0.3, and then, we read
0.3. Great! So, we're setting and retrieving the Master Volume just fine. I'll leave
that test object there for a moment. Let's move on. OK, so let's move
on to level unlocking. So, I will write the
setter and you get write the getter. So, public
static void
UnlockLevel (int
level) and it'll take an integer level index into
this method. Fine!
What are we going to do in there? Well, I want to check it makes sense first. I'm going to
say, if level that we've passed in
is less than or equal to Application
.levelCount -
1). Why -1? Well, just take a
look at the Build Settings for two seconds. We have
8 levels here, but of course, we start counting at 0, so what
I'm saying is, the highest I can ask about is the number of levels
8 - 1, which is 7. So provided it's 7 or less, we're good to go;
otherwise, I'm asking you to unlock a level that's not in the build order, which is strange.
Let's capture that straight away, else Debug
.LogError ("Trying to unlock
level not in build order")
or something like that. Alright, so that's
captured the error condition or one of the many infinite possible level
error conditions. Now, let's go ahead and do the PlayerPrefsManager bit.
PlayerPrefs.SetInt
Now, what do we set as the key? Well, it's just going to be
(LEVEL_KEY but this time we're going to concatenate
level.ToString() on the end, so that what we end up
with there is something like "level_unlocked_"
1 or 2 or 0. Alright, so that's
that bit! And then, what are we actually going to set? Well, we're going to use 1 here. We're
going to say that 1 "// Use 1
for true". OK, it's a bit nasty but as I said we don't have bool,
so we're writing this wrapper to do it for us.
OK fantastic! So, let's just see that that is working
properly very quickly, over in our test script. Let's just unlock level 2 or something
like that. PlayerPrefsManager
.UnlockLevel
and then just (2); and then,
we're going to print... Well, we can't get it back yet actually, but what we could do is we could read the
raw thing. We could say PlayerPrefs
.GetKey, but we don't want to start doing this OK,
because I always want you to talk to PlayerPrefs right through the PlayerPrefsManager.
That's the whole point of it being there, so let's not put that habit in. What  I want
you to do now, is to write the rest of this IsLevelUnlocked().
There's your signature. IsLevelUnlocked takes in an integer, returns true
if the value against the key is 1. It's not a float, sorry about the mistake
on the slide. Just 1, it returns false otherwise, and if the level
index is not in the build order, we log a helpful error and return false. Go
ahead and do that now please.
OK welcome back! So this
is how we're going to do it, public static. What's it going to return?
A bool actually. We're actually allowing the PlayerPrefs through this wrapper to
return a different data type, which we didn't have access to before, and the method is
going to be called IsLevelUnlocked, and we
pass in the level we're asking about. Fine! Same type of thing,
if the level that we're asking about is less than
the number of levels -1, less than or equal to the level minus
1 then we're all good. So, let's just say "// return
bool" for now. We don't quite know how to do that yet, so we just write a comment.
else then this is where we capture the error,
and it's basically the same error as before.
It's ("trying to query
level not in build order"); OK,
sort your brackets out; "not all
code paths return a value", because we haven't filled in the code here now. Now, to fill in the code here I
want to put a couple of intermediate variables in just to make this life easier. Firstly,
we have the levelValue. This is the thing on the right-
hand side, this 1 that we've set, this nasty integer we've had to set.
= PlayerPrefs, this is where we actually dive into the PlayerPrefs and get
the integer back for the (LEVEL_KEY
+ concatenated with the
level name we're asking about, level.ToString());
like that. So that gets back either
0 or nothing or 1, but if it gets back a 1 then that's
when we want a bool isLevelUnlocked
= (); And it equals some expression. Now, what's the expression?
Where it's (levelValue == because it's a
comparison 1); OK,
fantastic! So what do we return? We simply
return isLevel
Unlocked; What did I say we'd return if
we have an error? Well, we're going to return false,
but we need to log the error as well. OK fantastic!
Now, let's try this over in test. We have UnlockedLevel (2), let's
do exactly the same thing as before. Let's print (PlayerPrefs
Manager, always use it, .IsLevelUnlocked (2);
OK, now we unlock
it and then we print again. Let's see what we get!
"False", it's not unlocked initially, and then it is unlocked. Perfect!
So, we're talking to the PlayerPrefs through a much much safer interface!
Final challenge for you in this video then. I want you to write
the entire difficulty wrapper. We've already used the constant string DIFF_KEY =
"difficulty" simple as that. I want you to write public static void difficulty Set
Difficulty. It takes in a float. You need to check that it's between 0
and 1, log if it's not, an error if it's not, and then just a getter as well,
and check it all in that same test function. Go ahead and do that now please.
OK
cool! So, let's get this guy finished off! So,
we're going to have a difficulty wrapper; public static
void
SetDifficulty takes in a (float
difficulty) OK,
now your next instinct should be a check. if (difficulty
is greater than or equal to
0 float and difficulty is less
than or equal to 1 float, then do what
we're going to do, else
we're going to log an error. Let's immediately think about helping people, helping our designer
to actually set these things properly.
So, what are we going to log?  Debug.Log
Error ("Difficulty
out of range"); simple as that. OK, now there's lots of other errors you could catch
and you could use exception handling, as I've said before, but this is just fine for now.
So, how are we going to actually do this? We go to PlayerPrefs
.SetFloat again. We're just going to use a float. We're going to have a percentage difficulty between
0 and 1. (DIFFICULT_KEY,
difficulty); OK fantastic!
And then, that's it actually. And then, how do we do the getter? Well, relatively
simple as well. It's public static but it's no longer void, it's float.
We're going to get our value out called float GetDifficulty ()
takes nothing in
and this literally just reads the PlayerPrefs, so we may as well just take it from here.
return so the return value
is PlayerPrefs.GetFloat and
we don't need to provide any value, because we're just saying tell me what's on the other end of that key.
GetDifficulty SetDifficulty. Let's test it!
I'm going to take this pattern actually here, so
we see what it does beforehand. (PlayerPrefsManager.Get
Difficulty); and it's just a kind of global difficulty value.
Fine. PlayerPrefsManager.Set
Difficulty, and let's set it to, I don't know,
0.2 float. Print has some invalid arguments,
that's because the difficulties are methods, and I'm not calling them as methods,
so I need to be putting on my brackets.
That build is fine, let's try it here. Great!
So initially the difficulty is 0, that seems to be the default, we can worry about defaults later.
Then, it's 0.2 after we've set it. The final thing to try is, let's try setting it out of range
1.2 or 12 or something.
"Difficulty out of range", and it stays as it was.
OK, it does not change it. Perfect, awesome job! I'm going to just
tidy up by getting rid of the TEST object. I'm going to get rid of the TEST script,
and I'm going to just leave you in awe of the beauty of our
PlayerPrefsManager on the screen there. Mainly the bit up at the top,
which is where we, through all of this architecture, keep complete central control over
all of our strings, provided no pesky toe rag goes off and tries to
access PlayerPrefs dot anything [Laughs]
like that, we're always going to go through our manager. Congratulations, this is an awesome topic, and we'll see you soon!