Hey welcome back so it's time to get our options
screen working properly. In this video we're
going to introduce UI sliders. and both volume
and difficulty sliders. Create ourselves an
options controller.cs script and ensure that
it all works properly. So I'm going to start
with the volume. I'm going to help you with
the volume. and then I'm going to challenge
you in a little bit to get the difficulty
sliders working yourself.
So. let's go ahead and customise this scene.
Now you're welcome to customise your scene
how you like. I'm just going to make a few
changes to mine and then we'll add the sliders.
So My changes are going to be the title is
just going to become options for me. the subtitle
is going to be nothing actually. I'm going
to use the subtitle for volume. I'm going
to rename it volume label. like that and then
change the UI element with my 'T' key and
then move it down.
Now I'm going to choose to have may back button
all left aligned an right down at the bottom
of the screen like that. I'm going to choose
to put my defaults somewhere else. somewhere
like that. and then I'm going to duplicate
my volume label and call it difficulty label
and move the guy down. something like that;
and then just manually change the value. Nothing
too difficult there. apart from I need to
make it large enough... di-fi-cul-ty. vol-ume.
Perfect. OK so I thin that that looks reasonably
good as a screen. now what we want to do is
start adding our game object UI slider component.
that's where it is in the menus. OK? Pop that
in. straight away move it to where you want
it and name it volume slider. OK. I'n not
actually going to do the difficulty slider
at all I'm going to completely leave that
to you. So let's just make this volume slider
large enough. I'm actually going to chose
its size based on the bottom here. because
I don't want to encroach on the tree too much.
So in fact I'm already crowding the fox. the
fox needs a bit more space. so ok. if that
was the difficulty slider it would be fine
so I'm going to move it up to the volume's
position. and then you can do the difficulty
slider later. So let's see how this slider
works. When you play you can just slide it.
Good that. isn't it? Just like it says on
the tin; and as you slide it. if you look
at the slider volume properties you'll see
here that we have a value. in fact changing
the value in the inspector also moves it in
the game so scene. hopefully you can see that;
and we have a choice over the maximum and
minimum value. you could set the maximum value
to four.
Of course it will still go from fully left
to fully right but now the top represents
four - it's a float. They're always floats
these guys. Alright? When I stop playing it
reverts to one. because all changes in play
mode are obviously not saved. So now we have
a volume slider in place. the question is
how are we going to write the value of that
to PlayerPrefs? Well. I think that it's appropriate
to have a separate object in this scene called
the Options controller. So I think that's
a good architecture. I'm going to reset this
thing's transform and add a dedicated script
to it called Options Controller. it's very
clear what that does.
Just tidy your scripts up. and let's get in
the options controller and think how it's
going to work. So what's the general pattern?
We are going to come into the options. it
want to load into the sliders the moment we
come in whatever's in the PlayerPrefs. and
then whatever value we set. when we click
back. we want to save to the PlayerPrefs.
so it's going to need access to a level manager.
which we don't yet have so let's put a level
manager into this scene. because we're going
to need an instance of it to wire up. with
no auto-load that's perfect.
So it needs a level manager. we'll need a
music manager if we're going to be able to
hear the effect of changing volume but the
music manager only exists in the splash screen.
but we can confidently assume that it will
be here in the options screen provided we
started in the splash screen and we'll find
the music manager. but it's still going to
work if you can't find it it's just that you
won't be able to hear what's going on; and
then what else do we need in this scene? What
else does this need access to? It needs access
to the sliders themselves.
So let's get into the script and start doing
it. so a few things; first thing we're going
to need. well it's not really in any order.
public slider volume slider. Now slider doesn't
come up in the list; why? Why can I not auto-complete
slider at the moment? No matter what I do.
even if I type it right. it's not going to
work. we need using UnityEngine.UI we need
to User Interface word space. Great. so public
slider volume slider. there he is. So now
we have a slider we can drag in. let's take
a look at it. there it is. Drag the slider
in off we go.
Fantastic. step one done. what else did I
say we needed? We need a level manager. OK.
save it. drag the level manager in. So the
level manager is wired up. cool. so we can
now change levels. What are we going to do
about the music manager? Well let's have a
private music manager in here. OK and then
on start let's find the music manager that's
almost inevitably in the scene. So it's music
manager equals. we've done this plenty of
times. GameObject.FindObjectOfType()
and it's a method; and let's just make sure
we are finding this music manager. let's just
Debug.Log what we've got.
OK. so if we now run this we should get an
error saying null; well not error. just null.
there is no music manager alright? However.
if we were to run from the splash screen all
the way through persistent music is there.
persistent music is there. persistent music
is here and then it logs out persistent music
music manager. Alright? So that's all working
fine. we're finding the music manager providing
we start from the splash screen. Fan-diddly-an-tastic
so. what do we need to do next?
Well. when we hit this back button over on
the options scene. we need to call something
different. We're not just going to call the
level manager and go straight back to the
start. we need to call something like save
and exit so let's call it that. Public void
SaveAndExit. OK and what's save and exit going
to do? Well. it's going to go to PlayerPrefsManager
and it's going to set the master volume to
volumeSlider.Value; and then it's going to
say levelManager.LoadLevel and now it's going
to go back to the start. Does that make sense?
it's going to save and exit; and later of
course we;re going to have a line in here
where you are going to save the difficulty.
That's fine. so. let's wire that back button
now to our new entity. Back Button. wired
into our options controller like so. dragging
the options controller onto the On Click event
of the back button's button script in the
inspector. Now choose Option Controller's
save and exit. Let's see what happens. Back.
well it comes out. which is great. but whether
or not it wrote the PlayerPrefs. well. we
don't know yet. because we haven't done quite
the other half of it. So let's look back at
the options controller that's great so we
can save and exit.
When we start. once we've found the music
manager. what else would make sense? Well
it would make sense to set the volume slider
to... I'll leave a little bit of space here...
volume slider's value to PlayerPrefManager.GetMasterVolume()
just set it to the master volume. Great so
let's try it. make sure that the value gets
saved. So we turn the volume down. we go back.
we go to options. it's down where it was.
you go up you go back it's down now the crucial
thing is here - oh. it didn't seem to save
there you see I put it up. I go back. go to
options... Oh it has saved that's fine.
Just check again. put it in the middle. back.
and options. Great. it's saving it and it
would save even if we stop the game let's
put it somewhere here. just slightly under
the top. back. back to commit it to player
prefs; stop playing the game. play the game
again and you see it's remembered it even
between play sessions this is stored persistently
in the storage of the device. Great eh? Pretty
cool. So now you have the structure that you
need. Now what I don't like is that I can't
hear the music change - if you notice if we
were to start from the splash screen and if
you do this on yours and you listen for the
music. if you get into the options as we drag
music nothing happens as we drag; so what
I want is that I want this to actually change
the music levels.
So how are we going to do that? Well. we've
got a music manager so it's not actually too
challenging to do this what we can do is on
every single frame actually we can say music
manager... dot change volume oh... we don't
have a change volume method. but it would
be nice if we did wouldn't it? What would
we set it to? Well we'd set it to the volume
slider value. OK. so as a little challenge
for you why don't you go write change volume
inside music manager? It's going to be a pretty
simple method. Go and have a go. are you pausing
the video and having a go or are you waiting
for me to show you how?
I bet you're pausing the video and having
a go... but you can't be otherwise you wouldn't
hear me... OK come on let's just get in there
and do it. So over in music manager we need
a public method right? Otherwise nothing else
can see it. It's not going to return anything.
it's going to be change volume. and it's going
to take in a float. So float... volume...
like that. and then when it receives message
what is it going to do? Well it's going to
go AudioSource.volume = volume. Simple. It
provides a method to change that volume so
back here in options controller change volume
now works; if you don't like change volume
and you want it to be set volume you can actually
change it right here by clicking control or
command "r" and you can just change it to
set volume and click OK. and look at this
it has changed the music manager as well.
as long as you save your scripts. OK it's
pretty cool. right? Now let's try it. starting
from the splash scene. We've purposefully
reduced that delay. that's working a treat
for me. and when I play a second time. the
start scene's just as loud as it was and that's
by choice. but this is exactly where I left
it. Now. about that start scene being as loud
as it was remember. on the start scene we
had a load sound with a hard-wired volume
in here. well I've left it at point nought
four. I'm actually long term going to recommend
that it's at about point five and we could
modify our music manager script to allow for
the master volume to affect this but I actually
don't want for the master volume to affect
this. you know when you first open an app
on say the iPad for example. and you hear
an intro sound that's a really good time to
set your system volume appropriately; you
know is it late at night or is it a loud environment;
and if that's always the same volume then
it gives you an idea about where you are;
if it's really loud then you know it's your
system volume that's too loud. or if it's
just right but when you get into the game
it's too quiet then you're going to know straight
away to go into options and change the volume.
So that's a design choice that we're going
to allow that first one to be fixed and then
everything else to change. Hopefully that
makes sense. Cool. so now let's just recap.
what did I say we were going to do? We're
going to introduce UI sliders. hopefully that's
done. they're just little things that set
a float value in the inspector and you can
have programmatic access to those values.
Add volume and difficulty sliders; well. you're
getting the job of the difficulty one. Create
OptionsController well I've done that and
check they work; I've kind of done that.
So I want you to get Difficulty options working.
I need you to change the check in the PlayerPreferencesManager.
currently it says taht difficulty is between
zero and one. we you want difficulty to be
between one and three inclusive because the
next thing that you can do with your difficulty
slider is that you can actually set it to
whole numbers and you can say I want it to
have a value between one and three that'll
give a nice snapping effect of kind of easy.
medium and hard and you won't even need to
write the words because it's going to be so
obvious to the player that that's what's going
on but you're going t need to change your
check on PlayerPrefsManager.
Follow exactly the same pattern as I did for
the volume load and save and just check it
all works so I'd like you to put a Debug statement
on some script in level one and just check
by calling the PlayerPrefsManager. check that
the difficulty is actually being set when
you go ll the way through to the game. So
go ahead. pause the video. spend some time
and do that now and I'll see you when you've
cracked it. Or not and need some help. See
you in a mo.
OK. so let's get this done quite quickly.
In the options menu then we need to take the
volume slider and duplicate it. going to drag
that down. zoom in so I can see that it's
lined up with the word difficulty. the blue
snap lines will show when you're centrally
aligned. That's no longer the volume slider.
that's the difficulty slider. OK. now the
values. this is what we are talking about.
Minimum value one. maximum value three whole
numbers. Watch what this does. It gives you
a nice snap. isn't that cool. OK? That's fantastic.
we're getting object reference not set that's
because of the Music player. that's not a
problem.
So now what do we need to do in the options
controller in order to make this difficulty
saving work? Well. before we go into that
I said that I'd give you the hint that we
need to go into the PlayerPrefs manager and
there's a couple of things that I want to
do I want to allow volume to be zero and I
want to allow volume to be one. so that when
the slider is at the top and bottom we don't
get an error. and then when it comes to setting
the difficulty I want the difficulty range
to be one to three inclusive now. we're just
changing the whole API. we're changing the
way that we've decided to do it. OK so back
over in the options controller. your job is
relatively simple here.
What you're going to do is unload. you're
just going to go difficulty. hopefully you've
already done this. difficulty slider. Now
you don't have a difficulty slider. I'm going
to declare mine right here. OK I'm just going
to call mine diff slider there he is. and
I'm immediately going to save and drag that
difficulty slider in to my options controller.
So options controller. drag it in as soon
as it starts asking for it one moment. It's
not asking because I've left a d in the script.
The script needs to be able to build in order
for you to be able to drag things into it.
There you go. it's asking for the difficulty
slider now. so I've just dragged it across.
Back to the script. now it's quite simple.
diffSlider.value = PlayerPrefsManager.GetDifficulty()
very very similar pattern to before fantastic.
What are we going to do on Update? Do we need
to be setting the volume or the difficulty?
Is there an equivalent here for the difficulty?
No. there isn't. Then on the way out what
do we do? We go PlayerPrefsManager.SetDifficulty
and then we give it the difficulty slider
value and there it is. Absolutely fantastic
so we are pretty much good to go let's check
that this is working now. so my difficulty
is on one or what I call low if I put it there
and go back to options. set it to medium.
back. back to options.
OK? And if you want to test that this is persisting
through. you can then go to your level one
scene. and you could drop a script on one
of these options and just print it out. but
I'm not going to bother. I'm pretty happy
that's going to work. What I am going to do
is test it from the splash screen one final
time. Options. hear my music getting louder
and quieter. set my difficulty. and then that's
it. Now the defaults button is the very final
thing to crack. and that's pretty simple.
all we'll do is we'll have a set defaults
method - Oh that was fun. let's go back to
source OK.
So we'll have a public void SetDefaults and
that set defaults method is just going to
hard code in what we want. So we're going
to have Volume Slider. we're going to have
the default of eighty percent and a default
difficulty of two in the middle; and the final
thing that we're going to do is wire the button
to set defaults. so that defaults button on
your options scene. I'm going to show you
that code that I did so quickly in a moment.
I'm going to wire it and then I'll show you
the code.
So hang on a second. the defaults button I'm
just going to wire to the options controller.
the function is going to be set defaults.
OK? Let's test it works then I'll show you
the code. Move some things around. set defaults.
look off we go. Beautiful. So here's your
code. set defaults simply says volume slider
is point eight and diff slider is two. Isn't
that cool? You have options fully working.
congratulations on huge progress. nice architecture.
and we are now ready to dive in to the level
one and start actually putting animated characters
into our scene.
So it's the start of a new chapter. see you
soon.