Hey Welcome back. so this is a ratio math primer. in this
video will be looking at the
fundamentals of ratio math or maths
in England; what screen aspect ratios
mean and how to convert between
different aspects so here it is in
summary: so let's start with a pretty
common thing which is a 4:3 screen. the
old fashioned screen resolution of
televisions but also found in some
devices like iPads and the like so what
does a 4:3 screen mean? Well it simply
means that you've got four units of
something one way - they could be
centimeters. they could be a 40 pixels. it
could be whatever - by three in the other
direction... just draw that a little more evenly. Something
like that
okay and then that is cool four colon
three. so it's a fraction four colon
three is the same as 4/3 which is the
same as for over 3 like that which is
the same as about 1.3 or one and a
third OK. 1 33333... or the mathematicians
might like to write it 1.3
recurring. Alright so that's what a 4:3
screen is what happens if we have a 16:9
screen how do we get from 4:3 to 16:9 and
then how do we become fluid at translating
between the two? So I'm going to use red to
represent the 16:9 screen. Well if we have
three squares vertically one way to get
to 9 would be to divide each of these
three into three. so if we just do that
then suddenly we have nine vertically
now. and then if we're going to divide
one way we'd better divide the other way by three
so that we're doing the same thing
both ways and that's a common thing in
algebra is you're doing the same thing
to both sides of an equation. that's
what we're doing by dividing the screen
the same both ways. So now if we look at
the Red we have 12 along this way but
still nine this way so that's fine but
the ratio of this screen is still 4:3. So
how do we get it to 16:9? Well. we have
12:9 red squares. we need to extend the
red out
by two on either side don't we. so we have 12.
13. 14 and then on the right hand side we
have 15. 16. so now this new screen has a
ratio of 16 to 9 which is a different
ratio to 4:3. OK so just before I give you a
quick challeng I want to show you another
trick which helps understanding how to
do ratio maths a little bit easier. which
is that if I said to you well
scale 11 by 4:3 in the ratio 4:3
and it's always like do I multiply by 4 and divide by 3
or the other way round well just think
do you want it to get bigger or smaller?
If you want it to get smaller then multiply by
three and divide by 4. and if you
want it to get bigger then multiply by
4 - the bigger thing - and divide by
3. So that's a pretty easy way of
saying look if I want to put something
through a ratio - change something by a
ratio - then just think to yourself do
I need the thing to get bigger or smaller. if I
say another awkward number like
seventeen and I want you to make it bigger in
the ratio 16 : 9 well then
multiply it by the bigger number and
divide it by the smaller number. OK if you
want to get smaller in the ratio of 16
to 9 then multiply it by the smaller number
and divide by the bigger number.
Hopefully that makes sense and that's
quite a useful rule of thumb. it's certainly
the way I think about scaling things
through a ratio. Fantastic I have a quick
simple challenge for you. I want you to calculate
the screen for me. if a 16:9 screen is four
centimetres high. how wide is it? show
your reasoning in the discussions. Just
waiting for me to show you are you?
OK. welcome back so it's pretty simple you've
got a 16:9 screen. it's four centimetres
high. how wide is it? Well I like to write
the units in.
so four centimetres. Now is it getting
bigger or smaller? Just draw yourself a
sketch if you're not sure. It's a 16:9 screen. it's
four centimeters high. The width is going to
be bigger than the height right so we
multiply by 16 it doesn't have any units
and divide by nine and then you just
have to do that calculation which is
sixty-four over nine which is and that's
when we just grab a calculator... 16
sorry 64 / 9 is 7.1 Now how many significant
figures do quote this to? Well we only
started by telling you it was a four
centimeters wide screen so really seven
centimeters is good enough I'd let you
get away with 7.1 but any more than that and
you're giving me more information back
than I gave you. I only said it was four
centimeters wide so seven is good enough.
Learn to be easy on the decimal places
or significant figures. So up here in
the top right of this is your solution
to your challenge. about seven
centimetres wide and congratulations if you
got that right I'll see you in the next
where we'll be setting up world space UI
canvas.