Hey guys and welcome to a new chapter in
this game. We're gonna do some animation at
last. We're gonna talk about what a sprite
sheet is. also known as a sprite Atlas. we're gonna
make a comparison to bone based
animation; we're gonna import and slice
sprite sheets and then make our first
animation. So what is a sprite sheet? Well
if you go to google images and search
for sprite sheet these things are all
sprite sheets. they're frames of animation.
Remember the old flip books? I'll just
search for flip book... this type of thing
where you flick through. it turns out if
your brain sees more than about 24
still images a second it blends them all
together and that's how they discovered
and made movies so that's the basis of a
sprite sheet animation. The other type of
animation that we've got and we're gonna
be using a lot more in 3d in unity is
bone based animation. so on the left you
have a character from an open source
project called dragon bones and he
has all his limbs separate and then what you
can do is use pivot points like sticking
a pin through pieces of card and then
have these bits of the body move
relative to one another. So that is bone
based on the left
sprite sheet or sprite atlas animation is on
the right. and that's where you have
multiple frames of an animation all laid out
on one sheet like that. Normally they're in
a regular grid. this guy this Ninja isn't
in a regular grid actually but normally
they would be. So how would you find
yourself a sprite sheet? Well for this
game I'm going to use the sprite sheets
from glitch again. If we scroll down to
actually get to be on the home page to
get to the assets... Glitch the game you've
got downloads but you've also got see all
details and downloads. from there you can
get to a full sprite sheet. it's very big. three
hundred and odd meg. So you could download
that and pick a sprite sheet. you can pick the sprite I use from the
course assets or you could just go to
google images and just search for sprite
sheet. Or sprite
atlas and you will end up with things
like this. and they will normally be in a
regular grid like this girl. The other
thing you want to look for is the fact it's
on a transparent background indicated by
the hash. OK so once you've got one of
these sprite sheets how would you work
out how to import it? How would we get it into unity
Well let's take a look I'm gonna do that
with my chosen asset right now so
import new asset. I've got this glitch
PNGs folder here and I've still got a
bunch of things I'm interested in using.
foxes and all the rest of it and one of
these guys is a deimaginator and he has
an appear animation so let's use that.
So when your spreadsheet first comes in
it's just gonna be treated as a single
sprite and it isn't a single sprite so
we need to go up to the inspector. make
sure that the texture type is sprite. and
then that the sprite mode is multiple.
Now click sprite editor and you'll open
up something like this. Now how we gonna
get all these guys out we don't do it
manually so that's actually a slice
option at the top left and we can go to
grid. And it's going to say what's the
pixel size of these boxes? Well. good
question. you've got to go work that out
So how are you going to work it out?
Well here's the basic formula for
working it out. what we want to do is.
assuming there's no padding and grid
sheets normally have no padding then the
width is the image width divided by the
columns and the height is the image
height divided by the rows.
So what does that actually mean? Well
let's look at this image; I'll look at it in
my system. whatever your default image
editor is. and go to the inspector on the Mac
or if you're on a PC just ask your image
editor what size is this sheet and
it's saying it's 753 by 1674 pixels. so
what I tend to do he was just open up a
calculator and then have this image size
visible on the screen
753 divided by one. two three columns
251. so it's 251 pixels wide. I'll just keep a note of
that for the moment 251 and then what is
the height 1674 divided by 1. 2. 3. 4. 5. 6. 7. 8. 9 so
1674 over 9... 186. 251 / 186 so over in your
sprite editor slice grid 251. 186. slice
and they've laid their sheet out in a nice way
so look it's perfect. if we scroll in each
frame is its own box. and yes the guy
moves to the left but he's supposed to. he's
jumping into the scene. there's no padding. it
all works just fine. click Apply; and then
close your sprite editor. Now. let's take a look
what've we got here? Look at that. when you click the
little arrow every frame of this
animation is separately now shown when
you unpack that sprite like that. isn't that
cool? I think it is. so that's how you
work it out. you just basically say how
many are there wide. how many are there high and do the division. Pretty simple. so what I want
you to do now is pause the video
Find yourself a sprite
sheet it doesn't have to be the one I've
used. it doesn't even have to be from
Glitch it can be from anywhere. and calculate
your own grid width and height and import and slice your
own sprite sheet. So go ahead. pause the video and do that now please.
OK. so now you've got all the frames of
animation set up I bet just dying to
make this little guy move. Me too. Some of
you may already know there's a shortcut
to this which is to select all of these
frames and drag them into the hier archy
but don't do that because it just does
too much in one go and you won't have
the basic understanding plus it tends to
mess things up a little bit in terms of
where everything where everything sits
and how things are related you can do
that later once you understand what's
going on but let me take you through the
first principles first OK. of how we're gonna set
this up. So what we need to do first is
say well we need a  game object. so let's
just have an empty GameObject. let's
call it lizard and let's just leave him where
he is. Now don't worry about how these
things sit relative to the game space at
all. in fact in this video we are
not going to make these sprites sit
properly on the game space. we need to
make a serious change to the level
camvas shortly. as you'll see. So I'm just going
to put my lizard GameObject at the
origin like that and then double click
on it to frame it
fantastic so let's take one of these
frames and use that as the avatar
for the animation it would be helpful to
use a frame where you can kind of see
what's going on; so the last frame's not
particularly helpful. the first frame is
not particularly helpful. typically
something in the middle is quite helpful
Here if you drag that onto your lizard.
then look and see what's happened it's
actually created a new object with a
sprite renderer so one way of doing it
but it's pretty messy cuz you got a new
sub-object on your lizard there. so I would
prefer that you went to your lizard and
manually just add a sprite renderer so we
know what we're doing. then grab a
frame. a single sprite. drop it onto the
sprite renderer and double click the lizard to
frame it. don't worry about the fact he's
crazy scale compared to the background
move it away from the background if you
wish. there he is OK. so there you just
have a lizard which only has a sprite
renderer with one of these sprites on it.
Fantastic. that is a great starting point.
so what comes next?
Well next we need to add an animator so if we go
to the component menu and have a look
through and see what we've got. and you start
typing anima- you're gonna get animation
and animator. we want the animator. The animation
system is being phased out. So
use the animator. So now you've got an
animator. We'll do absolutely nothing
quite yet. because what you need is an
animation controller next. so let's
collapse down our sprite. make ourselves a
folder called animations
go into it and then go to assets or
right-click in here and say create
animation controller and it's an
animation controller for the lizard
there we are now if you double-click
into that. what have we got? We have any
state at the moment. that's it. It just has a...
no animation states. I'll explain that
in a moment.
Pop back to your lizard. Now if you
click on your lizard. where it's asking
for an animation controller you can now
drag your new blank animation controller
in to him. OK. that's fantastic.
Now what we need to do is we need to
create an animation state. and that's
going to be his appearing in the scene
state. At the moment there are no states
Firstly I want to reorganize my workspace I'm
going to put my animator down the
bottom which is my state diagram in
future this will go from any state to
appear to walking to attacking to
walking again. It's going to be that kind
of loop as you saw in lazer defender and
at the top I'm gonna create a new
window which is my animation window I'm
going to dock that up next to game. So this new
layout here I may as well save. right? Save
layout and call it
animation and if you want a different
layout of windows. knock yourself out. You
have multiple screens. do what you like.
This is how I need to do it for this
recording. Great. so let's recap we've got a
lizard with a sprite renderer.
one of the frames just as a placeholder
and an animation with this animation controller on
it. Now we need to actually add an
animation clip. which is the thing that
makes him move. you click on the lizard
first. very important. In the
animation window click this little drop
down here and then you'll see create new
clip. You see that? It's actually an unlabeled drop
down. Right once you click on Create new
clip this is where it says create new
animation for the game object lizard. fine
let's do that let's call it
lizard appearing. That's very simple and we have a
state called lizard appearing. its orange
which means it's the default state
and we have a line in our animation for
this clip. We are nearly there
we've nearly created ourselves an animation.
So. go back to your images. open up your
dude. select all of his animation frames
and drop them. like so. onto the animation.
You can see in the animation timeline a tiny
indication of of the animation playing
through in time. In fact if you scroll
your mouse wheel you can zoom in and pan
and you can see all of the frames.
Fantastic. it's not actually jumping to the
right it's just that it's showing one
frame after the other
now at the moment you have probably come
by default into animation recording mode
you see there's a record button here and
all of the play pause and next step but tons
have gone red. that's 'cause the
animator's now expecting you to start
playing with the animation in the scene
view and recording what we call
key frames but we're not going to be
doing that quite yet so come out of
recording mode by clicking the record
button. now your red play is no longer
a play. Now I just want to preview the
animation to finish this video so how are we
gonna preview the animation? Click on the
animator and then on your lizard
and click play
let's just take a look. go back to the scene
view... there he is. he's jumping. So in the scene
view if you frame on your lizard and you
can see in the animation state
Controller you see it's looping around
jump jump jump jump fantastic. There's
another way to preview this guy as well.
you can stop playing - you don't even have
to be in play mode - double-click
lizard appearing and you should at the bottom of your
inspector. once you've double-click that
state. have a preview panel; if you don't
you'll be able to bring it up from the bottom.
Now it's gonna say no model is available
for the preview. well give it a model.
drag the lizard on. OK. now it's almost uselessly
small but preview it and then you can
use the right mouse button drag to turn
it round. look from either side. there you go.
you can see the preview now why is it so
damn fast? Well.
this speed here is the speed of the
preview. the speed I'm changing in the
inspector. That's not going to indicate
how fast it's actually gonna run the
reason it's too fast is this setting up
here . At the top of our animation window
we have sixty samples which means it's
assuming this animation was drawn at 60
frames or samples a second. Well let's change
that down to maybe twelve. and you can
immediately see the effect in the
preview window down the bottom right
here he's now jumping in too slowly I
would say. that looks a bit silly so
let's just change the samples up until
it looks right.
Ideally would ask your artist how fast
it should be. 24 frames maybe try 30. now here
we're just gonna have to pick something that
you think looks good but I think 30
frame animations will look fine. it looks
like this is set up to be around about
that. Now because you change the samples per
second here in your animation. when you
go back to the scene and play - you'll have to go
back to scene of course. there you go -
his speed has changed and you're looping
around the lizard appearing animation
state. Before you run off and create too
many animations like this just hold your
horses a moment and wait a few videos
because I'm going to show you that we
actually need to structure both our
animator and our sprite a little bit
differently in this game to get the
flexibility we need. so just create this
single animation for now and we will add
the others
a little bit later with my guidance. So to recap.
this is how you do it
You create an empty GameObject. you drag one of
the sprites on as a placeholder better to
actually add a sprite renderer and drag
the sprite to the sprite renderer
add an animator - animations are being
phased out - go into to the animation window
and then create a new clip and go from
there
Fantastic. remember this slide is
available for you. all of the slides are
available at the start of the section.
just download them under your section
notes. now it's time for you to make your
animation. Make and preview your own; make
sure the frame rate. the samples is
correct and don't worry about it fitting
in the game window for now. it will not
sit properly on this level canvas because our level
canvas is not set up right right now.
See you soon.
=======
Kind: captions
Language: en
Hey guys and welcome to a new chapter in
this game. We're gonna do some animation at
last. We're gonna talk about what a sprite
sheet is, also known as a sprite Atlas, we're gonna
make a comparison to bone based
animation; we're gonna import and slice
sprite sheets and then make our first
animation. So what is a sprite sheet? Well
if you go to google images and search
for sprite sheet these things are all
sprite sheets, they're frames of animation.
Remember the old flip books? I'll just
search for flip book... this type of thing
where you flick through, it turns out if
your brain sees more than about 24
still images a second it blends them all
together and that's how they discovered
and made movies so that's the basis of a
sprite sheet animation. The other type of
animation that we've got and we're gonna
be using a lot more in 3d in unity is
bone based animation, so on the left you
have a character from an open source
project called dragon bones and he
has all his limbs separate and then what you
can do is use pivot points like sticking
a pin through pieces of card and then
have these bits of the body move
relative to one another. So that is bone
based on the left
sprite sheet or sprite atlas animation is on
the right, and that's where you have
multiple frames of an animation all laid out
on one sheet like that. Normally they're in
a regular grid, this guy this Ninja isn't
in a regular grid actually but normally
they would be. So how would you find
yourself a sprite sheet? Well for this
game I'm going to use the sprite sheets
from glitch again. If we scroll down to
actually get to be on the home page to
get to the assets... Glitch the game you've
got downloads but you've also got see all
details and downloads, from there you can
get to a full sprite sheet, it's very big, three
hundred and odd meg. So you could download
that and pick a sprite sheet, you can pick the sprite I use from the
course assets or you could just go to
google images and just search for sprite
sheet. Or sprite
atlas and you will end up with things
like this, and they will normally be in a
regular grid like this girl. The other
thing you want to look for is the fact it's
on a transparent background indicated by
the hash. OK so once you've got one of
these sprite sheets how would you work
out how to import it? How would we get it into unity
Well let's take a look I'm gonna do that
with my chosen asset right now so
import new asset, I've got this glitch
PNGs folder here and I've still got a
bunch of things I'm interested in using,
foxes and all the rest of it and one of
these guys is a deimaginator and he has
an appear animation so let's use that.
So when your spreadsheet first comes in
it's just gonna be treated as a single
sprite and it isn't a single sprite so
we need to go up to the inspector, make
sure that the texture type is sprite, and
then that the sprite mode is multiple.
Now click sprite editor and you'll open
up something like this. Now how we gonna
get all these guys out we don't do it
manually so that's actually a slice
option at the top left and we can go to
grid. And it's going to say what's the
pixel size of these boxes? Well, good
question, you've got to go work that out
So how are you going to work it out?
Well here's the basic formula for
working it out, what we want to do is,
assuming there's no padding and grid
sheets normally have no padding then the
width is the image width divided by the
columns and the height is the image
height divided by the rows.
So what does that actually mean? Well
let's look at this image; I'll look at it in
my system, whatever your default image
editor is, and go to the inspector on the Mac
or if you're on a PC just ask your image
editor what size is this sheet and
it's saying it's 753 by 1674 pixels, so
what I tend to do he was just open up a
calculator and then have this image size
visible on the screen
753 divided by one, two three columns
251. so it's 251 pixels wide, I'll just keep a note of
that for the moment 251 and then what is
the height 1674 divided by 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9 so
1674 over 9... 186. 251 / 186 so over in your
sprite editor slice grid 251, 186, slice
and they've laid their sheet out in a nice way
so look it's perfect, if we scroll in each
frame is its own box, and yes the guy
moves to the left but he's supposed to, he's
jumping into the scene, there's no padding, it
all works just fine, click Apply; and then
close your sprite editor. Now, let's take a look
what've we got here? Look at that, when you click the
little arrow every frame of this
animation is separately now shown when
you unpack that sprite like that, isn't that
cool? I think it is, so that's how you
work it out, you just basically say how
many are there wide, how many are there high and do the division. Pretty simple, so what I want
you to do now is pause the video
Find yourself a sprite
sheet it doesn't have to be the one I've
used, it doesn't even have to be from
Glitch it can be from anywhere, and calculate
your own grid width and height and import and slice your
own sprite sheet. So go ahead, pause the video and do that now please.
OK, so now you've got all the frames of
animation set up I bet just dying to
make this little guy move. Me too. Some of
you may already know there's a shortcut
to this which is to select all of these
frames and drag them into the hier archy
but don't do that because it just does
too much in one go and you won't have
the basic understanding plus it tends to
mess things up a little bit in terms of
where everything where everything sits
and how things are related you can do
that later once you understand what's
going on but let me take you through the
first principles first OK, of how we're gonna set
this up. So what we need to do first is
say well we need a  game object, so let's
just have an empty GameObject, let's
call it lizard and let's just leave him where
he is. Now don't worry about how these
things sit relative to the game space at
all, in fact in this video we are
not going to make these sprites sit
properly on the game space, we need to
make a serious change to the level
camvas shortly, as you'll see. So I'm just going
to put my lizard GameObject at the
origin like that and then double click
on it to frame it
fantastic so let's take one of these
frames and use that as the avatar
for the animation it would be helpful to
use a frame where you can kind of see
what's going on; so the last frame's not
particularly helpful, the first frame is
not particularly helpful, typically
something in the middle is quite helpful
Here if you drag that onto your lizard,
then look and see what's happened it's
actually created a new object with a
sprite renderer so one way of doing it
but it's pretty messy cuz you got a new
sub-object on your lizard there, so I would
prefer that you went to your lizard and
manually just add a sprite renderer so we
know what we're doing, then grab a
frame, a single sprite, drop it onto the
sprite renderer and double click the lizard to
frame it, don't worry about the fact he's
crazy scale compared to the background
move it away from the background if you
wish, there he is OK, so there you just
have a lizard which only has a sprite
renderer with one of these sprites on it.
Fantastic, that is a great starting point,
so what comes next?
Well next we need to add an animator so if we go
to the component menu and have a look
through and see what we've got, and you start
typing anima- you're gonna get animation
and animator. we want the animator. The animation
system is being phased out. So
use the animator. So now you've got an
animator. We'll do absolutely nothing
quite yet, because what you need is an
animation controller next, so let's
collapse down our sprite, make ourselves a
folder called animations
go into it and then go to assets or
right-click in here and say create
animation controller and it's an
animation controller for the lizard
there we are now if you double-click
into that, what have we got? We have any
state at the moment, that's it. It just has a...
no animation states, I'll explain that
in a moment.
Pop back to your lizard. Now if you
click on your lizard, where it's asking
for an animation controller you can now
drag your new blank animation controller
in to him. OK, that's fantastic.
Now what we need to do is we need to
create an animation state, and that's
going to be his appearing in the scene
state. At the moment there are no states
Firstly I want to reorganize my workspace I'm
going to put my animator down the
bottom which is my state diagram in
future this will go from any state to
appear to walking to attacking to
walking again. It's going to be that kind
of loop as you saw in lazer defender and
at the top I'm gonna create a new
window which is my animation window I'm
going to dock that up next to game. So this new
layout here I may as well save, right? Save
layout and call it
animation and if you want a different
layout of windows, knock yourself out. You
have multiple screens, do what you like.
This is how I need to do it for this
recording. Great, so let's recap we've got a
lizard with a sprite renderer,
one of the frames just as a placeholder
and an animation with this animation controller on
it. Now we need to actually add an
animation clip, which is the thing that
makes him move, you click on the lizard
first, very important. In the
animation window click this little drop
down here and then you'll see create new
clip. You see that? It's actually an unlabeled drop
down. Right once you click on Create new
clip this is where it says create new
animation for the game object lizard, fine
let's do that let's call it
lizard appearing. That's very simple and we have a
state called lizard appearing, its orange
which means it's the default state
and we have a line in our animation for
this clip. We are nearly there
we've nearly created ourselves an animation.
So, go back to your images, open up your
dude, select all of his animation frames
and drop them, like so, onto the animation.
You can see in the animation timeline a tiny
indication of of the animation playing
through in time. In fact if you scroll
your mouse wheel you can zoom in and pan
and you can see all of the frames.
Fantastic, it's not actually jumping to the
right it's just that it's showing one
frame after the other
now at the moment you have probably come
by default into animation recording mode
you see there's a record button here and
all of the play pause and next step but tons
have gone red, that's 'cause the
animator's now expecting you to start
playing with the animation in the scene
view and recording what we call
key frames but we're not going to be
doing that quite yet so come out of
recording mode by clicking the record
button, now your red play is no longer
a play. Now I just want to preview the
animation to finish this video so how are we
gonna preview the animation? Click on the
animator and then on your lizard
and click play
let's just take a look, go back to the scene
view... there he is, he's jumping. So in the scene
view if you frame on your lizard and you
can see in the animation state
Controller you see it's looping around
jump jump jump jump fantastic. There's
another way to preview this guy as well,
you can stop playing - you don't even have
to be in play mode - double-click
lizard appearing and you should at the bottom of your
inspector, once you've double-click that
state, have a preview panel; if you don't
you'll be able to bring it up from the bottom.
Now it's gonna say no model is available
for the preview, well give it a model,
drag the lizard on. OK, now it's almost uselessly
small but preview it and then you can
use the right mouse button drag to turn
it round, look from either side, there you go,
you can see the preview now why is it so
damn fast? Well,
this speed here is the speed of the
preview, the speed I'm changing in the
inspector. That's not going to indicate
how fast it's actually gonna run the
reason it's too fast is this setting up
here . At the top of our animation window
we have sixty samples which means it's
assuming this animation was drawn at 60
frames or samples a second. Well let's change
that down to maybe twelve, and you can
immediately see the effect in the
preview window down the bottom right
here he's now jumping in too slowly I
would say, that looks a bit silly so
let's just change the samples up until
it looks right.
Ideally would ask your artist how fast
it should be, 24 frames maybe try 30, now here
we're just gonna have to pick something that
you think looks good but I think 30
frame animations will look fine, it looks
like this is set up to be around about
that. Now because you change the samples per
second here in your animation, when you
go back to the scene and play - you'll have to go
back to scene of course, there you go -
his speed has changed and you're looping
around the lizard appearing animation
state. Before you run off and create too
many animations like this just hold your
horses a moment and wait a few videos
because I'm going to show you that we
actually need to structure both our
animator and our sprite a little bit
differently in this game to get the
flexibility we need, so just create this
single animation for now and we will add
the others
a little bit later with my guidance. So to recap,
this is how you do it
You create an empty GameObject, you drag one of
the sprites on as a placeholder better to
actually add a sprite renderer and drag
the sprite to the sprite renderer
add an animator - animations are being
phased out - go into to the animation window
and then create a new clip and go from
there
Fantastic, remember this slide is
available for you, all of the slides are
available at the start of the section,
just download them under your section
notes, now it's time for you to make your
animation. Make and preview your own; make
sure the frame rate, the samples is
correct and don't worry about it fitting
in the game window for now, it will not
sit properly on this level canvas because our level
canvas is not set up right right now.
See you soon.
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1:Unity/Section7/GG13 Sprite Sheet Animation.srt