Time to start getting a little
animated lizard dude and our background
level canvas talking to each other. So
previously we set the level canvas to a
screen space overlay but we actually
want it to be a world space canvas
because the grass is actually part of
the world space and we want them to
integrate together so set your canvas
to world space and then what we're gonna
work towards is a situation where each of
these square grass blocks are perfectly
square have one world unit per block. and
a nice coordinate system where the
bottom left grass square on an iPad is
at coordinate 1. 1 and then we go up in a
standard coordinate system up to 9. 1 and 9. 5
up here. That's what we're working towards.
The way we're gonna do it is we're gonna change
to a world space canvas as we just did;
adjust the grass tiling. add a temporary
core game panel; translate and scale the
whole level canvas and then adjust and
prefab so that it's alright fo the future. So
what are we gonna do? How are we gonna get
this grass tiling exactly right? We did it
roughly right before. now let's get it
exactly right. So what we gonna do is
take a look at the grass and then ask
yourself the question well how many
times do we want this to repeat? Well
take a look at this slide. so according to
our GDD we want nine columns. or nine
tiles wide as an absolute minimum
and our minimum aspect ratio is 4:3. So how
many would we have when we have a 16:9
aspect ratio screen and we've got more
width? Well 9/3 times 4. we would have 12
wide. So we'd have an extra 3 or an extra one
and a half tiles on either side of the
screen when we have that extra width. Now
there are two grass squares per tile. let's
just look at that. make sure you're clear
why. Here's our grass tile on my screen
and if you look at it - it's a bit small now. just
look at it in unity - have a look. there's one
square but either side of that square
there's half a square. so actually in
total it's two squares wide.
therefore we want the width the. UVW
value to be 12/2 that six tilles wide.
6 tiles gives us 12 squares. OK so
let's set that first. go to your grass and
look at your W and it actually is
correct. it's 6. any more than six and we
would have too many tiles and any less and
we would have too few so six is good but what we
never did before was actually make sure
that these things were square. So let's
have a think about how we're gonna get our
tiles exactly right and perfectly square.
Remember that the tile that we have provided
you. the tile texture. consists of two
squares and if you look carefully on the
left hand side of this slide you'll see
that there's one grass square in the
middle of the tile and then exactly half
a grass square either side and the same
thing happens vertically. so one tile as in
texture tile is two grass squares. So starting
with a. we know from the definition of
our game we want nine grass squares wide
in 4:3. that's the minimum. the narrowest
aspect ratio for example an iPad. So
moving on to b. if we divide that nine
squares by four. which is the width ratio.
and then multiply out by three. the height
ratio we find out that we have
6.75 grass squares tall and that's fine. we
only need five for our play space and that
leaves a little bit of room for our user
interface. So of course in 16:9. moving on
to Part C. we still have 6.75 squares
so the only thing that changes is the
number of squares wide. so casting your eye
down to point D we have to do the same
aspect conversion again. 6.75 squares
tall. divided by 9. the height ratio times sixteen.
the width ratio tells us that we end up with
twelve squares wide in 16:9. so basically
going from nine squares to 12 squares
depending on our device. In the widest
device like an iPhone 5 we would have 12
squares wide and in the narrowest device
in terms of aspect we would have nine
squares wide. and in all cases we would have a
fixed height of 6.75. So there are
squares wide in both aspects it's 6.75
grass squares tall.
remembering that there are two grass
quest per tile that gives us a W value
a width of six tiles wide and a height of
6.75 over two which is 3.375 tiles high.
If you want to find out more about UV mapping then
there's the Wikipedia article there. it
basically is talking about how we map
our image texture onto our play space.
So a minor tweak then. the result of all of
that is that the height of the UV rect
wants to be 3.375 I wanted to show you the logic
for that. Now all these squares are well.
perfectly square which is great alright.
Now I want to show you something really
quickly. you might wonder what this set
native size button is. Well hopefully your
grass is set to 1600 900 pixels that's
our target resolution if we click Set
native size its gonna get a whole lot
bigger because our grass tiles are
actually 512 by 512 that's not the size
of the image on our desk the size of the
image on the disc that we provided is
actually bigger it's 600 by 599 but
Unity has snapped that to the nearest what we
call power of 2. and it's snapped it to 512 by
512 the reason for that is that it can do
something called molto in parvum. which is
its ability to quickly scale down the
texture as we look at it from a further
distance very fast like that so we have
more than enough pixels but thats fine
there's no harm in having more we're not
gonna cause a significant performance
problem so let's have 1600 by 900.
more pixels than we need we've
got six by 3.375 so the squares. the
grass squares are perfectly square now. Great.
so we're currently focusing on getting our
grass right. Back to the slide deck for
guidance.
Next adjust the temporary... add a temporary
core game panel so the core game is
going to be in the middle of the screen
so translating 1600 pixels wide to 4:3 you
get 1.200 pixels wide. That should cover
nine columns per the GDD and five rows
high leaving some space. Centre it on the
screen and this will be our world space
coordinate system. What the hell does
all that mean? Let me show you. Add yourself a
GameObject UI panel. call it core game.
This is just for you to see where your
call game focuses fantastic. I'm going to reset its
transform altogether and then make
it's width 1200. so now we need to work
out the height of this guy so firstly let's
centre him. position 0 X. position 0 Y. and
then say well how do we translate 1200
width to height when we're going through the 16:9
aspect ratio? It must have the same aspect
ratio as the screen this little bit. Well
we go 1200 divided by sixteen. times nine
and we get 675 high. All right we're well
on the way. look our core game area is looking
about right apart from we have about 5 -
1. 2. 3. 4. 5 - but it's not mapped quite right. so
how do we change the mapping? Well that's
back at the grass. and then the y value
of the grass needs to shift until it
lines up perfectly. See that? We just need
to move the y value of the grass until
our core game area - there we go. the bottom and
the top of the core game area just need
to line up nicely. Great. so now what we
have is we have a kind of iPad core
gameplay area
showing here under core game; and
that's where all the action's going to
happen; these are our lanes and our
columns. Now over in the game tab
hopefully your build settings are webplayer by
the way. if they're not web player you'll
have a different set of aspect ratios
here. you change to webplayer under
build settings. web player. switch
platform if you need to. So let's just take a look. we
can choose between 4:3 and 16:9. that's the
whole point. We want to be able to play the
game in this outer white box here. this
one that's showing. this level canvas.
or all the way out to the full width. the
difference being iPhone to iPad and
everything in between including all the
Android devices. Fantastic so we have
that core game area showing there and
that works absolutely fine. what we
finally need to do is translate and scale
whole level canvas so that we get a nice
coordinate system. well 1 grass square.  let's
make it one metre in the world. that
seems about right and let's call
one metre one world unit. Well if the
width of the whole world is 1600 pixels
and thats 12 units wide. this entire width
here is 12 wide.  9 and then one and a half on
either end gives you 12. then the pixels per
world unit we're gonna be using for this
game is 133.33.... OK so to scale your canvas
it needs to be a tiny fraction of
its current size right down to 0.0075. so scale
the entire level canvas. here once it's
width and height are right. first get its
width to 1600 and its height to 900 so it's the same
size as the grass. now scale it down to 0.0075
in X and Y and it doesn't need any Z scale. Now let's
go into a level canvas. Still
looks the same but look at our lizard
now. Let's find our lizard. reset his
transform. go over to the lizard's
sprite sheet here and just set 133.33333
just a few threes pixels per unit and
apply that. Now the lizard's not visible. why's
the lizard not visible? Change the order
in layer of the lizard to 1 and if you
still can't see him it's because your
lizard's in one part of the scene and
your level canvas is in the other you
see the position of the level canvas? We want 0. 0.
Now we have the lizard and the
camera all in the middle of the scene
and crucially if we grab the lizard and
move him around you'll notice that when
he's one unit to the right he's in that
square... 2. 3. 4 get it? so one world unit
now is precisely one grass square. Worth all the effort.
One more thing. I want the origin of the
game space to be here where my mouse
is. just to the left of the word
lose condition. so that this point here
is 1.1 1.2 1.3 et cetera. So how am I gonna
make that happen? Well I go to the level
canvas and I just move it. knowing that
this camera is at the
origin you could also put the lizard at
the origin if you wanted. So you get to your
level canvas. you drag it. you can see that
is going to have to be five World units in X
and then you drag the Y and you can see that's
going to need to be three units in Y. So. if
your level canvas is sitting at 5. 3 1600
by 900 is all correct. correct scale it's a
world space render mode. we'll worry about the
camera in a second. we're nearly there
let's just take a look. let's put our
lizard... say we want to put our lizard here
where is this? Well this is at position 1. 2. 3. 4
by 1. let's see if that works.
position 4 in X. 1 in Y. great. How about
if I want to put him at the top right? Well that would
be 9 by 5. right? So we have
a coordinate system that's super simple
when we come to coding up positions of
enemies and everything later isn't going
to be easy if we just say we want it
at position 9. 5. What would the middle of the
game space be? What you set you co-ordinates to?
for the middle of the game space? 5. 3 yeah you
get it
ok that's really nice. so here's our
origin. that's what we've decided.
Fantastic so the final thing we need to
do then is to get the camera working
right. where is this damn camera now? It's all over
the place. if we're go into
the 3d mode the camera's an orthographic
camera on the wrong side of the play space.
well it's actually the right side but it's just not right
So let's get this camera right; firstly
let's give it a position in the negative
Z direction that's a minus ten 10 metres.
10 world units away like so. Fine. It
can still be an orthographic camera. how
big should it be? Well that's a good
question;
the size; the height. we've covered this
before. but half the vertical height in
world units.
So what is the vertical height of our
space 1. 2. 3. 4. 5. 6. 7 world units so we want a
height of 3.5 OK is that working? Not at
all at the moment. so you need to
continue to adjust your camera until we
get it in exactly the right place . So we can go
back to 2D. Now the problem with the
camera now it's not sitting over the
middle square where the lizard is. where's
the lizard at 5. 3 so the camera wants to
be over 5. 3. Now the camera's bang over
the middle of the game space. so the easiest way
to get this camera size exactly right
is to understand that the size is half
the vertical height. so what is the
height of our game space? Well it's going
to be 12 world units wide. divided by
sixteen. times nine get you 6.75 world
units high in total and we have about six
point seven five grass squares divide that by
two and you get 3.375. That is your correct vertical size
of your camera. There it is look. perfect
Now over in game if we're set to 4:3 then our
camera is perfectly showing what the
iPad would show and as we go up through
the aspect ratios look what happens we
just reveal more grass to the sides...
that's really nice. it's exactly what we
want. Very graceful changing resolution right?
Well aspect ratio perfect! So our camera's good to
go now. let's now attach this camera to
the... well let's prefab the camera first
actually cuz we've got a good camera
Call it game camera rather than main camera .
prefab it. Now that it's prefabbed. let's
drag it into the event camera and the
point of that is that now when we click
lose or win condition the UI knows where
we're clicking. it understands how to interpret
our position in the game world. Now that
our level canvas is good let's re-
prefab the whole level canvas ok? So you
can drag it down here and it'll create
you a new level canvas prefab. let's just
do that completely. so here's a brand new
level canvas prefab. Final thing to do is
good each of your scenes. starting at level one. each of your
game scenes and make sure that you've
got the game camera in it and the
level canvas.
Obviously everyone does cause we've been
working on it. level 2 well just
delete the main camera and the level canvas
and just drop them back in from the
prefab
so level two is set up and that's the
great thing about the prefabs now that
we have both the camera and the level
canvas prefabs any changes we make to
those later will come across. so put your level canvas and your camera prefab in every level. Awesome. so we have multiple
levels all set up properly
all gonna be running beautifully on
iPhone and iPad and Android devices so
congratulations on getting this far and
hopefully you understand a lot more now
about how you choose your resolutions
and pixels for these world spaces. Just
as a quick note by the way for you. one
centimeter is basically one pixel if you
look at your guy here he has a pixel per
unit of 133. well he's about 1.3 meters
high that seems perfectly reasonable. so
there you go. Well done on getting this far and I
shall see you soon.