I never thought I'd say it but I have a
fuzzy lizard problem. See. I don't know if you caught
that. let me just replay from the
beginning. This dude is fine when he's
walking but look what happens when he starts
talking. Fuzzy as hell. Now if you
think that looks a bit like a dodgy
YouTube video on low bandwidth then
you'd actually be pretty right. it is to
do with compression. Let's talk about
what's going on. So we're gonna talk
about why my lizard animation looks
fuzzy. what we're gonna do about it. we're
going to talk about maximum texture
sizes and then briefly while we're there
we'll talk about mip-mapping. just for fun.
OK. so what you need to get is that this
attacking sprite sheet is actually
treated as a texture. It's still a
texture. So what that's a texture and what's a
sprite? Well a texture is just a bunch
of pixels that are going to be applied
to a 2D surface; a sprite is just a
rectangular version of one of them.
It's pretty simple... so this is treated as a
texture. it's actually telling us
something here that it's a not power of
two texture - an NPOT texture and that's
because of the size of it. in fact if I
expand out my inspector its 1024 by 304 is
how it representing it but the problem
is that it's been down sampled to 1024 by
304. have a look at the original image.
member when we looked at it before. it is
much bigger than that. Just
bring my inspector across. It is 3700
pixels wide. whereas unity has scaled it
down to 1024 wide and that's why he looks
so fuzzy. So what we have here - come out ot play
mode. otherwise the settings won't stay.
What we have here is a... well actually I'm
gonna leave in play mode. so you can
immediately see the effect. I'll come out of play mode
again later.
There you go. just pause... I'll just leave him running.
I need to make him loop so let me make him loop
attacking set it to loop. Fantastic. ok so
let's get him in his dodgy attack loop
on the screen nice zoomed in scene view.
wobbling like a good 'un. OK. so take a look
at the underlying texture. Just quickly
work down the texture settings. It's a 2D
sprite. fine but it's still a texture.
It's just... you know... it's being treated as a
square sprite. It's a multiple
sprite sprite sheet. that's all fine.
Packing tags. nothing to do with unity
free that's for the pro version. Pixels per
unit is how it scales. Generate MIP maps we'll talk
about in a minute we'll skip over filtering
altogether for this video but this is
the bit you have a default maximum
texture size and then you have an
override for each platform. so different
platform has different allowable
texture sizes and what happened is Unity's
default is 1024. so it has downscaled this
image by about threefold. If we set it up
to 4096 and click Apply.
watch the lizard - fixed completely
fixed and if we set it to 2048 then it'd
be somewhere between still fuzzy because
it's being downscaled. So again. the source
image was three thousand and something
pixels so we're gonna need 4096 now
there's a word of warning here. a couple of
things happen when you make it this much
bigger. Firstly look at the size of the
texture. it's quite small and subtle that's
better. It's 10.7 megabit texture right
now whereas previously it was only point eight
of a megabit so it'd be much faster to
load and take up much less video memory
in your device so it's fine to set it to
4096 on most devices but what we need to
look at is what are the maximum
texture sizes for the various devices?
They're only just starting. here in 2015. to
support that type of texture size. So if we
look here the old iPhones only do 1024.
even the iPhone 4 and iPad support only
2048 and then the iphone4s onwards and the
iPad 2 onwards will support 4096. There's
the same list here for Android. Right so
generally 2048 is what we want to target
if we're designing this for mobile. I've left
this on another slide at the end of
this slideshow called useful resources
so don't worry about this URL.
So yes you can set 4096 but
understand that some older devices will moan
and not like it
The other thing you can do is decide
whether it's a compressed texture which
is 10.7 meg; whether it's 16 bit
which is going to look rubbish cause
the cut... well it depends on the
sprite but this... already you are
starting to see some color artefacting.
you see this weird banding here on his hat
or you could set it true color. which is
uncompressed. but now your sprite size has
doubled. it's gone up to 21 megabits or
your texture size has doubled so leaving
compressed is normally the way. you get
slightly better image quality if it's
true color but it's unnecessary. An
example of this in the real world by the
way not that you can really see it is
that when they ported Rayman legends
from xbox 360 and ps3 over to ps4 and
Xbox one they made the textures
uncompressed or true colour because
there was enough texture memory on the
new generation consoles. the video memory to
do that. It didn't make a lot of
difference actually as you're seeing
here it's not actually that dramatic the
quality difference. it's really not worth
uncompressing it. So there is another
solution to this which is to pack your
sprite sheet a lot more densely. The
current sprite sheet is terribly loosely
packed. let's look at it. The massive
amount of space between all these guys
that is not a tightly packed sprite
sheet they could be right but up next to
each other and then they would actually
fit in 2048 by 2048 comfortably. I'm
not going to show you that in this video
because it's a little bit fiddly and it's
beyond the scope of what we're doing it's
really a performance optimization but
just wanted to give you those warnings.
Alright. if you do want to be changing the
texture sizes or packing these
textures you're gonna need two things -
shoebox and texture Packer. It's gonna take
quite a lot of fiddling around but you'll
do something like extract all of the
images. all the sprites into individual
images using shoebox and then repack
them using texture packer and then you
need to make them all line up and the
padding will work... it's a bit of a pain but
it's possible to do and repack it at the
end of the day you have a smaller
texture that you have to load into video
memory. Hopefully that makes sense. the
final thing I wanted to talk about whilst
we're here is mip mapping. there's the option here
and you'll be wondering what it is. It's a
technique where an original high
resolution texture map
is scaled and filtered into multiple
resolutions within the texture file. I should
also tell you take up 33% much more
space to store but it's much much much
faster to render and it's not needed if
we're looking at a fixed distance and
actually here we are looking at a fixed
distance so here's my lizard
let me go to a different sprite sheet. the
walking one it's a bit clearer... here and then
this slider here shows you the mip mapped
version. so the first version here is
uncompressed and then you start to just
cut out information and the way it does
it has to do with just chopping bits off
in the binary storage of it and this is
why they sometimes make a distinction
between powers of two. PO two. and NPO two. They
like to be at a power of two in at least one
dimension 1024. vertically is a power of two
It makes it much quicker for the machine
to change how this thing looks at
greater distances so because we have mip
maps. what happens is when you go out to
a big distance from the character it's
actually not showing the full resolution
character but you can see it. I can on my
screen. really fuzzy right now and it's
fuzzy because it's using a approximated
version. it massively speeds up the
rendering at small storage costs; but we
actually don't need it here because we
never change the view distance. so you
can actually turn mip maps off if you
wish for all of your sprites; now I need to
come out of play mode of course
otherwise none of these changes will
take effect - you can turn off Mip Maps. and we can
set the maximum texture size to 4096
maximum default texture size... alright and
then that should all just run fine now
so as a summary here's how to prevent
fuzzy lizards. or more generally make
sure that your textures your sprite
sheets. which get turned into textures
actually result in nice. clean.
clear animations without compression. So
you check your sprite sheet size in
pixels. might be 2.000 by 3.000.
You look at the maximum X or Y directions
so in that example its 3.000 pixels. You
then need to ensure that your texture max
size is larger than that biggest
dimension and if you don't want to turn
your texture max size up you could compact
your sprite sheet down more if it's
possible. so the glitch garden
sprite sheets have massive spaces between
the sprites. it's
ok but it's actually pushing the
sprite sheets to the size that the
textures are too big to fit in the video
memory of older iPhones iPads Android
phones etc. So you could compact them
down and you can leave the compression
on so you can have a high res sprite
sheet but you're safe to leave the
compression on it really doesn't degrade
the image quality much unless you've got
absolute heaps of video RAM to play with.
Oome useful resources for you. you can
have a look at that unity answers
link at the top there which will give
you the maximum texture sheet sizes for
different platforms. you can have a look
at a couple of different utilities that
will help you unpack and pack textures so
you've got texture packer there and
you've got shoebox. So for example you
could you shoebox to rip out all of the
sprites from a sprite sheet into
individual PNGs and then you
could use texture packer to repack then in
a much more compact fashion. Don't spend too
much time going crazy on it but they are
useful facilities there.
a bit of a hassle to use but once you've got
them. really really powerful and remember
that you can get stuff that works just
fine especially for newer phones etc from
glitchthegame.com as per that link remember these slides
are available as a PDF at the beginning
of the section and please consider not
printing them out. let's save the trees.
another bonus if you don't print them out is
that you can go to the PDF and click
these links. and save your fingers as
well as the trees. So congratulations on
getting this far. I'm about to show you
how to animate all of the characters and
how to get animation and scaling working
properly we have a subtlety to discuss
so I'll see you soon.
=======
Kind: captions
Language: en
I never thought I'd say it but I have a
fuzzy lizard problem. See, I don't know if you caught
that, let me just replay from the
beginning. This dude is fine when he's
walking but look what happens when he starts
talking. Fuzzy as hell. Now if you
think that looks a bit like a dodgy
YouTube video on low bandwidth then
you'd actually be pretty right, it is to
do with compression. Let's talk about
what's going on. So we're gonna talk
about why my lizard animation looks
fuzzy, what we're gonna do about it, we're
going to talk about maximum texture
sizes and then briefly while we're there
we'll talk about mip-mapping, just for fun.
OK, so what you need to get is that this
attacking sprite sheet is actually
treated as a texture. It's still a
texture. So what that's a texture and what's a
sprite? Well a texture is just a bunch
of pixels that are going to be applied
to a 2D surface; a sprite is just a
rectangular version of one of them.
It's pretty simple... so this is treated as a
texture, it's actually telling us
something here that it's a not power of
two texture - an NPOT texture and that's
because of the size of it, in fact if I
expand out my inspector its 1024 by 304 is
how it representing it but the problem
is that it's been down sampled to 1024 by
304, have a look at the original image,
member when we looked at it before, it is
much bigger than that. Just
bring my inspector across. It is 3700
pixels wide, whereas unity has scaled it
down to 1024 wide and that's why he looks
so fuzzy. So what we have here - come out ot play
mode, otherwise the settings won't stay.
What we have here is a... well actually I'm
gonna leave in play mode, so you can
immediately see the effect. I'll come out of play mode
again later.
There you go, just pause... I'll just leave him running.
I need to make him loop so let me make him loop
attacking set it to loop. Fantastic, ok so
let's get him in his dodgy attack loop
on the screen nice zoomed in scene view,
wobbling like a good 'un. OK, so take a look
at the underlying texture. Just quickly
work down the texture settings. It's a 2D
sprite, fine but it's still a texture.
It's just... you know... it's being treated as a
square sprite. It's a multiple
sprite sprite sheet, that's all fine.
Packing tags, nothing to do with unity
free that's for the pro version. Pixels per
unit is how it scales. Generate MIP maps we'll talk
about in a minute we'll skip over filtering
altogether for this video but this is
the bit you have a default maximum
texture size and then you have an
override for each platform, so different
platform has different allowable
texture sizes and what happened is Unity's
default is 1024, so it has downscaled this
image by about threefold. If we set it up
to 4096 and click Apply,
watch the lizard - fixed completely
fixed and if we set it to 2048 then it'd
be somewhere between still fuzzy because
it's being downscaled. So again, the source
image was three thousand and something
pixels so we're gonna need 4096 now
there's a word of warning here, a couple of
things happen when you make it this much
bigger. Firstly look at the size of the
texture, it's quite small and subtle that's
better. It's 10.7 megabit texture right
now whereas previously it was only point eight
of a megabit so it'd be much faster to
load and take up much less video memory
in your device so it's fine to set it to
4096 on most devices but what we need to
look at is what are the maximum
texture sizes for the various devices?
They're only just starting, here in 2015, to
support that type of texture size. So if we
look here the old iPhones only do 1024,
even the iPhone 4 and iPad support only
2048 and then the iphone4s onwards and the
iPad 2 onwards will support 4096. There's
the same list here for Android. Right so
generally 2048 is what we want to target
if we're designing this for mobile. I've left
this on another slide at the end of
this slideshow called useful resources
so don't worry about this URL.
So yes you can set 4096 but
understand that some older devices will moan
and not like it
The other thing you can do is decide
whether it's a compressed texture which
is 10.7 meg; whether it's 16 bit
which is going to look rubbish cause
the cut... well it depends on the
sprite but this... already you are
starting to see some color artefacting,
you see this weird banding here on his hat
or you could set it true color, which is
uncompressed, but now your sprite size has
doubled, it's gone up to 21 megabits or
your texture size has doubled so leaving
compressed is normally the way, you get
slightly better image quality if it's
true color but it's unnecessary. An
example of this in the real world by the
way not that you can really see it is
that when they ported Rayman legends
from xbox 360 and ps3 over to ps4 and
Xbox one they made the textures
uncompressed or true colour because
there was enough texture memory on the
new generation consoles, the video memory to
do that. It didn't make a lot of
difference actually as you're seeing
here it's not actually that dramatic the
quality difference, it's really not worth
uncompressing it. So there is another
solution to this which is to pack your
sprite sheet a lot more densely. The
current sprite sheet is terribly loosely
packed, let's look at it. The massive
amount of space between all these guys
that is not a tightly packed sprite
sheet they could be right but up next to
each other and then they would actually
fit in 2048 by 2048 comfortably. I'm
not going to show you that in this video
because it's a little bit fiddly and it's
beyond the scope of what we're doing it's
really a performance optimization but
just wanted to give you those warnings.
Alright, if you do want to be changing the
texture sizes or packing these
textures you're gonna need two things -
shoebox and texture Packer. It's gonna take
quite a lot of fiddling around but you'll
do something like extract all of the
images, all the sprites into individual
images using shoebox and then repack
them using texture packer and then you
need to make them all line up and the
padding will work... it's a bit of a pain but
it's possible to do and repack it at the
end of the day you have a smaller
texture that you have to load into video
memory. Hopefully that makes sense, the
final thing I wanted to talk about whilst
we're here is mip mapping, there's the option here
and you'll be wondering what it is. It's a
technique where an original high
resolution texture map
is scaled and filtered into multiple
resolutions within the texture file. I should
also tell you take up 33% much more
space to store but it's much much much
faster to render and it's not needed if
we're looking at a fixed distance and
actually here we are looking at a fixed
distance so here's my lizard
let me go to a different sprite sheet, the
walking one it's a bit clearer... here and then
this slider here shows you the mip mapped
version, so the first version here is
uncompressed and then you start to just
cut out information and the way it does
it has to do with just chopping bits off
in the binary storage of it and this is
why they sometimes make a distinction
between powers of two, PO two, and NPO two. They
like to be at a power of two in at least one
dimension 1024, vertically is a power of two
It makes it much quicker for the machine
to change how this thing looks at
greater distances so because we have mip
maps, what happens is when you go out to
a big distance from the character it's
actually not showing the full resolution
character but you can see it. I can on my
screen, really fuzzy right now and it's
fuzzy because it's using a approximated
version, it massively speeds up the
rendering at small storage costs; but we
actually don't need it here because we
never change the view distance, so you
can actually turn mip maps off if you
wish for all of your sprites; now I need to
come out of play mode of course
otherwise none of these changes will
take effect - you can turn off Mip Maps, and we can
set the maximum texture size to 4096
maximum default texture size... alright and
then that should all just run fine now
so as a summary here's how to prevent
fuzzy lizards, or more generally make
sure that your textures your sprite
sheets, which get turned into textures
actually result in nice, clean,
clear animations without compression. So
you check your sprite sheet size in
pixels, might be 2,000 by 3,000.
You look at the maximum X or Y directions
so in that example its 3,000 pixels. You
then need to ensure that your texture max
size is larger than that biggest
dimension and if you don't want to turn
your texture max size up you could compact
your sprite sheet down more if it's
possible, so the glitch garden
sprite sheets have massive spaces between
the sprites, it's
ok but it's actually pushing the
sprite sheets to the size that the
textures are too big to fit in the video
memory of older iPhones iPads Android
phones etc. So you could compact them
down and you can leave the compression
on so you can have a high res sprite
sheet but you're safe to leave the
compression on it really doesn't degrade
the image quality much unless you've got
absolute heaps of video RAM to play with.
Oome useful resources for you, you can
have a look at that unity answers
link at the top there which will give
you the maximum texture sheet sizes for
different platforms, you can have a look
at a couple of different utilities that
will help you unpack and pack textures so
you've got texture packer there and
you've got shoebox. So for example you
could you shoebox to rip out all of the
sprites from a sprite sheet into
individual PNGs and then you
could use texture packer to repack then in
a much more compact fashion. Don't spend too
much time going crazy on it but they are
useful facilities there,
a bit of a hassle to use but once you've got
them, really really powerful and remember
that you can get stuff that works just
fine especially for newer phones etc from
glitchthegame.com as per that link remember these slides
are available as a PDF at the beginning
of the section and please consider not
printing them out, let's save the trees,
another bonus if you don't print them out is
that you can go to the PDF and click
these links, and save your fingers as
well as the trees. So congratulations on
getting this far, I'm about to show you
how to animate all of the characters and
how to get animation and scaling working
properly we have a subtlety to discuss
so I'll see you soon.
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1:Unity/Section7/GG16 Texture Size & Compression.srt