So before we go on to any more
animations that are based on sprite
movement like this little lizard guy i
wanna talk about another type of
animation and that's bone based animation,
and then once we've done that we can get
all of our animations done in one go
regardless of whether they're gonna be sprite
or bone based. So what are we gonna do this
video? We're gonna introduce them based
animation briefly, use GIMP on a Mac or
PC to slice the images, but the
principles that I show you will apply to
any other image editor and then I'll
show you how to import those new
sprite sheet and set pivot points. So
let's take a look at what we mean by
bone based animation just to give you
the context if you go to Google Images
and type dragon bones you'll get... well I
get these images. So this dragon dude
here, sitting on a transparent background
is a composite of all these bits and
pieces there and what bone animation
means is you make him move by putting these
all back together and then moving them
and pivoting them relative to one
another; let's look at the end result of
that. Go to dragon bones dot effecthub dot com,
here and if you go to demos there they have
have some flash demos or  -here you go, let's have a look
take a look at, say... what's one that I know's going to
work? This one here - dragon chases
starling alright? So have a look at how
he's moving. The different parts that you
saw separately before I now just
pivoting the top of the arm, the bottom
of the arm, the tail even gives a nice
movement effect but it's really just a
solid tail that's pivoting at his bottom
and at the tip. The hairs are moving. So that's what
we mean by bone based animation you can
see actually that there's not a single
requirement to draw any body part more
than once. All that goes into making that
is - let's just take another look now you've seen it
moving - is these pieces. They've been
separated out on the page here so that
they can be sliced
as a multiple sprite when you import
them and then re- composited back into
something like this and then in the
hierarchy it's all been arranged together so
that you can remove these pieces around
pivot points. So a completely and
fundamentally different way of animating.
So perhaps you're the sort of person, or
you have an artist that's great at drawing
a one off, but really not so sure about
animating the frames in between this is
a whole new approach. So how are we gonna do
this? Let's just take an overview from
the slide first, we're go into GIMP and
do the following we're gonna take our
sunflower in my case, make the canvas
bigger mess around with some stuff in
GIMP and then export it again with the
gap between the flowers and the base. So
let's just get on with it. But the first thing
you're gonna need is something to slice
up or a bone sheet, you could maybe use
the dragon bones why not go ahead and
put dragon bones into your game and make
one of your attackers maybe turn my
whole game around maybe one of your
attackers a dragon bones but I'm going
to use the star trophy cuz I seriously
lack in imagination. So what I'm gonna do
is I'm gonna importing a new asset, I'm gonna go
and find the glitch garden PNGs which I
have in a folder over here somewhere
Glitch PNGs and one of those is a
star trophy, it should be starred at the top I may need to
sort by my starred things... so here
we go
and somewhere in here we have the cactuses
and the trophy and the rest of it and
that's the guy. OK so we have a trophy,
and what I want to do is I want to make
this trophy pivot. I want the star - the sunny
bit at the top to rock left and
right and then I want it to emit stars.
Stars'll be our equivalent of suns. Alright so
let's open this guy here, let's reveal him
in finder and then open him in GIMP.
There we go, GIMP's going to
take a moment to open, if you haven't got
GIMP then you can get GIMP from GIMP.org
and let me show you that, make sure
you're familiar. You may have already got
to it in the course, you may be using
Photoshop, absolutely fine, you may want
to use any other image editor that
supports resizing of the canvas and also
needs to support exporting of
transparent background so this is the
site for GIMP.org, there's a video earlier in the
course, just search the course contents
for GIMP
and you'll find another primer video on
GIMP in the Block Breaker section.
Alright, so once you've got this image
inside of GIMP then we just need to do a
few simple things, let's look at the
instructions and walk you through. So
image canvas size increase by two
pixels vertically; I want to split the
top of this guy from the bottom so
firstly I'm going to zoom in a little
bit which is plus; on my keyboard Shift +
OK so image canvas size 38 pixels wide
by 60 high you wanna un-break this chain;
we don't want to lock the aspect ratio;
we want to increase this height by two pixels
without increasing the width. OK so I'm
making mine 38 by 62 but whichever direction
you're splitting your thing in you may be
giver yourself tons more space to start
with, but have a canvas that's big enough
Right. Now
second instruction on GIMP there's an
annoyance, which could really annoy you
if I didn't tell you this bit. You need to go layer / layer
to image size, otherwise you won't be able to make
this yellow box any bigger and if you
don't make the yellow box any bigger you
won't be able to move the base or paste
anything below the yellow line. So you
need to go layer / layer to image size, you need
to set this front layer to the size of
the entire image. That's cool. So now you've
got yellow box the size of the image you
go tools / selection tools / rectangle
select, simple enough. Tools selection tools and
rectangle select. Fine, now just draw
yourself a rough, rough area I'm leaving
two pixels at the bottom because I want
to be taking this, chopping it about here, going
control X, going down a couple of pixels,
control or command V. That is it
actually we can deselect, we can select
none if you want.
Select all or deselect all but doesn't
matter to be honest because it's done
There it is, you have a top and a bottom and a gap,
which is going to allow us to slice in
Unity. So what was the final instruction? It was
cut and paste two lower which we've done,
Save as a PNG in your unity assets folder, well let's do it.
Export as; and then we have lizard, we
have this trophy emblem so let's
just call it
trophy cut because it's been... well... cut dot PNG, let's
try that. Gonna leave the default settings in
here, go
back into unity, and here we have trophy
cut. Now, select that and make it a
multiple sprite cos we're actually gonna
split this into two; gonna ditch my other hole emblem
by the way, so there's no confusion.
I bet I'll regret this later I bet I end
up needing it later, but never mind, I will
do something about that when I get to it. So, trophy cut.
now it's a multiple sprite; so go to your sprite editor.
If you go to your slicing tool automatic
slicing will work, let's look what it's done.
It's put one area there, and one there.
The only thing you need to think about is the
base we're not gonna move, well I'm not
going to move, I'm not going to rotate it, if I did
rotate it I would probably want it to
rotate around the center but I don't
care, I'm not rotating it. However I am
gonna be rotating the top bit but not around
the center of the top bit, that would look
weird right if it rotates around the
centre it'd be kind of... I don't know,
but not the right thing. So what I'm
going to do is put this bottom here, not
necessarily bottom centre, it'll snap to a
bottom center but actually bottom center
looks like it's going to work fine, so
this becomes the pivot point right and
then let's just call these parts
trophy top and then I'm gonna name the other
bit trophy base. We have a single sprite
sheet with 2 sprites in it
trophy top and trophy base. Apply and
come out of the sprite editor. There you go,
trophy base, trophy top. Fantastic so now
what we can do in the scene is we can
create ourselves an
empty GameObject; I'm going to call it
star trophy like so; I'm gonna give a zero
transform for now, and then what I can
do with this star trophy is I can
actually have two sub-objects in there, two
child objects, the top and the base this
is how you want to do it not like that
but at the same level in the hierarchy.
OK and I'm simply gonna call them top and
base and then you put the sprites on
them. Right so I put the base on the base,
just drag it in, but if you drag it in
it's gonna see the effect of dragging it
in? that's a valid way of doing it but you
gonna create duplicate objects which is
absolutely fine or your alternative to
doing that of course telling you to suck
eggs at this stage in the course, is on
the top here you can add a component
sprite renderer, but I wanna make sure you're
remembering what all this stuff is doing,
take the trophy top and just pop it on
there like that. So you have the base and
the top. So where is this star trophy in
the scene? Let's make sure that the
sprite renderers both have an order in
layer of one so that we can see things
So what's happened here is the
top is in one place and the base is in
another, so let's just reset the transform of
the top, and it's not the top itself it's
the star trophy that has the problem and
therefore the base has a problem you see
how important it is to think about the
relative positions here we go, we're nearly
there, if we double-click on star trophy
the only trouble we have is I'm a bit OCD
and like to have top above base even
in the hierarchy, I'm also a bit OCD and
like to name them consistently, so let's
do that, and finally I just wanna move
the top up; and you get them up, obviously there's a point at which they gonna look exactly like they
did let's see how that looks, there's still
a gap, so just going to move the top
down a touch. So we're not actually going to animate it in this video, I just wanna get you to the point that you
could animate it, it just means nudging this
down a couple more pixels, fantastic so
now you have an object that if you
correctly
apply an animator to your going to be able
to independently control the rotation and
translation and scaling of the top and
the base. Now hold your horses don't go
away and try and animate everything like crazy
yet because I've still got to do a similar thing
thing with you with lizard, we need to pull its
sprite out into a sub-object, to do various
other things but i just want to show you
that this is the end point we want you
to get to which is basically a long way
of just ending up with a star trophy in
the scene but the difference is you now
have control over it cuz you have two
separate objects with pivot points, we
could rotate this top piece in the animator.
So what I want you to go ahead and do
now then is do this for all of your
animations that you're gonna do bone
animation on. So create at least one
sprite sheet for bone animation, make sure
there's a picture or two
gap around all your limbs; I'm using limbs
kind of in quotes; export with a
transparent background, import into
unity as a multiple sprite as I just
showed you and set pivot points around
the points that you want these things to pivot and rotate.
Alright? go ahead and do that for
all of the things that you want to
import and just as static items, don't
actually animate them yet, and then in
the next video in gonna show you how
to actually animate. See you soon.