So in this video we're actually gonna get our bone
animation working. we're going to make
the top of the sunflower rotate left and
right so let's get on with it. We have it
in two pieces already. what we need to do
is set up the animator appropriately. So
here we have the trophy top and base.
What I'm gonna do is I'm going to add an
animator to the root object. to the
star trophy itself. because it can
actually reach in and independently control
the top and the base. OK so we don't have
an animation controller yet. so let's build
this up from scratch to reinforce
everything. I'm gonna make a new
animation folder called Star Trophy. it's just
my way of organizing. I'm gonna pop the
trophy cut in there and then I'm gonna
create myself an animation controller
cuz we gonna need one of them right? I've put
an underscore because I like it to be
at the start of the folder so it always plays at the
start of the folder there and then when we go
ahead and look at this star trophy. where
it says animation controller in the
inspector animator controller we give it
the new one we've created so we can build
it up bit by bit.
Drop it in there and now we have an
animation controller. fantastic. So let's
go into the animator and create
ourselves a new clip which will create
both a animation clip and a animation
state and then we'll be able to actually start
sticking things in. So let's have an idle
state first. what does the star trophy do when
it's idle? So there's are idle state. how
many samples the second? Well it doesn't
have to be consistent with everything
else. let's maybe go for 30 samples that second
Actually it doesn't matter. this has to do
with the fidelity of your animation. So
what I want to do is I want to add curve.
Now when you add the curve look
carefully transform and animator are here
and then top and base are slightly
indented. they kind of don't look indented
because they're missing their symbols
but they are the transform applies to
the star trophy itself; whereas the top.
you can independently control the
transform of the top and of the base. so you see
how that works?
The star trophy's transform. the top's
transform and the base's reflects the
layout of the hierarchy. So in our case
it's the top's transform that we want to
rotate so add that in top transform
rotation. That gives us control over the
rotation of the top. So if we start off with
just something going at one second let's
just try rotating it at one second to...
I don't know. minus 8 point
77032 how's that for an arbitrary number
degrees to the left or right. let's see
what happens there. Now you're gonna need to
focus on your - there you go. look actually
it's to the right so sue me there it
goes and it just but it just snaps back.
If you look at the animator and then you
click on your star trophy you see how it's in
the idle state but its snapping back to
the middle but it's working right. So
that's pretty cool.
another way you could have set that
value is to use the record functionality
here and then to go off into the scene
and actually make the rotation but we
can kind of see what's going on now
so if I zoom out. if I say that it's
rotated minus eight degrees after
this amount of time. after 30
frames. then what am I going to do to get it back to the
center? Well I'm gonna need to put
another key frame in which is this
button here. a little diamond and
I'm going to need to put that in at an
appropriate time. and an appropriate time would be
60 frames right? Exactly twice as long. I
want a key frame where the rotation is
zero. Try that. Now let's see what happens as it
loops around. There it goes and at least it goes back to
the middle and then bounces. So here's a
micro challenge for you. I want you to
add in another two keyframes after this in
time so that it not only wobbles to the
right and back but it also wobbles to the
left and back to the centre. so we get a
smooth swaying motion. Go ahead and have
a go at making that smooth swaying motion
yourself right now.
So to get that full rotation working
what we need to do is say well if it's
minus a point seven degrees rotation
around the Z axis at 30 frames well then
let's go to ninety frames there. click a
new keyframe and then put exactly the
opposite in. so one way of doing that by
the way is to click on the frame that
you want a copy from. you could go copy
component. and then you can go to the
target frame and then paste component
values. Of course you'd have to make the
negative into a positive. So let's try
that; it's nearly there but of course we need
to return to centre. so when we look at
the sunflower it's nearly gonna be there but
it's gonna snap and I've accidentally
done something to the base. It's all about that
bass. 'bout that bass. So... what have I done
now? I've done something with the Star Trophy
position by mistake. If you do that. get
an extra curve just delete it. simple.
So let's look at the rotation now just
at the top again. Now what's happening?
You see. interesting. Now you're seeing
compound animation. You're seeing both
the whole star trophy and its base being
animated at the same time... and it's top
being animated at the same time. It's fine.
but it's not what we want right. So again
we take out the star trophy animation
line; it's a different line to the top
rotation. that is a completely separate
animation curve. OK so take that one
out and now we're just down to the base
which goes from zero to minus 8.7. to zero. to
plus 8.7 or it would do had
we pasted onto the right thing. Now all
of those mistakes have very useful so you see
the sort of common things that can
happen if you apply your curve to the
wrong object. Nearly there. it's just
snapping at the end of the animation and
I think you know why. congratulations if
you did manage to do this yourself by
the way so a hundred and twenty frames in
we just need to reset to zero. Let's just
check it works. sometimes with this you
need to reset to like 359 instead of 0 or
something to stop glitching; or to get the
direction right but this is fine look. here
we go it rocks. I mean it literally rocks and it rocks
you get the idea
so we have an idle state so the other
state that we may want to produce for
this would be a little star who starts
in the middle and then expands over time
and then pops off and goes up to the top
so let me show you that quickly and then
I'm going to go into fast motion and
animate all my characters because you
now have. or you will have all the
fundamentals you need so let's go find a
star. Here we go. star dot PNG  there... So I'm gonna
make a new game object here I 'm gonna make a
new child object for the star trophy and just call it star
Alright. so there it is then I'm gonna
give that star a sprite renderer and
attach it or I could have just dragged the star straight to the star trophy and it would have done all of
that for me. There it is. the challenge is of course
this order. this sort order. this sort
order business having to constantly set
the sort order - pain in the butt as far as I'm
concerned. why don't we take our level
canvas and just - if you look at it in 3d
take the whole level canvas - just move
the guy back a little bit. let's just say
give you some positive z. So .5 in the Z direction
OK so just move the level canvas back
away from the camera. so that's setting the
level canvas's position in Z to
nought point five. Now if we had
accidentally with our star not bothered
to set the order in layer to one.  left it at zero it'd
still show. handy tip eh? And it can save you a ton
of time again. As it happens we still do
need order in layer. in fact we need two. because
we want the star to be on the top this
time we actually do want it on top of an
existing sprite use the sprite renderer or
order in layer to order sprite parts on
top of each other.
Don't use it to try and get the sprite
itself above the background. because
that's just a hassle having to do that
every time. We want by default when you
drop a sprite down on the background for
it just to work. right? It makes sense to
me and then if you want to if you want
to change the ordering within a sprite
like we're doing here then you use the
ordering in layers. Anyway. here we go. let's
move this star trophy up a little bit
and then re-scale and after a few
iterations we'll get to a point where we've
got what we want - which is a star that
sits in the middle of the
trophy and now we can go in and animate
growth and eventual departure of this
star. so let's take a look at doing that.
We add a curve and and this time we look for
the star's
transform but this time instead of
animating either its position or rotation
we're going to animate its scale; and what is the
scale of the star gonna be when the
trophy is idle and just rocking left and
right? Well you can set the scale to zero.
that is one option. let's just do that and
then I'm going to show you another option to
achieve exactly the same result. So if we
set the scale of the star to 0 at the
beginning. and let's just set it say to
what it is at the end. watch what happens -
the star will grow during the idle state. You
see it growing there? It's not moving with it.
you can tell me why in a minute.
do you know why? Why is the star just sitting
there well it's because the star is childed
to the trophy if you
childed the star to the top itself
look what happens just by dragging in
the hierarchy. it now takes its
transform relative to the top... and
there it goes it rocks away with the top.
So let's watch the animation again. yeah it's
rocking away with to the top but over in
the animator now the star's scale is no
longer working properly and has actually
gone yellow. and that yellow means that
it has nothing to animate and that's
because the star
object itself has been moved in the
hierarchy so the animator has lost track
of where it is in the hierarchy. So let me
show you the other way to get the star
to not be there during the idle phase.
remember at this point we're in the idle state.
So another way to do this would simply be
to go like this; drill through the top on
here to the star. and that's why I lost
it as it was moved in the hierarchy. and use
the IsActive method. and you can just
say here in the animator no it's not
active at the start and in the idle
state it's also not active at the end. So
what happens then we look at it is it's
just it's there the star. ready to go
ready to animate but it's not active. right?
Great so how about if we were to have
another clip and let's say it's
what do we call it? Star birth or producing
the star or something like that. I'm
gonna call it star birth. here we go so we have
a star birth state. and then what's
going to happen in that star birth state?
Well the very first thing is that we go
drill through the top to the star and
make it active. Tick. fine and then once
it's active we want it to grow over a
period of maybe four seconds. so add
another curve to the star itself
transform all the way through to its
scale. now we can control its scale so
at the start we're going to have it's scale 0
and at the end it's going to be this
point two that we've found ourselves - if
you're not sure go over. use the record mode.
go into the scene and scale the star whilst
selected on the key frame you want so
select on this key frame. go to the
scene and then move it how you want it
and then when you come back you'll find
it will have set these properties. that's what
this red means. that's what the red here
means - it means it's in record mode. and that's what
the red play. pause. and step means. OK
so star birth.
that's fine. let's think to ourselves
very briefly under what
circumstances would the star be born? Well
actually it would be born after a
certain number of loops of the idle
animation. let's say maybe after 5. so after 5 loops a
star is born. and then if you right click
again on star birth and say make transition.
after one cycle of star birth it goes back to
idle. Let's watch this work. Look in the scene
view. it's going to cycle around idle 5 times
actually it didn't in this case. we'll check
why in a minute but the star birth bit is
working . So idle... ok and the reason is
it's a very easy on these transition
arrows to not save the value so really
aggressively hit the enter key and make
sure that value gets saved. and then a
single iteration of star birth. OK. so they're
your transitions. you're saying do me
the idle animation i.e. the rocking for five
cycles and this is where you adjust how
often a star trophy actually gives out
star by the way. it's actually a
play tuning in here
So it rocks a certain number of times
and then eventually the transition will
happen into star birth. at
which point it stops moving. the star comes
up and we're nearly there we just want the
start to float up. ok so how far do we
want it to float up? Well go to the
star birth thing and let's say at four
seconds. so go and select at four seconds let's
use - which you can do by just clicking on
a key frame - let's use the this record system so
make sure you're in record. go to the scene.
and then just do what you want to do to
the star over in the scene it's a core
facility. Just get your star selected. get
your transform tool selected. and say
well after four seconds I want it about
this high. so imagine one of these was in
the top row. it would be one whole square
up which is perfectly reasonable but
also looking at it like this at this
zoom level I think to myself actually
I want it bigger. so why not just do it right there.
You can just scale the star however you like here.
Cool. so what that's done back at the
animator is it's recorded those things
that you've just done into the animator.
just click Play you'll see. So we just wait
for the transition to happen. there we go.
watch the star - up it comes it comes up
and expands and then pops - perfect. how
cool is that? We have a star trophy
animation that's working really nicely for
us ok now if you are somebody who likes
to keep everything in one place and you
don't like the fact that the number of
cycles of idle before the star gets
released is encoded inside the animator
here then that's fine. if you want to
have it somewhere else like in a script
you could just have a script set this
value but we're not doing that for now.
We've got a great result which is that the
star trophy is using bone based animation
to rock back and forth. to create a star
and the star comes out and floats up to
the top.
Fantastic. so you have all the building
blocks you need because not only do you
have that type of animation but of
course if we click over we have a lizard
here which is completely different; this
guy is a sprite sheet based animation
with multiple states. so pretty cool. I'd
like you to firstly create at least one
bone based animation for yourself.
OK that's all I want you to do. so at
this stage have already created one
sprite animation
in my case the lizard now I want you to
create one bone animation so add life to
a still sprite. for example a gravestone
or star trophy; move or rotate its
transform slightly over time;
make the animation loop continuously;
give it at least two animation states as
we've done there. and then for example that
could be an idle and attacking or
attacked state. So go ahead and make your
bone animation now. I'm not going to show you
how because I've just shown you how
with mine. If you want to use exactly the
same asset as I have and follow me through well
you're welcome to rewind. but I really
would prefer you stop the video and do your
own animation now with reference to what
I've just done. Cool. congratulations. good luck
with that and I shall see you in the
next video where we'll talk about
movement and childing in a little bit
more detail before you then go off and
do all of the animation. See you soon.
=======
Kind: captions
Language: en
So in this video we're actually gonna get our bone
animation working, we're going to make
the top of the sunflower rotate left and
right so let's get on with it. We have it
in two pieces already, what we need to do
is set up the animator appropriately. So
here we have the trophy top and base.
What I'm gonna do is I'm going to add an
animator to the root object, to the
star trophy itself, because it can
actually reach in and independently control
the top and the base. OK so we don't have
an animation controller yet, so let's build
this up from scratch to reinforce
everything. I'm gonna make a new
animation folder called Star Trophy, it's just
my way of organizing. I'm gonna pop the
trophy cut in there and then I'm gonna
create myself an animation controller
cuz we gonna need one of them right? I've put
an underscore because I like it to be
at the start of the folder so it always plays at the
start of the folder there and then when we go
ahead and look at this star trophy, where
it says animation controller in the
inspector animator controller we give it
the new one we've created so we can build
it up bit by bit.
Drop it in there and now we have an
animation controller, fantastic. So let's
go into the animator and create
ourselves a new clip which will create
both a animation clip and a animation
state and then we'll be able to actually start
sticking things in. So let's have an idle
state first, what does the star trophy do when
it's idle? So there's are idle state, how
many samples the second? Well it doesn't
have to be consistent with everything
else, let's maybe go for 30 samples that second
Actually it doesn't matter, this has to do
with the fidelity of your animation. So
what I want to do is I want to add curve.
Now when you add the curve look
carefully transform and animator are here
and then top and base are slightly
indented, they kind of don't look indented
because they're missing their symbols
but they are the transform applies to
the star trophy itself; whereas the top,
you can independently control the
transform of the top and of the base, so you see
how that works?
The star trophy's transform, the top's
transform and the base's reflects the
layout of the hierarchy. So in our case
it's the top's transform that we want to
rotate so add that in top transform
rotation. That gives us control over the
rotation of the top. So if we start off with
just something going at one second let's
just try rotating it at one second to...
I don't know, minus 8 point
77032 how's that for an arbitrary number
degrees to the left or right, let's see
what happens there. Now you're gonna need to
focus on your - there you go, look actually
it's to the right so sue me there it
goes and it just but it just snaps back.
If you look at the animator and then you
click on your star trophy you see how it's in
the idle state but its snapping back to
the middle but it's working right. So
that's pretty cool,
another way you could have set that
value is to use the record functionality
here and then to go off into the scene
and actually make the rotation but we
can kind of see what's going on now
so if I zoom out, if I say that it's
rotated minus eight degrees after
this amount of time, after 30
frames, then what am I going to do to get it back to the
center? Well I'm gonna need to put
another key frame in which is this
button here, a little diamond and
I'm going to need to put that in at an
appropriate time, and an appropriate time would be
60 frames right? Exactly twice as long, I
want a key frame where the rotation is
zero. Try that. Now let's see what happens as it
loops around. There it goes and at least it goes back to
the middle and then bounces. So here's a
micro challenge for you, I want you to
add in another two keyframes after this in
time so that it not only wobbles to the
right and back but it also wobbles to the
left and back to the centre, so we get a
smooth swaying motion. Go ahead and have
a go at making that smooth swaying motion
yourself right now.
So to get that full rotation working
what we need to do is say well if it's
minus a point seven degrees rotation
around the Z axis at 30 frames well then
let's go to ninety frames there, click a
new keyframe and then put exactly the
opposite in, so one way of doing that by
the way is to click on the frame that
you want a copy from, you could go copy
component, and then you can go to the
target frame and then paste component
values. Of course you'd have to make the
negative into a positive. So let's try
that; it's nearly there but of course we need
to return to centre, so when we look at
the sunflower it's nearly gonna be there but
it's gonna snap and I've accidentally
done something to the base, It's all about that
bass, 'bout that bass. So... what have I done
now? I've done something with the Star Trophy
position by mistake. If you do that, get
an extra curve just delete it, simple.
So let's look at the rotation now just
at the top again. Now what's happening?
You see, interesting. Now you're seeing
compound animation. You're seeing both
the whole star trophy and its base being
animated at the same time... and it's top
being animated at the same time. It's fine,
but it's not what we want right. So again
we take out the star trophy animation
line; it's a different line to the top
rotation, that is a completely separate
animation curve. OK so take that one
out and now we're just down to the base
which goes from zero to minus 8.7, to zero, to
plus 8.7 or it would do had
we pasted onto the right thing. Now all
of those mistakes have very useful so you see
the sort of common things that can
happen if you apply your curve to the
wrong object. Nearly there, it's just
snapping at the end of the animation and
I think you know why, congratulations if
you did manage to do this yourself by
the way so a hundred and twenty frames in
we just need to reset to zero. Let's just
check it works, sometimes with this you
need to reset to like 359 instead of 0 or
something to stop glitching; or to get the
direction right but this is fine look, here
we go it rocks. I mean it literally rocks and it rocks
you get the idea
so we have an idle state so the other
state that we may want to produce for
this would be a little star who starts
in the middle and then expands over time
and then pops off and goes up to the top
so let me show you that quickly and then
I'm going to go into fast motion and
animate all my characters because you
now have, or you will have all the
fundamentals you need so let's go find a
star. Here we go, star dot PNG  there... So I'm gonna
make a new game object here I 'm gonna make a
new child object for the star trophy and just call it star
Alright, so there it is then I'm gonna
give that star a sprite renderer and
attach it or I could have just dragged the star straight to the star trophy and it would have done all of
that for me. There it is, the challenge is of course
this order, this sort order, this sort
order business having to constantly set
the sort order - pain in the butt as far as I'm
concerned, why don't we take our level
canvas and just - if you look at it in 3d
take the whole level canvas - just move
the guy back a little bit, let's just say
give you some positive z. So .5 in the Z direction
OK so just move the level canvas back
away from the camera, so that's setting the
level canvas's position in Z to
nought point five. Now if we had
accidentally with our star not bothered
to set the order in layer to one,  left it at zero it'd
still show, handy tip eh? And it can save you a ton
of time again. As it happens we still do
need order in layer, in fact we need two, because
we want the star to be on the top this
time we actually do want it on top of an
existing sprite use the sprite renderer or
order in layer to order sprite parts on
top of each other.
Don't use it to try and get the sprite
itself above the background, because
that's just a hassle having to do that
every time. We want by default when you
drop a sprite down on the background for
it just to work, right? It makes sense to
me and then if you want to if you want
to change the ordering within a sprite
like we're doing here then you use the
ordering in layers. Anyway, here we go, let's
move this star trophy up a little bit
and then re-scale and after a few
iterations we'll get to a point where we've
got what we want - which is a star that
sits in the middle of the
trophy and now we can go in and animate
growth and eventual departure of this
star, so let's take a look at doing that.
We add a curve and and this time we look for
the star's
transform but this time instead of
animating either its position or rotation
we're going to animate its scale; and what is the
scale of the star gonna be when the
trophy is idle and just rocking left and
right? Well you can set the scale to zero,
that is one option, let's just do that and
then I'm going to show you another option to
achieve exactly the same result. So if we
set the scale of the star to 0 at the
beginning, and let's just set it say to
what it is at the end, watch what happens -
the star will grow during the idle state. You
see it growing there? It's not moving with it,
you can tell me why in a minute,
do you know why? Why is the star just sitting
there well it's because the star is childed
to the trophy if you
childed the star to the top itself
look what happens just by dragging in
the hierarchy, it now takes its
transform relative to the top... and
there it goes it rocks away with the top.
So let's watch the animation again, yeah it's
rocking away with to the top but over in
the animator now the star's scale is no
longer working properly and has actually
gone yellow, and that yellow means that
it has nothing to animate and that's
because the star
object itself has been moved in the
hierarchy so the animator has lost track
of where it is in the hierarchy. So let me
show you the other way to get the star
to not be there during the idle phase,
remember at this point we're in the idle state.
So another way to do this would simply be
to go like this; drill through the top on
here to the star, and that's why I lost
it as it was moved in the hierarchy, and use
the IsActive method, and you can just
say here in the animator no it's not
active at the start and in the idle
state it's also not active at the end. So
what happens then we look at it is it's
just it's there the star, ready to go
ready to animate but it's not active, right?
Great so how about if we were to have
another clip and let's say it's
what do we call it? Star birth or producing
the star or something like that. I'm
gonna call it star birth, here we go so we have
a star birth state, and then what's
going to happen in that star birth state?
Well the very first thing is that we go
drill through the top to the star and
make it active. Tick, fine and then once
it's active we want it to grow over a
period of maybe four seconds, so add
another curve to the star itself
transform all the way through to its
scale, now we can control its scale so
at the start we're going to have it's scale 0
and at the end it's going to be this
point two that we've found ourselves - if
you're not sure go over, use the record mode,
go into the scene and scale the star whilst
selected on the key frame you want so
select on this key frame, go to the
scene and then move it how you want it
and then when you come back you'll find
it will have set these properties, that's what
this red means, that's what the red here
means - it means it's in record mode, and that's what
the red play, pause, and step means. OK
so star birth,
that's fine, let's think to ourselves
very briefly under what
circumstances would the star be born? Well
actually it would be born after a
certain number of loops of the idle
animation, let's say maybe after 5, so after 5 loops a
star is born, and then if you right click
again on star birth and say make transition,
after one cycle of star birth it goes back to
idle. Let's watch this work. Look in the scene
view, it's going to cycle around idle 5 times
actually it didn't in this case, we'll check
why in a minute but the star birth bit is
working . So idle... ok and the reason is
it's a very easy on these transition
arrows to not save the value so really
aggressively hit the enter key and make
sure that value gets saved, and then a
single iteration of star birth. OK. so they're
your transitions, you're saying do me
the idle animation i.e. the rocking for five
cycles and this is where you adjust how
often a star trophy actually gives out
star by the way, it's actually a
play tuning in here
So it rocks a certain number of times
and then eventually the transition will
happen into star birth, at
which point it stops moving, the star comes
up and we're nearly there we just want the
start to float up, ok so how far do we
want it to float up? Well go to the
star birth thing and let's say at four
seconds, so go and select at four seconds let's
use - which you can do by just clicking on
a key frame - let's use the this record system so
make sure you're in record, go to the scene,
and then just do what you want to do to
the star over in the scene it's a core
facility. Just get your star selected, get
your transform tool selected, and say
well after four seconds I want it about
this high, so imagine one of these was in
the top row, it would be one whole square
up which is perfectly reasonable but
also looking at it like this at this
zoom level I think to myself actually
I want it bigger, so why not just do it right there.
You can just scale the star however you like here.
Cool, so what that's done back at the
animator is it's recorded those things
that you've just done into the animator,
just click Play you'll see. So we just wait
for the transition to happen, there we go,
watch the star - up it comes it comes up
and expands and then pops - perfect, how
cool is that? We have a star trophy
animation that's working really nicely for
us ok now if you are somebody who likes
to keep everything in one place and you
don't like the fact that the number of
cycles of idle before the star gets
released is encoded inside the animator
here then that's fine, if you want to
have it somewhere else like in a script
you could just have a script set this
value but we're not doing that for now.
We've got a great result which is that the
star trophy is using bone based animation
to rock back and forth, to create a star
and the star comes out and floats up to
the top.
Fantastic, so you have all the building
blocks you need because not only do you
have that type of animation but of
course if we click over we have a lizard
here which is completely different; this
guy is a sprite sheet based animation
with multiple states, so pretty cool. I'd
like you to firstly create at least one
bone based animation for yourself.
OK that's all I want you to do, so at
this stage have already created one
sprite animation
in my case the lizard now I want you to
create one bone animation so add life to
a still sprite, for example a gravestone
or star trophy; move or rotate its
transform slightly over time;
make the animation loop continuously;
give it at least two animation states as
we've done there, and then for example that
could be an idle and attacking or
attacked state. So go ahead and make your
bone animation now, I'm not going to show you
how because I've just shown you how
with mine. If you want to use exactly the
same asset as I have and follow me through well
you're welcome to rewind, but I really
would prefer you stop the video and do your
own animation now with reference to what
I've just done. Cool, congratulations, good luck
with that and I shall see you in the
next video where we'll talk about
movement and childing in a little bit
more detail before you then go off and
do all of the animation. See you soon.
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1:Unity/Section7/GG18B 2D Bone Based Animation.srt