So in this video we're going to be looking at different ways of animating objects.
different ways of moving the transform or the pivot point of those objects.
and then. options for combining those together. So by the end of it.
what we're looking to do. and by the way. this is just a preview of what we're going to have in
the next few videos time is. things like this. We're going to be able to put Defenders
down. they're going to have Sprite Sheet Animation. some of them. These Cactuses are purely
based on frame based animation. Then. these Star Trophies are pure
bone based animation. at the top half. The Defenders here are
rotating and translating. and then. the Attackers have a combination as
well. So that's a preview of what's coming! Let me just
show you a slide that should help you to understand these different ways of
moving objects. So we've got Sprite Sheet. which is where we're changing the frames in a
flip-book style. We have Bone Based. which is where we are changing the transform.
rotation. or scale of the object. or part of the object like
if we look back here at the sun. The top of the sun is a Bone Based
Animation. just swinging left and right and pivoting around the base of the sun.
whereas the Cactuses are purely Sprite Sheet based. And then. we have it Moving
the Pivot in Script. So in the case of the Lizard. its
pivot point is moving because of a script. and the actual
frames of the animation are coming from a Sprite Sheet. So let's go through and take a look!
All the Attackers are going to be using Sprite Sheet for their animation.
they'll have no Bone Based Animation. and they will all have their pivot point moved by
script. So that's the division of labor. if you like. for the
Attackers. The Defenders. how about them? Well the Gnome and the Cactus
will be using Sprite Sheet Animation. but the Star Trophy
and the Grave Stone we're going to animate through Bone Based. The Star Trophy. you can already see.
is wobbling left and right. and the Grave Stone. when we get to it. is going to shake based
on a movement of it's transform. Neither of them will have any movement
of their pivot point in script. they're just going to sit still. And then. finally we have the
Defender Projectiles. So what does that mean? That means things like this zucchini or Cactus...
Sorry this Zucchini or in English Courgette. [Laughs] Ah. here it goes!
Now that is a combination of two things. that is a single frame.
so it is a Sprite Sheet but it is just one frame for the Courgette
or the what do I call it? A cucumber. that's what I call it!
[laughs] And then. the Rotation! What's happening with Bone Based
part of the animation is the Rotation is being controlled through Bone Based
Animation. and the movement is happening through Translation
from script. So basically. we just take a single frame. we just
spin it using the Animator. and then. we move it by using script.
So by the end of it. that'll all come together. and we'll have a rich set of different types of
animations. So in this video we're going to focus just on animating the Lizard.
So here we are. where we left off with our Lizard. Now there's a 5 step process outlined
in your section notes. like that. and I'm going to take you through step by step.
just for the Lizard and then give you time to do it yourself. So you could just watch me or you can follow along.
but you'll have time in your challenge to actually take these steps. So the first
step is to create a character parent and a child body object. What does that mean?
Well. at the moment. the Lizard is the only object. What we want to do is
Create an Empty Child object on the Lizard. So with the Lizard selected.
and then. I'm going to call that body. Now the reason is.
we want to move the Lizard. the top-level object.
in script. but we want the animation to occur on the body. And we want the Lizard to
be able to see it right in the middle of the square. so we want independent control of the position
of the body and the rest of the Lizard as a whole. That means our Sprite Renderer
has to come off the Lizard. so I'm going to Copy the Component. the Sprite
Renderer of the Lizard. I'm going to go to the Body and then Paste the Component
as new on the Body. and then. remove it from
the Lizard. So all I've done there is moved. carefully moved the Sprite Renderer down to
the Body. This means we can now move our Lizard around.
Now. in terms of where our Lizard is positioned. the frame that we have
here for this animation is not very helpful. He's mid-flight in my case. so
if that's the case for you. then go and find yourself a Lizard appearing frame.
that's towards the end of the animation or even the final frame. And remember
that you can just select that frame. once you've opened the tray out. and drop it
onto the sprite. And then. that will move the Lizard to his last
frame of animation. Now. I can move the Body of the Lizard around. you see. like this.
and I can get him to a nice even space like 5. 3.
And then. 5. 3 should be 1. 2. 3.
4. 5. 1. 2. 3. So 5. 3 should be in the middle of the square he's
nearly in the middle of. So I can make my final adjustment in the body.
You see the power that gives us! Now our script can move the Lizard
transform. and it could go from 5. 3. to 4. 3 or 5.
3. or 6. 3 you see. And I can just move him along integer squares.
Perfect. so I'll leave him there for now. And then. the Body can make the final
adjustments. Cool! OK. so that is the Lizard positioned
properly. The top level object just has an Animator. and the bottom
level object has a Sprite Renderer. So that's step 1 complete! Let's have a look at the next
step. Create the character parent and child body. Done! Number 2. ensure
there is an Animator on the parent object. Well we already have one! Here is the parent. the Lizard.
and it has an Animator. Wicked! Let's move on! Convert the Sprite Sheet
into separate frames. Well in the case of the Lizard we've already done that. Here they are. they're
already done for the appearing and for the attacking and for the
walking state. so this is easy. Number 3. 4 even. if I could count
add a Sprite Renderer curve to the body object. OK. let's take a little look
at that! We have a Sprite Renderer. and if I look in the animation.
we used to have a Sprite Renderer Curve. But it's confused now. it's gone
yellow. because it's looking for the Sprite Renderer against the Lizard. In fact. when I
select this line in the appearing clip. in the Animation tab.
you can see it's trying to find it on the Lizard. In fact.
if I play. it may even give me that error message. No it doesn't. but it's the yellow that's
indicating that it's missing. So I'm just going to delete this clip.
OK. so with nothing left in appearing. we're going to Add a Curve. Now.
notice you can now drill down into the body. The Animators at the Lizard
level. but it can drill through the body. into the Sprite Renderer. and then. Sprite.
That's where we want to go! Body. Sprite Renderer. Sprite on the
appearing curve. Great! We get a couple of frames. leave them there for now. It's really
handy just to leave them there. because then you can select all of the frames of appearing. pop them in.
we've done this before. delete the frames it came with. and then. move
the rest. Control A will select them all. over to the left. Now remember. you can hold
down Alt and scroll. and and you can change the
size. You've done a lot of this before. And there you go. we have an animation for Appearing.
Let's just get the Animator up. so we can see the state. and go
to our scene and play. There he comes. boom! Wicked! He
appears! Now. the final thing we said we wanted him to do is appear for 3
seconds. didn't we? So we need to decide how long we stay on
Appearing for. Well if you look at the animation. you can see it's at 30
samples a second. and he seems to have 24
frames. So we've got to decide in this transition. from Lizard Appearing
to Walking. how many cycles are we going to do to end up
in 3 seconds in total. Well at 30
frames a second it's tricky to work out. How about if I set the Animation to 24
samples a second. It makes life a little bit easier because one cycle then
lasts precisely a second. in which case the exit time
for this transition is after 3 cycles. This is an exit time in number
of cycles. And you see Lizard Appearing there. Lizard Appearing. Lizard Appearing 3
times. each one lasting 1 second. And I shouldn't have messed up the frame-rate too much. Let's have a look!
There he goes. and that's appearing for 3 seconds. Great!
So the next thing we want to do is have him walking for 3
seconds. So the aim of this game is to have the Lizard Appearing. the Lizard
Walking. and the Lizard Attacking. So I think this is a good time to put you over to your challenge. I
think you can try finishing it off. and I will help you if you need it. So let's see
if you can finish animating your Lizard. Animate the Lizard in place. using the Sprite Sheet
just as I did with that 5 step process. but do the same thing now
for the two other animation states. for the Walking and the Attacking
states. And then. cycle through the states every 3 seconds. So we want him to Appear
for 3 seconds. Walk for 3 seconds. and then. Attack for 3 seconds.
So pause the video. see if you can make that work and figure out what goes where now. and if you can't
for any reason. no problem. just resume the video I'll show you how to do it. And you'll have ample opportunity
to practice this on all of the other characters.
Welcome back! O.K. so let's look at the Walking
animation state now. In the Animation tab. go down to Walking. We've got the
same problem. it's gone yellow because it's lost track. I'm going to go
find the Walking frames. down in my Project tab.
under Assets. I'm going to pull all my Walking... Ah. hang on. before I do that
I'm going to add a Body. Remember Sprite Renderer. Sprite.
Curve. that one there. I'm going to leave the frame.
so that I'm scrolling up with two fingers on my Trackpad or rolling the Mouse Wheel.
Drop the frames in. delete the stuff that came at the start. Control
A or box select around. Drag it to the
left. observe how long this is. It's 15 frames.
so it's 1/2 a second. because we have 15 frames and
30 frames a second. therefore we want to go from Walking to Attacking after how many cycles?
Well it's going to be 6. because we have 1/2 a second each.
Let's check that works!
1.000. 2.000. 3.000. Appearing. Walking for 1. 2.
3. and then. he goes to Attacking. Well of course he doesn't go to Attacking. because that's the final
state I need to do. Same process. Delete the curve!
Add a new Curve. selecting Body. That's important! Then. Sprite Renderer.
then Sprite. Cool! Default frames. they're fine. we'll leave them
there for now. They're handy. they prevent us from losing our line.
We want to find the Attacking state. Ooh. lots and lots of frames in this guy.
Drop it in. delete what was there.
drag to the left. observe how long this lasts for.
This is lasting for nearly 3 seconds on its own. so that's going to be good enough. So at a
frame-rate of 15 a second it's lasting nearly 3. Let's take a look! Animator
open. play. He appears for about 3 seconds.
as before he transitions to Walking. does 6 cycles of
Walking. and then. he's just doing 1 cycle of Attacking. which happens to last
about 3 seconds. Ah. he's not doing 1 cycle. [Laughs]
So to limit the amount of tacking. rather than it just looping around. I'm going to transition back
to Lizard Appearing. for now. and exit after 1 cycle.
So in the scene view. let's just take a look and make sure it works. He
appears for 3 cycles. walks for 6. because each one takes
1/2 a seconds. attacks for just 1 cycle. and then goes
back to appearing. Awesome. so that is our Lizard animated! Just
to recap. let me go show you the slide that shows you the process!
Now. you'll make more sense. Here it is! So we create the parent.. we create
the child. we ensure there's an Animator on the parent object. because it can reach into the child.
We convert Sprite Sheet into separate frames. we add a Sprite Renderer Curve to the
body object. and then. we adjust animation to taste and repeat. So that's what
we're going to do for all of the other animals. in our upcoming videos!