OK, so I'm going to go to the Animation's part of my
Assets and just take stock. So I have a Cactus. I'm just going to rename these
clips cactus attack, just so that we have
unique clip names. OK, so that's the Cactus
done! OK, we're not bothering to animate the projectiles yet.
The Fox, so Fox next! Let's just do it! When you get to it, don't double handle
things, right. You've just arrived at the Fox, do the Fox right now. So
it is an Attacker. Create Empty Child, call it Fox.
Now, I'm going to do things a slightly different way. Let's create another
empty child of the Fox. Let's call it Body, and then,
on the Body let's put the Sprite Renderer. I'm going to go and
get a, what shall we have, a walking sprite as the default.
That's good! Now where is my Fox in the world?
Well let's zoom out, there he is! Let's just move him to
somewhere on grid, say here. We have
him precisely on grid 5, 4. You might be wondering what's going to be different,
not a lot, just the order that I add the controllers and things in. Moving the
Body sub-component. Remember scaling the Body subcomponent. Just
doing this by eye, so that your Fox is at grid, your Body isn't.
OK, that's pretty cool! So what am I going to want to do
now? I'm going to want to add an animation to the Fox. What happens if I select the Fox
Body and then just add an animation clip straight off? Let's
see what happens OK. Fox walk, let's call
it. Now, it's added to clip, but unfortunately it's added an
Animator to the Fox Body, so it's not a good place to have it. So
this is why I tend to specifically make the Animator
on the parent first, then
go to the trouble of making myself an Animator. You see it's even
called the Animator, Body, it's all wrong, so this is why I've been doing it the slow way.
Now, I know that if you add a curve to the Body, it will create an Animator
Controller for you and stuff, but it does all the naming wrong, so let's just do it manually,
it doesn't take long. Create an Animator Controller, call it _Fox.
May need a capital, just to go with the name of the Fox. It doesn't
really matter. OK, let's pop it into the Controller
slot, and that's good! Down to the Body, now
we have a default sprite. So he's looking good! Now, we can add
a clip at last. By the way, the difference between a curve
and a clip is, the first time it does the same thing. The second time, it'll add a second curve to the
same clip, which means that you can control multiple things at once, maybe the X and the Y movement
independently. But in this case, it doesn't really matter, so this is fox walk.
Because we're going to start off by walking in, we're replacing
that clip. That's fine! We're going to work on the Sprite Renderer
of the Fox. There it is! We're going to leave the zoom out to
see the default frames, leave them there for the moment. Go grab all the walking frames,
which really is getting the same, but I want to show you step by step.
Previously in the course I did this as a sped up video, but I got a lot of kickback that it was very
hard to follow, so I'm doing it frame by frame and step by step now. So
fox walk. Let's have a look! There he is walking away,
bless him. Cool! Quite fun! Walking a bit quick, I would
say. Let's slow down the samples to 30, let's see what that looks like.
Yeah, that's a bit more like it!
Yeah, he's walking kind of smoothly. O.K., that's fine! So the Fox is
walking. Let's think about the next clip, not curve. Adding a curve here would allow
you to change something else, as well as the sprite, but we're adding a new clip.
Fox jump,
there's the state. How long is it going to be before it transitions? Well
let's have a look. The walk went 30 frames a second, and we've got
just over 20 frames here, so it would need to
be about 3 and 1/2, something like that
cycles, so let's try 3 and 1/2, it's close enough.
After 3.... Oops, not 35 [Laughs] we'll be there forever. After 3 1/2
cycles, let's test what we've just done. 1,000, 2,000,
3,000 then it moves! That's good! So the Fox was walking for about
the right amount of time. Let's go over to his jumping animation.
Add a Curve to the Body, Sprite Renderer.
Perfect! Let's go find the jumping frames.
Here they are. Cool, look how high he jumps. Drop them in, delete
the defaults. I drop them in before deleting the defaults, so we don't lose the whole
curve line. OK, we better use 30 frames a second to be consistent
with the walking, before we even look at how long this should last.
And it's got about 30 frames, so it's going to be about 3
loops, before we transition to the next state but let's just check. 1,000,
2,000, 3,000, then he starts jumping.
Cool! And he's going to stay in there forever,
because we haven't got a state for him to go to. What's the state that he's going to go to?
Well it's going to be attacking, isn't it. So let's add a new state. Clip adds a state,
if you remember, as well.
Fox attack, make a transition from the jump
to the attack. We need about 3 cycles, we decided,
and let's go sort out the attack state, so click on attack.
Add yourself
a curve, which is the Body, Sprite Renderer.
Go find your frames. Here they are, boom in
they go! Delete the defaults. Oops!
If you make a mistake, Control Z, and
move it across. Now, 30 frames a second, let's be consistent. How long does this last?
Well it's about 20, so we need to go about 3 1/2 cycles again.
So fox attack back to walk is about 3 and
1/2 cycles. I'm just doing rough mental calculations here.
Let's just check it all works. Go back to the scene. 2,000,
3,000 starts jumping. 2,000,
3,000 attacking! Nearly there but attacking unfortunately is
something wrong with that. What's wrong with attacking? Did I put the wrong frames in? I think I
may have done that, let's have a look. Let's watch him
attacking. Maybe it's just subtle, maybe he just like chews and you can hardly see it?
Nah, that's too subtle for me. [laughs], So let's
delete all the fox attack frames.
Jump, walk... Yes I did, look I needed this attack
one here. You may have wondered what I was doing at the time. Now, how would I do
that? I need to go and add the curve again. So that's fine, that sort of thing
happens. Just suck it up and say, no problem I'll just do it again.
It's really not worth getting yourself stressed over those things. It's just not worth
the shortening of your life. So I'm holding down Shift
to select those two, move it all across, 30 frames a second. Observe
that this guy is about 20 frames long now, so we need...
Well let's do a calculation this time. It's 20 frames
long, so it's 20 divided by 30, which is 0.6667.
What would we need... So I'm going to add that to my memory. If
I want 3 seconds divided by memory recall, we have 4.5.
So 4.5 transitions we need to
do in the animation. I have to go back here. Not 3.5 but 4.5.
Let's just check! Scene view, 2,000,
3,000. 1,000, 2,000, 3,000,
and attacking! Cool, our Fox is groovy!
So let's go back to where we were! If you remember the tree that we were going through, when
we were looking down here. The Fox is looking good! The Gnome, how's the Gnome?
He's named well, gnome hop, gnome idle. That's all good! The Gravestone, gravestone
attack, gravestone idle. Cool! Lizard, lizard appearing. Oh, well it ought to be lizard appearing
hey! So let's just make that unique, lizard appearing clip name,
lizard attacking,
and lizard walking.
Wicked! OK, that's good! So projectiles we're going to worry about later,
and the Star Trophy, we're going to worry about later. We have finished our Attackers.
Awesome job guys!
So we're pretty much there. Now I, this is
the patch to the video, this has been applied 9 months after the course was originally
made, and some of the things I've just done will be slightly different to what
you see in the next video. For a start, in the next video, these things will be laid out on the screen
differently. Now I could painstakingly go through and get it all to exactly the same
state, but to be honest, I think the changes are going to be very minor. So in the next
video, don't be shocked if these things moved a little bit. Also, don't be shocked if my animation timings are a little bit different.
But if you do want to access the exact code, at the end of this video, or
indeed at the end of any video in any of our courses, then this is exactly how you do it.
By the way, I'm going to give you all of this in a challenge slide in a minute and I'm going to ask you to
go and try it, but for now, let me just show you it through. Just watch through. Go to github.com/bentristem
If you're already a member of GitHub, follow me.
It'll be really fun! If you're not, you don't need to be signed in. In fact, I'm not signed in right here.
So then you need to go find the Complete Unity Developer Organization,
or you can go direct there using this URL, which will be on your challenge slide. You find the
section in question, which in this case is Glitch Garden. Now, a slight
complexity with Glitch Garden. In general you would click commits,
and again, this will all be in your challenge slide, step by step. And you'll be on the
Master Branch, and you'll find that these names here correspond to the
names, videos in general. But because I've just done a major patch to this section, the last
four videos have been updated many months after the event. You're going to need
to click on Branch: master and fix-animation-2. You don't have to do
any of this, by the way, but this is just how you get to our code if you want it. Now,
once you're here you can see that March 2016, considerably
after February 2015, are the four videos I've just fixed. This replaces
one video. It used to be called Combining Animation Types, it was horrible! It was
sped up nearly 3 times and it was very hard to follow. Now we have 4 that are nice
and easy to follow. If you want to get to the state, at the end of this video, which is called
Finishing Our Attackers, you click on the right-hand side here, "Browse the repository at this point
in history". You don't need to be logged in. You get to here and then you
can click Download ZIP. And what you'll get is a ZIP of the entire
Glitch Garden folder. Now, that's in Unity 4.6, if you open it
in Unity 4.6 it'll be fine. Remember to save your project first. If you open it in a later
version, Unity 5 point something, it will ask to upgrade the project, which is fine,
and you can still look and see exactly how we have everything setup, if you want
to. But this in general goes, if we zoom right back out to me,
this goes for all my courses. You can see what I'm doing across all courses, over
all time. I have organizations here for all the different courses, and this is quite a cool
place to go and see all the projects as they evolve. So thanks for watching that, and I shall see
you in the next video, where we'll pick up the project where we left off!