So in the last video I left you to finish off the Defenders! So what other
Defenders do we have to think about? Well let's have a look in our Assets. The
Cactus. we've already done. The Fox is an Attacker. The Gnome
is the next Defender. so let's go ahead and make the Gnome! So we Create an Empty
GameObject. We call it Gnome. G n o m e. [Hums]
We give it a Animation Controller. an Animator rather.
which is the same thing. In the Gnome. I'm going to create an
Animator Controller. I'm going to call it
Gnome. underscore Gnome. Why underscore
you say? It floats to the front. Pop it on the Gnome. pop the Gnome in the
Defenders. and we're starting to see a pattern. I'm going to create an empty child.
I'm going to call it. guess what. Body. I'm going to go
find myself an idle frame of animation. and stick it
against the Sprite Renderer of the Body. so same pattern. The Gnome
has an Animator. it has a sub-object called a Body. it has a Sprite Renderer on it. The Sprite
Renderer has like a default sprite for positioning. and then. we
need to go in and do a couple of things with the Gnome. actually. One is I'm going to move
him down. I'm going to move him to a whole number. so he's on
grid. That's good! I'm going to go to the Body of the Gnome. So the Gnome is now
at 4. 2. but the Body of the Gnome... It doesn't matter where you put these. by the way. I'm just showing you`
the principles. The Body of the Gnome is a little bit big to my eye. so I'm going to go to the Scale Tool. and
just put the white bit in the middle. scale him down a little. Now. you're going to ask me how
do I turn him around? How do I make him face the other way? Well
what you do on the Body is. you make the X scale. look red is the X axis.
make it negative. Boom! And he turns around. and he looks pretty
good there! OK. so to recap. the Gnome is at 4. 2. precisely.
It's scale is OK as an Animator. but the Body has a negative
X scale. That's how I've turned him around! Pretty cool hey! OK.
so what do we need to do next? Well we need to make sure that the Gnome has its Animation Controller.
It does! Then. we need to start making the clips don't we? So we Add a Curve to the Gnome.
What shall I call it? Well I'm going to start prefixing these things with
the name of the object. just so that we don't have multiple animation clips in
our project. all with the same name like Idle. OK. so I'm just going to call it gnome
idle.
Boom there you go! It's the Body's Sprite Renderer
that we animate. It comes with a couple of default frames. we don't worry
ourselves about those. We grab the Gnome. we stick his frames in. it's all getting very
routine now. but some things in game development are just like this. So there's
the Gnome. he's got himself an idle state. Let's look at the Animator.
Gnome Idle. That's fine. and let's just see what it looks
like. Gnome Idle. I can't really see him there. so we'll zoom in. There he is. blinking away.
He's absolutely fine! Cool! Let's get the next state. before we worry about
how long we need to be in idle. So we're going to add a new clip.
I'm going to call it gnome
hop. I think when I looked at the frames of animation. it kind of looked like a hop. and
I named it hop here. Yeah. so gnome hop! We Add the Curve to the
Body. Remember the sub-objects. Sprite Renderer. Sprite. same old same old
I'm afraid. And let's go grab all these
hop frames. Yep. pop them in. Boom!
Delete whatever came there in the beginning. move all the rest to the left.
and there's hopping. OK. wonderful! So
this is at 60 frames a second. whereas the idle I think
was at 30. so I'll set them both to 60 before I worry about the timings.
OK. move the animation
all the way to the left. in both cases. Call idle and
hop. Alright. so now let's try and get the transition times going. So how long does
Idle last? Firstly. let's have a look in here.
Well let's just watch it.
Not very long at all. it's only lasting for 6 frames
and it's 30 frames a second. so it goes around that 5 times a
second. So when we make our transition. if we want 3 seconds then we'd
better go 5 times 3. which is up to 15. Let's just make sure that looks about right.
1.000. 2.000. 3.000.
and then into hopping. So let's look at this hopping animation a little bit more
closely. Idle is fine. he's just blinking his eyes. Hopping is going a little bit weird.
Look he just kind of does a tiny bit of a hop and then he stops for ages.
So let's go have a look at the hop animation.
So go to the Gnome. go to the hop. zoom out... Ah! I've got
an extra keyframe on the end! That was the two default keyframes it made! That one
on the end means he's waiting. before he does anything else. Let's try now!
So he's idle. idle. idle. Let's zoom in and then he hops
a little bit. And is it enough times? Well he's going to stay in
hop isn't he. because there's absolutely no reason for him to go back. So we make the transition
to go back. and then. we think how long? Well gnome hop.
how long does that last? It looks like it's lasting 11
frames. at 30 frames a second. So let's round terms
1/3 of a second. So if we want 3 seconds. then we're going to need to do about
9 cycles. So 9 on the exit time. let's see what happens!
It's about 3 seconds in the idle.
and he's not doing much in there. so maybe it didn't
save. Yeah. I have to try again. You must be not in play mode but in
9. Return. check your preview graph. make sure it actually gets the change.
and then. try again. Let's have a look at this guy a bit more
closely. He's blinking away and he's hopping away! Great! And he
should go over to blinking in a second. There you go! Awesome! So we now have
all of the Defenders that we want. right. Let's just check the Assets.
Oh no. we have a Gravestone! Final Defender. so let's take a look at the Gravestone!
OK. so let's do this fairly sharp time. because this is something
you've seen before. Grave Stone. two words. I'm going to put it
on grid at say 3. 2. or something. for now.
Let's give him an Animator. Done!
Let's make him an Animator. I'm doing this manually
each time. just to show you. or Animator Controller rather. show you
what it entails so that you understand it from the basics right.
_Grave Stone Animator
Controller. There you go! Now the Grave Stone Animator Controller needs to go on
there. Then. we need to make a Body sub-object again. create
an empty child. call it body. Give that a Sprite Renderer.
Yes. there are lots of shortcuts to this. but we just want to understand. really
burning. exactly how this works right. how all of these components relate.
It's just a single frame. so let's give it a single frame. Let's go look in the scene.
Where is it? It's there! Firstly. it's too big so scale it down. Now.
it's in I would say a slightly strange position. so using the W key I'm going to move it
up and across to roughly 1.2. And then. I'm going to set
it in the Inspector to precisely 1. 2. Then. I'm gong to go and take a
look and see how it seems to fit. That looks about OK to me. actually.
So he's sitting there. let's do the checks. It's got an Animator. it's got a Body.
the main item is perfectly on grid at 3.
2. The parent. that's really important. That's all awesome.
OK. so there you go! Now. this guy is going to need some animation.
He's going to need to do something like wobble or shake.
when he gets attacked. and the rest of the time. perhaps he should just sit
still doing nothing. So we're going to have Grave Stone Attacked and Grave Stone
Idle. Let's get to work on that. Also. Grave Stone. of course. needs to be in the Defenders. So
Defenders. good to go. Grave Stone. OK animation!
Add. well a Curve will do actually! Let's call it
gravestone idle.
That is going to do absolutely nothing. it's just going to
sit there alright. So it's just going to be a state against the Grave
Stone. called gravestone idle. OK.
so let's make the other curve. Now we're going to.
We're going to look at the Body. but instead of messing around with the sprite. we're going to
go to the transform position. OK. and what I'm going to do
is. about eery 1/2 a second I'm just going to move it. so I
don't know. something like this. Take a small fraction of a second. set yourself a
key frame. So we're in the Body position of the Grave Stone.
When you're in this red record mode. if you're not you hit the red button under
Scene. then go across and just move the Grave Stone a little.
OK. now try playing. You've just. Ah. there you go. you see what's happening?
This guy is just shaking back and forth. If we look at the animation. it's just because
it's passing from this position on the left. the position is 1. 2.
to a position of 1.06. 2. But using the record mode allowed
me to actually go into the scene and record that. So that works really well. look it's
just shaking away. OK. so that's fine. but of course.
what I've done here is I have set that against the idle. which
I shouldn't have done. So I could just rename the idle clip.
If you do something like that. you can just say GraveStone. what do we call it. attacked.
Yeah. it's being attacked. And then. I can make myself
another clip called. well
[Create New Clip]. gravestone idle.
And that is the one that is going to do nothing. and it's going to be the default state. So
which one's which? Gravestone idle 0. gravestone attacked? Let's have a look!
So if you click in the Animator tab. you see if I say click on gravestone
idle I can look here and it says gravestone attack. So that's the one I need to
change the name. Oops. attacked. And then. this guy
gravestone idle 0 should actually just be called gravestone idle. they should be swapped around.
I think it makes sense to go from left to right. So once these two are in
the right way. we can change the default. The default's currently on the right. so we right click and
say Set As Default. The orange moves to idle. Let's see how long it stays in idle.
OK a second or two. So now we can just
change the Exit Time. in this case. by just putting in the number of seconds. 3 seconds. Let's
check it in the preview. Yep. it looks right! because we have
no animation points. this Exit Time actually becomes a time in seconds; the
rest of the time. it's a number of cycles. So let's check that it stays in idle for 3
seconds. and then. it starts to go to attacked. So that's awesome!
So let's make our return state. Now. how long should
the return state take? So our thing here is
happening between 10 frames. There are 60 frames in a second. so it's a
1/6 of a second. If I want 3 seconds. we need 6. 12. 18.
18 cycles on here. You're welcome to change all these and mess around with them all
you like. I'm just trying to get a rough idea of how many cycles we need. in order to get back. So he
sits idle for 3 seconds. and then. he attacks for 18 cycles.
which is about 3 seconds. then he goes back. Awesome! All of our defenders are
now behaving themselves and switching between their states.
Is that right? Yep. the Cactus is right. but actually. let's just
make a quick change to the Cactus. He's facing the wrong way. and he's a bit big isn't he?
So I'm gong to go to the Cactus. to the Body sub-element.
I'm going to scale him down a little. bring him inside. There you go. that's
a little bit better! And then. the other thing I'm going to do on the Cactus is to switch him
around. Now. that's a micro challenge for you. Before the end of this video. if any of your Defenders
are facing the wrong way. I want you to remember. from what I said earlier. how to switch their position.
So go ahead. switch the position of the Cactus around now. and I'll be back in a second!
Welcome welcome! So remember it was putting a minus on
the X. Awesome! So now they really do. all of these Defenders. look
like they are cycling through their different states properly.
and we're setting up a nice little showcase. Why not take a screenshot of this and paste it into
the discussions and share it with your other students now. and I'll see you in a minute!