So welcome to Animating our Cactus! In this video
we'll be animating the cactus from scratch and recapping the 5-step process!
So let's dive in! So let's take a look at the Star
Trophy now. make sure that is working OK. We're going to move him over next to the Lizard.
Ooh. I've just moved the Top. Make sure. if you're moving the Star Trophy. of course. that you move the entire
thing. Now the Star Trophy already has this parent child relationship.
so we can put him precisely on grid at 4. 3. and then. we
can use the fact that the Top and the Base are child objects to
just adjust that position slightly. Now. let's make sure we're obeying our rules.
We have an animator at the top level. and we have. actually in this case. two body
objects. which is fine because we're making a bone based animation. Cool!
Let's go take a look! The Idle animation. how is that working? Well it's a
bone based animation that we've already setup. and it lasts a total of 4
seconds. so we're going to be in there for 4 seconds. that's OK. And then. the
Star Birth. let's take a look at that. that lasts a total of 4 seconds
as well. So the Star Trophy should already be going from Idle
for 4 seconds to Star Birth
and then back to Idle. So let's just check these transition arrows. At the moment.
we've got 5 cycles before we leave. that's a lot. So I'm making
sure that we're not playing when we adjust the Exit Time. 1 cycle Exit Time.
Let's try that now! So we should get a
single cycle of the star going left and right. and then. a transition over to
Star Birth. That's absolutely fine! So this star is up and running!
Good. we've already done a load of the work! Now. before I continue and start adding other defenders
and attackers. I just want to do a couple of things to make it tidier. I'm going to create another
empty game object called Attackers.
I'm going to put this at 0. 0. 0. and then. I'm just going to put the
Lizard into Attackers. And I'm going to make another empty. at the root. must
be at the root. So this guy. that I just made. is at the root. just be careful you
make it at the root. Call it Defenders.
set it to 0. and then put the Star Trophy in. So all we've done here is
organized our Attackers and Defenders together. Fantastic! So now it's
time to start composing our second object. Now you've seen how to do both Sprite Based Animation.
with the Lizard. and Bone Based Animation. with the Star Trophy. It's
time to crack out the third type of character. So which
should we go for next? Well let's go look at our Asset Pack! So over
here in the section assets. that you would have downloaded. I'm using version 8 in this video.
You can open the Unity package. and what it'll do
for you is. it will detect the assets that are not already in your game. only
the ones that aren't. and it'll allow you to import them. Well let's just go ahead and do that!
And in they come! Now suddenly.
we've got all the things we need organized into folders. We've got a Cactus. a
Fox. and a Gnome. etc.. etc. So why don't we just start at
the top? Let's have a Cactus! OK. now I will set this entire
Cactus up from scratch to you. according to the new scheme. and then. I will challenge you
to do the next one. So the Cactus is what? Well it's a Defender!
So let's make an empty object. let's call it Cactus.
Let's decide where in the scene we're going to put it. somewhere
on grid. 3. 2 will be fine or 4
2. just so it's below the other Defender. OK fine! Now. we
said that for all of these we want a separate sub-body
object. Now the Cactus is going to have an Idle sprite sheet animation. so I'm
going to call this Body.
I'm going to add a Sprite Renderer to the body.
and at the Cactus. just like on the Lizard we have an Animator. We need a
Animator on the Cactus.
OK. that's fantastic! Now. remember the Lizard had an Animator
Controller? Well we're going to need one of those. so let's make ourselves.
in the Cactus Animations folder an Animator Controller.
Call it Cactus. which is consistent with
the Lizard. Now you may want to call it underscore Cactus. like I did before. because that
just makes it float to the start of the folder. and it's kind of the root
object of the folder. so that makes sense. Now. the Cactus here.
in the root Cactus object. we can give it an Animator Controller. So now let's
give ourselves a default sprite. I'll use the first frame. so I've
clicked on the Cactus body now. and against the Sprite Renderer
I'm popping the Cactus Idle frame. Ah. there we go!
We have a Cactus Idle! Now if this is too big for your taste. of course. with the body
element selected. another benefit of having a separate body element is you can do some scaling.
And all this positioning and scaling has happened without. at the Cactus level. changing
the fact the Cactus is nicely on grid. which our code is going to be very
pleased with. Fantastic! Let's go into the animation! Let's
create a new clip. let's call it the same as the names
down here in the Assets. so I'm going to call it Idle to start with.
We're going to add a curve. drilling into the body remember. then the Sprite Renderer.
and then. Sprite. It comes up with a default couple of frames. we're used to that.
Select all the frames that we want. drop them in. Remove
the frames it came with by default. move the rest across to the left. and then
have a look at the time-frame. We want this to animate for about 3
seconds. We have a frame-rate of 60. That's very high. let's look at see if it's
OK. Does it look OK? I think it does for that!
So how long is this lasting? Well it's 60 frames
a second. We've got. I'm not sure how many frames but you can see
that this animation cycle is lasting about 3/4
of a second. so we're going to want
about 4 of these. in order to get the right times. So
in the Animator. we're going to go from Idle to the next state. after about
4 cycles. but we're not quite ready to do that yet. because we need the next state to be
ready. So how are we going to do that? Well we can come here and create a new clip. What's
the new clip going to be called? Well what's it called in the
Assets? It's called attack. so why don't we call it Attack!
So create a new clip. call it
Attack. Now look over in your
Animator and you'll see it's made an Attack state here. And let's
make the transition from Idle to Attack. We set it
once to go. I think after about 4. Let's just test that! So
1.000. 2.000. 3.000. and it stops. That's about
right. Fantastic! Now Attack needs to do something. so
it's the same as before right. We Add a Curve to the Body. because
the Animator is controlling the sub-object. We're going to swap out the sprite. we're going to
leave the default frames there. Loads of frames in this Attack animation.
select all of them except for the last blank ones. We don't want those blank ones. Drop
them in. get rid of the frames it started with. Control
A or Box Select. Have a little look at how long this is. it's a minute and 10
seconds. so we want to come out after about 3 cycles. I'm being rough with these
cycle times and that's absolutely fine! So we want to go from Attack back
to Idle. after about 3 cycles. Let's
see how this look! So about 1.000. 2.000.
3.000. then 1.000... Ooh. so he's not doing 3 full
cycles. Let's check the return condition. it didn't remember that. Remember that when you
set your exit time. you must hit Return and not be in Play Mode.
Let's try that again! 1.000. 2.000. 3.000.
1.000. 2.000. 3.000. He's just going back and forth.
Awesome. so finally the Cactus is a Defender. so I'm going to drag it under Defenders.
And we have some structure coming on. we have Attackers. Defenders.
and of course. we're just going to keep repeating this process. Now remember. the
slide that I gave you in the previous video. this one Character Animation
Overview. We create a character parent and child body object. We ensure
that the Animator is on the parent object. We convert the Sprite Sheet into separate
frames. that's been done for you in the Asset Pack. We add a Sprite Renderer
Curve to the body object. and we adjust
animation to taste. So that's what we're going to need to do for everything.
So I want you to animate the rest of the Defenders now. Animate all the other Defenders.
aim for them to cycle every 3 seconds. and if you're stuck. watch me over the
coming videos. So pause the video. have a go at animating the rest of the Defenders now.
and in the next video. this time. I will start to show you my solution.
=======
So welcome to Animating our Cactus! In this video
we'll be animating the cactus from scratch and recapping the 5-step process!
So let's dive in! So let's take a look at the Star
Trophy now, make sure that is working OK. We're going to move him over next to the Lizard.
Ooh, I've just moved the Top. Make sure, if you're moving the Star Trophy, of course, that you move the entire
thing. Now the Star Trophy already has this parent child relationship,
so we can put him precisely on grid at 4, 3, and then, we
can use the fact that the Top and the Base are child objects to
just adjust that position slightly. Now, let's make sure we're obeying our rules.
We have an animator at the top level, and we have, actually in this case, two body
objects, which is fine because we're making a bone based animation. Cool!
Let's go take a look! The Idle animation, how is that working? Well it's a
bone based animation that we've already setup, and it lasts a total of 4
seconds, so we're going to be in there for 4 seconds, that's OK. And then, the
Star Birth, let's take a look at that, that lasts a total of 4 seconds
as well. So the Star Trophy should already be going from Idle
for 4 seconds to Star Birth
and then back to Idle. So let's just check these transition arrows. At the moment,
we've got 5 cycles before we leave, that's a lot. So I'm making
sure that we're not playing when we adjust the Exit Time, 1 cycle Exit Time.
Let's try that now! So we should get a
single cycle of the star going left and right, and then, a transition over to
Star Birth. That's absolutely fine! So this star is up and running!
Good, we've already done a load of the work! Now, before I continue and start adding other defenders
and attackers, I just want to do a couple of things to make it tidier. I'm going to create another
empty game object called Attackers.
I'm going to put this at 0, 0, 0, and then, I'm just going to put the
Lizard into Attackers. And I'm going to make another empty, at the root, must
be at the root. So this guy, that I just made, is at the root, just be careful you
make it at the root. Call it Defenders,
set it to 0, and then put the Star Trophy in. So all we've done here is
organized our Attackers and Defenders together. Fantastic! So now it's
time to start composing our second object. Now you've seen how to do both Sprite Based Animation,
with the Lizard, and Bone Based Animation, with the Star Trophy. It's
time to crack out the third type of character. So which
should we go for next? Well let's go look at our Asset Pack! So over
here in the section assets, that you would have downloaded, I'm using version 8 in this video.
You can open the Unity package, and what it'll do
for you is, it will detect the assets that are not already in your game, only
the ones that aren't, and it'll allow you to import them. Well let's just go ahead and do that!
And in they come! Now suddenly,
we've got all the things we need organized into folders. We've got a Cactus, a
Fox, and a Gnome, etc., etc. So why don't we just start at
the top? Let's have a Cactus! OK, now I will set this entire
Cactus up from scratch to you, according to the new scheme, and then, I will challenge you
to do the next one. So the Cactus is what? Well it's a Defender!
So let's make an empty object, let's call it Cactus.
Let's decide where in the scene we're going to put it, somewhere
on grid, 3, 2 will be fine or 4
2, just so it's below the other Defender. OK fine! Now, we
said that for all of these we want a separate sub-body
object. Now the Cactus is going to have an Idle sprite sheet animation, so I'm
going to call this Body.
I'm going to add a Sprite Renderer to the body,
and at the Cactus, just like on the Lizard we have an Animator. We need a
Animator on the Cactus.
OK, that's fantastic! Now, remember the Lizard had an Animator
Controller? Well we're going to need one of those, so let's make ourselves,
in the Cactus Animations folder an Animator Controller.
Call it Cactus, which is consistent with
the Lizard. Now you may want to call it underscore Cactus, like I did before, because that
just makes it float to the start of the folder, and it's kind of the root
object of the folder, so that makes sense. Now, the Cactus here,
in the root Cactus object, we can give it an Animator Controller. So now let's
give ourselves a default sprite. I'll use the first frame, so I've
clicked on the Cactus body now, and against the Sprite Renderer
I'm popping the Cactus Idle frame. Ah, there we go!
We have a Cactus Idle! Now if this is too big for your taste, of course, with the body
element selected, another benefit of having a separate body element is you can do some scaling.
And all this positioning and scaling has happened without, at the Cactus level, changing
the fact the Cactus is nicely on grid, which our code is going to be very
pleased with. Fantastic! Let's go into the animation! Let's
create a new clip, let's call it the same as the names
down here in the Assets, so I'm going to call it Idle to start with.
We're going to add a curve, drilling into the body remember, then the Sprite Renderer,
and then, Sprite. It comes up with a default couple of frames, we're used to that.
Select all the frames that we want, drop them in. Remove
the frames it came with by default, move the rest across to the left, and then
have a look at the time-frame. We want this to animate for about 3
seconds. We have a frame-rate of 60. That's very high, let's look at see if it's
OK. Does it look OK? I think it does for that!
So how long is this lasting? Well it's 60 frames
a second. We've got, I'm not sure how many frames but you can see
that this animation cycle is lasting about 3/4
of a second, so we're going to want
about 4 of these, in order to get the right times. So
in the Animator, we're going to go from Idle to the next state, after about
4 cycles, but we're not quite ready to do that yet, because we need the next state to be
ready. So how are we going to do that? Well we can come here and create a new clip. What's
the new clip going to be called? Well what's it called in the
Assets? It's called attack, so why don't we call it Attack!
So create a new clip, call it
Attack. Now look over in your
Animator and you'll see it's made an Attack state here. And let's
make the transition from Idle to Attack. We set it
once to go, I think after about 4. Let's just test that! So
1,000, 2,000, 3,000, and it stops. That's about
right. Fantastic! Now Attack needs to do something, so
it's the same as before right. We Add a Curve to the Body, because
the Animator is controlling the sub-object. We're going to swap out the sprite, we're going to
leave the default frames there. Loads of frames in this Attack animation,
select all of them except for the last blank ones. We don't want those blank ones. Drop
them in, get rid of the frames it started with, Control
A or Box Select. Have a little look at how long this is, it's a minute and 10
seconds, so we want to come out after about 3 cycles. I'm being rough with these
cycle times and that's absolutely fine! So we want to go from Attack back
to Idle, after about 3 cycles. Let's
see how this look! So about 1,000, 2,000,
3,000, then 1,000... Ooh, so he's not doing 3 full
cycles. Let's check the return condition, it didn't remember that. Remember that when you
set your exit time, you must hit Return and not be in Play Mode.
Let's try that again! 1,000, 2,000, 3,000.
1,000, 2,000, 3,000. He's just going back and forth.
Awesome, so finally the Cactus is a Defender, so I'm going to drag it under Defenders.
And we have some structure coming on, we have Attackers, Defenders,
and of course, we're just going to keep repeating this process. Now remember, the
slide that I gave you in the previous video, this one Character Animation
Overview. We create a character parent and child body object. We ensure
that the Animator is on the parent object. We convert the Sprite Sheet into separate
frames, that's been done for you in the Asset Pack. We add a Sprite Renderer
Curve to the body object, and we adjust
animation to taste. So that's what we're going to need to do for everything.
So I want you to animate the rest of the Defenders now. Animate all the other Defenders,
aim for them to cycle every 3 seconds, and if you're stuck, watch me over the
coming videos. So pause the video, have a go at animating the rest of the Defenders now,
and in the next video, this time, I will start to show you my solution.
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1:Unity/Section7/GG19c Animating Our Cactus.srt