Before we start this video I 'd just like
to warn you in advance and apologize
that it's not going to be the easiest
video to follow we're aware of that now
and at some point we will change the
video that takes a surprising amount of
work to do so I'm gathering
information from the community before I
go ahead and do it. In the meantime
please click over to the Resources tab
that you can see here showing on the
screen and the important thing to see is
you put lots of support firstly. do know
that you can download our project end
state and that is our unity project you
can download it open it up and look at
all the items and see exactly how they're
set up the other thing I want you to
look at is under view external resources is
Elija's helpful post - now he really helpfully
has gone through carefully and written
some instructions for you. I'd suggest
you read that overview that before
you even start this video. so there's a
link there to it in the discussions. It is in the
discussions of this lecture but that
link takes you straight to the post in case
it gets buried. and also there's a slower
version of the lecture from three
minutes 43 when I speed up that's
all
at closer to normal speed on YouTube and
there's a link for you there again in the
external resources so do read the
comments. do have a look around. do
overview the video first perhaps. just
watch the whole thing through without
doing anything. that would probably be
your best bet. watch it all through.
read these comments then watch it
through again and try and follow it and
at some point I will replace the entire
video in the meanwhile hopefully this
will help a lot. So in this video we're
going to discuss different ways of
animating objects or at least a recap
those ways; talk about different ways of
moving transforms i.e. moving the object
as a whole; options for combining these and
then I would challenge you to animate
everything. So over in unity I've just moved
my star trophy under the lizard that's
all I've done between videos. and if we
remember we've got two different types
of animation. very different at the moment.
the lizard is frame-based sprite-sheet
based and then the star trophy is bone
based but neither of these actually move
as a whole the lizard looks like he
moves as a whole but he actually doesn't
what's happening is it's a frame by frame
animation. his transform doesn't move
and the
transform of the star trophy as a
whole doesn't move. So how we gonna
combine the movement into this and what
are our options? So let's take a look at
this table . you've got attackers
defenders and the defenders projectiles
- what they throw and the animation types
and some notes. So the attackers they
are all animated in my case by sprite
sheet I'm gonna have a lizard and a fox
all frame animated - and we're going to
move their transforms. their center of
gravity. that's the CG by script. So body
animation by sprite sprite sheet. CG
movement by script. The defenders - well
the movement of the defenders
themselves is both by sprite
sheet and bones. so the Gnome for
example. my garden gnome I'm gonna find from
the Glitch assets. is being animated by
sprite sheet only and then we've just
been through the star trophy base that
is being animated by bone animation and
then they none of them actually move
bodily. so none of the defenders - so
there's no center of gravity movement
and then defender projectiles. well... lots
of ways we could do this. I'm actually
going to use bone based animation to
spin the projectiles in my case an axe
and a courgette so that's going to be
changing their position
well actually their rotation and scale.
We're going to not try and move their
position from both animator and the
script because that just causes
confusion. It is possible but for now we
don't want to do it. so I'm going to use
script to move their transform center of
gravity. Right so animate the transform
position with the animator XOR - meaning
one or the other but not both -
script. That's the take-home from here. So
your challenge is to animate all your
characters. All characters and defenders
animated but stationary. don't try and
move their transforms. Use a mix of sprite
and bone based animation. I want
each one to cycle through their given
animation states every three seconds. That
will cause you a little bit of work that
they'll have to undo later. but it's all
great practice of the animation state
controller.
Put them in a showcase scene so all of your
attackers and defenders are there in a
scene. all standing on the spot mind you.
and then share the scene on gamebucket.io
with everybody else so they can see all
your cool animations and all the sprites
you've chosen. So that's your challenge.
Now what I'm going to do is I'm gonna do
all that for my game. but I'm going to
speed the video up several times because
you're gonna get bored stiff because
everything I do now over the next 10 15
minutes you've seen before. There's
nothing new. so I'm going to go ahead and
record that and then you're gonna hear me
narrating over the top
any new information or anything useful
you wanna see; but have a go at doing it
on your own first. If you get stuck. watch
my narrated version with my assets if
you want to follow me through on that
you're welcome I would much prefer you
create your own stuff so go ahead and
have a go now. if you're stuck. watch mine
then have a go again.
OK so here we go video is sped up two
and a half times so that you don't die
of boredom. What I'm doing is what we
discussed before I'm creating a body
element here for the lizard's actual
sprite so now we can position and
scale and the lizard's body sprite
independent of the transform of the
lizard as a whole. So that means we can
put him in the middle of a square while
the lizard still sits perfectly. in this
case at 5. 3. I just quickly turned my 3d
gizmo size down there because the
camera's getting in the way. Right. so next to
tidy the hierarchy I'm creating an
attackers and defenders GameObject just
to tidy things into for now. I'm putting
both my lizard and my star trophy in
their appropriate game objects; provided
that that attacker and defender game
object had zero transforms that won't
change a damn thing. Right. so the lizard
currently has three animation states. the
way that I am arranging for the
animation state to last three seconds is
to use the clip inspector on the right
hand side to drag to 3 seconds. so we'll
see that several times during this video
what I'm doing here is exactly what I
showed you before I making sure I'm
adding the animation frames to the body
sub-object that contains the sprite
renderer. These things with yellow
that I'm deleting are the animation clips
where there is no longer a sprite render
attached
to the lizard itself. it has become
attached to the body; so this is why
I said to you I only want you to animate one
attacker the way that I showed you. it's
because I knew that you were gonna have
to fix this attacker before then going
on and creating all of your other
attackers. actually in a previous version
of this part of the course I got you to
animate all of your attackers
before then asking you to undo them and
reanimate them and one of our students
quite rightly said that's a pain in the
butt and I fixed it. so that's what's
going on here. So the fox. here he is.
exactly the same deal he needs an
independent body that contains the
sprite; we want the Fox to be at a perfect
transform because this an on-grid game;
Dorry Robert your wife would hate that
and what we want is to be able to have
the transforms at perfect positions but
the sprites to be different so I'm just
going here to the Glitch garden
download. this is the full download from
the Glitch garden website also any assets I use
of course will be in the course assets
and I'm gonna go find myself the
appropriate asset so in this case I got
three of the Foxes animations. he has
an eating animation. a jumping animation
and a walking animation. so for each of
these I need to work out what the sprite
dimensions are so I'm going to do the
calculation that I've shown you before - I'm
going to divide the width of the sprite
sheet by the number of horizontal
sprites to get a hundred and fifty-three
pixels per Fox and I'm going to do the
same vertically; now not all sprite sheets are
laid out like this but these Glitch garden
assets are grid based sprite sheets and
they're quite loosely packed but that's
because for example the fox is jumping
right and they want to keep things
simple and have the Fox stay within his
bounding box even when he jumps; so now
that I've specified the multiple sprite
I have lots and lots of frames against
the fox. and then of course I'm gonna
need to have an animation controller. I
prefix those underscore Fox you see that
at the bottom of the screen I do that so
that it floats to the front of the folder.
Just for simplicity; and now I go ahead and
start creating the animation clips for
the Fox now remember that does two
things: it creates not only an animation
state but it creates an animation curve
I'm prefixing with Fox. you'll see why
later because if you just say attack.
jump etcetera i.e. the simplest possible
name. then in your list of motion clips if you
were to ever try and choose them in the
inspector you will just see walk. walk. walk.
jump. jump. jump. attack. attack. attack and
you can't distinguish easily - or at all
between the different characters. so I
always prefix the animation states and
hence the clips with the name of the
animals so we have fox attack. fox jump.
fox walk and then for each of these
states I'm just making sure that I add
the relevant animation frames; now what
I've done here by mistake is I have
added those frames to the fox itself
which we have created a sprite renderer on
the fox and I'm animating the wrong thing. I
want to be animating the sprite renderer
on the fox's body so I'll notice that
mistake in a moment. in the meanwhile I'm
busy working out what the transition
times are - there you go. that was me deleting the
excess sprite renderer and hence I need to
remove the old broken yellow clip OK. so
just be really careful about this -
by the way the reason there I dragged
the frames in and then dragged them left is
because if you try and delete both of
the existing frames that come in when
you do this add body sprite renderer thing.
those two frames that are sitting there. if
you delete both of those then the whole clip
goes cuz it's got no information in it.
so one easy way to sort that out is to
select all the frames. drag them up and
then to remove the first two frames
afterwards. So. what I'm doing he was just
saying let's assume that the next right
sprite sheet uses exactly the same dimensions. and
the Glitch garden assets do which is good news.
so that I don't have to calculate it all
again. So over in the transition
inspector you can actually choose how
long in time you want the cycle to go
round and that's the easiest way to get
to three seconds without doing any
calculations just drag the sliders until
you get to three seconds' worth of
animation. Why are there two sliders? Because
of blending and we'll see that in a bit.
So again. all of these sprite sheets have
the same dimensions
and then I drag the frames to
the left and off we go. Perfect. so now we
have thirty frames a second is my choice
for the fox and we have an animation for the fox. So
now we're going to the Fox attack
state; now you don't have to use the same
sample rate for all different animation
clips. there's nothing that says you have to
do that unless your code for some reason
is expecting it. so I'm using 15
frames per second for some parts of the
fox and lizard and 30 for another - that's absolutely
fine; and again I'm using the transition
inspector over here to drag the
left-hand and right-hand side of that
transition marker to 3 seconds; now there's a left and
right because of blending. if there's a
gap then it can actually spend time
blending between two animation states. We're
not gonna worry about that for now but it is
pretty handy so here we go the lizard.. sorry
the fox we're focused on here. he walks
for three seconds. jumps for 3 seconds and
attacks for three seconds. Of course it's
just over a second at this current video
speed. So I'm just gonna move the
lizard to a more sensible place. move
the fox. always set their transforms to
perfectly round positions and make sure
that you're moving the root object not
the body sprite. yeah?
Really important that the root objects
are the things that you're moving. and
that they're sitting at round numbers. So here
I'm selecting all elements of the star
trophy and then scaling them up and
then moving the star trophy to a perfect
position. then moving the sprite elements
down so that all of our guys - our attackers
and defenders sit on the grid; awesome. so now
it's just a question of going through
exactly the same thing -
setting up all the root transforms for
our defenders. So I just do that for a
moment. the gnome. the star trophy...
Takes me awhile to settle on whether I
want to name the gravestone with or without a
space so excuse the inconsistencies it
is ok to name a GameObject in the
hierarchy with a space. look at what
Unity does. it does level canvas with a
space but then it does event system
without so if there's gonna be
inconsistency anyway then I'm not too
worried about it.
Same deal for the defenders right. we're
creating separate childed bodies
to contain the sprite. It does actually make
using the animator a little bit harder in some
ways this. because of the way the
animator by default sets up animations. but
in our case because we're an on-grid
game we need to do it so that... well anyway. I've
gone on about the grid business
enough. you get the idea. but it does make
things a little harder. The animator's not
really expecting you to do this with
sprites. It's OK. it works better if we do. So
the underscore in from of a cactus animation
controller is there and then I'm going
through and creating all my clips. Right so it's the
same rote process each time. I'm going to start
talking a little less now because I
think you've got the idea. I'm just gonna
look for instances where I do something
new or novel. Like importing multiple sprite
sheet at the same time. and immediately
renaming those sprite sheets so that we
know what they are. then I'm doing a calculation
here. getting fed up with trying to
remember the numbers so writing into a
text editor. but then accidentally
dividing horizontal by vertical or
something like that so I think I've got
the 126 right but not the 168 but that's
ok. You know I'm sporting my mistake.
fixing it out here - when I can hit the right
keys and we finally get 157 by 126 for
the cactus. which I put in here into
the multiple sprite editor - Forgetting numbers
again. there they go - 157. 126 slice looks
good
apply; now if you go straight to the
second sprite sheet it would remember your
settings. so why not just do all of your
sprite sheets at the same time; so
this is a better workflow. because it's quicker.
Unfortunately you can't multi select them and slice
them all at the same time. but do one go
straight onto the next. you're good to go. An
alternative way of creating states here
is to create the states as I just have and
pick the motion clip but you see without the
prefix here you can't tell which object
you're talking about. which is why I say cactus
attack cactus idle. gnome attack etcetera.
Same deal but in this case the the
cactus does not have the last two frames
- the last few frames there we don't want
to use so it actually may feel a pain in
the butt to have to select all the frames
of your animation but in instances like
this where you see the cactus at the
bottom has missing frames. we need to do
it because it's a grid sheet and some
of the grid squares are not full. so it's
actually important. So here I've made a -1 on
the transforms to make the cactus turn
around and then I'm rescaling him. and
I'm doing all this on the cactus
body. So the main cactus transform
behaves exactly the same. and then the
cactus body is flipped around in X minus
one. it's a great trick with spreadsheets to
turn them round. and then the same deal here
I'm just making sure that I add my
transitions in. and that I make them
last three seconds. and then again have
to do each animation state. Again that sheet
you're missing three - the last four Cactus
attack. empty. you don't want them if you
put them into the animation then you're
going to end up with four frames where there
is no cactus. What you're actually doing
here by the way when you add in a sprite
renderer clip is you're saying this is an
event. you're adding a whole load of key frames.
you see those
triangular key frame things or diamond
shaped frames? You're saying every
30 times a second I want to change the
sprite you could also be changing the
position. or changing the opacity. or
whatever else; you're actually changing the
sprite. swapping it right out. That is what
key frame animation is. Or at least flipbook animation.
Using a keyframe for every single frame. So here's my gnome. looks lie I forgot the underscore. who cares I'll fix
it later. Again prefixing the states with
gnome so I can find it in a list of
motion clips later easily. A general rule is to
name things as simply and concisely and
specifically as possible so if I could
just name the animation state idle and
establish that that is the gnome from
the context then I would. because it's
shorter. it's less typing. it's simpler and it's
less likely to make a mistake like call the
gnome's animation state the wrong
character. but in this case I need it
So again I'm reaching into the Glitch garden
assets they are again provided in the
course or go to the Glitch garden
website. and when you go into there you
can actually download all of their
assets if you dig around a little
bit and you'll get this full zip file that
I have got. I'll also attach that zip
file to the course assets. So you have all
the Glitch garden assets even if they go away or the
website goes away. So the only value
really in selecting those frames
individually is that you get to leave
out any frames you don't want. Again
sample rates can be inconsistent although
your animator will probably - or your
graphic designer will probably kill you if
he has designed a animation to be 30
frames per second and you go and play it
at 60 or 15 or something like that. but
I'm sure you'll survive. Well if he kills you you won't survive. but you get the idea. So here we are. that's the
transition. goes round three times. so
they gnome just transitions between
idle and attacking
Now I'm just making sure that the
parent's at the right place. that the sprite
itself has a negative X. again in
the case of the gnome so remember this
if you want to turn a sprite
horizontally or vertically - to mirror it
horizontally or vertically you make a
negative scale. It can still be a non-integer scale
like .6. this gnome is -.6 I think. his sprite. but negative
will flip it around. a simple way to do it with a sprite.
You can see why I'm speeding the video up now.
in fact the pregnant pauses where I sip on
a cup of tea because if you were watching this at
single speed then this video would be
well over half an hour long about 40
minutes and I'll have commited a Udemy instructor
sin by making such a long video and I
would have probably killed you with boredom. So
this is one of these things where
there's not a huge amount more to learn.
I just have to do the work of going
through and adding all these animations
states. so this is a good compromise this
type of video you get to see everything
if you really want to follow us through
verbatim. you don't miss a trick
as it were. but... you also get to survive
the video. There's my geavestone. same deal if you
hold down the right key. and you can see
that on my key overlays that I put on. you can see
me hunting for the right key. it's one of
the ones in the bottom there. and then you
can zoom in and out and that has the
effect on the scale tool - if you click
the little white bit I'm actually
rescaling in both directions so you
don't distort it. Literally the same
thing but the gravestone is going to be
animated not by frame but by bone based.
So what I've done there is I've just moved
its transform a little tiny bit and
then it wobbles in the gravestone
attacked state. So in idle it stays still and
in the attack state it wobbles. Now I can
see that I've left attacked as the
default. which is wrong actually but I'm
leaving it like that because that's
where we're going to pick up in the next
video. So the orange on your animation
controller there is your default state. so
when you play you're gonna have a
wobbling stone even when it's not being
attacked. but. no problem we can fix that
later. We can fix anything later. That's it. it's all
working that is the end result I want you to get to.
So congratulations. and projectiles next...
=======
Kind: captions
Language: en
Before we start this video I 'd just like
to warn you in advance and apologize
that it's not going to be the easiest
video to follow we're aware of that now
and at some point we will change the
video that takes a surprising amount of
work to do so I'm gathering
information from the community before I
go ahead and do it. In the meantime
please click over to the Resources tab
that you can see here showing on the
screen and the important thing to see is
you put lots of support firstly, do know
that you can download our project end
state and that is our unity project you
can download it open it up and look at
all the items and see exactly how they're
set up the other thing I want you to
look at is under view external resources is
Elija's helpful post - now he really helpfully
has gone through carefully and written
some instructions for you, I'd suggest
you read that overview that before
you even start this video, so there's a
link there to it in the discussions. It is in the
discussions of this lecture but that
link takes you straight to the post in case
it gets buried, and also there's a slower
version of the lecture from three
minutes 43 when I speed up that's
all
at closer to normal speed on YouTube and
there's a link for you there again in the
external resources so do read the
comments, do have a look around, do
overview the video first perhaps, just
watch the whole thing through without
doing anything, that would probably be
your best bet, watch it all through,
read these comments then watch it
through again and try and follow it and
at some point I will replace the entire
video in the meanwhile hopefully this
will help a lot. So in this video we're
going to discuss different ways of
animating objects or at least a recap
those ways; talk about different ways of
moving transforms i.e. moving the object
as a whole; options for combining these and
then I would challenge you to animate
everything. So over in unity I've just moved
my star trophy under the lizard that's
all I've done between videos, and if we
remember we've got two different types
of animation, very different at the moment,
the lizard is frame-based sprite-sheet
based and then the star trophy is bone
based but neither of these actually move
as a whole the lizard looks like he
moves as a whole but he actually doesn't
what's happening is it's a frame by frame
animation, his transform doesn't move
and the
transform of the star trophy as a
whole doesn't move. So how we gonna
combine the movement into this and what
are our options? So let's take a look at
this table , you've got attackers
defenders and the defenders projectiles
- what they throw and the animation types
and some notes. So the attackers they
are all animated in my case by sprite
sheet I'm gonna have a lizard and a fox
all frame animated - and we're going to
move their transforms, their center of
gravity, that's the CG by script. So body
animation by sprite sprite sheet, CG
movement by script. The defenders - well
the movement of the defenders
themselves is both by sprite
sheet and bones, so the Gnome for
example, my garden gnome I'm gonna find from
the Glitch assets, is being animated by
sprite sheet only and then we've just
been through the star trophy base that
is being animated by bone animation and
then they none of them actually move
bodily, so none of the defenders - so
there's no center of gravity movement
and then defender projectiles, well... lots
of ways we could do this. I'm actually
going to use bone based animation to
spin the projectiles in my case an axe
and a courgette so that's going to be
changing their position
well actually their rotation and scale.
We're going to not try and move their
position from both animator and the
script because that just causes
confusion. It is possible but for now we
don't want to do it, so I'm going to use
script to move their transform center of
gravity. Right so animate the transform
position with the animator XOR - meaning
one or the other but not both -
script. That's the take-home from here. So
your challenge is to animate all your
characters. All characters and defenders
animated but stationary, don't try and
move their transforms. Use a mix of sprite
and bone based animation, I want
each one to cycle through their given
animation states every three seconds. That
will cause you a little bit of work that
they'll have to undo later, but it's all
great practice of the animation state
controller.
Put them in a showcase scene so all of your
attackers and defenders are there in a
scene, all standing on the spot mind you,
and then share the scene on gamebucket.io
with everybody else so they can see all
your cool animations and all the sprites
you've chosen. So that's your challenge.
Now what I'm going to do is I'm gonna do
all that for my game, but I'm going to
speed the video up several times because
you're gonna get bored stiff because
everything I do now over the next 10 15
minutes you've seen before. There's
nothing new. so I'm going to go ahead and
record that and then you're gonna hear me
narrating over the top
any new information or anything useful
you wanna see; but have a go at doing it
on your own first. If you get stuck, watch
my narrated version with my assets if
you want to follow me through on that
you're welcome I would much prefer you
create your own stuff so go ahead and
have a go now, if you're stuck, watch mine
then have a go again.
OK so here we go video is sped up two
and a half times so that you don't die
of boredom. What I'm doing is what we
discussed before I'm creating a body
element here for the lizard's actual
sprite so now we can position and
scale and the lizard's body sprite
independent of the transform of the
lizard as a whole. So that means we can
put him in the middle of a square while
the lizard still sits perfectly, in this
case at 5, 3. I just quickly turned my 3d
gizmo size down there because the
camera's getting in the way. Right, so next to
tidy the hierarchy I'm creating an
attackers and defenders GameObject just
to tidy things into for now, I'm putting
both my lizard and my star trophy in
their appropriate game objects; provided
that that attacker and defender game
object had zero transforms that won't
change a damn thing. Right, so the lizard
currently has three animation states, the
way that I am arranging for the
animation state to last three seconds is
to use the clip inspector on the right
hand side to drag to 3 seconds, so we'll
see that several times during this video
what I'm doing here is exactly what I
showed you before I making sure I'm
adding the animation frames to the body
sub-object that contains the sprite
renderer. These things with yellow
that I'm deleting are the animation clips
where there is no longer a sprite render
attached
to the lizard itself, it has become
attached to the body; so this is why
I said to you I only want you to animate one
attacker the way that I showed you, it's
because I knew that you were gonna have
to fix this attacker before then going
on and creating all of your other
attackers, actually in a previous version
of this part of the course I got you to
animate all of your attackers
before then asking you to undo them and
reanimate them and one of our students
quite rightly said that's a pain in the
butt and I fixed it, so that's what's
going on here. So the fox, here he is,
exactly the same deal he needs an
independent body that contains the
sprite; we want the Fox to be at a perfect
transform because this an on-grid game;
Dorry Robert your wife would hate that
and what we want is to be able to have
the transforms at perfect positions but
the sprites to be different so I'm just
going here to the Glitch garden
download, this is the full download from
the Glitch garden website also any assets I use
of course will be in the course assets
and I'm gonna go find myself the
appropriate asset so in this case I got
three of the Foxes animations, he has
an eating animation, a jumping animation
and a walking animation, so for each of
these I need to work out what the sprite
dimensions are so I'm going to do the
calculation that I've shown you before - I'm
going to divide the width of the sprite
sheet by the number of horizontal
sprites to get a hundred and fifty-three
pixels per Fox and I'm going to do the
same vertically; now not all sprite sheets are
laid out like this but these Glitch garden
assets are grid based sprite sheets and
they're quite loosely packed but that's
because for example the fox is jumping
right and they want to keep things
simple and have the Fox stay within his
bounding box even when he jumps; so now
that I've specified the multiple sprite
I have lots and lots of frames against
the fox, and then of course I'm gonna
need to have an animation controller, I
prefix those underscore Fox you see that
at the bottom of the screen I do that so
that it floats to the front of the folder.
Just for simplicity; and now I go ahead and
start creating the animation clips for
the Fox now remember that does two
things: it creates not only an animation
state but it creates an animation curve
I'm prefixing with Fox, you'll see why
later because if you just say attack,
jump etcetera i.e. the simplest possible
name, then in your list of motion clips if you
were to ever try and choose them in the
inspector you will just see walk, walk, walk,
jump, jump, jump, attack, attack, attack and
you can't distinguish easily - or at all
between the different characters, so I
always prefix the animation states and
hence the clips with the name of the
animals so we have fox attack, fox jump,
fox walk and then for each of these
states I'm just making sure that I add
the relevant animation frames; now what
I've done here by mistake is I have
added those frames to the fox itself
which we have created a sprite renderer on
the fox and I'm animating the wrong thing, I
want to be animating the sprite renderer
on the fox's body so I'll notice that
mistake in a moment, in the meanwhile I'm
busy working out what the transition
times are - there you go, that was me deleting the
excess sprite renderer and hence I need to
remove the old broken yellow clip OK, so
just be really careful about this -
by the way the reason there I dragged
the frames in and then dragged them left is
because if you try and delete both of
the existing frames that come in when
you do this add body sprite renderer thing,
those two frames that are sitting there, if
you delete both of those then the whole clip
goes cuz it's got no information in it,
so one easy way to sort that out is to
select all the frames, drag them up and
then to remove the first two frames
afterwards. So, what I'm doing he was just
saying let's assume that the next right
sprite sheet uses exactly the same dimensions, and
the Glitch garden assets do which is good news,
so that I don't have to calculate it all
again. So over in the transition
inspector you can actually choose how
long in time you want the cycle to go
round and that's the easiest way to get
to three seconds without doing any
calculations just drag the sliders until
you get to three seconds' worth of
animation. Why are there two sliders? Because
of blending and we'll see that in a bit.
So again, all of these sprite sheets have
the same dimensions
and then I drag the frames to
the left and off we go. Perfect, so now we
have thirty frames a second is my choice
for the fox and we have an animation for the fox. So
now we're going to the Fox attack
state; now you don't have to use the same
sample rate for all different animation
clips, there's nothing that says you have to
do that unless your code for some reason
is expecting it. so I'm using 15
frames per second for some parts of the
fox and lizard and 30 for another - that's absolutely
fine; and again I'm using the transition
inspector over here to drag the
left-hand and right-hand side of that
transition marker to 3 seconds; now there's a left and
right because of blending, if there's a
gap then it can actually spend time
blending between two animation states. We're
not gonna worry about that for now but it is
pretty handy so here we go the lizard.. sorry
the fox we're focused on here, he walks
for three seconds, jumps for 3 seconds and
attacks for three seconds. Of course it's
just over a second at this current video
speed. So I'm just gonna move the
lizard to a more sensible place, move
the fox, always set their transforms to
perfectly round positions and make sure
that you're moving the root object not
the body sprite, yeah?
Really important that the root objects
are the things that you're moving, and
that they're sitting at round numbers. So here
I'm selecting all elements of the star
trophy and then scaling them up and
then moving the star trophy to a perfect
position, then moving the sprite elements
down so that all of our guys - our attackers
and defenders sit on the grid; awesome, so now
it's just a question of going through
exactly the same thing -
setting up all the root transforms for
our defenders. So I just do that for a
moment, the gnome, the star trophy...
Takes me awhile to settle on whether I
want to name the gravestone with or without a
space so excuse the inconsistencies it
is ok to name a GameObject in the
hierarchy with a space, look at what
Unity does, it does level canvas with a
space but then it does event system
without so if there's gonna be
inconsistency anyway then I'm not too
worried about it.
Same deal for the defenders right, we're
creating separate childed bodies
to contain the sprite. It does actually make
using the animator a little bit harder in some
ways this, because of the way the
animator by default sets up animations, but
in our case because we're an on-grid
game we need to do it so that... well anyway, I've
gone on about the grid business
enough, you get the idea, but it does make
things a little harder. The animator's not
really expecting you to do this with
sprites. It's OK, it works better if we do. So
the underscore in from of a cactus animation
controller is there and then I'm going
through and creating all my clips. Right so it's the
same rote process each time. I'm going to start
talking a little less now because I
think you've got the idea, I'm just gonna
look for instances where I do something
new or novel. Like importing multiple sprite
sheet at the same time, and immediately
renaming those sprite sheets so that we
know what they are, then I'm doing a calculation
here, getting fed up with trying to
remember the numbers so writing into a
text editor, but then accidentally
dividing horizontal by vertical or
something like that so I think I've got
the 126 right but not the 168 but that's
ok. You know I'm sporting my mistake,
fixing it out here - when I can hit the right
keys and we finally get 157 by 126 for
the cactus, which I put in here into
the multiple sprite editor - Forgetting numbers
again, there they go - 157, 126 slice looks
good
apply; now if you go straight to the
second sprite sheet it would remember your
settings, so why not just do all of your
sprite sheets at the same time; so
this is a better workflow, because it's quicker.
Unfortunately you can't multi select them and slice
them all at the same time, but do one go
straight onto the next, you're good to go. An
alternative way of creating states here
is to create the states as I just have and
pick the motion clip but you see without the
prefix here you can't tell which object
you're talking about, which is why I say cactus
attack cactus idle, gnome attack etcetera.
Same deal but in this case the the
cactus does not have the last two frames
- the last few frames there we don't want
to use so it actually may feel a pain in
the butt to have to select all the frames
of your animation but in instances like
this where you see the cactus at the
bottom has missing frames, we need to do
it because it's a grid sheet and some
of the grid squares are not full, so it's
actually important. So here I've made a -1 on
the transforms to make the cactus turn
around and then I'm rescaling him, and
I'm doing all this on the cactus
body. So the main cactus transform
behaves exactly the same, and then the
cactus body is flipped around in X minus
one, it's a great trick with spreadsheets to
turn them round, and then the same deal here
I'm just making sure that I add my
transitions in, and that I make them
last three seconds, and then again have
to do each animation state. Again that sheet
you're missing three - the last four Cactus
attack, empty, you don't want them if you
put them into the animation then you're
going to end up with four frames where there
is no cactus. What you're actually doing
here by the way when you add in a sprite
renderer clip is you're saying this is an
event, you're adding a whole load of key frames,
you see those
triangular key frame things or diamond
shaped frames? You're saying every
30 times a second I want to change the
sprite you could also be changing the
position, or changing the opacity, or
whatever else; you're actually changing the
sprite, swapping it right out. That is what
key frame animation is. Or at least flipbook animation.
Using a keyframe for every single frame. So here's my gnome, looks lie I forgot the underscore, who cares I'll fix
it later. Again prefixing the states with
gnome so I can find it in a list of
motion clips later easily. A general rule is to
name things as simply and concisely and
specifically as possible so if I could
just name the animation state idle and
establish that that is the gnome from
the context then I would, because it's
shorter, it's less typing, it's simpler and it's
less likely to make a mistake like call the
gnome's animation state the wrong
character, but in this case I need it
So again I'm reaching into the Glitch garden
assets they are again provided in the
course or go to the Glitch garden
website, and when you go into there you
can actually download all of their
assets if you dig around a little
bit and you'll get this full zip file that
I have got, I'll also attach that zip
file to the course assets. So you have all
the Glitch garden assets even if they go away or the
website goes away. So the only value
really in selecting those frames
individually is that you get to leave
out any frames you don't want. Again
sample rates can be inconsistent although
your animator will probably - or your
graphic designer will probably kill you if
he has designed a animation to be 30
frames per second and you go and play it
at 60 or 15 or something like that, but
I'm sure you'll survive. Well if he kills you you won't survive, but you get the idea. So here we are, that's the
transition, goes round three times, so
they gnome just transitions between
idle and attacking
Now I'm just making sure that the
parent's at the right place, that the sprite
itself has a negative X, again in
the case of the gnome so remember this
if you want to turn a sprite
horizontally or vertically - to mirror it
horizontally or vertically you make a
negative scale. It can still be a non-integer scale
like .6, this gnome is -.6 I think, his sprite, but negative
will flip it around, a simple way to do it with a sprite.
You can see why I'm speeding the video up now,
in fact the pregnant pauses where I sip on
a cup of tea because if you were watching this at
single speed then this video would be
well over half an hour long about 40
minutes and I'll have commited a Udemy instructor
sin by making such a long video and I
would have probably killed you with boredom. So
this is one of these things where
there's not a huge amount more to learn,
I just have to do the work of going
through and adding all these animations
states, so this is a good compromise this
type of video you get to see everything
if you really want to follow us through
verbatim, you don't miss a trick
as it were, but... you also get to survive
the video. There's my geavestone, same deal if you
hold down the right key, and you can see
that on my key overlays that I put on, you can see
me hunting for the right key, it's one of
the ones in the bottom there, and then you
can zoom in and out and that has the
effect on the scale tool - if you click
the little white bit I'm actually
rescaling in both directions so you
don't distort it. Literally the same
thing but the gravestone is going to be
animated not by frame but by bone based.
So what I've done there is I've just moved
its transform a little tiny bit and
then it wobbles in the gravestone
attacked state. So in idle it stays still and
in the attack state it wobbles. Now I can
see that I've left attacked as the
default, which is wrong actually but I'm
leaving it like that because that's
where we're going to pick up in the next
video. So the orange on your animation
controller there is your default state, so
when you play you're gonna have a
wobbling stone even when it's not being
attacked, but, no problem we can fix that
later. We can fix anything later. That's it, it's all
working that is the end result I want you to get to.
So congratulations, and projectiles next...
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1:Unity/Section7/GG19b Combining Animations .srt