So in this video we're going to give our
projectiles some rotation in the animator.
we're also gonna give them some
translation from the animator.
temporarily. and we're going to see the
combined motion. So let's take a look at
that. So back over in Unity. firstly a tiny
bit of housekeeping. I've noticed that in my
cactus animation folder I've got this
core game animator that's created itself
accidentally created an extra animation
controller so I'm going to get rid of that
and just check that the cactus still
animates properly. I'm confident he will.
provided I click the right buttons... there he is. he's
happy and hopefully he'll change state there
he goes. Cool.
so that's fine the other thing I've
noticed is that I talked about in that
sped up video about the naming and of
course my trophy here is just called idle.
it may make sense to call it trophy idle. and
star birth I'm gonna call it
trophy grow... just so that we know
that is the trophy in both cases. OK
fantastic so let's move on. we need to
get the cactus and the gnome firing
things; so let's start with the cactus.
what's the cactus gonna fire? Well I'm
gonna import a new asset and I'm
gonna go to find the Glitch garden .pngs and I'm
gonna get him firing a zucchini...
or in real language (sorry Americans!) a courgette.
I just never heard of a zucchini until I spent a
few months living in America. but
apparently a courgette is called a zucchini
over there. So there it is. there is a
zucchini or courgette and it's going to
come flying out of one of our defenders
which is gonna be a cactus just cos
they're both green. I can't
give you any more reason than that. So
how are we going to animate this
thing? How are we gonna have a zucchini
flying off the cactus? Well there's a
good question. So let's create a child
GameObject for the cactus called
a courgette. Not sure if it's U - R or just R. Let's just leave it
like that for now. it doesn't matter. So
it's going to need a sprite renderer. I know anybody who thinks spelling
matters is going to really hate me right
now I'll check it and change it later if
it's wrong; so there we have a courgette
sitting in front of the cactus. I'm just
gonna move it. translate it to the right a
little bit in order to stop it looking
like it's completely covering the
cactus' face. and then I'm going to
scale it down a little bit like that. OK.
so we have a courgette childed  to the
cactus. so what we want to do is look
at rotating that as it flies off t o the
right so we can actually use the cactus'
animator. that is fine. because we can
reach through into the courgette to its
transform and we can give it some
rotation just like we did before. in fact as a
challenge why don't you give it some
rotation. so just get it rotating get the courgette rotating now. Go on. I'm not going to do it until you've done it...
Right. so basically at the beginning it has
no rotation. at the end let's say let's
try minus 359 degrees - I think it's
gonna need to rotate that way. what
happens?
Absolutely nothing. why? Because that's
the attack state where the rotation is
happening. there's no rotation in the
other states... that's ok we can just wait
let's see. so he's sitting in the idle state
cause it doesn't and then when he fires
the courgette it rotates. OK. it only
rotates once of course. so how would you
sort that out?
Well. you need to make the rotation loop
but it already is looping - the point
is he's only rotating while he is in the
attack state. So you could apply the same
rotation to the idle state if you want
to. So there it is. that's the rotation.
how about translation? How about if we
were to come in here and say actually
when he fires this thing we want to
translate the transform of the courgette
not the whole cactus. but of the
courgette. Well then you could do that as
well. you could say at the end I want
him to be... I don't know 10 squares to the
right let's try that. So in idle the
courgette's still showing. we'll deal with that in a
minute they you go. off it goes and it's firing.
Looks pretty good right? I'm getting a slight
fuzziness on my courgette and I
think that's cause of texture compression
or my low screen resolution but I'm not
worried. OK now how about if we don't
want the courgette to appear in the idle
state? Well then you've got courgette
is active and we set this to false
in both keyframes. let's try it. So in the idle state
there's no courgette and then he fires
and it comes out. So that's one way of
dealing with it. we're actually going to
deal with things differently later. we're
going to animate the position of the
projectiles using script. remember we
talked about the different ways of doing
it in the decisions. but I wanted to show
you that you can animate it this way it's
just gonna have consequences we don't
want later. but this is an example say
you wanted a boomerang with a specific
type of animation you could do it like
this.
The challenge comes with something like
a boomerang. what happens... when do you turn
it round? If you've got a fixed 10 unit
offset in your animation like we have
here like our transform moves 10 units
in the attack state. here you go. position 10
units. then what would happen if the
cactus was in the middle of the place?
It would go right out the game space and back .
so something has to modify the animation.
So either we have a different animation
from every single starting position.
every column. or we actually move it in
script which is what we're gonna do; but
there's an example. lets do the same thing
for the gnome just so there is an axe in
the scene. and I'm gonna create the axe
a different way. I'm not gonna create a sub-
object yet. I'm just gonna import
the asset which is a class axe as they
call it and if I just drag and drop that
on the gnome look what happens. we get nearly
what we want - apart from it ends up in the
wrong place so we can reset its transform. that's
better we can move it away from the
gnome and the other problem is it just
gives the object a crazy name. let's
just call it an axe. Slightly less crazy now
and again you can animate the axe in
exactly the same way. let's take a look.
Let's go into the gnome. add a curve for... well in
the idle state there is nothing so firstly in
the idle state we're going to have to make the axe inactive. now bear in mind we're only doing this
as an example of some
animator features. I don't suggest it's how
we end up doing it. we'll show you how to
do it a different way from
instantiation from script later; but here's
the attacking gnome. he has an axe and we
want it to do two things we want it to
translate and to rotate the axe. Starting to
get how this animator guy works? I'm going
to zoom in. scroll left and then say what
rotation do we want? Well let's do a full
rotation by the end of the frame again.
359 or minus 359... let's try 359. I'm not sure which
way the axe needs to rotate. We need to wait
for the animation state to switch is rotating
backwards. No. we want the actual blade
to hit people in the head don't we. because we're psychos. So -359 would be better. OK. now the
translation again let's have him fire it
10 units off; OK. take a look. In the idle state
the gnome has no axe active and then in the
firing state it goes flying off. Now. massive
difference in speed between the
projectiles of the gnome and the
cactus - why is that? Can you think why?
It's because the number of frames of
animation we have in the gnome compared
to the cactus - the cactus has enough
animation frames that at 30 frames per
second its loop lasts two and a half
seconds whereas the gnome is only
lasting a fraction of a second so
another reason we're going to end up
controlling all this in script. but for now you have
a pretty good situation. So up next we're
gonna be looking at using the Unity
remote to start previewing how we're  doing
on the mobile but before we go there I
need to make you aware of something... this
part of the course you're watching has
actually been replaced and in order that
the next video on the Unity remote looks
very similar to what you're seeing here
I've had to go through and change a few
things. so you are gonna notice a few
things spelt differently. like the star
trophy may have capitals instead of
lower case. trophy here is purposefully
misspelled for example you'll also see a
few other little things like the
cactus scale is 1. 1 at this level and
then his body is a different scale
whereas later in the course we will
actually go through the process
of getting to that point. so you're gonna
see a few little things. your cactus.
your gravestone scale's going to be
looking similar but achieved a slightly
different way. a different balance between
the scale of the major transform and its
child and then just a few differences in
renaming which I've done since I just
faded out a moment ago I've changed a
few of these assets here to be called
attack maybe instead of cactus attack
this is all to get us back to a state so
that the next video you go to should be
very similar to this but you will see
the odd little glitch from now all the
way through to nearly the end of the
project you'll just see some minor
differences I'm afraid. but I've done my
best using our source control system
here to keep track of all the changes
and to minimize them. Things will be in
slightly different positions and there
will be just some little oddities where
you think that's not quite what I've got
in my project. It will only apply to you if
you've been following me through. really
verbatim. really precisely and it'll also
only apply to you of course if you're
creating a very similar project. If
you've been doing your own thing you
won't really notice a difference
hopefully. If you do notice anything
jarring when you get into the Unity
remote videos. or after please
immediately post that to the discussions
and we'll look to see what we can do
about it but hopefully you can look past
any minor changes and keep focusing on
the learning. so good luck and I'll see you soon.
=======
Kind: captions
Language: en
So in this video we're going to give our
projectiles some rotation in the animator,
we're also gonna give them some
translation from the animator,
temporarily, and we're going to see the
combined motion. So let's take a look at
that. So back over in Unity, firstly a tiny
bit of housekeeping. I've noticed that in my
cactus animation folder I've got this
core game animator that's created itself
accidentally created an extra animation
controller so I'm going to get rid of that
and just check that the cactus still
animates properly, I'm confident he will,
provided I click the right buttons... there he is, he's
happy and hopefully he'll change state there
he goes. Cool,
so that's fine the other thing I've
noticed is that I talked about in that
sped up video about the naming and of
course my trophy here is just called idle,
it may make sense to call it trophy idle, and
star birth I'm gonna call it
trophy grow... just so that we know
that is the trophy in both cases. OK
fantastic so let's move on, we need to
get the cactus and the gnome firing
things; so let's start with the cactus,
what's the cactus gonna fire? Well I'm
gonna import a new asset and I'm
gonna go to find the Glitch garden .pngs and I'm
gonna get him firing a zucchini...
or in real language (sorry Americans!) a courgette,
I just never heard of a zucchini until I spent a
few months living in America, but
apparently a courgette is called a zucchini
over there. So there it is, there is a
zucchini or courgette and it's going to
come flying out of one of our defenders
which is gonna be a cactus just cos
they're both green. I can't
give you any more reason than that. So
how are we going to animate this
thing? How are we gonna have a zucchini
flying off the cactus? Well there's a
good question. So let's create a child
GameObject for the cactus called
a courgette. Not sure if it's U - R or just R. Let's just leave it
like that for now, it doesn't matter. So
it's going to need a sprite renderer, I know anybody who thinks spelling
matters is going to really hate me right
now I'll check it and change it later if
it's wrong; so there we have a courgette
sitting in front of the cactus, I'm just
gonna move it, translate it to the right a
little bit in order to stop it looking
like it's completely covering the
cactus' face, and then I'm going to
scale it down a little bit like that. OK,
so we have a courgette childed  to the
cactus, so what we want to do is look
at rotating that as it flies off t o the
right so we can actually use the cactus'
animator, that is fine, because we can
reach through into the courgette to its
transform and we can give it some
rotation just like we did before, in fact as a
challenge why don't you give it some
rotation, so just get it rotating get the courgette rotating now. Go on, I'm not going to do it until you've done it...
Right, so basically at the beginning it has
no rotation, at the end let's say let's
try minus 359 degrees - I think it's
gonna need to rotate that way, what
happens?
Absolutely nothing, why? Because that's
the attack state where the rotation is
happening, there's no rotation in the
other states... that's ok we can just wait
let's see, so he's sitting in the idle state
cause it doesn't and then when he fires
the courgette it rotates. OK, it only
rotates once of course, so how would you
sort that out?
Well, you need to make the rotation loop
but it already is looping - the point
is he's only rotating while he is in the
attack state. So you could apply the same
rotation to the idle state if you want
to. So there it is, that's the rotation,
how about translation? How about if we
were to come in here and say actually
when he fires this thing we want to
translate the transform of the courgette
not the whole cactus, but of the
courgette. Well then you could do that as
well, you could say at the end I want
him to be... I don't know 10 squares to the
right let's try that. So in idle the
courgette's still showing, we'll deal with that in a
minute they you go, off it goes and it's firing.
Looks pretty good right? I'm getting a slight
fuzziness on my courgette and I
think that's cause of texture compression
or my low screen resolution but I'm not
worried. OK now how about if we don't
want the courgette to appear in the idle
state? Well then you've got courgette
is active and we set this to false
in both keyframes, let's try it. So in the idle state
there's no courgette and then he fires
and it comes out. So that's one way of
dealing with it, we're actually going to
deal with things differently later, we're
going to animate the position of the
projectiles using script, remember we
talked about the different ways of doing
it in the decisions, but I wanted to show
you that you can animate it this way it's
just gonna have consequences we don't
want later, but this is an example say
you wanted a boomerang with a specific
type of animation you could do it like
this.
The challenge comes with something like
a boomerang, what happens... when do you turn
it round? If you've got a fixed 10 unit
offset in your animation like we have
here like our transform moves 10 units
in the attack state, here you go, position 10
units, then what would happen if the
cactus was in the middle of the place?
It would go right out the game space and back ,
so something has to modify the animation.
So either we have a different animation
from every single starting position,
every column, or we actually move it in
script which is what we're gonna do; but
there's an example, lets do the same thing
for the gnome just so there is an axe in
the scene, and I'm gonna create the axe
a different way, I'm not gonna create a sub-
object yet, I'm just gonna import
the asset which is a class axe as they
call it and if I just drag and drop that
on the gnome look what happens, we get nearly
what we want - apart from it ends up in the
wrong place so we can reset its transform, that's
better we can move it away from the
gnome and the other problem is it just
gives the object a crazy name, let's
just call it an axe. Slightly less crazy now
and again you can animate the axe in
exactly the same way, let's take a look.
Let's go into the gnome, add a curve for... well in
the idle state there is nothing so firstly in
the idle state we're going to have to make the axe inactive, now bear in mind we're only doing this
as an example of some
animator features, I don't suggest it's how
we end up doing it, we'll show you how to
do it a different way from
instantiation from script later; but here's
the attacking gnome, he has an axe and we
want it to do two things we want it to
translate and to rotate the axe. Starting to
get how this animator guy works? I'm going
to zoom in, scroll left and then say what
rotation do we want? Well let's do a full
rotation by the end of the frame again,
359 or minus 359... let's try 359, I'm not sure which
way the axe needs to rotate. We need to wait
for the animation state to switch is rotating
backwards. No, we want the actual blade
to hit people in the head don't we, because we're psychos. So -359 would be better, OK, now the
translation again let's have him fire it
10 units off; OK, take a look. In the idle state
the gnome has no axe active and then in the
firing state it goes flying off. Now, massive
difference in speed between the
projectiles of the gnome and the
cactus - why is that? Can you think why?
It's because the number of frames of
animation we have in the gnome compared
to the cactus - the cactus has enough
animation frames that at 30 frames per
second its loop lasts two and a half
seconds whereas the gnome is only
lasting a fraction of a second so
another reason we're going to end up
controlling all this in script, but for now you have
a pretty good situation. So up next we're
gonna be looking at using the Unity
remote to start previewing how we're  doing
on the mobile but before we go there I
need to make you aware of something... this
part of the course you're watching has
actually been replaced and in order that
the next video on the Unity remote looks
very similar to what you're seeing here
I've had to go through and change a few
things, so you are gonna notice a few
things spelt differently, like the star
trophy may have capitals instead of
lower case, trophy here is purposefully
misspelled for example you'll also see a
few other little things like the
cactus scale is 1, 1 at this level and
then his body is a different scale
whereas later in the course we will
actually go through the process
of getting to that point, so you're gonna
see a few little things, your cactus,
your gravestone scale's going to be
looking similar but achieved a slightly
different way, a different balance between
the scale of the major transform and its
child and then just a few differences in
renaming which I've done since I just
faded out a moment ago I've changed a
few of these assets here to be called
attack maybe instead of cactus attack
this is all to get us back to a state so
that the next video you go to should be
very similar to this but you will see
the odd little glitch from now all the
way through to nearly the end of the
project you'll just see some minor
differences I'm afraid, but I've done my
best using our source control system
here to keep track of all the changes
and to minimize them. Things will be in
slightly different positions and there
will be just some little oddities where
you think that's not quite what I've got
in my project. It will only apply to you if
you've been following me through, really
verbatim, really precisely and it'll also
only apply to you of course if you're
creating a very similar project. If
you've been doing your own thing you
won't really notice a difference
hopefully. If you do notice anything
jarring when you get into the Unity
remote videos, or after please
immediately post that to the discussions
and we'll look to see what we can do
about it but hopefully you can look past
any minor changes and keep focusing on
the learning, so good luck and I'll see you soon.
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1:Unity/Section7/GG20b Projectile animation.srt