Hey guys, so as a final video in this
part of the section we're gonna just
tidy up a few things. So firstly I'm
going to read the music on load and
improve the win and lose screens; so why
do we need to read music on load? Well
let's see what happens right now - plays our
startup sound , goes over to the options
screen but this volume is not what we've
set it. So say I've set the volume very
quiet, if I stop playing the game and
play again I want that initial volume to
be fixed
not change with the options but listen
it's loud now. You may not be able to hear clearly
but as soon as I click options it
goes down to whatever this value is. So
what I want to happen is I want to read
the value that's set in the player prefs
at the moment we get to the start scene
so let's just get on with it now. So a
valid way of doing this is to create an
empty game object on the Start scene
called scripts and this is purely to
hang scripts that are going to run on this
scene off, I like to put it at the top and
have a neutral transform on it. So then we
could make ourself a new script for this,
which would be fine, and which should be
just set start volume for instance. OK so
we have a set start volume script, let's
just tidy it away into the scripts
folder and take a look at it. You're not
gonna get away quite that easily at this
stage in the course, why don't you do it?
Come on, you can do it we have a
persistent music manager so it doesn't
actually exist in this scene right now
only when we start from the splash
screen so you're gonna need to find the music
manager, and then you gonna need to call
it with the options from the player
prefs. Remember the player prefs' a static
so you don't need to find them or do
anything clever, you can just call
directly on the player prefs manager.
Have a go at it, see if you can make the
start scene obey the volume level in
options.
Cool, welcome back. So we're going to need a
private music manager, why private? Well
because we're gonna find it inside here
we're not gonna be dragging it across in
the inspector there he is, so on the start
we to find it, how we gonna do that?
So we're going to game object dot
find object of type music manager and
it's a method; now what's going to be
that? It's gonna be the music manager now
I always like here just to check we've got it.
debug dot log found plus... found music
manager and then just a add on the end
log out the actual manager; let's just
make sure that works, firstly it
shouldn't work from the start scene
because there is no music manager in the
start scene, let's try. Well it's saying found music manager but there's no object on the end of that sentence and
that's as we expected so it's saying
debug dot log found Music Manager,
if you want it to not even logged out you
just say if music manager and then if
there is no music manager then that log will not
be called; we could actually deal
with its exception right now, so else
debug dot log warning I think it's a
warning if we're not setting the
volume, no music manager found on start
scene - or in start scene so can't set volume. OK?
and then we close our brackets, let's try
that. First without the music manager. What
does the console say? No music manager found
in scene so can't set volume. Fine, good
now let's run it from the splash screen,
keep an eye on the console it's making
the persistent music player which
arrives in the start scene and that's
fine. It's
found persistent music manager music
manager so it's actually found it in this
case and where is it? There it is, persistent
music. Great, so that's one part of it
done and we've caught the case where it
doesn't happen then what do we need to
do well on start if we have found a
music manager I don't think we need to
log it any more, now that we know that
it works, we'll just log the exception, all we
need to do is go ahead and set that
music so it's music manager
Well we first need to get the volume, so
float volume equals player prefs manager
dot get master volume and it's a method.
Fine, and then we just need to say music
manager . now where is it... set volume volume. You see that?
Relatively simple? OK let's play and
make sure it works properly so starting
from the splash screen
Go into my options, set the volume very very
very quiet, come out to make sure it's
saved and stop playing the game. Now let's
try again, we have a loud splash screen we should have
a very quiet start scene. We do, just try it at the
other end, it's very loud, back to save, stop
playing, play from the splash screen. Splash
screen comes in and now it's playing at
full volume. Perfect, so let's just recap
the code, make sure you're clear on
how we've done that, so we use a private
music manager because we're gonna find
the music manager and we do not want it
exposed in the editor. We go ahead and
find it right here, if it exists we read
the player prefs using this static
method which we can call anywhere public
static remember we can do that from
anywhere which is very useful, we have our
own player prefs interface which was
created which is pretty handy and then
we go ahead and just set the volume on
that music manager instance that we
found and if we couldn't find one we
log a warning. Cool, on to the next tidy up task
then quickly. So the next thing is catch the
first-order error with auto load level
after. What the hell does that mean? Well let's
just take a quick look at it, thank you
to the people in the discussions for
bringing this up so on our splash screen, on
the level manager, we have this autoload
next level and then it says three so the
question is what happens if somebody puts a
negative value in? Well let's just catch
that, there are lots of ways we could
deal with it but let's... I'm going to make
this as simple as possible and I'm just
gonna say... hang on a second, I had a little crash of mono there so just let it reload, come back to life...
here it is, and it's the level manager I
want. OK so if the autoload level
next level after is less than or equal
to 0, I'm going to say... I'm just gonna
change it to less than or equal... level
load autoload disabled, use a positive
number in seconds. Now you could rename
this whole thing auto load next level
after seconds, thanks Marco for the
suggestion, that would be even longer... my
challenge with that is it's so long it
doesn't really fit
over here in the inspector so you're
probably gonna miss it anyway unless you've
expanded it out. Already with the word after
it's kind of too long so we just leave
it like this now if somebody tries to put
a negative value in they'll get a
log rather than an error or a warning just
a log entry, because they may want auto
load disabled, so that's a very minor tweak
but valid points there from everybody.
Thank you for that... OK, alternative fade without coding,
thanks to Ryan for this one so when we
get to the start scene we fade in with
this fade panel entity here and we have
a script on it, a fade in script which is
fine and let's just have a quick look at that
fade in script. It's relatively simple but
it does a few things, it has to find
components and mess around, how about doing
it with the animator? That's a good idea from
Ryan that's perfectly valid, so let's
disable the script so now when you run
the Start menu it will not fade in, it'll
just sit there, it's actually got a murky panel
hanging on it right now. So let's look
how we'd do it now that you're clear with
the animator. You add an animator, let's
create a animation controller and let's
call it fade. Just simply fade. Let's
attach the fade animation controller to
it - by the way I think you can do this
yourself so I would encourage you to try
stopping and doing a fade in on your own,
if not just continue to watch me and I shall
show you had to do it, so there's the
fade, there's the fade animation, let's just
take a look at it then. If we go over to the
animation what have we got? We don't have
a curve yet, we need one so fade in.
There's the fade in animation there, great
so we're gonna fade in over how long?
Well two seconds is what we had before in
the script, so let's go for two seconds.
So what we do is we had a keyframe, well
first we need to decide on the curve. The
curve is going to operate on the image
color, that's what you need: the image
color. OK? Great so we drag the keyframe
out to 2 seconds,
so in the beginning we set the color at
zero time we want 255 we want a
fully opaque black box and then at two
seconds over here, we want to set the
color keyframe down to 0s, so a fully
transparent black box. Nearly there,
the only problem with this at the moment
is it will fade just fine even though the
script's disabled but it's going to keep
fading in loops, so the way we change
that if we go here to the fade in
animation and turn off looping. Great, the
second thing that's going to go wrong is
we're not going to be able to click because we've
got a panel sitting over the top so we
need to disable the panel in the
animation you can also do that you go to
this image and you choose the Enabled
property it's enabled on the first
keyframe but it is disabled
towards the end, actually at the end. Now you
might say how about if we want to be able to
click before the fade is finished, well
you could try that but when the panel
disappears you get a sharp bang, you see that
bang in color? So you are going to
need to do it at the end there unless we get
more elaborate which we don't need to. So
that's it, you have an animation sitting
on the fade panel that has a color and a
fade like that, perfectly valid. In fact
it's so valid that I am going to leave it
like that, I will leave the fade script
disabled and just use the fade animation
so we have two options, alright and there
it goes; and of course you could get a
lot more customisation over it this way
if you wanted to. So thank you for that Ryan
let's look at the next tweak.
Pretty much there we just need to save
our scene that we worked on so hard
and make sure we prefab everything so if
we go to level one here then we've got a
lot of stuff in this scene right let's
just zoom to the level canvas, all
these guys here are fine, we want
everything prefabbed. So the camera is
already prefabbed, you can see it from the
inspector, the level canvas is preffabbed,
what we want to do is start prefabbing
the attackers and defenders, we've done
a lot of work on them so I'm actually gonna
create a subfolder of prefabs called
attackers and it's literally just a
question of dragging each one into there
so they go blue and any changes we make
to the attackers on this level
reflect over on any future level that we
create using prefabs so create another folder
for defenders inside your prefabs and
then take each of your defenders and
prefab them by dragging one at a time...
gnome, cactus, gravestone, star trophy perfect
now the final thing I would like to do
here is go to level two and just look at
the differences between that and level
one, well we have a game camera which is fine,
we have a level 1, level canvas 1 in level 2,
what's that all about?
So I'm gonna confidently delete my level
canvas 1 and bring in my prefabbed level
canvas cos it should just work; what else
do we need from level 1, I want to make sure the
attackers and defenders... Ok so let's try
it without necessarily putting them in any
folders, let's drop a fox in and let's drop
a lizard in, great and let's just check they
animate and of course they do because
they're all prefabbed. Great, so we don't need
to go any further with level 1 and level 2
at the moment, we've proved that prefabbing
works, so pretty happy, that's all good
and that's the end of this section;  if
you look back to see... this part of the
section sorry... if you look back to level one
you'll see that basically we have all
the animation we want, the main job now
is to script all the types of behaviours we want,
and that's going to be the subject of
the next part of this section. See you soon.