Hey and welcome back. so our game is now
crying out for our attackers to be
moving. I think that's the next most
important thing. We also want to
understand how we move things from
script when we also have animations
involved so that we can decide how we're
going to deal with these inconsistent
speeds of our projectiles and the courgette
disappearing halfway through the
animation here; so in this video we are
going to create an attacker dot cs
component. I'll explain why we're going to
use a component model rather than
inheritance and then we''l tune our
animation to avoid moonwalking. What do I
mean by moonwalking? You'll see in a
moment.
Alright so basically we have these guys.
these attackers and let's talk
to them - about them rather at the pre-fab
level. We have a fox and a lizard at the
moment. Now we could create separate Fox
and lizard scripts and then copy and
paste code between them that's common and
then decide what to factor out.
refactor or factorise out. that's
absolutely fine. Another approach would
be to say straight away we know they're
both attackers. so why don't we add an
attacker script to both of them. put all
the common behavior in there and then
anything we need to do that's specific to a
particular attacker. maybe we create
another script. maybe we just put like a
checkbox on the attacker script like can
jump for example on the Fox. So let's see
how we go let's start off with a with a
methodology of creating an attacker's
component right? So I'm going to call it
attacker. There it is. attacker script sitting
there on the lizard and let's also add
it to the Fox attacker... now cos I'm tidy
and neat I'm gonna stick that straight in
my scripts folder and I'm going to open
the wrong script. it doesn't matter cos we
gotta wait for mono to load anyway. So
once Mono has loaded I will grab the
attacker script... come on Mono. you can
do it hey here we go. attacker. So
currently attacker does the sum total of
absolutely nothing. which is fine.
So the first thing I want to be able to do is get
the center of gravity of these guys
moving and don't be put off by center of
gravity. by that I just mean their transform.
I'm using the word centre of gravity
because they actually animate now and
they move around in fact strictly it's
not the center of gravity. it's the center
of the animation. strictly speaking what
we gonna be moving is the pivot point of
the animation if we look here say at the
jump frames in the sprite editor you'll
see that they all have that circular
pivot point in the middle so it's
actually that that we're going to be moving. at
least for now. We don't really want to
get involved in changing the pivot
point for every frame of an animation.
you could do that in the long term. you
could come in and say let's put this
at his centre of gravity on every single
frame and that'd be a different way of
dealing with it. perfectly valid as well
but I don't think that that's what I
want to be doing here. So gonna leave the
animations and the pivot points as they
are and just move the whole transform
and what will happen is that that whole
sprite block will move. OK. so how are we going to
do it? Well. it is relatively simple. I'm going to show
you a new annotation. We want a public
speed and we can just go public float
walk speed like that and that will work
fine and over in the inspector then all
attackers when we get back to the
prefabs will have a walk speed; but what
range is reasonable to set the walk
speed in and how do I set it? Well I can
drag left and right like this by just
clicking on walks speed and dragging but let me
show you useful annotation. it goes like
this... goes a little something like this. you go
range and you open some brackets and
close some brackets and close some square
brackets and whatever you put in here.
say minus one float to 1.5 float - if you
put that immediately above or if you
wish
in front of that definition either of
these will do. the white space doesn't
matter then watch what happens over in
the inspector... here you go. so no you've got a
range of minus one to 1.5 so just an
alternative for you. it can be a great
interface to your designer that basically
saying to them hey set a range in this
in this area they can type minus three
but when they try and do it look what happens
as soon as you hit return it just defaults
to -1. so it basically puts a minimum and a
maximum allowed value. If you don't have
a separate designer. well you're your own
separate designer this is a great
discipline to get into that as a programmer
you think about what makes sense to
change in the inspector.
Cool. so we have a walk speed. then the question
comes how we're going to update the
position of the guy every frame; well this
is relatively simple stuff now for you
guys at this stage in the course. it's
not too tricky I'm gonna show you some
slightly different ways of doing it just
to give you some alternatives so what we're
gonna do here is just say transform dot
translate... we haven't done that before
you can look it up in the docs if you
want but rather than us creating a new
vector and passing it in and all that business
this transform dot translate simply
moves the transform in the direction
of the translation. alright so that's
gonna make life a bit easier. and we can
also use something like this: Vector3 dot
left which is going to be left on our
screen if we've used the coordinate
system that we've used; or put
differently if we find an attacker and
have a look at our coordinates you can
see that it is in the negative X direction
that's what left means. right so we can say
translate vector three dot
left now that's fine that's the
direction what's the...
how far? Well distance is speed times time;
so what's the time? What am I gonna put
in here because it's in the update it's going to
depend on the frame rate. we've seen this
lots of times - time dot Delta time. OK.
fantastic so we're basically saying
distance equal speed times time here. and this
is just a unit vector pointing to the
left so it doesn't affect the speed at
all its just telling us which direction
we want to be going in. Cool. so that
would do the translation. let's try it - we hit
play - there we go. the fox is walking; and
where's the lizard? Well let's click on the actual
lizard. give him a speed. and if he has a
positive walk speed off he goes. OK. there
he goes. perfect.
So that is how you set the speed. the
movement of the transform as a
whole from script and this is a useful
annotation in here that allows you
to drag in the inspector. So what I want
you to go ahead and do now then is to
just tune the walk speed for both of
these guys. the Fox and the lizard or
whatever attackers you have. find the
ideal speed for each attacker and save
the speed values back to the prefabs.
So what I mean by moonwalking briefly
before you go into that is as follows
If I then zoom into say the lizard when
he's doing his walk bit we want his
feet to not look like they're slipping.
right now he's walking too fast and
right now he's walking too slow. so it's
a question of tuning it so that he
walks with grip rather than kind of
sliding. that's the idea. So pause the video. go ahead
and save your ideal walk speeds and work out
how to save those back to the prefabs
you can test you got it right by
dropping new guys into the scene and
they should continuously move to the
left at walk speed. That's obviously
going to look strange for the appear
animation and for various other animations
but one step at a time.
OK cool so I'm just gonna start with the
with this guy with a lizard what I'm
gonna do with the lizard for the minute is
I'm just gonna fix him into one animation
state because I don't want to be having
to constantly see him transition out of
that animation state so I can go to my
animation layout which has got all the
things I need. lizard animation. lizard
going to appearing I could just suppress
that; I could mute that at the moment yeah?
So I can click mute up here in the inspector
and then if we watch the lizard he now
won't come out of appearing. so obviously
I'm muting the wrong thing there. what I need
to be muting is the walking to
attacking so he will appear and then
start walking but then he will never
leave the walking state which is what I
want. Great. so now I'm going to zoom into
the scene view - there he is - scroll around a little
bit and fiddle with the walk speed. Now. bear
in mind whatever changes I make to
this now will not be saved back to the
prefab at the moment. which is fine. so just kind of
do this by eye. what looks right. and if you wanna
get him to the back the reason I gave you a
negative walk speed is because we can kind of
reset him. it's kind of fun isn't it? If you like that
sort of thing. OK. so you get the idea.
what I'm doing is just getting the
walk spees so it looks reasonable it doesn't look
like he's slipping there. let's just give him a walk speed
of one. Simple. now of course you haven't saved
that so you could either copy the
component here. stop playing in which
case it'll disappear and then paste
component values - that's fine so you've
got it on this particular instance of
the lizard but if you look at your
prefab lizard he still has a walk speed of zero.
so the way that you get it from the
instance to the pre-fab is either set the
pre-fab manually or you can click Apply
here the walk speed is no longer bold cos
it's no different from the pre-fab
click on the pre-fab and you'll see his walk
speed is one. The final test I said was
to drag a lizard prefab into the scene
and see if he starts walking how we
expect so let's try it. let's drag
a new lizard into the scene
There he is. walking just fine
OK cool. just gonna quickly do the same
thing for the fox then. so go into the
animator for the fox. we want him to
walk but want him to not leave the
walking state so we mute that transition for now.
we take a look and make sure he's
walking. zoom into him. get your screen
set up so that you can see what's going
on and then adjust the walk speed - I'm going to go
in to scene view because I can see a bit better.
Just reset him - this is really looking like moon-walking now as he goes backwards. pretty
cool... alright so we just want his feet to
kind of stick to the ground. that's OK
.46. Shall I say .45 just to satisfy my obsession
with round numbers? Just check he looks
alright. just bring him back. Drag him
back by his transform. it's kind of fun. I
think that's not okay now I think he's
now. no he's sliding forward so I'm gonna
stick with non-round numbers. Come on
fox. back you come. let's have a look at
your walking. Mate. Yeah I think about point
four is about right. I'm determined to a
round number aren't I? No getting round it. So point
four. again I can copy component if I want to. stop
running paste component values and then
apply back to the prefab. and if I
really want to drop a new fox in I
could but I'm sure that the prefab has
updated. in fact look we can see it there.
Perfect. so that is it. We have managed to
now get the guys moving at the right
speed different speeds between the two
attackers and they are now walking
properly. So congratulations on that bit.
the lizard is much faster than the fox.
that's his strength but the fox's
strength is he can slyly jump over
gravestones which we'll deal with shortly.
So. see you soon.