Welcome back in this video we're gonna talk
about what
animation events are and why we want
to use them. gonna tell you which metrics
can and can't be called from animation
events and then we're going to make some
modifications to attacker dot cs so that
the animator can control the speed of
our characters. we're gonna get the
animation transitions working for all the
attackers and then add ourselves a
wishful strike current target method. so
that we can start to think about the
animator also dealing the damage. So what
are these funny animator event things?
Well if you look at Unity's manual for it
the crux of it is this: in the animation
controller you can see here you have a
little button you can press where you
put these little flags in and they allow
you to call certain functions and
pass in parameters. so pretty handy. and we're
going to use that for setting and un-
setting speed and for dealing damage and
possibly for some other things. So let's
take a look at how that all pans out over in
Unity; so here we are at the moment our
lizard comes in and he does three
cycles of animation whilst still moving left
and then goes into his walk. so
clearly he needs to not be moving when
he appears. So how're we gonna orchestrate
that? Well it turns out that animation events
are super handy for this. so if we look at
the lizard prefab - best to work on the
prefabs here - and then go into his
animation what we could do at the start
of  lizard appearing is we could say
that we want to put an animation event
in. Now in order to actually operate on
the animation you cannot do that
unfortunately directly on the prefabs so
you're gonna have to take the lizard itself
the instance but we need to be very
careful to apply any changes we make
back to the prefab. So always try and
work on your prefab if you can. but where
you can't you're gonna need to work on
the particular instance being very
careful to apply back. So if we add this
animation event in it's gonna give us a
list of functions we can call and at the
moment it's only on trigger enter 2D
where's it got that from? Well it's got it
from the attacker script here - this
attacker script we have attached has an
on trigger enter 2d.
It's a bit weird that it can call that. you don't really
want it to. but it is there because it's a
method on the attacker. Now what
scripts can you call?  Well you can call any
functions that are attached to
any scripts attached to the actual
parent object but not to child objects
so if on the body
we had a script. let's just to create a
script called foo for a minute. and then in
foo let's just make ourselves a public method.
just as a test public void test method
ok and nothing in it... now if we go back
to the animator and we try and use this
event to call that test method it won't
appear because foo is on the sub. on
the lizard's body which is a child -
you just can only do it on the top level
object. so if we take this food script
and remove it but stick it on the lizard
itself. and then say to the event what do
you want to call then you get test method
and you can pass certain parameters and
certain others you cannot pass; you can
for example pass bools and floats. it will
tell you somewhere in their docs what
you can pass. Here you go. the parameter can be a
float. a string. an int. an object reference
or an animation event object; we're
basically going to use floats for now
alright cool so that is the idea of it
it's a way of the animator calling a
script which I really like - let me just get
rid of the foo script because it was
just there as an example.
Alright. so to allow us to control the
speed from script. this is what we can do.
Go in to your attacker script and we had
this publicly exposed walk speed and we gave
it a range in the inspector. which is
fine. it was a very fine way of tuning
the walk speed of both the lizard and the fox.
right and we came down to the idea that
the lizard has a walk speed of one and
the fox we gave a walk speed of point
four which fitted in ok with their animations.
Now what we want to do is start doing
this from the animator. so we're gonna
need a method. we can't just make the
walk speed public. in fact it already is
public and you'll see that this
little event guy. against say the lizard
appearing cannot talk to the members. It can
only call methods. So in pure object
oriented fashion we're gonna create ourselves
a very thin method here that just sets the
walk speed; before we do that let's
rename walk speed to current speed. it's
more meaningful now; so walk speed
becomes current speed. then what we're gonna
do is have a little method that uses public
void set speed and it's going to take in a
float for the speed. There it is. now it's simply
just gonna say current speed =
speed. It's as simple as that but the
benefit of this is that at the start of
the lizard appearing we can have an
event that immediately says set speed 0
let's take a look at that working. you
see the lizard appearing with zero
horizontal speed. Now I know he has
movement from left to right. let's watch
it frame by frame for a minute. I know he's
moving but he's only moving because of
the animation ok it's not his
transform that's moving. if you watch the
transform it stays where it is. alright so
we're doing his center of gravity by what I
by that I mean center of sprite sheet
control from script in this case
so there you go. that's fine. so he only
wants to appear once of course. so go into
the animator. look at your animator
for your lizard and on your transition
criteria we have three repeats here; well
we only want one repeat. easy enough to sort
out right? Exit time after one repeat but it
is atomic we don't want to be able to interrupt the
appearing animation. so there you go now
if you've got nasty blends and things you can
either sort them out by dragging around
or just delete the transition. don't be
afraid to just delete the transition and
start afresh. You just fresh say atomic
exit after one in fact that the default.
let's see that work. The atomic only has
an effect when you try and interrupt
the animation. so now it does a single and it
moves now the problem is that at the start
of walking he has no walk speed. so I want
you to do that. I want you to go to the
lizard walking animation. add yourself an
animation event. and set the speed to
whatever we had the lizard speed as.
So here on the lizard when
he's walking we just add another
animation event. we set the speed and let's try 1; I don't remember whether the lizard walked at 1 or 4. let's see
how his walk looks. That's ok
his feet aren't slipping... so there you go.
great so what's the next speed look at
the lizard attacking. well when he starts
attacking we don't want him moving. you get the
idea? OK now he doesn't have the opportunity to go
into an attack state so let's look at
the rest of these transitions he goes
from appearing to walking just once and
he does a single animation of appearing
atomically without break and goes to
walking - done. When does he go from
walking to attacking well he does that -
lets un-mute it - he does that when his
attacking bool is set now we've got it as
an attacking trigger at the moment -
triggers only do one animation. that's
great for the Fox jumping over the
stone but we're actually for
attacking it's continuous so we're actually going to
use a bool. so Im going to add a new parameter to the
lizard animator. and I'm gonna call it bool
and I'm going to say is attacking. alright. and then the
criteria for transiting from walking to
attacking is exactly that bool. Let's
remove any unnecessary transitions. it's never
gonna go back to lizard appearing. so from
walking to attacking the criteria is is
attacking is true and from attacking to
walking that happens when his attacking
becomes false and by deleting the
transitions we're getting rid of all that
rubbish that we had that had to do with
you making things that stay in existence
for three seconds. so there he goes. he's
walking walking walking if I click is
attacking down here in the animator he goes
into an attacking state and he will loop
through that attacking state
continuously until I und0 it. at which
point he will immediately go back to
walking. Cool. that is it for the lizard
OK so let's take you into
another challenge. What I want you to do
is on the attacker dot cs I want you to
add a wishful method called strike
current target that takes in an amount of
damage.
Do nothing inside it apart from to log to
the console that something is doing some
damage. you may want to include what's
doing the damage with the keyword name
and then add at least one animation
event per attacker in their attack state
that deals some damage. so just put a little
flag on. it can be at multiple points in the
animation you may want to kind of do a
jab and then a right hook for example. but put in at
least one animation event to deal a
certain amount of damage so if it was
jab and right hook you may do 5 damage
with the jab and 20 with the right hook or
something. So go ahead and do that now.
and just get it logging to the console when
they're in the attack state. Cool so here
we are then. let's just look at the
attacker script and let's get
ourselves a new method that we can get
to from the animator. Strike current
target. so later we'll work out what that
target is and how we find that out but
for now we're just gonna deal some damage
and all we're gonna do is just debug dot log name
plus damage caused damage and then I'll put
the amount down. There you go. so there's a strike
current target method. so what we can do
back in the animator is for both the lizard
in his attacking state. so where in his
attacking state? Well it's up to us. Somewhere
in his attacking state I'm just gonna
stick it here he is going to go deal
some damage. but it's not appearing in the
list so why is it not appearing in the
list and the reason it's not appearing
in the list is. if you see. there's a
compile error at the bottom... even though I'm in the habit
of going control or command b for
build I still missed this compile error. of course it's
public void. it returns nothing. If I now
build. back to unity. you have no errors
at the bottom now; now this little event
that we got. we can say strike current
target and let's just in the middle of
our animation deal 5 damage. Now we could
add another damage somewhere else. here
you can see there are two stacked on top
of each other
and I could strike some more damage. I
could do another five later on. Alright so
what that's going to do is when we are
in the attacking state we're going to
lizard caused damage. you're going to
see some damage there. You also have an error
that the lizard animation event has no
function name specified. so let's just
find out which one that is. set speed
strike current target. no function selected
so somehow we missed that; that's what
that means if you see that error. now let's try
running again. then twice per frame when
the lizard is in the is attacking
state we should go to the animator and you
click the parameter on then you're going
to see lizard caused damage 5 once twice
every time that it goes round this
animation it'll go one. two. at about one second and ten
frames and then at two seconds and one
frame in my case. Cool. so that's the lizard
doing damage. let's just while we're here
get the Fox doing some damage. so Fox
attack state. just gonna stick in a
single event somewhere in the middle
here maybe. normally you'd synchronise this
with your animation and we can fine tune
that later but we're just going to
strike something maybe with a damage
of 10; so now when the fox is in his
attacking state he will deal damage. but
of course we can't get the fox into
his attacking state yet because our animation
states aren't right; so let's fix the fox. The
default state is the orange walk. he goes from
walk to jump when? Well. let's just remove
all these transitions and start afresh
to be honest because the problem with
him is they're inheriting a whole bunch
of blending information here on the
right. and that's just confusing. so let's
just get rid of all our animations... ok
fantastic. so what's the first one? He
goes from walk to jump when? Well this is
where we do use a trigger and I'm gonna
call it jump trigger; the difference
between a trigger and a bool is that a
trigger just gets called; you just set it
once from script.
it'll go into a single loop of jump and
then go back to walk. so let's try
it. You go from walk to jump on jump
trigger and you go from jump back to
walk with... you don't need any criteria
for that. you just do a single jump
animation and then you go back to walk
so just putting a default transition
should do the job and then when you go
from walk to attack? Well. same thing. we
need a new thing but this is a bool because
attacking is a continuous thing; use a
trigger when it's a one off like a jump
and attack and that typically lasts a
certain amount of time and a bool for
when it's something that's continuous. so
we're gonna have another is attacking.
like so. and we're gonna say that he can go
from walk to attack when is attacking is
true. and guess what. to attack to walk when
is attacking
is false. OK. let's try him. let's have a go
with our lizard here.
Our fox rather. so our fox is walking. it's not moving
as we haven't set a speed parameter yet but
if I put jump trigger... boing he jumps
once and goes back to walking. you see
that in the state machine? Awesome. how about is attacking
well it goes into attacking. now his
attacking animation looks very similar
to his walking animation to me. let's
have a look. Suspiciously similar
OK so I think there's a problem there.
let's just take a look at the fox walk
attack apart from having different frame rates
they're the same. so let's try and be
a bit more consistent with these frame rates.
what's the lizard using? 30 frames a
second. ok let's make the fox use 30
frames a second for everything. jumping.
walking and attacking. but we need to
change out the sprites; we have just
put - or I have just put the wrong sprites
in. so if you've made the same mistake by
following me blindly no problem. just go get
your fox attack frames. stick them in
remove the fox previous fox frames.
because they're just his walking frames.
move his attack frames over. and then at
some point in the attack he needs to deal
damage. and also while you're here why
not set the speed?
What speed is he going to jump at? Well I
don't know. let's try three he needs to jump a
bit faster. so at the start... Oh sorry. he
attacks at zero speed. He
attacks at zero speed. he walks at... well let's
set it now. I think it was nought point four
if I remember rightly. he walks at a
speed of Nought point four and at the
start of his jump. this is where we give
him a speed of let's just try three. so
you see what I'm doing here. I'm saying to the
fox when you attack you start off with
a speed of zero and you - in the
middle of your animation you deal 10
damage. when you start walking you start
walking with a speed of four. and when you start
jumping you set your speed to three; let's
try him. if you're in the animator with the fox selected.
If I jump - woah look at that. pretty cool... now watch something about the jump look what happens when he
lands... you see he slides on the landing? Why is he sliding on the landing?
Well what we can do is we... is because
we do three times the speed at the start
but he never stops so maybe he wants to
come to a halt maybe wanna go set speed
and just after he lands maybe set the speed to zero. so when he jumps. he jumps. stops and then
starts walking. that looks better. but it's your
choice where you put those things you
see the flexibility of actually setting
these things from the animator? Pretty
awesome. hey? You can do a huge amount.
let's just check that the fox now goes
into a sensible animation state for
attacking; let me zoom in. there he is. Hello lizard.
walking by... so there's the fox attacking. there's him
walking. and then there's him jumping.
Cool. so just need to finish off the
states for the lizard now just make sure
he's got everything he needs - he walks
and he attacks. what else do we need?
That's about it
alright so for this video we've done
everything that we set out to do. At the
start we said we were going to... tell you
what and why animation events are. what methods
can be called and what can't. basically
only methods on the object itself. on
scripts that are attached to the object
itself. not its children.
We modified attacker dot cs to accept
speed event. we got animation
transitions working for all the
attackers. i.e. the fox and the lizard. and
we added a wishful strike current target
method which later will actually deal
damage. Congratulations and I'll see you soon.