So I've rearranged my game space here just
to demonstrate something the next thing
we want this game to do is for the
lizard to stop and attack the stone when
it gets to it but the fox wants to jump
over it and then when both the lizard and
the fox get to the gnome and the cactus at the
back they both want to attack. So this is
some abstraction we need to be doing
here. we need - they're both attackers but
they need to behave slightly differently;
how are we going to achieve that? In this video
I'm gonna talk about two different
approaches to abstraction; talk about the
benefits of a component model. and we'll
get strike - I'll challenge you to get strike
current target working. So what's the
difference between the two different
ways of doing things? Well the difference between
abstraction and inheritance is as
follows:
instead of sharing code between two
classes by having them inherit from the
same class we do so by having them both
own an instance of the same class; that's
from the game programming patterns
website and book which I highly
recommend. So what we're saying here is
that the lizard and the fox both have
attacker scripts on them. you can see
that in the inspector. what we gonna be
doing is... that makes them
both attackers. but what we gonna be
doing is adding scripts called fox
and lizard respectively to introduce their
specialized behavior. So they are both
attackers because they both have an
attacker script. that's what Robert means
when he says both of them own an instance
of the same class. that's both the lizard and
the fox having an attacker script on
them. So why do it this way will let me
show you a table. At the moment we have a
fox and a lizard interacting with the
stone. a star trophy. and a cactus - the top
left of this table and we want the fox
to jump over stones. attack star
trophies and attack cacti. and we want
to lizard to attack everything. but
imagine in future that we introduce a mole
and a jumping mole as enemies. and a land
mine and a big stone as other types of
defender then we may have more
interesting behaviors for instance
the mole may burrow under a big stone
but nobody can jump over a big stone
it's just too high;
jumping mole may burrow under a big stone
but jump over a normal stone for example
- so it's a pretty dangerous guy this jumping
mole. The cool thing about this is they're
just script names fox. lizard mole.
jumping mole. they would all be scripts
you add to an attacker alongside their
attacker script. and then you get the
specialist behavior you're looking for. and then
these other scripts we already have a
stone. star trophy. cactus... and you would
be adding land mine and big stone
scripts to those defenders; you may also
have a general defender script that ties
them all together. if nothing else to
tag them as a defender. although you could use
Unity's tag. but if there's any general
defender behavior they would all exhibit you
would put it in there. So this is why
it's so powerful because we can extend
our code and our behavior without
changing our existing code base or
breaking anything. Imagine you're releasing a
patch to your game and it introduces new
enemy types. much safer to do it this way.
So let's start thinking about setting up
to do that. how are we gonna do it? Then well
we're gonna need two different scripts.
we're going to need a fox and a lizard script which
you just simply add to these guys.
you're going to want to use some on trigger
enter 2d method inside the fox and lizard
script. and then that's going to want to
call into attacker; but I'm gonna leave
all of that to you. so this is gonna be
a big challenge for you. go ahead and
have a go at it - add a fox and a lizard cs
script for the specialized behavior.
arrange for these scripts to talk to
attacker dot cs. they can also trigger the
animator directly. still no need to actually
deal any damage. just logging that out is
fine. and put your on trigger enter 2d on
the fox and lizard; at the end of the
challenge I want to see the fox and the
lizard approach the stones. the lizard
attacks the stone. the fox jumps over the
stone. and then the fox continues on
until he gets to another defender. at which
point. like a gnome or a cactus he
just attacks that. and as long as they're doing that it's
fine; we don't need the stone to disappear.
we don't need them to deal any damage yet.
So. go for it. and I shall see you on the other side.
How did you get on with that challenge?
Well. let's take a look at how we're gonna
do this then. so start off by giving the
fox some specialist behavior - the first
thing I want to happen let's say is the
fox jumps over the stone. so let's
create a new script called fox - you have
an on trigger - void on trigger enter 2d
method and we're gonna need to know what
the collider is that he has triggered
with. so let's talk about the collider
2d. collider. like that now the
first thing I would like to do is make
sure that this is actually happening. so
debug dot log. and then we say
something like fox collided with and
then plus collider; so let's just see if
the fox collides. but before we get too
excited about the fox colliding with
anything let's make sure he can collide
with something; he has on him... what does
he have. he has a box collider but he's
moving. so if he's moving he's going to need
a rigid body on him as well now
previously we did that in script this
time I'm gonna do it the other way I'm
going to do it by adding a rigid body
and making that rigid body kinematic so
he has a kinematic rigid body
collider. you always need that when something's moving.
and then I'm gonna move that up next to
the collider they kind of go together. So we
have a 2D box collider with kinematic
rigid body on it which makes it a rigid
body trigger collider; kinematic rigid
body trigger collided. OK. that's good
now let's just check the thing he's going to
collide with which is a gravestone. put this at the
top. what's that got on it? Just a box
collider that's a trigger. Good. so the fox now should
collide with the grave stone. let's make
sure that happened. in terms of the log
entries. gravestone trigger enter fox
collided with axe... lots of triggers. so
let me just turn off the maximize on
play. get a better look at the console.
what we're looking for is fox collided
with gravestone. there you go. so the fox is
colliding with a gravestone. Let's not
worry about all these other triggers. all these
other events for now. we need to
intercept the fact the fox collided with
the grave stone and then get him to jump
over the grave stone
using the jump trigger. OK so the first
thing I want to do is to pull off the
game objects from the collider. so let's
be clear on what's happening here. There is a
message being called on the fox because
its trigger collider has been entered.
Into that is being passed the collider
of the other object. the thing it's
collided with. so in this case it's
collided with a gravestone. So what I want to
create myself is a GameObject
ready to take that gravestone and let's
call it
obj just for now. just for simplicity. and
brevity it's the object that it has
collided with; and it equals collider dot
game object so when this fox hits the stone
obj will be the actual gravestone
object. Great. alright now
first thing we need to do is say well we
only gonna do anything if I've actually
collided with a defender. Say I've collided
with a projectile. or I've collided with
something else
another attacker I don't do anything so
the way we can do that is we can say if
obj dot get component and then defender. and its
nice and strong. now you could use tags but
this is much stronger because it
actually going to check this at
compile-time all of our defenders have
got a defender script on them right so
if our gravestone has to have a
defender script on it then why not just
look for that as the indication.
remember back to my slide
look here. This matrix is saying how do
we know that it's a stone? Well because
it has the grave stone script on it. How do
we know it's a defender in general?
Because it has a defender script on
it; how do we know it's a lizard? Because it has a
lizard script on it. you get the idea. So
if obj dot get component defender - if that is
true then what do we do? Well. actually we
want an abort condition at the top. so if
it's not a defender then we return. we
just get out of here
OK if you're not sure what that does just put
a comment in; abort or leave the method
if not colliding with defender.
OK cool. so we just get out of there if we're not
colliding with a defender. How about if we
are colliding with a defender? Well you
could move this debug log code below
here to find out that that is working
correctly. ok. now let's try that - now we
should only beginning log entries of the
fox colliding with defenders; so
previously it was colliding with the
gravestone. and the axe. and other things
let's try again now. Don't worry about any
errors for now. but what we're looking
for is for fox colliding with the gravestone but no
axe; it's not colliding with the axes.
So when we talked about collision
detection and collision matrices and things
in code. we've already started doing that here. Hopefully that makes sense to you. OK. so now we go
for the specialized fox behavior. we say
if object dot get component... just gonna copy
from above...
Now what? If it collides with the
stone then we have some special behavior.
what do we do if it collides with the stone?
Well we're gonna go straight to the
animator and trigger a jump animation.
why not? So what we need here of course
is the stones to have themselves a stone
script on them even if the gravestone
script doesn't do anything else but tell
us that we're dealing with a gravestone
we need that so on the prefabs for the
stones rather than just tagging it with
stone or anything. let's actually give it
a new script called stone; it's much
stronger. it can be checked at compile time
apart from anything else.
Tidy up our scripts. now if you're back in here
get component stone will actually work;
so if that happens we need to animator .
set trigger then the jump trigger;
remember over in the animator for the
fox let's take a look at the fox
look at his animator. how does he get into
jump? He gets into jump because we've got a
jump trigger. so we need
to set that trigger from code. so how do
we do that? Well we need to talk to the animator.
let's find the animator first. so at the
class level we're gonna need the animator. OK.
and then we need to find that animator
on start; ok so we've gone and found the animator
we have access to the animator now as anim.
. now how do you do this set trigger? Well
it's set trigger. and then what do you
give it? Well it just wants an id or a
string. and we called it jump trigger as a
string; so if it collides with the stone. jump
else what are we gonna do? Well if it doesn't
collide with a stone then we just want it
to attack; so let's have a way of talking
to the attacker and saying attacker .
attack alright? So how are we gonna talk to the
attacker? Well firstly here's a new thing for
you. require component: if fox's always
rely on an attacker here's an annotation
for you that's incredibly useful. require
component bracket type of brackets
attacker and the reason we're doing that
is because the fox makes no
sense without an attacker. the fox is a
specialization of the attacker behaviour
so we must have an attacker component so
this require component is a protection
mechanism; what it means is that in
future if we ever add a fox dot cs
script to a GameObject then at that time
when we add it in the inspector unity will
check to see if we've also got an
attacker. and if we haven't it will add
an attacker component for us. let's make
sure we do. here's our fox. he has both an
attacker and a fox script. we're good. Now we
need to find that attacker. so we're gonna
need a private attacker. and this is the
general pattern when you use components
here. and then in the start you need to
go find that attacker. Why don't you do that
right now? Why don't you go find that
attacker now? It's very simple. very similar to
the line above. Go ahead. do it without me OK
so it's just a standard get component again.
OK perfect so we have our attacker
available now. so what are we gonna do if
we're not encountering a stone in all
other cases if we look back at our
matrix when a fox meets anything else
apart from a stone it attacks. so why don't we
pretend we have a method called attacker dot
attack and just pass in the object -
moving quite quickly here to get this
finished off and keep the video short.
you can always rewind if you need to. let's go
over to attacker and make this attack
method public void attack. and it doesn't
need to... it takes in actually sorry
a GameObject
OK so let's be clear on what the difference between attack
and strike current target is; attack puts the
attacker into attack mode strike current
target is called from the animator at
the time of the actual attack. At the
time of the actual blow. alright but we
need to know what the current target is
so one thing we're going to need up here
is the current target; so by the way we
don't need the current speed or its
range to be publicly exposed in the
attacker anymore so make it private
I'm also gonna have myself a private
game object current target so the
attacker is always keeping track of the
current target; who is he supposed to be
attacking. so what do we do on this
attack thing? Well it's relatively simple
we're just firstly going to set the
current target to the thing that's been
passed in. so in this case the fox has
hit the stone and then it has passed the
stone in here as an object and we just
say obj. like that OK. so now the current
target becomes the object. we'll use the
current target and strike current target
in a different video. the other thing we
need to do is signal the animator to
change its state so we're going to need
the animator in here to
have access to the animator. possibly
in here or in the fox. possibly in
both; in fact as we've already got access
to the animator inside the fox why don't
we just attacker dot attack with a
capital A and then immediately before
that... before that lets say. let's
put the animator into a different
state animator . set bool is attacking
to true; so this script says if I hit a
stone then jump. otherwise set the
attacking state to true and then tell
the attacker to go into attack mode and
then the attacker does the general
handling of attack. which at the moment
just sets the current target. Let's see
what the behaviour is for now with this
fox; fox walks along. hits a stone. jumps
and then carries on walking. Beautiful. all we need
to do is get the behaviour into the lizard.
Now the lizard is going to be relatively simple
because he's very very similar to the
fox. he just has one small difference. So
let's take the fox's code; all of the
fox's code. copy it. go to your lizard. add
yourself a component called lizard.
a lizard script; go into to your lizard script
Also tidying the scripts as you go while we wait for
it to open... scripts / lizard. put all of your
fox code into the lizard. rename the
class at the top immediately to match
the filename. now it still needs an
animator it still needs the concept of
an attacker that it's going to be
talking to what it doesn't have is
anything about jumping over a stone.
Basically all the lizard does is attack
so basically if it's not a defender it's
meeting it leaves in the same way. but
otherwise it just
attacks straight away. so we don't need
this stuff about the stone and that is
reflected in the table that we have over
in our slide. if you have a look at the
lizard and its behaviour is just attacks any
defender. so we say if it's not a defender.
get out of here and then otherwise you
just attack it. and let's get just rid of the
debug statements and you have a very simple
lizard specialization and I'm going to
get rid of the debug statement in fox.
let's just check this all works and
we'll close up this video... so
lizard comes in. fox comes in and jumps.
liard comes in and does not start
attacking. so why is the lizard not
attacking? So if we look at the lizard he
doesn't have a rigid body on him. let's
just do this a different way once
and for all. let's have a rigid body on
the fox as well.
but lets just require the component in the
script instead of adding rigid bodies in
the start let's take another approach to
this which is just that we say. all
attackers require. because they moving.
require component type of rigid body
and that's just going to make sure that
we require a rigid body 2d in all of our
attackers and then we go back over here
and try running...
OK parameter is attacking does not exist
in the lizard. so animator set bool is
attacking and that's just because of the
way I've spelt it. If you have a look
over in the animator you'll find that we have
is attacking with a capital A for the
lizard and then the fox has is attacking
with a capital A as well for some reason
the fox's script has accepted is
attacking like that. where I actually
want is attacking. we never actually
waited 'til the fox got to attacking. so
change it to is attacking spelt properly.
and let's finally have a look at this.
it should work; getting no errors logged
now. there you go. the lizard stops and
attacks. the fox jumps the stone and
let's just watch him get to the end. and
he will attack the gnome with any luck.
OK let's try that again. lizard stops and
attacks. we'll sort out the collision
distances between the lizard and the
stone in a further refinement. everything
coming up on the log are just triggers.
and then when the fox hits the gnome.
provided we spell the trigger correctly...
great he sits there and just does
damage. No damage actually being caused
yet but we have got the behavior we want.
Long video! It's time to take stock for the
evening I think. see you soon.
=======
Kind: captions
Language: en
So I've rearranged my game space here just
to demonstrate something the next thing
we want this game to do is for the
lizard to stop and attack the stone when
it gets to it but the fox wants to jump
over it and then when both the lizard and
the fox get to the gnome and the cactus at the
back they both want to attack. So this is
some abstraction we need to be doing
here, we need - they're both attackers but
they need to behave slightly differently;
how are we going to achieve that? In this video
I'm gonna talk about two different
approaches to abstraction; talk about the
benefits of a component model, and we'll
get strike - I'll challenge you to get strike
current target working. So what's the
difference between the two different
ways of doing things? Well the difference between
abstraction and inheritance is as
follows:
instead of sharing code between two
classes by having them inherit from the
same class we do so by having them both
own an instance of the same class; that's
from the game programming patterns
website and book which I highly
recommend. So what we're saying here is
that the lizard and the fox both have
attacker scripts on them, you can see
that in the inspector, what we gonna be
doing is... that makes them
both attackers, but what we gonna be
doing is adding scripts called fox
and lizard respectively to introduce their
specialized behavior. So they are both
attackers because they both have an
attacker script, that's what Robert means
when he says both of them own an instance
of the same class, that's both the lizard and
the fox having an attacker script on
them. So why do it this way will let me
show you a table. At the moment we have a
fox and a lizard interacting with the
stone, a star trophy, and a cactus - the top
left of this table and we want the fox
to jump over stones, attack star
trophies and attack cacti, and we want
to lizard to attack everything, but
imagine in future that we introduce a mole
and a jumping mole as enemies, and a land
mine and a big stone as other types of
defender then we may have more
interesting behaviors for instance
the mole may burrow under a big stone
but nobody can jump over a big stone
it's just too high;
jumping mole may burrow under a big stone
but jump over a normal stone for example
- so it's a pretty dangerous guy this jumping
mole. The cool thing about this is they're
just script names fox, lizard mole,
jumping mole, they would all be scripts
you add to an attacker alongside their
attacker script, and then you get the
specialist behavior you're looking for, and then
these other scripts we already have a
stone, star trophy, cactus... and you would
be adding land mine and big stone
scripts to those defenders; you may also
have a general defender script that ties
them all together, if nothing else to
tag them as a defender, although you could use
Unity's tag, but if there's any general
defender behavior they would all exhibit you
would put it in there. So this is why
it's so powerful because we can extend
our code and our behavior without
changing our existing code base or
breaking anything. Imagine you're releasing a
patch to your game and it introduces new
enemy types, much safer to do it this way.
So let's start thinking about setting up
to do that, how are we gonna do it? Then well
we're gonna need two different scripts,
we're going to need a fox and a lizard script which
you just simply add to these guys,
you're going to want to use some on trigger
enter 2d method inside the fox and lizard
script, and then that's going to want to
call into attacker; but I'm gonna leave
all of that to you, so this is gonna be
a big challenge for you, go ahead and
have a go at it - add a fox and a lizard cs
script for the specialized behavior,
arrange for these scripts to talk to
attacker dot cs, they can also trigger the
animator directly, still no need to actually
deal any damage, just logging that out is
fine, and put your on trigger enter 2d on
the fox and lizard; at the end of the
challenge I want to see the fox and the
lizard approach the stones, the lizard
attacks the stone, the fox jumps over the
stone, and then the fox continues on
until he gets to another defender, at which
point, like a gnome or a cactus he
just attacks that, and as long as they're doing that it's
fine; we don't need the stone to disappear,
we don't need them to deal any damage yet.
So, go for it, and I shall see you on the other side.
How did you get on with that challenge?
Well, let's take a look at how we're gonna
do this then, so start off by giving the
fox some specialist behavior - the first
thing I want to happen let's say is the
fox jumps over the stone, so let's
create a new script called fox - you have
an on trigger - void on trigger enter 2d
method and we're gonna need to know what
the collider is that he has triggered
with, so let's talk about the collider
2d, collider, like that now the
first thing I would like to do is make
sure that this is actually happening, so
debug dot log, and then we say
something like fox collided with and
then plus collider; so let's just see if
the fox collides, but before we get too
excited about the fox colliding with
anything let's make sure he can collide
with something; he has on him... what does
he have, he has a box collider but he's
moving, so if he's moving he's going to need
a rigid body on him as well now
previously we did that in script this
time I'm gonna do it the other way I'm
going to do it by adding a rigid body
and making that rigid body kinematic so
he has a kinematic rigid body
collider, you always need that when something's moving,
and then I'm gonna move that up next to
the collider they kind of go together. So we
have a 2D box collider with kinematic
rigid body on it which makes it a rigid
body trigger collider; kinematic rigid
body trigger collided. OK, that's good
now let's just check the thing he's going to
collide with which is a gravestone, put this at the
top, what's that got on it? Just a box
collider that's a trigger. Good, so the fox now should
collide with the grave stone, let's make
sure that happened, in terms of the log
entries, gravestone trigger enter fox
collided with axe... lots of triggers, so
let me just turn off the maximize on
play, get a better look at the console,
what we're looking for is fox collided
with gravestone, there you go, so the fox is
colliding with a gravestone. Let's not
worry about all these other triggers, all these
other events for now, we need to
intercept the fact the fox collided with
the grave stone and then get him to jump
over the grave stone
using the jump trigger. OK so the first
thing I want to do is to pull off the
game objects from the collider, so let's
be clear on what's happening here. There is a
message being called on the fox because
its trigger collider has been entered.
Into that is being passed the collider
of the other object, the thing it's
collided with, so in this case it's
collided with a gravestone. So what I want to
create myself is a GameObject
ready to take that gravestone and let's
call it
obj just for now, just for simplicity, and
brevity it's the object that it has
collided with; and it equals collider dot
game object so when this fox hits the stone
obj will be the actual gravestone
object. Great, alright now
first thing we need to do is say well we
only gonna do anything if I've actually
collided with a defender. Say I've collided
with a projectile, or I've collided with
something else
another attacker I don't do anything so
the way we can do that is we can say if
obj dot get component and then defender, and its
nice and strong, now you could use tags but
this is much stronger because it
actually going to check this at
compile-time all of our defenders have
got a defender script on them right so
if our gravestone has to have a
defender script on it then why not just
look for that as the indication,
remember back to my slide
look here. This matrix is saying how do
we know that it's a stone? Well because
it has the grave stone script on it. How do
we know it's a defender in general?
Because it has a defender script on
it; how do we know it's a lizard? Because it has a
lizard script on it, you get the idea. So
if obj dot get component defender - if that is
true then what do we do? Well, actually we
want an abort condition at the top, so if
it's not a defender then we return, we
just get out of here
OK if you're not sure what that does just put
a comment in; abort or leave the method
if not colliding with defender.
OK cool, so we just get out of there if we're not
colliding with a defender. How about if we
are colliding with a defender? Well you
could move this debug log code below
here to find out that that is working
correctly, ok, now let's try that - now we
should only beginning log entries of the
fox colliding with defenders; so
previously it was colliding with the
gravestone, and the axe, and other things
let's try again now. Don't worry about any
errors for now, but what we're looking
for is for fox colliding with the gravestone but no
axe; it's not colliding with the axes.
So when we talked about collision
detection and collision matrices and things
in code, we've already started doing that here. Hopefully that makes sense to you. OK, so now we go
for the specialized fox behavior, we say
if object dot get component... just gonna copy
from above...
Now what? If it collides with the
stone then we have some special behavior,
what do we do if it collides with the stone?
Well we're gonna go straight to the
animator and trigger a jump animation,
why not? So what we need here of course
is the stones to have themselves a stone
script on them even if the gravestone
script doesn't do anything else but tell
us that we're dealing with a gravestone
we need that so on the prefabs for the
stones rather than just tagging it with
stone or anything, let's actually give it
a new script called stone; it's much
stronger, it can be checked at compile time
apart from anything else.
Tidy up our scripts, now if you're back in here
get component stone will actually work;
so if that happens we need to animator .
set trigger then the jump trigger;
remember over in the animator for the
fox let's take a look at the fox
look at his animator, how does he get into
jump? He gets into jump because we've got a
jump trigger, so we need
to set that trigger from code, so how do
we do that? Well we need to talk to the animator,
let's find the animator first, so at the
class level we're gonna need the animator, OK,
and then we need to find that animator
on start; ok so we've gone and found the animator
we have access to the animator now as anim,
. now how do you do this set trigger? Well
it's set trigger, and then what do you
give it? Well it just wants an id or a
string, and we called it jump trigger as a
string; so if it collides with the stone, jump
else what are we gonna do? Well if it doesn't
collide with a stone then we just want it
to attack; so let's have a way of talking
to the attacker and saying attacker .
attack alright? So how are we gonna talk to the
attacker? Well firstly here's a new thing for
you, require component: if fox's always
rely on an attacker here's an annotation
for you that's incredibly useful, require
component bracket type of brackets
attacker and the reason we're doing that
is because the fox makes no
sense without an attacker, the fox is a
specialization of the attacker behaviour
so we must have an attacker component so
this require component is a protection
mechanism; what it means is that in
future if we ever add a fox dot cs
script to a GameObject then at that time
when we add it in the inspector unity will
check to see if we've also got an
attacker, and if we haven't it will add
an attacker component for us, let's make
sure we do, here's our fox, he has both an
attacker and a fox script, we're good. Now we
need to find that attacker, so we're gonna
need a private attacker, and this is the
general pattern when you use components
here, and then in the start you need to
go find that attacker. Why don't you do that
right now? Why don't you go find that
attacker now? It's very simple, very similar to
the line above. Go ahead, do it without me OK
so it's just a standard get component again.
OK perfect so we have our attacker
available now, so what are we gonna do if
we're not encountering a stone in all
other cases if we look back at our
matrix when a fox meets anything else
apart from a stone it attacks, so why don't we
pretend we have a method called attacker dot
attack and just pass in the object -
moving quite quickly here to get this
finished off and keep the video short,
you can always rewind if you need to, let's go
over to attacker and make this attack
method public void attack, and it doesn't
need to... it takes in actually sorry
a GameObject
OK so let's be clear on what the difference between attack
and strike current target is; attack puts the
attacker into attack mode strike current
target is called from the animator at
the time of the actual attack. At the
time of the actual blow, alright but we
need to know what the current target is
so one thing we're going to need up here
is the current target; so by the way we
don't need the current speed or its
range to be publicly exposed in the
attacker anymore so make it private
I'm also gonna have myself a private
game object current target so the
attacker is always keeping track of the
current target; who is he supposed to be
attacking, so what do we do on this
attack thing? Well it's relatively simple
we're just firstly going to set the
current target to the thing that's been
passed in, so in this case the fox has
hit the stone and then it has passed the
stone in here as an object and we just
say obj, like that OK, so now the current
target becomes the object, we'll use the
current target and strike current target
in a different video, the other thing we
need to do is signal the animator to
change its state so we're going to need
the animator in here to
have access to the animator, possibly
in here or in the fox, possibly in
both; in fact as we've already got access
to the animator inside the fox why don't
we just attacker dot attack with a
capital A and then immediately before
that... before that lets say, let's
put the animator into a different
state animator . set bool is attacking
to true; so this script says if I hit a
stone then jump, otherwise set the
attacking state to true and then tell
the attacker to go into attack mode and
then the attacker does the general
handling of attack, which at the moment
just sets the current target. Let's see
what the behaviour is for now with this
fox; fox walks along, hits a stone, jumps
and then carries on walking. Beautiful, all we need
to do is get the behaviour into the lizard.
Now the lizard is going to be relatively simple
because he's very very similar to the
fox, he just has one small difference. So
let's take the fox's code; all of the
fox's code, copy it, go to your lizard, add
yourself a component called lizard,
a lizard script; go into to your lizard script
Also tidying the scripts as you go while we wait for
it to open... scripts / lizard, put all of your
fox code into the lizard, rename the
class at the top immediately to match
the filename, now it still needs an
animator it still needs the concept of
an attacker that it's going to be
talking to what it doesn't have is
anything about jumping over a stone.
Basically all the lizard does is attack
so basically if it's not a defender it's
meeting it leaves in the same way, but
otherwise it just
attacks straight away, so we don't need
this stuff about the stone and that is
reflected in the table that we have over
in our slide, if you have a look at the
lizard and its behaviour is just attacks any
defender, so we say if it's not a defender,
get out of here and then otherwise you
just attack it, and let's get just rid of the
debug statements and you have a very simple
lizard specialization and I'm going to
get rid of the debug statement in fox,
let's just check this all works and
we'll close up this video... so
lizard comes in, fox comes in and jumps,
liard comes in and does not start
attacking, so why is the lizard not
attacking? So if we look at the lizard he
doesn't have a rigid body on him, let's
just do this a different way once
and for all, let's have a rigid body on
the fox as well,
but lets just require the component in the
script instead of adding rigid bodies in
the start let's take another approach to
this which is just that we say, all
attackers require, because they moving,
require component type of rigid body
and that's just going to make sure that
we require a rigid body 2d in all of our
attackers and then we go back over here
and try running...
OK parameter is attacking does not exist
in the lizard, so animator set bool is
attacking and that's just because of the
way I've spelt it. If you have a look
over in the animator you'll find that we have
is attacking with a capital A for the
lizard and then the fox has is attacking
with a capital A as well for some reason
the fox's script has accepted is
attacking like that, where I actually
want is attacking, we never actually
waited 'til the fox got to attacking, so
change it to is attacking spelt properly,
and let's finally have a look at this,
it should work; getting no errors logged
now, there you go, the lizard stops and
attacks, the fox jumps the stone and
let's just watch him get to the end, and
he will attack the gnome with any luck.
OK let's try that again, lizard stops and
attacks, we'll sort out the collision
distances between the lizard and the
stone in a further refinement, everything
coming up on the log are just triggers,
and then when the fox hits the gnome,
provided we spell the trigger correctly...
great he sits there and just does
damage. No damage actually being caused
yet but we have got the behavior we want.
Long video! It's time to take stock for the
evening I think, see you soon.
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1:Unity/Section7/GG27 Components Vs Inheritance.srt