Hey and welcome back, so for me it's a
new day which is a good thing cos that
last video was really really long so
we're in a good place though, we have
animations working nicely, the next thing
we need to do is get these guys to
actually deal some damage, so by the end of
the video when you click for instance on
this stone here, that this lizard is
chomping on, we want to see a health
component that is decreasing as the
lizard chomps. So just to recap what we're
gonna cover in this video, we're
gonna talk about why a separate health
component make sense, we're going to create and
attached a health dot cs component to all
our attackers and defenders and then test
that it works
do some initial play tuning. This
doesn't include projectors by the way.
So why use a component for health? Well
because basically... we can and we're
practicing components in this section
and because both attackers and defenders
have health that operates in a very similar
way, so we may as well keep our code
in a single place. So what I want you to
do is create a component called health
dot cs, attach that to all attacker and
defender prefabs, give your attackers and
defenders a starting health of your
choice, and then what I want you to do is
to wire up the code into your attacker
dot cs, yes the methods that we recently
wrote, and then make sure that damage is
actually being dealt and the way you'll
be able to tell that is you'll click on the
item like a grave stone or a gnome and
you'll see that its health is going down
over time; so publicly expose the health.
You don't need to worry about the
projectiles hitting the guys yet because...
well the attackers yet because we haven't
yet decided exactly how we're going to
deal with a projectiles yet, that's coming
shortly in terms of their movement.
Alright, so enjoy that challenge as
a bonus get the defender to actually be
destroyed when the health equals 0.
If you're finding that a bit tricky because of
the way this section works don't worry
just leave it out I'll show you how in a minute.
Cool and welcome back so let's get on
with health. So I'm going to create the
script straight in the scripts folder
this time, just to be a rebel; there it is
health and I already gave you the first
line which is public health health
actually I don't know what I wrote on the slide but this
is what you need public float health; and it's just a
float that's going to be available. So let's
start attaching health to our prefabs
not just to any old thing, just do it
straight to the prefabs. We need to be
very careful by the way about what the
state of our prefabs and our instances is,
just before we get into attaching
to the prefabs are you sure that all of
your instances have had all of their
changes applied back so look at a lizard
for example, take a cursory look at the
lizard prefab, does it have an attacker
script a box collider, a lizard script and
a rigid body? No, it doesn't.
So we've been working on the instances
because the animator kind of encourages
us to do that, so this is a good time to
apply your changes from you instances
back to the prefabs. The only problem with the
way I've done that is that they have
then a default transform position but
that's ok, who cares if you drop a lizard
in the scene into the hierarchy and he
then appears over there, that's fine, that's a
reasonable position for him. In some ways it's
preferable to him appearing at the origin. So
again for the fox, take a look at the fox,
he's got lots of stuff on him, take a look at
the fox prefab, got less stuff so let's
apply. Alright so I think we can
confidently just apply our prefabs back
so we've only got one cactus, let's
just look at the defenders, and the
cactus defender versus the cactus
instance here, what's the difference?
Not a lot so I'm just going to apply it
back, the gnome same thing make sure
there's no value that we've left in the
pre-fab that we haven't put in here so
it can be a bit of a hassle sinking these,
the general rule is make the changes to the
pre-fab you can't always do that because
when you're trying to tweak animations
then it wants you to have an instance to
work on two grave stones, so there's a
dangerous thing, maybe they're out of
sync you know they shouldn't be if they're
the same as the pre-fab, but are they the same as
the pre-fab? Because I don't know I'm
going to apply it back and the same with
the star trophy. Alright just check
everything still works
should be fine, so I've just synced my instances
back to my prefab switches, so we know
that our prefabs are up to date with all
the latest value if you started adding
script your prefabs and then then you had
value left over in the instances then it
all becomes a nightmare because you don't
know what's what, so you need to
reconcile that regularly or just operate
directly on your prefabs when you can.
Alright so we can of course add the
script to all of these guys at the same
time, here we go.
Bang, now all defenders have a health
script and they have 0 health, well I'm
gonna give them a hundred health; you can
of course make a different health for each
defender. Let's make a grave stone five times as strong; though it could get boring waiting for the
lizard to chomp his way through it, so
now the fox and the lizard, again you can
just add health and they will start to
get that behavior, presuming that the
script actually does anything. So, that's
the first stage, every single attacker and
defender has a component attached, let's go
back to our challenge slide and see what
we said; so we've done the first two bits, now
we need to get health to actually do
something and wire it into attacker . cs so
let's take a look, what does health do?
Well from attacker dot cs we are going to
call into the health component so we're
gonna need to find the health component
of the object and they we're gonna call
into it here instead of just logging that
we've created damage we're gonna say
something like attacker where've we got it...
current target... if I type straight... dot
get component of type health . now this
is where we gonna make a method inside
our health component to deal damage so
what're we going to do? Current target dot get
component health . deal damage deal
damage sounds fine. Void, deal damage float damage.
OK, a very simple thin method here and we just
say health minus equals damage, that's it.
Well, actually if health minus equal
damage is greater than 0 then we're
going to deal damage. Otherwise what're you
gonna do when we have a partial... when
the amount of damage being dealt is
going to take the guy below zero health?
How do you want to handle this? So you
have a decision, do you want to deal
damage down to zero and then the guy
dies, or do you just let it deal into
the negatives and die? Well I think
that's fine, negative health is the
same as 0 health, so we actually don't
need to worry if our health goes negative.
You just have to decrement the health by
the amount of damage and keep it really
simple, okay? But it's definitely worth
thinking what happens in these edge
cases where we say have 15 health left
and we deal twenty damage. Well, the
consequence is the thing's going to die
anyway so it's just let it die. So that's
pretty much it for the health component,
you may want to give health a default
value that makes sense
at the top here just in case it doesn't
get set in the inspector; but basically
for health that is it - we don't really
need a start and... excuse me, you don't
really need a start and an update and in
future we will deal with the destroying
of the objects, we need to think a little bit about
animation, but first let's think about
attacker dot cs and get that wired up
sensibly, so what needs to change over
at the attacker? Well we've already got the
health here this component health off of
the current target, so we need to ask a
few more questions here really, so I'm
gonna say health health equals current
target dot get component health; so we've
taken the health component off the
current target, well, does it have one and
we have a current target? Well they're both
good questions, so let's deal with the
first one first
does the thing even have a health
component and do we even have a current
target we may not even have a current
target that we are talking to at the
moment; so let's wrap all this in an if current
target, now where's current target set?
Let's just talk about where this is
set, we have current target at the top of
it's a game object,
when does the current target get set? It
gets set down here in attack so there
will only be a current target if the
attacker is in attack mode, okay so there's no
point in trying to pull a health
component off our current target if there
is no current target. So put the line of
code that takes the health component off
the current target in an if statement
and you say if current target, what that
evaluates to is if there is no current
target that is going to return false and
it's not even going to try and take the
health component off in the first place.
So if there's a target take off the health
component, then what are we gonna do with it? Well,
we don't want to even assume that there's
a health component, so let's ask the
question if health, now I won't indent
these if statements more than two levels as
a general suggestion and I won't be
scaring you by doing any more than that
but let's deal with nested IFs here
so this stuff will only happen if
there's a current target, and then the bit we're going
to do next will only happen if there's
health, then we call health which is this
health component . deal damage, it needs to
be public of course, so make your health
deal damage method public, health dot
deal damage, and then how much damage? The
damage amount of damage, you gotta love object
oriented programming, sometimes you to
have t write the same things; ok let's test
what we've got, we should be dealing
damage already, let's take a look, save
all of your scripts and play; take a look for
example in the scene view is one of the
easiest ways of doing this at the stone, the
grave stone, I'm looking at the grave stone body
here if you click so go
up to the main gravestone and look it's
health is decreasing, cool let's take a look
at the garden gnome; again now that the
fox is having a go at him his health is
decreasing and just to prove not everybody's
health is decreasing the cactus
isn't. Now they won't disappear yet, you'll
notice in a moment that the grave stone
will, and the garden gnome will go to
negative health, the gnome's already there,
but we haven't, that's because
we haven't written that bit of code yet.
OK, so let's briefly talk about
destroying the objects, how are we gonna do
the destruction? It's going to happen in
health, health needs to signal the
destruction. The question is what would
happen if we wanted to be able to have
an animation
on the death? So let's do things like
this: if health is less than 0 then that's
obviously the die condition, but what are we
gonna do? Well you would optionally
trigger an animation and then the
animator would go into a die state
that's not how you spell optionally at all is it? Optionally trigger animation; so the animator would go into a die
state, alright but we're not gonna do that
for now because we don't have a sensible
die animation so we are simply going to
die now or destroy object ok and I'm
going to use a destroy object method
separately which seems like a waste of
time but it isn't because of course we
can call this from the animator so
public void destroy object very simple
method is just going to say destroy game
object and what is game object in this
case? The entire... not the health because that
would be destroy this, but destroy
game object is the entire thing that
health is attached to, so if we were to
have a death animation you would trigger
the death animation here and not call
destroy object and then
in the animator you would use an
animator event remember over here we would
use one of these little guys it's an animator
event, to then call back into the health
component and call destroy object; let me
just show you what I mean, let's imagine the
grave stone is gonna get destroyed and
that this is it's death animation, you
would come in here and you would find
that because it's attached directly to
the gravestone you can say destroy
object and you do that at the end of the
animation so that leaves the door open
for you to put death animations in if you
want to, which is great so now let's just
check that they actually do disappear
when their health runs out, let's take a
look. Ok, what's happening is that they're
destroying it absolutely immediately so
why are they being destroyed immediately?
Let's just check a couple of things, check
your animator, make sure that your
animator where I just fiddled around
with one of those things, I think I
fiddled with a gravestone, make sure that
you don't have any little events in here
that are calling destroy object, you see
that? Gravestone has a default destroy
object I put that in by mistake - it
proves it would work
but of course it doesn't have the
desired effect; so in fact that was all that
was wrong so the fox goes over, the lizard
attacks, take a look at the gravestone
inspect the grave stone, it's going to take a
while let's just bump it's health down to
thirty; if it's gonna let me, if the inspector will let
me, it has gone, they're not resuming their
walk yet, that's fine, we don't expect
them to resume their walking yet because
that is a different objective. So how do
we resume walking when the GameObject
standing in front of this lizard has been
destroyed?
Not entirely simple because it does not
send an on trigger exit message or
anything like that, it just disappears
from the scene.
Well one relatively simple way of doing
this is in the attacker script you could
just ask the question every frame is there
a target, and if there isn't you set the
animator state to is attacking is false.
So I want you to do that, I want you to
get access to the animator here in
attacker and then write a line in
update that says if there's no current
target then set the is attacking state
to false in the animator. Go ahead and do
that now.
Awesome so if we're going to do that
it's a standard private animator
animator find it on the start which we
don't have so let's create ourselves a start
method, you should get used to creating start
methods again if you need them now;
animator equals GameObject, sorry it just
equals get component because it's on
the same object, it's just one of the
components of this object, get component
animator; remember it's a method so it needs the
squiggly brackets, so here we're simply
saying if there is no current target
then what do we do? Well it's just animator . set
bool, now you've got to spell it right, is attacking, and then
to false. Now just make sure it is
attacking back over in unity, find
yourself an attacker like a lizard and
then do we have an "is attacking" bool, yes
we do that's good; you may as well while
you're here check the fox has the same
named parameter, we've got to keep those synched up.
OK, let's try that and we should be there so in comes
the lizard starts attacking the
gravestone which grave stone is it?
It's the second one down, got lots of
health so it's a lot of waiting so let's
just set the health to 50, 35, 30... here
we go, it's a waiting game now the fox is
also chewing on the gnome, so the gnome
should disappear and the fox
re-starts walking, perfect, because that
update has said I don't have a current
target I'm off, and exactly the same
with the lizard. So, congratulations, we now
have destruction working and walking
resuming; now that cactus is going to get
it. See you soon.