Welcome back. so it's about time we
sorted out these defender animations.
right now they're cycling through
animation states with no regard for what
else is going on around them.
also the projectile animations are a
mess. so we are now equipped to get this
completely sorted. So in this video we
are going to do the following: Number 1.
I'm gonna show you three different approaches to
projectile animation. we're going to
separate the defenders from their
projectile prefabs. animate projectiles
using both script and the animator and
that doesn't conflict with my previous
rule cos we're gonna move the transform - the
center of gravity - with the script and we're
gonna move the rotation with the animator.
and then we're going to fix up the defender
animation states. So firstly imagine that you're
gonna wanna do boomerangs; we're actually
not gonna bother doing boomerangs. but
imagine you wanted to go on an extend the
game and have this courgette fly out to
the far end lane and then come back again.
Well. how could you do that in a 2D
game like this or like a tower defense
game based on grids? Well three
fundamental ways that I can think of
Number one you could have a different
animation state for each start column. so
imagine it's a parabolic flight or an out
and return flight you could just have a
different animation state for every start
column. that would be ok for a limited
number of columns and permutations;
you could. number two create
stroke modify the animation from scripts
and kind of play with the animator from
script modifying parameters - you could do
that. quite difficult then to understand
how it's going to behave at runtime. so
it's not my favorite solution but it
could be useful when you have something
complex going on with the animation that
you then just want to change a small
parameter of from the script so it's an
opportunity for you.
Or number three you do all the
translation from the script and that's
actually how we're going to do our
translation of our projectiles. is with
number three.
Alright. so how are we... how are we going to achieve
all this? Well first let's get the prefabs
separated. right now we have defender
prefabs that have
projectiles attached to them and then in
the animator we are disabling those prefabs
We're disabling the axe on the idle state for
example. it's a great opportunity. yet you
sometimes want to do that thing but we
really want to treat the
projectiles as completely separate game
objects. once they're spawned they want to
fly on their own. if the defender dies
they need to continue on with their
little lives; they want to have their own
animators because they're going to do
different things so we want to
completely change this connection so
what I'm gonna do quite quickly is now
go through my gnome and my cactus. I'm
going to remove these from the idle
states I'm going to remove the curves that
talk about disabling their projectiles.
I'm going to stop trying to change the
courgette's position. I'm also gonna do
exactly the same on the gnome. I'm gonna say
let's not bother making his axe
inactive and also let's. in his attacking
state. not bother trying to animate the
axe; alright so that's stage one. freeing
these guys from the tyranny of connected
projectiles; so now I'm gonna move the
projectiles into their own prefabs. gonna
make a separate folder called
projectiles - you can child is under the
defenders folder if you want but I don't
want three level of folders. that scares
me; so I'm just gonna now create myself an empty
GameObject at the top level called
projectiles and later our script will expect
this to be there; because it's just a
holding object I'm going to reset it's
transform. its position has no
meaning so put it at the origin. Great. so
now it's a relatively simple job to take
the courgette and to prefab it into
the projectile folder and to take
the axe and prefab that into
the projectiles folder like so. now we
can actually remove the courgette and
the axe from the gnome and the cactus
respectively and update the prefabs.
quite importantly. so the end result of
this is that you no longer have axes or courgettes
in your scene at all. although we will
put them back in for testing in a little bit
and that if you look at your prefabs for
your defenders your cactus only has a
body sprite and your gnome only has a body
sprite; that's great. So we're on the way. Now
let's pop a couple of projectiles
into the scene after having reset their
transforms - we don't want prefabbed
projectiles to have any offset in their
transforms - I'm gonna drop both an axe and
a courgette into the scene. they
arrive down the bottom here. let's put
them somewhere random just to
reiterate the idea that they're not
actually being fired by these guys at
the moment. they're just independent
projectiles hanging around in the scene;
there they are. now let's play the same
trick with these projectiles as we did
with the gnomes. and that is to create
separate sub-objects. child objects. that
hold their bodies or their sprites and the
reason for that is we can then rotate
the body in the animator without
rotating the entire transform and that's
going to be important because when you
try and translate and rotate at the same
time if you do that on the same object
it's just going to go round in circles.
cause if you tell it to go right and then
go forward and go right and go forward.
that's going round in a circle
basically. so you'll see how that comes
true when we animate this thing. let's just
follow the same pattern as we did before
let's have separate sub-objects for the
bodies for the sprites. It's a bit weird to call it the
body of a projectile. use a different
word if you like. I'm just trying to be
consistent here. So I'm just gonna rip
off my sprite renderers here.
copy and then remove the component and
then stick it on the sub-objects. there it is for that
one and then same on the courgette and we're well on the way; so copy and remove the courgette component.
OK. fantastic so now these projectiles are set
up very much into the same pattern as
the defenders and the attackers. they're all
following the same pattern now. much
easier to get our head around. We couldn't
have got to this point of course until
we had ratified how we're going to use
attackers and defenders. Ratified. what
the hell does that mean? Brice pointed
out yesterday that it's just one of those
words. right? Anyway. I kinda know what it means. the dictionary kinda knows what it
means. and it makes you sound
really clever when you say it.
So there they are. two projectiles sitting in
the scene. of course for them to move
they need to have a script on them. so
let's do that. Let's call it projectile. and
there's a script sitting on the courgette. let's
add it to the axe as well. make sure you add
it to the top level. not to the actual
sprites; in this case I've added
it accidentally to the sprite. so the
courgette and the axe want a projectile
script at their top level and it's a
good time now to update the pre-fab so
the courgette and the axe. so there
they sit with their sprites in a
separate object and both have got a projectile
script. Cool so pop the projectile
script away and let's make it work. So in
this video we're only gonna make the
projectiles move we're not going to
worry about them dealing damage yet
we're going to do that in a separate
video; so all we need to do with
projectiles right now is make them move.
How do you make them move?
We're not going to add physics to them.
not in this game we're going to avoid physics
altogether in this game - it's not
necessary. even though the projectiles
will need. and we may as well do it now
they will need rigid bodies. because they
need to have rigid bodies on them in order
for them to be kinematic rigid body
trigger colliders. which is the type of
collider they were using. They do need to
have rigid bodies on them for that
purpose. and this is just to do with the way
that unity processes collisions. we're
going to click to say they're kinematic
right. so both the courgette and the
axe - all of your project - will have
kinematic 2D rigid bodies on them. only
because of what that does to the
collider. in fact I'm going to move the component
up next to the collider. so kind of
remind me that the only reason I put that on
there is to make the colliders on these
guys work properly; right so we have
these these box colliders sitting on
there. now you may want to check the
extents of your box colliders. lets worry about
the box colliders when we worry about
impacts and collisions OK? For now they're
absolutely fine; so the question becomes
how do you move these things through
space when you're not using physics well
you gonna write your own first tiny bit
of a physics engine. it couldn't be
simpler.
This is basically Newton's first law.
things carry on
unless there's a reason not to. i.e. an un-balanced external force. So how do we do it? What do we need
access to? Yada yada... well. you're going to need a speed right? So public float speed; It's going to be one of
their properties another property they're gonna
have later is damage. why not put it in
straight away cool so when looking at a
projectile now you will see that day
projectile script asks for speed. let's
give one of them a speed of 1. and let's
give the other a speed of say... I don't know. two just
for fun and let's give them both some damage when
while we're here. 10 and... I don't know an axe has gotta do loads more damage hasn't it? 25; this is going to be
about play tuning later. Update my prefabs
and back to the script. Now. how do we
make this move frame-by-frame? Well. if it
was a physics-based game we'd be using
something called fixed update but we're
not. this is purely visual game so we're
just going to make the calculations for
the position based on the frame. the
actual visual frame. so it goes in update
that's the first hint for you and this
is how we're gonna do it. relatively simple.
Transform dot translate and then Vector3
dot right. we can just get off the
shelf as a right hand vector. times the
speed times... guess what... time . yeah I
heard you singing it time dot Delta time.
So that's all we do every frame. we move
it by its current speed and its speed is
continuous. so let's try it
click play and watch the two projectiles -
hey there they go. one's going faster than
the other.
Perfect. that's great news now if you're
interested in building your own physics
engine from scratch and understanding it
better. then click on my little face in Udemy.
scroll down to my courses and you'll
see game physics - extend unity 3d engine
Unity 3d's physics engine. here it is
at game physics. so Udemy.com/gamephysics.
check out that course. people are loving
it and I will take you through in detail
how to make your own physics engine but
for now that is a very very simple first step.
OK. so there they go. the projectiles go
flying off to the right. now we need to
make them spin. so how do we make them spin?
Well. they're gonna need their own
animators. the projectiles OK? So
previously we were conservative with our
animators because we said we only need
one animator at the top level component
i.e. on the cactus or the gnome. but
now that projectiles have their own life
then we're going to give them their
own animators; fantastic do they need
different animations? I think it makes
sense for them to have different
animations. so I think I'll create a
folder called projectiles and then
inside the projectiles folder let's
create a couple of different animations.
One is going to be called axe flight
and let's make the other one called
courgette flight
I'll just fix courgette over here so I've
given you a hint on the naming of the
clips I want you to finish this off now
I want you to create the animation
controllers that you need. we've just
created clips for the axe and the courgette.
I also want you to go into the
animation controllers for all of the
other defenders and sort them out in
terms of their triggers and everything
else so our gnome. his state machine wants
to look sensible. he wants to be idle
unless is attacking. we haven't got an is
attacking etcetera. the same way as we
did for the attackers alright? So the end
result of this is going to be that in
your scene you have two projectiles
flying to the right as they are but
rotating using the animator rotating the
sprite - put the animator at the top level
but rotate the subcomponent. the sprite. you've done that before and the other
thing that I want to happen is I want
all of these guys here on the left. the
defenders to sit in their idle state
unless you come into the animator here
and in the parameter in the bool
parameter is attacking - unless you tick it on;
So there's is attacking. when you tick that on for
any of the particular selected defenders
I wanted them to go into an attacking state.
don't worry about them spawning any
projectiles for the moment. don't worry
about multiple projectiles. we're just
gonna have those single two projectiles
going off to the right and spinning.
that's that bit done. the other bit is
the defenders they want to stay idle
unless you click their is attacking
parameter on and then they will start
showing their attacking or agitated
animation; so the slide for the challenge
is here. sort out your defender animations.
OK. welcome back so let's get that working
let's start by just having the animation
working for these projectiles so what
are we missing on here?
Well. I'm gonna need a animation
controller for the projectile. so lots
of ways of doing that. I can click on the
on their axe and i can say well I need
an animation controller so I will make one -
create animation controller. there we go
Going to call it underscore axe. then I'm going
to create a new animation controller... you
could potentially have one animation
controller and share it. but I'm gonna have
a separate animation controller for the
axe and for the courgette; so they
now have their own animation controllers.
now it's the standard stuff. I'm just gonna
whip through it quickly. so the animation
controller gets attached to the axe.
the animation controller gets attached to the courgette.
we go into the axe's animation controller.
it has a state. I already made a clip so
I'm gonna make a new empty state called
flight which makes sense. it's in flight.
in fact it's its only state in this particular
instance. now what's the curve? What's the
motion rather for this thing? Well. we
already have it right. it's courgette. it's courgette
flighr. Alright. so that's that one done. let's go
to the axe...
I'm mixing myself up. it's not the courgette
flight. it's the axe flight; this is why. by the
way. we prefix all the motions with the
name of the object otherwise you just
have flight flight flight. idle idle idle as
you saw before; alright so there he is with
his clip now. axe flight. what is it
about the axe flight that we want to modify?
Well. 30 frames a second
sounds good to me. and then we want it
to spin about every second. so we're going to add a
curve. not working on the main object but
working on the transform of
the body. it's the body that has the sprite
attached to it. we're going to rotate
the transform of the body. that's
important now I have it on my screen right
now; okay and then you can actually get
it to interpolate between these points
automatically so it's by default put a
key frame at one second. perhaps the
rotation is minus three hundred and
fifty nine degrees after one second... like that
OK. now let's just try it. there it goes. see the axe spinning forward and then it stops?
Why does it stop? Well. if you go to the
axe flight motion it's not looping so we'll
set it looping for the both of them and
let's go to the courgette and get that
sorted as well. so again the courgette
state machine does not have a state right
now; create an empty state. I'm doing these all manually
just now to really rub it home how
this works. how they all sit and
interoperate. What is the motion for that?
Well. it's courgette flight. right? So courgette has courgette flight. an axe has an axe flight. fantastic so the
courgette flight. how's that going to look? Well let's
make it similar but not precisely the
same. again animating the transform of
the body. its rotation. let's make the
courgette go round faster. so in less than a
second it's gonna do minus 359 degrees.
why minus? Well. it just makes it spins
the right way if there's such a thing as the
right way. there's kind of a right way for the
axe for doing the maximal damage. but I
think the handles going to hit you before the blade
but anyway. let's not think about axes hitting
you; so that's working. that's that bit done.
so let's move on to the next bit. the
next and final bit here is getting the
animation states for all the defenders. firstly  before I
leave them let's re-apply the changes to
our prefabs and now let's take a look at
the cactus animation so what's the deal
with his state machine? He needs an is
attacking bool. right? Why a bool. because
it's a continuous thing not a one-off.
we use triggers for one-offs. how do we go
from - in fact I said let's delete any
transitions and start afresh because then
the animations are neat; so there is a new
transition but it's based on is attacking
being true. this is very rote. I'm afraid.
OK so that's when it goes from
attacking to idle based on that. and the
attack and Idle don't have anything
superfluous in them. later on we'll be
adding events into the attack so that
they actually spawn weapons. but that's
on its way let's just check this guy's
working properly without maximize on
play. so I'm going to click into the game
now come on.
maximize play is sticking on. OK there we
go. That's better. now if I click is
attacking on what happens? If you watch
the cactus which is the thing that
we're dealing with right now his is
attacking state is fine and then he
stops attacking. so that's his state
management done I'm now very quickly
gonna go through the other guys and do
the same thing.
Alright so I'm gonna apply my prefab for
the cactus. move down to the next
thing on the list which is the gnome. look at his state.
I don't trust the current transition
so I'm going to remove them. check that I've got an is
attacking parameter which I do. make the
transition to attack make the transition
back set up the transitions so we go
back when is attacking is false and
forward when is attacking is true. oh man if
you had a pound every time you did this or
a dollar or whatever your currency is you'd be
very rich because it can get a little
bit tedious doing these things; alright
so let's just check that. the next attacker
there he goes. agitated gnome attacking gnome
and not attacking gnome. fine so how about the
star trophy is the final one; I'm gonna
just apply the gnome by the way back to
the pre-fab. check they all work OK. yep
these are working; so how about his star
trophy what's the deal with the star
trophy and the gravestone? well the star
trophy has an idle animation and a
growing animation so I'm just gonna say
I'm gonna use a trigger for growing the star
because it grows a star as a kind
of one off when the script's ready. so grow
trigger for now. this is all kind of
extra optional stuff. I'm actually gonna
leave the state transitions out for now
and just leave it idle and then what
else do we need? We have a gravestone. so
apply my start trophy back. go to the top
gravestone and say to myself well what's
my under attack and idle animation same
deal exactly the same stuff I'm afraid
so is attacking bool in this case
because its continuous state. not just a
single cycle. and you make your transitions
Alright. we get the idea let's test it
and let's also make sure that our
prefabs have all been saved properly; so
is attacking true. is attacking false
that's all finished off. now
prefab your gravestone. and the way to
test that these prefabs have been
saved properly. there's lots of ways of
doing it but the simplest is just to drag
the prefabs into the scene and make sure
that the pre-fab themselves
operate properly. So let's put a few
defenders. one of each type of defender
onto the scene - you have to be scene view not
game view. it won't work - so you go into
scene view. drop a cactus. a gnome.
a gravestone and a star trophy and let's just
check that they all behave properly. So we
can now go through those things which
are messily sitting at the top of the
hierarchy and we can just click is
attacking and make sure that the gnome
works. the grave stone works apart from the
grave stone is defaulting to the wrong thing. so
we fix that by right clicking on it and
saying set as default on idle. and then
applying his prefab back... cactus... this cactus
instance is behaving itself and then the
star trophy. so it should be in idle by default and
we're not putting the transitions in yet.
great so they all are working fine. They're
the sort of things you may have to do
and we are good to go
we have completed the challenge for this
lesson. I guess the only thing to say is
why is my cactus starting in an
attack state? It's not because the
default state is idle in orange here
when you right-click. but because the
is attacking parameter by default has
been set to yes; hopefully that makes sense. so
there's two ways you can end up starting
in the wrong state; one is your default
state and others you may have a
parameter default.
Anyway congratulations.  huge progress on this video and I'll see you soon.
=======
Kind: captions
Language: en
Welcome back, so it's about time we
sorted out these defender animations,
right now they're cycling through
animation states with no regard for what
else is going on around them,
also the projectile animations are a
mess, so we are now equipped to get this
completely sorted. So in this video we
are going to do the following: Number 1,
I'm gonna show you three different approaches to
projectile animation, we're going to
separate the defenders from their
projectile prefabs, animate projectiles
using both script and the animator and
that doesn't conflict with my previous
rule cos we're gonna move the transform - the
center of gravity - with the script and we're
gonna move the rotation with the animator,
and then we're going to fix up the defender
animation states. So firstly imagine that you're
gonna wanna do boomerangs; we're actually
not gonna bother doing boomerangs, but
imagine you wanted to go on an extend the
game and have this courgette fly out to
the far end lane and then come back again.
Well, how could you do that in a 2D
game like this or like a tower defense
game based on grids? Well three
fundamental ways that I can think of
Number one you could have a different
animation state for each start column, so
imagine it's a parabolic flight or an out
and return flight you could just have a
different animation state for every start
column, that would be ok for a limited
number of columns and permutations;
you could, number two create
stroke modify the animation from scripts
and kind of play with the animator from
script modifying parameters - you could do
that, quite difficult then to understand
how it's going to behave at runtime, so
it's not my favorite solution but it
could be useful when you have something
complex going on with the animation that
you then just want to change a small
parameter of from the script so it's an
opportunity for you.
Or number three you do all the
translation from the script and that's
actually how we're going to do our
translation of our projectiles, is with
number three.
Alright, so how are we... how are we going to achieve
all this? Well first let's get the prefabs
separated, right now we have defender
prefabs that have
projectiles attached to them and then in
the animator we are disabling those prefabs
We're disabling the axe on the idle state for
example, it's a great opportunity, yet you
sometimes want to do that thing but we
really want to treat the
projectiles as completely separate game
objects, once they're spawned they want to
fly on their own, if the defender dies
they need to continue on with their
little lives; they want to have their own
animators because they're going to do
different things so we want to
completely change this connection so
what I'm gonna do quite quickly is now
go through my gnome and my cactus, I'm
going to remove these from the idle
states I'm going to remove the curves that
talk about disabling their projectiles,
I'm going to stop trying to change the
courgette's position, I'm also gonna do
exactly the same on the gnome, I'm gonna say
let's not bother making his axe
inactive and also let's, in his attacking
state, not bother trying to animate the
axe; alright so that's stage one, freeing
these guys from the tyranny of connected
projectiles; so now I'm gonna move the
projectiles into their own prefabs, gonna
make a separate folder called
projectiles - you can child is under the
defenders folder if you want but I don't
want three level of folders, that scares
me; so I'm just gonna now create myself an empty
GameObject at the top level called
projectiles and later our script will expect
this to be there; because it's just a
holding object I'm going to reset it's
transform, its position has no
meaning so put it at the origin. Great, so
now it's a relatively simple job to take
the courgette and to prefab it into
the projectile folder and to take
the axe and prefab that into
the projectiles folder like so, now we
can actually remove the courgette and
the axe from the gnome and the cactus
respectively and update the prefabs,
quite importantly, so the end result of
this is that you no longer have axes or courgettes
in your scene at all, although we will
put them back in for testing in a little bit
and that if you look at your prefabs for
your defenders your cactus only has a
body sprite and your gnome only has a body
sprite; that's great. So we're on the way. Now
let's pop a couple of projectiles
into the scene after having reset their
transforms - we don't want prefabbed
projectiles to have any offset in their
transforms - I'm gonna drop both an axe and
a courgette into the scene, they
arrive down the bottom here, let's put
them somewhere random just to
reiterate the idea that they're not
actually being fired by these guys at
the moment, they're just independent
projectiles hanging around in the scene;
there they are, now let's play the same
trick with these projectiles as we did
with the gnomes, and that is to create
separate sub-objects, child objects, that
hold their bodies or their sprites and the
reason for that is we can then rotate
the body in the animator without
rotating the entire transform and that's
going to be important because when you
try and translate and rotate at the same
time if you do that on the same object
it's just going to go round in circles,
cause if you tell it to go right and then
go forward and go right and go forward,
that's going round in a circle
basically, so you'll see how that comes
true when we animate this thing, let's just
follow the same pattern as we did before
let's have separate sub-objects for the
bodies for the sprites. It's a bit weird to call it the
body of a projectile, use a different
word if you like, I'm just trying to be
consistent here. So I'm just gonna rip
off my sprite renderers here,
copy and then remove the component and
then stick it on the sub-objects, there it is for that
one and then same on the courgette and we're well on the way; so copy and remove the courgette component.
OK, fantastic so now these projectiles are set
up very much into the same pattern as
the defenders and the attackers, they're all
following the same pattern now, much
easier to get our head around. We couldn't
have got to this point of course until
we had ratified how we're going to use
attackers and defenders. Ratified, what
the hell does that mean? Brice pointed
out yesterday that it's just one of those
words, right? Anyway, I kinda know what it means, the dictionary kinda knows what it
means, and it makes you sound
really clever when you say it.
So there they are, two projectiles sitting in
the scene, of course for them to move
they need to have a script on them, so
let's do that. Let's call it projectile, and
there's a script sitting on the courgette, let's
add it to the axe as well, make sure you add
it to the top level, not to the actual
sprites; in this case I've added
it accidentally to the sprite, so the
courgette and the axe want a projectile
script at their top level and it's a
good time now to update the pre-fab so
the courgette and the axe, so there
they sit with their sprites in a
separate object and both have got a projectile
script. Cool so pop the projectile
script away and let's make it work. So in
this video we're only gonna make the
projectiles move we're not going to
worry about them dealing damage yet
we're going to do that in a separate
video; so all we need to do with
projectiles right now is make them move.
How do you make them move?
We're not going to add physics to them,
not in this game we're going to avoid physics
altogether in this game - it's not
necessary, even though the projectiles
will need, and we may as well do it now
they will need rigid bodies, because they
need to have rigid bodies on them in order
for them to be kinematic rigid body
trigger colliders, which is the type of
collider they were using. They do need to
have rigid bodies on them for that
purpose, and this is just to do with the way
that unity processes collisions, we're
going to click to say they're kinematic
right, so both the courgette and the
axe - all of your project - will have
kinematic 2D rigid bodies on them, only
because of what that does to the
collider, in fact I'm going to move the component
up next to the collider, so kind of
remind me that the only reason I put that on
there is to make the colliders on these
guys work properly; right so we have
these these box colliders sitting on
there, now you may want to check the
extents of your box colliders, lets worry about
the box colliders when we worry about
impacts and collisions OK? For now they're
absolutely fine; so the question becomes
how do you move these things through
space when you're not using physics well
you gonna write your own first tiny bit
of a physics engine, it couldn't be
simpler.
This is basically Newton's first law,
things carry on
unless there's a reason not to, i.e. an un-balanced external force. So how do we do it? What do we need
access to? Yada yada... well, you're going to need a speed right? So public float speed; It's going to be one of
their properties another property they're gonna
have later is damage, why not put it in
straight away cool so when looking at a
projectile now you will see that day
projectile script asks for speed, let's
give one of them a speed of 1, and let's
give the other a speed of say... I don't know, two just
for fun and let's give them both some damage when
while we're here, 10 and... I don't know an axe has gotta do loads more damage hasn't it? 25; this is going to be
about play tuning later. Update my prefabs
and back to the script. Now, how do we
make this move frame-by-frame? Well, if it
was a physics-based game we'd be using
something called fixed update but we're
not, this is purely visual game so we're
just going to make the calculations for
the position based on the frame, the
actual visual frame, so it goes in update
that's the first hint for you and this
is how we're gonna do it, relatively simple.
Transform dot translate and then Vector3
dot right, we can just get off the
shelf as a right hand vector, times the
speed times... guess what... time . yeah I
heard you singing it time dot Delta time.
So that's all we do every frame, we move
it by its current speed and its speed is
continuous, so let's try it
click play and watch the two projectiles -
hey there they go, one's going faster than
the other.
Perfect, that's great news now if you're
interested in building your own physics
engine from scratch and understanding it
better, then click on my little face in Udemy,
scroll down to my courses and you'll
see game physics - extend unity 3d engine
Unity 3d's physics engine, here it is
at game physics, so Udemy.com/gamephysics,
check out that course, people are loving
it and I will take you through in detail
how to make your own physics engine but
for now that is a very very simple first step.
OK, so there they go, the projectiles go
flying off to the right, now we need to
make them spin, so how do we make them spin?
Well, they're gonna need their own
animators, the projectiles OK? So
previously we were conservative with our
animators because we said we only need
one animator at the top level component
i.e. on the cactus or the gnome, but
now that projectiles have their own life
then we're going to give them their
own animators; fantastic do they need
different animations? I think it makes
sense for them to have different
animations, so I think I'll create a
folder called projectiles and then
inside the projectiles folder let's
create a couple of different animations.
One is going to be called axe flight
and let's make the other one called
courgette flight
I'll just fix courgette over here so I've
given you a hint on the naming of the
clips I want you to finish this off now
I want you to create the animation
controllers that you need, we've just
created clips for the axe and the courgette,
I also want you to go into the
animation controllers for all of the
other defenders and sort them out in
terms of their triggers and everything
else so our gnome, his state machine wants
to look sensible, he wants to be idle
unless is attacking, we haven't got an is
attacking etcetera, the same way as we
did for the attackers alright? So the end
result of this is going to be that in
your scene you have two projectiles
flying to the right as they are but
rotating using the animator rotating the
sprite - put the animator at the top level
but rotate the subcomponent, the sprite, you've done that before and the other
thing that I want to happen is I want
all of these guys here on the left, the
defenders to sit in their idle state
unless you come into the animator here
and in the parameter in the bool
parameter is attacking - unless you tick it on;
So there's is attacking, when you tick that on for
any of the particular selected defenders
I wanted them to go into an attacking state,
don't worry about them spawning any
projectiles for the moment, don't worry
about multiple projectiles, we're just
gonna have those single two projectiles
going off to the right and spinning,
that's that bit done, the other bit is
the defenders they want to stay idle
unless you click their is attacking
parameter on and then they will start
showing their attacking or agitated
animation; so the slide for the challenge
is here, sort out your defender animations.
OK, welcome back so let's get that working
let's start by just having the animation
working for these projectiles so what
are we missing on here?
Well, I'm gonna need a animation
controller for the projectile, so lots
of ways of doing that, I can click on the
on their axe and i can say well I need
an animation controller so I will make one -
create animation controller, there we go
Going to call it underscore axe, then I'm going
to create a new animation controller... you
could potentially have one animation
controller and share it, but I'm gonna have
a separate animation controller for the
axe and for the courgette; so they
now have their own animation controllers,
now it's the standard stuff, I'm just gonna
whip through it quickly, so the animation
controller gets attached to the axe,
the animation controller gets attached to the courgette,
we go into the axe's animation controller,
it has a state, I already made a clip so
I'm gonna make a new empty state called
flight which makes sense, it's in flight,
in fact it's its only state in this particular
instance, now what's the curve? What's the
motion rather for this thing? Well, we
already have it right, it's courgette, it's courgette
flighr. Alright, so that's that one done, let's go
to the axe...
I'm mixing myself up, it's not the courgette
flight, it's the axe flight; this is why, by the
way, we prefix all the motions with the
name of the object otherwise you just
have flight flight flight, idle idle idle as
you saw before; alright so there he is with
his clip now, axe flight, what is it
about the axe flight that we want to modify?
Well, 30 frames a second
sounds good to me, and then we want it
to spin about every second, so we're going to add a
curve, not working on the main object but
working on the transform of
the body, it's the body that has the sprite
attached to it, we're going to rotate
the transform of the body, that's
important now I have it on my screen right
now; okay and then you can actually get
it to interpolate between these points
automatically so it's by default put a
key frame at one second, perhaps the
rotation is minus three hundred and
fifty nine degrees after one second... like that
OK, now let's just try it, there it goes, see the axe spinning forward and then it stops?
Why does it stop? Well, if you go to the
axe flight motion it's not looping so we'll
set it looping for the both of them and
let's go to the courgette and get that
sorted as well, so again the courgette
state machine does not have a state right
now; create an empty state. I'm doing these all manually
just now to really rub it home how
this works, how they all sit and
interoperate. What is the motion for that?
Well, it's courgette flight, right? So courgette has courgette flight, an axe has an axe flight, fantastic so the
courgette flight, how's that going to look? Well let's
make it similar but not precisely the
same, again animating the transform of
the body, its rotation, let's make the
courgette go round faster, so in less than a
second it's gonna do minus 359 degrees.
why minus? Well, it just makes it spins
the right way if there's such a thing as the
right way, there's kind of a right way for the
axe for doing the maximal damage, but I
think the handles going to hit you before the blade
but anyway, let's not think about axes hitting
you; so that's working, that's that bit done,
so let's move on to the next bit, the
next and final bit here is getting the
animation states for all the defenders, firstly  before I
leave them let's re-apply the changes to
our prefabs and now let's take a look at
the cactus animation so what's the deal
with his state machine? He needs an is
attacking bool, right? Why a bool, because
it's a continuous thing not a one-off,
we use triggers for one-offs, how do we go
from - in fact I said let's delete any
transitions and start afresh because then
the animations are neat; so there is a new
transition but it's based on is attacking
being true, this is very rote, I'm afraid,
OK so that's when it goes from
attacking to idle based on that, and the
attack and Idle don't have anything
superfluous in them, later on we'll be
adding events into the attack so that
they actually spawn weapons, but that's
on its way let's just check this guy's
working properly without maximize on
play, so I'm going to click into the game
now come on,
maximize play is sticking on, OK there we
go. That's better, now if I click is
attacking on what happens? If you watch
the cactus which is the thing that
we're dealing with right now his is
attacking state is fine and then he
stops attacking, so that's his state
management done I'm now very quickly
gonna go through the other guys and do
the same thing.
Alright so I'm gonna apply my prefab for
the cactus, move down to the next
thing on the list which is the gnome, look at his state,
I don't trust the current transition
so I'm going to remove them, check that I've got an is
attacking parameter which I do, make the
transition to attack make the transition
back set up the transitions so we go
back when is attacking is false and
forward when is attacking is true, oh man if
you had a pound every time you did this or
a dollar or whatever your currency is you'd be
very rich because it can get a little
bit tedious doing these things; alright
so let's just check that, the next attacker
there he goes, agitated gnome attacking gnome
and not attacking gnome, fine so how about the
star trophy is the final one; I'm gonna
just apply the gnome by the way back to
the pre-fab, check they all work OK, yep
these are working; so how about his star
trophy what's the deal with the star
trophy and the gravestone? well the star
trophy has an idle animation and a
growing animation so I'm just gonna say
I'm gonna use a trigger for growing the star
because it grows a star as a kind
of one off when the script's ready, so grow
trigger for now, this is all kind of
extra optional stuff. I'm actually gonna
leave the state transitions out for now
and just leave it idle and then what
else do we need? We have a gravestone, so
apply my start trophy back, go to the top
gravestone and say to myself well what's
my under attack and idle animation same
deal exactly the same stuff I'm afraid
so is attacking bool in this case
because its continuous state, not just a
single cycle, and you make your transitions
Alright, we get the idea let's test it
and let's also make sure that our
prefabs have all been saved properly; so
is attacking true, is attacking false
that's all finished off, now
prefab your gravestone, and the way to
test that these prefabs have been
saved properly, there's lots of ways of
doing it but the simplest is just to drag
the prefabs into the scene and make sure
that the pre-fab themselves
operate properly. So let's put a few
defenders, one of each type of defender
onto the scene - you have to be scene view not
game view, it won't work - so you go into
scene view, drop a cactus, a gnome,
a gravestone and a star trophy and let's just
check that they all behave properly. So we
can now go through those things which
are messily sitting at the top of the
hierarchy and we can just click is
attacking and make sure that the gnome
works, the grave stone works apart from the
grave stone is defaulting to the wrong thing, so
we fix that by right clicking on it and
saying set as default on idle, and then
applying his prefab back... cactus... this cactus
instance is behaving itself and then the
star trophy, so it should be in idle by default and
we're not putting the transitions in yet,
great so they all are working fine. They're
the sort of things you may have to do
and we are good to go
we have completed the challenge for this
lesson. I guess the only thing to say is
why is my cactus starting in an
attack state? It's not because the
default state is idle in orange here
when you right-click, but because the
is attacking parameter by default has
been set to yes; hopefully that makes sense, so
there's two ways you can end up starting
in the wrong state; one is your default
state and others you may have a
parameter default.
Anyway congratulations,  huge progress on this video and I'll see you soon.
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1:Unity/Section7/GG29 Animating Defenders' Projectiles.srt