So the purpose of this video is going to
be getting our projectiles firing and
spawning properly. Before we do, let's
just have a quick recap about this
component architecture, so if we look at
our attackers and then flip between them,
looking over in the inspector; I've
changed around the order of the
components by the way, by moving up and
moving down, just to make it look clear
and I'd maybe collapse down the rigid body and
the box colliders, so it may look very
slightly different to yours; but the
question is what's the general structure
here? So start with attackers: all attackers
have an attacker script, that's fair
enough, and what does the attacker script
do? Quite a lot of general attack
behavior, so that makes sense. Then, again
looking at the attackers, they have
specialist behaviour for the fox and the
lizard, well is that worth it? Is it worth
a whole component? Well the lizard
certainly is, and looks like the fox is as well
OK, so they look absolutely fine in terms
of structure, and they both have health;
is health worth it? Just, very small but
it saves us repeating the code in lots of
different places - bear in mind that that
health object is used across all of
our attackers and defenders. OK, so also
the thing to note here is that both the
fox and the lizard have box colliders which
are set as triggers and they have rigid
body 2Ds which are set as kinematic
so they are kinematic rigid body trigger
colliders. OK, that's all consistent and
fine, now the defenders. All defenders have
a defender script, so let's look at the
defender script briefly. Very thin in
fact I'm gonna get rid of this log
entry in here, in fact I don't have anything
in the defender script once I get rid
of the log entry, so why the hell are we
keeping a defender class? Well, good
question. We're keeping it because
something uses it as a tag, remember? If
you go search, find in files in Mono,
and then you search the whole solution
for the word defender you'll remember
that several things try getting
component defender like the fox and the
lizard, the specialisations do that.
So at the moment this is only being used
as a tag for now. OK now that is pretty -
you know, it's a pretty heavy weight
solution using a entire component - an entire
class just to say that I am a defender.
You could tag all these guys using the
tag system up here in the inspector but
we're keeping it this way for now, I'm gonna
start worrying about excess components if
we get to more than three components
on a given object, but the other thing to
notice about the defenders is they all
have box colliders but they don't have
any rigid body on them because they're
static colliders, they're not moving and
the other thing to notice is that stone
again has a script that does absolutely
nothing and it's just used as a tag for now.
So when you realize that it may be a good
idea to combine your code immediately.
Again that may be over the top but it's
fine for now if towards the end of the
game you realize you really aren't going to
be adding any more
code into these scripts I would probably
change the way we do things, but not a
problem for now because they don't have -
you know we don't have lots and lots of
scripts on each object, and at the end of
the day Unity is pushing you heavily
down the component route anyway, look how
many components you've got even without
our script, you've already got a transform, an
animator, a box collider. Alright, now the
projectiles again with the projectiles
they are projectiles that have kinematic
rigid body trigger colliders because of
the combination of these two components,
box collider and rigid body, but they're
also projectiles because we have
projectile scripts on them. So what I'm
proposing now then is that we actually fire
by animation events, and who's going to
fire? Well it's only some of the defenders, were
going to specialize the defenders into
shooters: the cactus and the gnome
will be doing the firing, and they'll
have a fire gun method which the
animator will be able to access and we'll also put a
gun object on them so that they have
somewhere to spawn the projectile
from. So for now I'm gonna go
ahead and specialize my cactus and
my gnome by creating myself yet another
script called shooter. So I'll
create a new script called
shooter, and this now has got three
components on it, so that's about as many
as I want but cactus and gnome have shooter,
just to be tidy I've gotta move that
script again, I wish I could create it
straight in the scripts folder but you either
create it attached to an object or you
create it in the scripts folder, it doesn't seem
that you can do both. If you know differently
let me know. So now the cactus and the gnome
have shooter scripts on them, we need to think
about how this shooter object is gonna
work . Well let's go into it and take a
look.
OK so what is shooter gonna need access
to? Well shooters... we're gonna need to know
what the projectile they fire is, so let's make a
public GameObject projectile; that's fine
and then immediately that we've done
that lets go ahead to the prefabs and
tell the shooter script what they fire,
so the cactus fires a cougette
and the gnome fires an axe. OK great, so we
got hold of the projectile that they're
going to fire; then the other thing they're
going to need privately, I think it's safe
that they make the assumption that there
is a gun sub-object attached to the actual
defender. So the cactus and the gnome are
going to create new child objects in
here. They're gonna be called gun, not gun
GameObject just gun, and then that can be
moved crucially; if you have trouble
moving it in the scene view just
move it in the inspector. So the cactus
could spawn his courgettes right at his
hand there and the gnome will have a very
similar gun object up here somewhere,
maybe from his belly, and he is going to
fire axes out of the gun.
so we're also gonna need to child these
projectiles when they arrive to
something. What are we gonna child them to?
So we're not gonna child them to the gun,
the gun is just there to adjust the
position they are instantiated at, the
reason we're not going to child them to the
gun is that childing them to the gun means that
they're in turn childed to the actual
game object, the cactus, and when the
cactus gets destroyed we want it's
projectiles to stay in flight, we don't them
to just disappear, that's why we've created
a projectiles object here. So we want them to
be childed to the projectiles object.
So we're going to have a public pet
another public GameObject, and I can
declare it straight after this, called
projectile parent like that, again let's
immediately go in there and do this. So
the cactus' shooter script wants to
know where is it going to parent the
things that it creates to, to the projectiles
object and the same with the gnome, I'm
gonna parent to the projectiles object.
Now you could find that projectiles
object a different way than dragging it
in, you could just find it at start by
name and then log out to the designer
hang on you haven't made one, you need to create
one. That's an alternative approach
which is completely valid. So the main
thing that we need in the shooter class
is a fire method, and it can actually be
private, and I always prefer to go private if I can
so private void fire, have a look. If you
go to the animator now for the cactus
which has a shooter script on it you'll
find that you can actually select fire
even though it's a private method, so
just to let you know the animator can
reach into private methods; so we have a
fire method, what is fire going to do?
Well it needs to instantiate a projectile
That's the first thing that it needs to do but
we need to get the new game object that
it instantiates and keep hold of it.
So the type is going to be GameObject, it's gonna
be a new projectile and it is the result of
the instantiation. Now, I'm not going to
show you through all of this, I thought you hope...
I think that you are thinking I was
going to sit there and show you exactly
how to do all this. I'm afraid that's not how this
course works, it's all about challenges, so
I've told you what we need to do, we have
created a shooter dot cs, we've created a
fire gun method, now we've also created
the gun game object to spawn projectiles
to. So I want you to finish it off, you
need to write the rest of the code that is
going to parent those new projectiles and
then when they appear they go flying
off to the right as they already are, we
already have the animation for that, and
we want the animator as I showed you to
call the fire gun, at least once per
cycle, once per clip. Now you're gonna
have a problem possibly if you're using
my assets with your known because his
attack animation is so short that he
will be firing very, very rapidly. I will
show you a solution to that in my
solution. Feel free to try and create
your own solution. So, see you in a moment.
So welcome back let's get this working,
so the new projectiles transform dot
parent - the parent of the new projectile
is projectile parent dot transform.
OK so that should now instantiate...
when we call the fire method it should
instantiate a new projectile at the
position of parented to projectile
parent let's make sure that it does and
then we'll worry about the position of it; so
here we are going to use say the
cactus in its attack - and in its
attack animation I'm going to put in an
event here and I'm going to fire once
per attack at say one second into his
attack animation. Now let's have a look
at the error we have down here, I can't
implicitly convert something, we
need to instantiate as a GameObject or it'll
come back as an object; cool, let's try this, see
what happens. Run the game, have a look
at our projectiles, now. Nothing's gonna
happen of course until we put our
cactus into the attacking state,
so let's do that and here you go, he's
instantiating courgettes and they are
being childed to the projectiles
GameObject. Awesome, of course they're never
dying, it would be useful if they died at
some point let's get that working real
quick so into the projectile script. There's a
very easy way to do this, it's void on
became invisible and that method there
will destroy the game object. That means
when no camera is seeing it, let's take a
look at the docs for on became invisible.
On became invisible is called when no
camera can see the object. So let's just
try it, let's make sure now that these
things that are being spawned as they
get spawned here obviously they're being
spawned from the wrong place, in a minute
we'll move them immediately they're instantiated to
the gun position. OK but let's just
watch and see what happens to them,
watch the number of courgettes here, how
many are there? and do they just keep increasing?
They do, so why does on became invisible not
work in this instance? Well the reason is
you can't actually use it here, because on
became invisible is sitting on a script
that is on the courgette, but the
courgette has no sprite renderer, it's only the
body that has a sprite render so the
courgette as far as it's concerned never
becomes invisible; its confused the method,
so we're not gonna be able to use on
became invisible but that's a common
trap to get in, you could easily spend
a lot of time trying to work out how to deal
with that. So we're going to use a
shredder that we've used so many times
before so very quickly I'm just gonna
put a shredder into the scene; gonna
reset its transform for now; gonna move it;
scale it, once I put a box collider 2d on
it, which is going to be a trigger - gonna
use triggers for everything, nice and
wide so that if things are going fast
they they don't pass through it
accidentally, off to the right of the
play space and 10 units high in Y, or five
units is it?
Or 9 or 8... there you go, 8, that's plenty to everything that goes off to the right is going to hit
the shredder, quick script, shredder, and
shredder simply... on trigger enter 2d they don't
actually have to put the parameters in
if you're not going to do anything with
them on trigger enter 2d simply destroy GameObject but, what would that do? That would destroy the
shredder, OK? So you do need the
parameters; it's a collider 2d, collider and
we are destroying collider - the other
thing that it hits, or the thing that's hitting it dot
game object. OK? I hope that makes sense
apart from we need a void in front of that,
just watch the shredder work, you see the moment
we see a bunch of projectiles being
fired and not being tidied up we want to
get into tidying them up, so let's set
this cactus firing, watch our number of
courgettes and then you can see they're
hitting the shredder, you can see more
clearly in scene view, especially if you
highlight the shredder and as soon as
they hit it they get minced. Perfect,
ok so they are now being minced, let's go
back to the firing code in the gun;
or the shooter and we said that the new
projectile's transform dot position
equals what? Now we need the gun's
transform position, so how we gonna do
this? Do you want to drag it into the Inspector? Do you want to find it? I'm just going to say gun here, make
it really easy, and then it's just gonna
be gun dot transform dot position
Now the dark side is you then have to
drag things around, we have to go back to
the inspector, we have to look at our
prefabs for two of our defenders and we
have to independently say who the gun is
and who the projectile parent is because
we need to be doing this in the prefab.
Now we have an important rule here to
consider is that we should be dragging
prefab to prefabs, not instances to
instances. So at the moment there's no
projectile parent against the pre-fab, if
you look at the cactus it has a
projectile parent but the prefab doesn't
OK so that's quite an important point.
Now let's apply the changes to the
cactus. Now the cactus prefab has a
gun sub-prefab in it. So, it is the
cactus that wanted to know about its
own gun, it's dragging a prefab to a prefab
Does that make sense? And the same for the
gnome, the gnome currently as we've been
playing around with the instance does
not have a gun in its prefab we apply, and it
does have a gun in its prefab, now we can say
to the gnome's shooter script here is
your gun. So how about the projectile
parent? Do we want to be prefabbing the
projectile parent? Well I would suggest
we do actually but not with an axe and a
courgette built in, but just a straight
prefab of the projectiles and the
shredder actually because when we set up
a new level, remember we want everything to be
prefabbed, so we just drop one of
everything in. So we will keep the
projectiles prefab even though it's
a nothing we'll keep it prefabbed; now when
you go to your defender prefab and you
look at its script and it's saying give
me a projectile parent you can and you
can give it the projectiles prefab you
must drag a prefab to a prefab, alright?
Hopefully I've rubbed that in enough now. If
you're always using prefab down here for
practically everything and you are - and
you are always dragging prefabs to
prefabs, you're in a good place. Should
you be prefabbing the event system? No,
because it's independent for every
different scene and it will come
automatically, but the canvas, should you be
prefabbing attackers and defenders itself? Yeah,
why not, we'll do that when we tidy up later
Alright, so the other defender was the
gnome and he's asking for a projectile
parent, so we don't drag the instance from
there, we drag the prefab from here. So
hopefully that's useful learning for you.
So here we go, let's try again, what is
happening when our attacker is in the
- sorry our cactus is in the attack
state? Let's put him in the attack state, and
now they're being spawned - they're far too big,
these courgettes, but they are being spawned from
his hand. So that's great, and then this
exactly the same thing would apply to
the gnome, let's put the gnome in his
attack state. The reason the gnome is not
firing yet, do you know why? It's because in the
gnome's animation I have not yet in his
attacking animation added a call to fire
a weapon but I have now; update my gnome prefab, now I can put my gnome in the attacking state and he
fires axes; there's far too many of them,
we'll deal with that in a moment, but
he's firing them, and again if we go to
the cactus and put him in attack state,
he then fires his axes. Great so that's
working really nicely. That's enough for this video,
let's leave it there and in the next
video we will work out how we can use
different states to better control our
firing rate and basically tidy up and
tweak these firing animations. So see you
shortly