So in this video let's take a look at why our gnome.
or my gnome in my case is firing too fast
Possible solutions to that type of issue:
why are we choosing to create a separate firing
state and then we'll fine tune
everything get. it working nice. OK so
let's take a quick look at the problem.
the problem is that once in the
attacking state. in fact it while we sort
this I'm gonna set the gnome's default
attacking state - default animation state
to attacking alright. so I'm going to go
into is attacking here rather than
changing the default state I'm going to set
the default parameter for both the gnome
and the cactus to is attacking so we can
immediately see them attacking rather
that change the default states. so they're
attacking all the time now. what's
happening here?
Well if you look at the cactus it has an
animation that consists of quite a few
frames well 30 frames a second; 2. 10 so
must be about... I don't know seventy frames
70 something frames. so we're firing once in
seventy something frames when it comes
to the cactus. so once every two and a bit
seconds. and that's what we see over in
the game; well we would if the cactus was
still alive; and then how about when it
comes to the gnome? Well look at the
gnome's animation. he only has a few
frames. literally a handful of frames. and
how many frames? Exactly 11 frames. so
his animation last less than a
second you see. your second is over here. about a
third of a second. So in comparison the
gnome is firing three times every second.
in fact dammit I'm going to put myself
another gnome - I have an abundance
mentality when it comes to gnomes; I can
have another gnome. Oops...
54.9. he's well high. OK and I'll have
another cactus because I want them out of
the attack line. OK fine. so watch this.
The gnome is firing three times a second.
crazy. what can we do about it? Well
there's a hacky way of sorting it which
is to go to the gnome and go well. why don't
we put more frames of animation in? It's kind
of ugly right. I don't really want the speed
he fires at to depend on the number of
frames in the animation. I'm certainly not going to copy frames and paste them in and stuff.
rubbish. Why don't we use the animator to
solve this? Why don't we create a new
state called fire? It doesn't change
anything else. everything else can just
go in and out of attack but the animator
itself go to attack to fire and back after a
certain number of loops of attack .and
then it's fire that will actually do the
firing. Does that make sense? Just one more
state here over on the right? Of course it does.
so that's going to be a simple solution
we only need to in my case do it for the
gnome. you could of course also do it on
your cactus. whatever characters
you've created you know. you may need
to do a similar thing I just wanna show
you this technique. Am I gonna show
you how to do it?
yes. Am I gonna show you how to do it before you try
it yourself? No. we really want you
doing the challenges. I hope you haven't
slipped out of habit of doing the
challenges. if you have this is a great
time to turn over a new leaf because
we're nearing the end of this 2D
course and we are going to need to be
leaving you to be able to do your own
things and think for yourself. So create
a new state called fire. transition into it
after a certain number of loops of
attack it's up to you; use attack motion
in fire state for now. so what do I mean
by that? What I'm saying is that what are
you going to use as an animation clip
when he's firing? Well in my game I'm
going to use the same motion - the same
attack motion and then move your fire
event to the fire estate and test it all works. So
go ahead and do that now.
Welcome back. so let's make this happen.
So we need a state firstly called fire.
so that's simple enough. Now in this fire
state we're going to use the same motion
as the attack motion but can we use
exactly the same motion? Well no because
this motion here is... would end up
being exactly the same for fire and
attack. we need the same sprites but we
need a different motion if that makes sense.
because we're going to have -
when we go to this line here:
gnome firing. we want a different clip so
actually a new way. a different way which
you've seen before
of creating a new state is to just say
create new clip and you can call it well
what let's go to our animations put it
in the right place or a sensible place
and what is it? It's the gnome firing; ok
so gnome firing. Now we have a motion for
gnome firing and we have a name. I'm just
going to simplify the name of the state to
firing and then the motion we just
recreate actually so it's going to be
simpler to just recreate it. and what - how
do we create it? Well. just go and get your
sprites right? It's his hopping motion that
we want to put in here
fine and the reason for that is now we
have a different motion here that we can
choose in the attacking state we're gonna
remove that event and in the firing
state which looks exactly the same we're
going to add in a fire. Now let's watch
him animate and see how he does. OK so fine
but we haven't put any transitions in
yet so let's put a transition in and
let's say after five cycles of attack
you go to firing and then after one
cycle of firing which is the default you
go back to attack. Is that working? Not
really. so because 5 never got stored.
OK. let's try that
1. 2. 3. 4. 5 fire 1. 2. 3. 4. 5 fire - you get the idea? Now is
he still animating when we go to the
firing state? He appears not to be. he
appears that when he's firing he's not
doing anything. So what's that about?
Gnome attacking changes the body sprite. gnome
firing tries to change the gnome sprite and
is no gnome sprite so we have again
to be careful that it is the body's sprite
renderers sprite that we are changing and we
need to create this a bit carefully so we are
making we are making it a little bit
difficult for ourselves by having these
these childed bodies here because the
animator doesn't quite work how we
want it to but it does really reinforce
how it works and gives you a lot more
flexibility so I'm going to stick with
it. I'm quite happy. Here he goes. he fires and
when he's firing he's still exhibiting
exactly the same animation. in fact he's not
pitching even so great alright? That's a
lot more sensible and now you control
your fire rate in here. So that bit's done.
let's take a look back to our challenge
and see what else we needed to do. Guess what.
we've done it. so what we gonna
do just to finish off is the bottom here.
fine tune the projectile size and spawn
position. So let's start off with the
gnome. I'm going to apply his prefab back
take a look at him and in slow motion. so
push pause. go back to the scene view.
and just frame-by-frame let's see what
happen. Well actually we'd beter wait 'til
he's in the attacking state. could be a
while. OK here we go. so there is that axe ok? Just
look at in real-time yeah it's ok it's a
bit big and it's coming out a bit low so
pretty easy to sort that out it's coming
out low so you move the gun up a bit so
like so. and then it's a bit big so you
simply go to the pre-fab for it. for the
axe. and you go to its not the axe
itself but to its sprite and let's just
make it eighty percent of the size let's
say in X and Y. Now it'll be higher and
smaller when it comes out of the gnome. OK it's
smaller for sure. I'm not particularly sure
that it's any higher so let's make sure
that we apply that back to the pre-fab
and possibly move it up a little bit more.
OK so that's moving the gun moves the
vertical position and horizontal.
in fact it needs a horizontal
position coming out because it's kinda
coming out of his face right now.
Anyway I don't need to obsessively tune
this. I will leave it to you guys
to make far better versions of this game
than we have got the time to make but
the point is you've got control over the
size of this axe and the position it
spawns at. OK. so that's great now
again same thing quickly for the
cactus. how's the spawning going?
Well the courgette's far. far too big so
let's just make the sprite of the
courgette a bit smaller. let's find ourselves a
courgette. put in the scene so we can
see how big we want it and then on this
instance of the courgette go to its body.
the scale tool. scale it down and then apply
that back to the courgette prefab and remove the instance. Alright. let's try it. Great so now the
firing animations are sensible you might
say how about if I want to change the
fire rate in script well that's one of
the tradeoffs we're making here. you could
but you'd have to be accessing animator
properties. it's a bit of a weird thing
to do. so the purpose of this is that
we're having a consistent fire rate but
it's up to the animator to be able to choose
when. By the way notice that these axes
continue even after the gnome has died
which is exactly the behavior that we
want. So this stone is standing up
well to the lizard's attack... in the next
video we need to get the projectiles
actually hitting the attackers and only
the attackers. not other defenders and
not... well that's it.
Not other defenders basically. and
not other projectiles as well.
OK so we'll look forward to doing that in a
moment. See you soon.
=======
Kind: captions
Language: en
So in this video let's take a look at why our gnome,
or my gnome in my case is firing too fast
Possible solutions to that type of issue:
why are we choosing to create a separate firing
state and then we'll fine tune
everything get, it working nice. OK so
let's take a quick look at the problem,
the problem is that once in the
attacking state, in fact it while we sort
this I'm gonna set the gnome's default
attacking state - default animation state
to attacking alright, so I'm going to go
into is attacking here rather than
changing the default state I'm going to set
the default parameter for both the gnome
and the cactus to is attacking so we can
immediately see them attacking rather
that change the default states, so they're
attacking all the time now, what's
happening here?
Well if you look at the cactus it has an
animation that consists of quite a few
frames well 30 frames a second; 2, 10 so
must be about... I don't know seventy frames
70 something frames, so we're firing once in
seventy something frames when it comes
to the cactus, so once every two and a bit
seconds, and that's what we see over in
the game; well we would if the cactus was
still alive; and then how about when it
comes to the gnome? Well look at the
gnome's animation, he only has a few
frames, literally a handful of frames, and
how many frames? Exactly 11 frames, so
his animation last less than a
second you see, your second is over here, about a
third of a second. So in comparison the
gnome is firing three times every second,
in fact dammit I'm going to put myself
another gnome - I have an abundance
mentality when it comes to gnomes; I can
have another gnome. Oops...
54.9, he's well high. OK and I'll have
another cactus because I want them out of
the attack line. OK fine, so watch this.
The gnome is firing three times a second,
crazy, what can we do about it? Well
there's a hacky way of sorting it which
is to go to the gnome and go well, why don't
we put more frames of animation in? It's kind
of ugly right, I don't really want the speed
he fires at to depend on the number of
frames in the animation, I'm certainly not going to copy frames and paste them in and stuff,
rubbish. Why don't we use the animator to
solve this? Why don't we create a new
state called fire? It doesn't change
anything else, everything else can just
go in and out of attack but the animator
itself go to attack to fire and back after a
certain number of loops of attack ,and
then it's fire that will actually do the
firing. Does that make sense? Just one more
state here over on the right? Of course it does,
so that's going to be a simple solution
we only need to in my case do it for the
gnome, you could of course also do it on
your cactus, whatever characters
you've created you know. you may need
to do a similar thing I just wanna show
you this technique. Am I gonna show
you how to do it?
yes. Am I gonna show you how to do it before you try
it yourself? No, we really want you
doing the challenges. I hope you haven't
slipped out of habit of doing the
challenges, if you have this is a great
time to turn over a new leaf because
we're nearing the end of this 2D
course and we are going to need to be
leaving you to be able to do your own
things and think for yourself. So create
a new state called fire, transition into it
after a certain number of loops of
attack it's up to you; use attack motion
in fire state for now, so what do I mean
by that? What I'm saying is that what are
you going to use as an animation clip
when he's firing? Well in my game I'm
going to use the same motion - the same
attack motion and then move your fire
event to the fire estate and test it all works. So
go ahead and do that now.
Welcome back, so let's make this happen.
So we need a state firstly called fire,
so that's simple enough. Now in this fire
state we're going to use the same motion
as the attack motion but can we use
exactly the same motion? Well no because
this motion here is... would end up
being exactly the same for fire and
attack, we need the same sprites but we
need a different motion if that makes sense,
because we're going to have -
when we go to this line here:
gnome firing, we want a different clip so
actually a new way, a different way which
you've seen before
of creating a new state is to just say
create new clip and you can call it well
what let's go to our animations put it
in the right place or a sensible place
and what is it? It's the gnome firing; ok
so gnome firing. Now we have a motion for
gnome firing and we have a name, I'm just
going to simplify the name of the state to
firing and then the motion we just
recreate actually so it's going to be
simpler to just recreate it, and what - how
do we create it? Well, just go and get your
sprites right? It's his hopping motion that
we want to put in here
fine and the reason for that is now we
have a different motion here that we can
choose in the attacking state we're gonna
remove that event and in the firing
state which looks exactly the same we're
going to add in a fire. Now let's watch
him animate and see how he does. OK so fine
but we haven't put any transitions in
yet so let's put a transition in and
let's say after five cycles of attack
you go to firing and then after one
cycle of firing which is the default you
go back to attack. Is that working? Not
really, so because 5 never got stored,
OK, let's try that
1, 2, 3, 4, 5 fire 1, 2, 3, 4, 5 fire - you get the idea? Now is
he still animating when we go to the
firing state? He appears not to be, he
appears that when he's firing he's not
doing anything. So what's that about?
Gnome attacking changes the body sprite, gnome
firing tries to change the gnome sprite and
is no gnome sprite so we have again
to be careful that it is the body's sprite
renderers sprite that we are changing and we
need to create this a bit carefully so we are
making we are making it a little bit
difficult for ourselves by having these
these childed bodies here because the
animator doesn't quite work how we
want it to but it does really reinforce
how it works and gives you a lot more
flexibility so I'm going to stick with
it, I'm quite happy. Here he goes, he fires and
when he's firing he's still exhibiting
exactly the same animation, in fact he's not
pitching even so great alright? That's a
lot more sensible and now you control
your fire rate in here. So that bit's done,
let's take a look back to our challenge
and see what else we needed to do. Guess what,
we've done it, so what we gonna
do just to finish off is the bottom here,
fine tune the projectile size and spawn
position. So let's start off with the
gnome, I'm going to apply his prefab back
take a look at him and in slow motion, so
push pause, go back to the scene view,
and just frame-by-frame let's see what
happen. Well actually we'd beter wait 'til
he's in the attacking state, could be a
while. OK here we go, so there is that axe ok? Just
look at in real-time yeah it's ok it's a
bit big and it's coming out a bit low so
pretty easy to sort that out it's coming
out low so you move the gun up a bit so
like so, and then it's a bit big so you
simply go to the pre-fab for it, for the
axe, and you go to its not the axe
itself but to its sprite and let's just
make it eighty percent of the size let's
say in X and Y. Now it'll be higher and
smaller when it comes out of the gnome. OK it's
smaller for sure, I'm not particularly sure
that it's any higher so let's make sure
that we apply that back to the pre-fab
and possibly move it up a little bit more.
OK so that's moving the gun moves the
vertical position and horizontal,
in fact it needs a horizontal
position coming out because it's kinda
coming out of his face right now.
Anyway I don't need to obsessively tune
this, I will leave it to you guys
to make far better versions of this game
than we have got the time to make but
the point is you've got control over the
size of this axe and the position it
spawns at, OK, so that's great now
again same thing quickly for the
cactus, how's the spawning going?
Well the courgette's far, far too big so
let's just make the sprite of the
courgette a bit smaller, let's find ourselves a
courgette, put in the scene so we can
see how big we want it and then on this
instance of the courgette go to its body,
the scale tool, scale it down and then apply
that back to the courgette prefab and remove the instance. Alright, let's try it. Great so now the
firing animations are sensible you might
say how about if I want to change the
fire rate in script well that's one of
the tradeoffs we're making here, you could
but you'd have to be accessing animator
properties, it's a bit of a weird thing
to do, so the purpose of this is that
we're having a consistent fire rate but
it's up to the animator to be able to choose
when. By the way notice that these axes
continue even after the gnome has died
which is exactly the behavior that we
want. So this stone is standing up
well to the lizard's attack... in the next
video we need to get the projectiles
actually hitting the attackers and only
the attackers, not other defenders and
not... well that's it.
Not other defenders basically, and
not other projectiles as well.
OK so we'll look forward to doing that in a
moment. See you soon.
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1:Unity/Section7/GG31 Separate Attack Fire States.srt