Hey welcome back so this is a pure
challenge video. I want you to code for
projectile damage. It's relatively simple, it
uses the same concepts as before
Basically make projectiles damage
anything that has both an attacker and a
health on it. Set up a play space and
start tuning the damage and health
levels and we'll play tune again later once we
can spawn both enemies and defenders.
So go ahead and see if you can get those
damn projectors damaging the attackers.
OK welcome back let's look at how we're
gonna do it. So which script do you think
it's gonna be in? Which script did you do it on?
Well it makes sense to work on the projectile
script right? OK so where? What method?
Well it's the on trigger enter 2D; you are
remembering all 2Ds right? Without that
it's going to get slippery, and we're
going to need the collider so let's put
in the parameters, there it is great. So
what we do on there? Well we need to know
firstly about the attacker and the health as
I said, so let's be very specific,  let's
use the attacker type
attacker attacker equals collider dot
game object,so we go from the collider of the
thing that's hitting the project - or the
projectile is hitting to the game
object; from the GameObject we get the
component of type attacker, if there is
one which we'll ask in a minute; and then we do
a very same thing with the health. If you
didn't do the full
challenge then is a good
opportunity for you to do at
least a mini challenge which is just
finish this line before I do. It's gonna be
exactly the same pattern as above. There we go
OK great so we now have the attacker
and te health component - well if they exist
off the thing that the the projectile is
colliding wit, so what could it be
colliding with? It could be colliding
with an another projectile, well
would that have attacker and health on
it? No; it could be colliding
with a defender would that
have attacker and health on it?
No. Could it be colliding with an attacker? Well yes, and all attackers have health, and if
they don't we're not going to damage
them anyway. So the if statement is
simply if attacker and health. Even in a
physics-based game you may want to use
this method of filtering by actual game; by script, by class, by
component by wheat have you wanna call
it. It's a pretty strong way of doing things.
So what we gonna do if that's the case?
So we're gonna health dot deal damage; how
much? Well we have damage available, it's the
damage that the projectile does. So we're
going to deal this projectile's amount of
damage and then we're going to destroy
what are we gonna destroy? The projectile, right?
The projectile is responsible for
destroying itself so GameObject looks
through the current script which is
projectile dot cs and destroys the very
game object it's attached to. Cool, let's
see if it works
So somewhere I've missed a void; OK the name health
does not exist in the current context
that's just coz I spelled it wrong. The name
health, I really don't spell health right
do I? H-E-A-LTH. OK health dot deal damage, there we
go. So hopefully compilation errors are
gone and we can run and watch the damage
being done by the projectiles now. So how
would we know? Well let's take a look at
that liard for example, is that lizard
being damaged? So if we zoom out, click on the
lizard, you have to go to himself rather than
his sprite as I've said before, well he's gone
so presumably he was taking damage. In
fact also you can see that the fox
disappears, so the fox jumps over the stone,
gets twatted by an axe a few times and then
dies. Great, so that's fine in fact I'm
not going to mess around with the play
tuning now because seemed not too far
off the mark actually so I'm gonna leave
it at that. Bear in mind that you can go
into any of your projectiles, your axe,
your courgette, any of your projectiles,
you can change the amount of damage they
do, you can change how fast they fly, you
can also for all of your attackers to
help change the tuning you can change
how much health they have and then that
will change the balance of play for you
currently the stone has got a huge
amount of health, arguably too much
that's the one thing I will change. Give it
maybe two hundred and we really want to
play tune this properly once we have the
ability to spawn objects, but quite a
good bit of progress here we have
attackers coming in, responding
differently depending on their behavior,
projectiles disappearing either when
they hit an attacker or when they go off
the screen, have a bit of a collision issue,
not really sure about when these things
are colliding so let's just take a quick
look at the colliders on the projectiles
How are you gonna do that? You're gonna need a
projectile in the scene to look at it so
I'll just stick it in the bottom.
So let's just take a look at this axe. where's
it's box collider? There it is
why is it sitting like that? Well it
depends what animation state it's in
right? So if we look at that axe as it
goes through the air, well one of the exes
you could see what was happening there
you see? The collider's ahead of it, that's why
it appears to be doing damage before it
actually hits the object in question, so
that's easy enough to sort out, go to the
axe focus on it, just go to your box
collider of course and move its center.
Something more like that would be
appropriate and the same kind of deal
with the courgette, let's look at the
courgette and say is that a good collider?
It's alright but is it the right size? Not
really, so let's just pull it down a
little bit, and that's because the system
fitted it to the size of the courgette
before we made its sprite smaller, but we
now have independent control over the size of the box collider and the sprite which is fine
OK let's take a look at it now, you're gonna have a
couple of rogue projectiles in the scene
and just make sure that the things look
like they're actually hitting the
objects - yeah that doesn't look far off.
Great you can always tune all these
colliders to your heart's content but
we've achieved what we wanted to achieve
which is we now have projectiles dealing
damage, so if you did all that on your own
congratulations, if you didn't and you needed
some help no problem, I hope you've learned a lot
and I shall see you soon.