Hey hey, so the goal of this video is to
get ourselves some buttons that we can
use to select the defender that we want
to place. So by the end of the video we'll
have a little panel up here in the top
of our play space with our four defender
types in it and I'm gonna have them all
silhouetted against... just black
silhouettes against a background panel,
and when you click them they will highlight and
then also we will have a static ready to
be called from anywhere and that can be
used to actually place the defender
prefab. So said differently we gonna set
up buttons for the defender, or in a more
general tower defense game a tower
selection; initially they just toggle the
sprite color, then we'll set up defender
selector, or just button dot selected
defender static and then we'll test that
static at the start and on button
presses to make sure that it works
properly. So first let's just make our
buttons area, so I'm going to create an
empty object and call it buttons and put
it above the defenders, seems to make sense to me.
Reset the transform, and inside
it I think I'm going to use a quad
and just child that quad into the buttons and then
you can move it, the reason I want to use a quad is
because it's world space basically how
wide do I want it? Well four, so four
units wide, not 44 - four, perfect. Move it
roughly in the right place and then you
can very quickly reason that it should
be at exactly 2.5 by six. Great, that's fine,
so gonna need a quick material here
because this guy has no sensible looking
material so where should we store it? I'm gonna
store it in this case in images, it's a
bit weird but why not, we're only gonna have
one of them; going to call it
button panel and diffuse material is
just fine just give it a color like a bluey
color or something like that, whatever
you like apply that material to the
quod and I might just make it a little
bit transparent, in which case we would
need to just make it
transparent diffuse and then when you
make it transparent it'll actually have
some effect. So there you go slightly transparent
background cast there, doesn't really
matter if that overspills the play space, that just
says that's where my buttons are. I'm just
gonna call it a background so it makes
some sense in the hierarchy cool, now
let's actually make the buttons, let's
make the package from scratch it's gonna
be easier. So they need to be childed to
buttons here and then let's just give them
names, go through them, so where are my
prefabs? My defender prefabs, just gonna
set up four buttons, and in a moment I'm
gonna be asking you to get some behavior
in code but for now cactus, can sit
here roughly and then it's gonna need a
sprite so what sprite renderer are we gonna
use? We just have a basic sprite renderer on
it and then we can take any of the
cactus sprites, whatever we like the
look of and just apply it over here, so
we could just search for cactus, pick
one you like the look of, a kind of hey
pick me, doesn't really matter. There's
lots and lots of variations here, I'll go for
that one and then we need to make sure
that it's scaled appropriately in fact I
need to scale the whole do down a little
bit so that he kind of fits in the space
that's fine and then add myself a
collider so that we can click on him. Now,
when adding these colliders, if you've
scaled down the sprite we will have
here just a simple object right, we're
not putting the sprites in separate
sub-objects, we just have a button organiser
and then cactus. We will also have
another object here next to cactus
called gnome. I'll do the gnome now just so
you can see the two working together, the
gnome will sit here, he will also have a
sprite renderer on him and you get the
pattern hopefully, so we choose a sprite,
pick one that we like and preferably pick
one that will work well in silhouette
and scale him down a little bit so he
works as a button.
OK, so that's all very well, how are we gonna
know when we've clicked on these buttons
and also we can't really see the
buttons that well, so not being in to see
them is to do with the order in layer, if you just set that
to one then they'll pop out, that's great.
Clicking on them is this... that's the
purpose of this collider that's why
we've got a box collider 2D but we
need to get the size right, because I
want it to be exactly right at least in
the x direction so the way you calculate
the size is you say well if we've scaled
the transformed down by point 64 then you
can do a calculation 1 divided by .64 is
1.56, so if you put that in the X scale
and the Y scale of the collider,
now it's in exactly the right place. If
we set the X transform right, look
that's perfect. What I want you to do
briefly is just set up the other buttons,
just go ahead and set up all of your
buttons so they have colliders that are
the right X width precisely, sprites that
look a sensible size and fit in the
screen space you've got left, I don't
mind if your colliders overspill the top of
the game space but I don't want them
going into the lanes below, so they should
look like that. I'll just do it on the gnome
just to help you out
So a box collider on the gnome looks lie that again
I do a calculation I take the X value, I
do 1 divided by the value, copy that in my calculator and
paste it in and scale up that size. Now
this guy needs a little bit of Y
offset so that I don't risk going into the
lane if in doubt leave a bit of a gap.
Better that they click. Imagine
how the failure cases on the borderline here
imagine you stick your finger on the
border what's bad? What's bad is that you
accidentally place a defender
because you can't undo it, what's ok is if you accidentally
select a defender, so in that spirit I'm
gonna move that one up a little bit as
well. You see how
the collider's are working there, imagine where
the finger presses will be, but if you
select two of them you see they're
perfectly matched up in the x-direction
provided at my transforms here, the
X part of the transform is whole
numbers one and two.
So just go ahead and do the other two
buttons, I'm gonna do that while you're
doing yours; I''ll just shut up and get on with it.
ok finally ending up with four, the trophy
looks a little bit off that's because
its X position is not precisely four, and
the also the gravestone's X position is
not precisely 3. OK selecting them all
together
looks pretty good, I don't mind if they're
slightly out of line that's good enough
for government work, so now we have four
very simple game objects each of which
have colliders on them and appropriately
sized sprites, and now we need a button
script so I'm gonna add a button script to
all of these and let's edit the script. So
here we have a button script. So what's the
message that we intersect when we wanna
know that somebody's clicked the button?
We have box colliders, they actually ought
to be trigger colliders, it doesn't really
matter for this case actually but I want
everything to be trigger colliders, so we
have box colliders but they're not colliding with
colliders, they're colliding with our finger
finger that's the word, or the mouse so it's
actually the On
mouse down event that we need, so let's
just start real basic, let's prove that
we can intercept our clicks just by
simply logging out - I'll print this time
I'm just gonna say nam, which is the name of the object
plus pressed and also I think I've got
a debug dot log left over in my attacker
script under the on trigger enter 2D, if
you've still got that remove it, we only
want one thing logging to the console
right now. Let's just check that we can
actually click and log;
Cactus, gnome, stone, trophy and if you hit somewhere
on the borderline it does nothing that's good.
Perfect so now it's over to you for another challenge
Get the sprite color toggling working.
Start with no defenders selected, they're
all black, click toggles to the clicked defender,
all unselected offenders are blacked out and
then the selected defender has a
different sprite color to the rest when
you click on it
alright so you get the idea click goes
to the color
white or whatever colour you've chosen, and
all the others have got to be black so
good luck trying to work out how to do that and pause
the video and have a good crack at it even
if you don't succeed in these challenges
it's the trying to succeed in the
challenges that really matters because
that's where you're really learning and
I shall see you soon.
Cool welcome back; what do we want to do next?
let's next check the we know how to
actually set the sprite color so how do
we set the sprite color? Well for the
thing in question, for the button in
question we simply get component sprite
renderer dot colour - whoops it's a method dot
color equals color dot white, for example
let's try that so we click on one of the
things that isn't white and look, up it comes.
Great, so we can change the color to white
then how do we turn all the others back to
black?
well there's a few ways you could do it
I'm gonna do it this way I'm going to
have a private button array called button array.
Call a dog a dog, call a horse a horse! Ok
and then on start I will find that
button array so button array simply equals
what is it equal? Game object dot find
objects of type, we've done this a billion
times now, button so find all your buttons, great so we have all our buttons in this array
Then what? Well why don't we try looping for
them. For them? Through them for each
button the type this button - just to be
sure we don't confuse it with any sort
of instance of button or anything like
that just for each button, this button, in
button array, so we go through all the
buttons in the array and what we do? We
go this button . get component
same thing as before right
sprite renderer - in fact I'm going to copy it
apart from the white and it's colour dot black
OK let's try it. So the first thing we do is set the other buttons to black and then we set the one we've clicked to
white, see if it works. Bonza! OK and is it also
selecting one randomly at the start? Well
we don't know right now because this
gnome has a white setting by default
let's just put him black like everybody
else see what happens with the start
condition here, nothing is selected.
Well that's okay that's okay or it could
randomly select one at the start, we'll
worry about that when we get to the
prefabs bit. Right now having nothing
selected is just fine
OK cool, so on to the second half which
is that we need to now actually link
some prefabs to these things and set a
static so why a static? Because from
outside of this class I would like to be
able to say button . selected button or
selected defender so it's over to you to
get that bit working, I want you to set up
the static when a defender is selected
set that static and test by logging from
another method's update for instance
attacker dot cs and there's no need to
actually place the defenders yet you
might wonder what the type of this
static is, I want you to make it a GameObject
and I want you to publicly expose for
each button the defender that they should
be spawning and drag it in so the
cactus button has a cactus prefab
dragged into it, and then you set that as
the static. So from your other method
say in the update method of attack when
you say print selected defender - button
rather dot selected defender what you'll
get back is an actual game object that
is the GameObject prefab relating to
that button, all ready to be instantiated
later. Hopefully that makes sense and
have a go at setting up that defender
selected defender static yourself now.
Welcome back so we have a private static
GameObject called selected defender. Now what
does it mean that it's static, just to
revise? It means that there's just one of them in
the entire game, it's on the class it's
on the template, it's on the mold that makes
the buttons not any of the individual
buttons, and this is a sensible place to
store it because we only have one ever
have one defender selected so where's it
gonna get this from? Well I think we just
pass in publicly for simplicity public
GameObject prefab to - defender prefab, ok
so each but now has a prefab, or will have when
we associate a prefab, so we go to the
cactus for example, tidy up my button script, and we
just give it the cactus prefab. So
the cactus button is associated with a
cactus prefab. There're only four of these so it
doesn't matter that it's a very manual
process, gnome gnome, stone gravestone, trophy
trophy, great. So they now all have access to
an actual game object which is great, we
have a static that we're gonna be able to
store that in - where did my script go?
Slippery little bugger, let's go and find it
OK we have a static we'll be able to store that in,
so what is the essence of clicking a button?
Well it's just saying that selected
defender equals defender prefab does that
make sense and then we could just print
selected defender and stop printing
anything about pressed here. So, we're
setting the static when we click them, let's
see if it works, we click here what does
the log say? It says that we've got a
cactus in that static and then we click
this guys who says we've got a gnome in that static and
then we click this guy and it says we've got a gravestone in the static. Perfect, now any other method
from the outside like even attacker here
could every frame for instance just as
a test say print button . now we've got
available here
provided we've made our static
public not private that was a mistake
of mine, so the static game object should be
public so other things can see it provided we
have a public static watch attacker button
dot selected defender - very easy, any
method without an instance even of a
button in the scene, although we will have
them can just say what's the selected
defender. So let's stop logging it over
here and log it every frame from a
different method, let's watch. What's it
logging? Null well that's fine, cos what do we
have selected as a defender? Nothing,
cactus, cactus, cactus; gnome, gnome, gnome
grave stone, grave stone, grave stone you get
the idea see how simple an interface that
is from the outside, attacker just says button
tell me - button class, tell me what your
current defence;  selected defender is, so
that's my solution there's the code on the
screen a private static selected
defender prefab comes in and then when you
click you clear all the previous
existing buttons
set yourself to white and then set the
static. Easy as pie, congratulations if
you managed to do that on your own and I
will see you soon.