Hey guys welcome back so just before we
dive in and actually get the defender
spawning working I want to sort out a
little glitch that we're going to end up
with because of the way that we are
handling this projectiles parent
placeholder; now it's a good idea to
organize your spawned objects into
parent objects when the game starts
running, so if we have a look here, back
over on the scene view, once the game
starts running we've currently organized
that all new projectiles go into this
projectiles placeholder object and you
can see them spawning in here, all the
axis et cetera. That's a good idea
otherwise your hierarchy would end up
filling up and it'd be really hard in
this mode to see what's going on and to
get a handle on anything. So that's good
and it does best practices out there on
the web, here's a blog post which I'll
link you to, Glenn Stevens best
practices and he says you know spawning
objects don't let spawned objects
clutter your hierarchy
totally agree - good idea, the way that we've
gone about it so far that I've taken you
down is not ideal so let's introduce
another best practice and the second
best practice I'm getting from another
great blog post which you'll find in the
slides which is this devmag blog post
here and it's got a whole bunch of best
practices for unity, we've actually got
them all on our wall, we're making sure we're infusing them
through the course and one of them is
making the game runable from any scene
Now you can read this in detail
yourself but there's a pattern here that
basically says if we need something like
this parent game holder then
find it and if we can't find it create it.
Ao that's what we're going to do in this
video so what we gonna do here is - I'll
explain in a bit more detail what the
problem with the current way of doing
things is. You've got a link there to the
Glenn Stevens article on Unity 3d best
practices that massively overlaps with
the devmag one which is also linked on
the next slide, and I'm going to show
you and then help you implement a pattern
for checking and creating the parent
objects rather than the way we doing it
now. So what's the problem with the way
we're doing it now? Let's take a look. If we
drop a new defender in here like a gnome,
bang, into the scene - you need to be in scene view
clearly - and start running let's see what
happens - what happens when he starts
spawning objects? Well
he needs - you see they're spawning at the top
here? He hasn't found that there's a
projectiles object, so why not? You might
say well let's look at the gnome, he has
a prefab right and how come the
projectile parent prefab is not
connected to hit to the gnome? Well you
could and that's why I went down the
route with prefabs, you could drag the projectile
parent prefab into the projectile
parent here obeying a good rule which
is that prefabs should be dragged to
prefabs, but sometimes combining two good
rules i.e. prefab should be dragged to
prefabs and the idea that we should
parent spawned game objects actually can
create something that's still more
complicated than we need. Alright the
problem with this is you've got to do
that for every object, it has actually lost
the connection for me but even if I go
fix the connection for the gnome I've gotta
make sure it's in place for the cactus
and the star trophy et cetera - hassle right?
Just spells hassle to me so why don't we
introduce you to a whole new pattern, a
whole new way of doing things. I'm going
to start by deleting the projectiles
parent game object and the projectiles
prefab, we're not going to have it at all
alright? It doesn't exist anymore
OK then what I'm going to do is
challenge you to make the necessary
changes to the shooter script, because
that's the script that does it
It's specifically things that do shooting
I'm going to ask you to make the necessary
change in the shooting script to look to
see if there is a game object in the
hierarchy called projectiles, here's the
shooter script and if there is then
just use it for the parents - all this
code here can stay the same - but
if it doesn't exist then you're going to
need to create it, so as a hint it's
going to be in the void start method and
in here you're gonna put some code that's
going to follow the following pattern, let's
take a look at the slide. So here's the
pattern. My object = find object in scene
that's kind of pseudo code that's not
gonna work but something very similar
will work, so go looking for it go
looking for something called projectiles
if it exists fine, if it doesn't exist
spawn it alright, so that's pseudocode on the
screen but it's gonna be enough for you
to have a go at it so go ahead try and
make this work
Awesome welcome back so let's take a
look at how we are going to make it work
So projectile parent gun and projectile
well firstly we're no longer in a publicly
expose the projectile parent, we're going to
take that pain away and we have much
more naturally now that shooters you
just tell them about their projectile
and their gun. Privately they worry
about whether or not they need a parent
to spawn to OK? so then we have a private
game object projectile parent. OK, fine
so what we do on start? We go looking for
it right so it's valid to say projectile
parent equals GameObject dot find and
then projectiles; ok fine now if
something in the hierarchy called
projectiles exists, so if projectiles or
put it this way if there is nothing
called projectiles then projectile parent
will be null so if not projectile parent
ok if there is no result of this game
object dot find then create one, well how are you gonna create one? Projectile parent... now you might be
tempted to try and use instantiate here, don't
use instantiate - instantiate's for
instantiating prefabs, we're doing
instantiation down here
of a projectile prefab but here which is
creating a blank GameObject, so how do
you create a new Vector? You go new vector
three right? How do you create a new
anything? You use the keyword new, does that
make sense so we go looking for
something called projectiles if we find
it then projectile parent is already set
if not projectile parent does not
evaluate so we skip over this and we go
ahead and do the parenting if however we
cannot find a projectile parent then
this will take the value of now and then
we will create one, let's see if it works and the
way I've written the code we get the
following error in the shooter script
an expression requires brackets square or
squiggly on line 14; so back to the code
what have we done? Line 14, well GameObject
What I would do here is go look at the
docs, what we're actually missing is just a
pair of brackets like that but why? So
let's go look at the docs for game
object; so here we are at the docs of
game object when you construct a new
game object what parameters do you
pass in if anything? So if you search for
constructor on the page you'll find here
in this section - and this is a general pattern for
most of the methods you'll see in unity
you may have a constructor, so let's
look at it. It's actually got three
constructors, look carefully at the docs
one signature is this that you do
game object and then you pass in a
string, you see them down here? They're
saying new game object call it player
alright let's move down, there's another
signature here, there should be a big black
line there isn't; another signature from
this point down, different stuff as we
said before; second signature says don't
pass anything in, new game object alright
well let's try that so now that we've
got our brackets it knows to actually
construct a new game object, let's try
running, see what happens
Gonna get some issues here you go now we've
got five new game objects, why? Why have we got
five new game objects?
well because there are five different
things in the scene with that script
attached and each one of them is creating
a new game object and parenting it's
projectiles to it because none of them
have actually named the GameObject
projectiles. So you could name the game
object projectiles like this, you could
gather this new projectile parent you've
created and then say . name equals
projectiles, let's just try that, why would
you do that? Good question, you wouldn't but
let's just show you that it works; now
the first one immediately creates something
called projectiles, everybody else finds it and
says that's fine I'll use that and they
stuff their projectiles under there; good
news so the only thing I would say is
that why write all that code when you
can take this projectiles bit and use
the helpful constructor that lets you
name it
while you create it; I'll re-type projectiles,
there you go so we don't need to address the
projectiles . name later there is
actually a third variation down here
this one here which takes in a name and
an array of components which could be
useful if you want if you want to
construct a rich object that has a
whole lot of things already attached to
it, maybe sprite renderers, maybe scripts
whatever then you could get into that
but we're using this top version here where we
just say new game object and give it a
name while we're at it
alright guys so that is what's happening
there now this process is much more
robust now when we drop our guys in the
scene they will just create a
projectiles game object if there's not
already one there, so we don't even have
to have one in the scene.
Let's just test that on a second
scene just to rub the point home
So here this scene's got no defenders in
it whatsoever, if I stick a gnome in
this scene and hit play look at the
hierarchy on the left, he immediately goes I
can't find any projectiles, I'm gonna
create one and if we stick a cactus
in he'll come along and go - you
actually have to be in the scene view so
I'll put him in the hierarchy, here is the
cactus he goes I can't find any
projectiles I'll also create one and he
will spawn all of his things if he fires
anything to the same thing; so let's do another gnome, just to prove the point, two gnomes standing on
top of each other they both find the
same projectiles object and they stick
their axes in there and that keeps our
hierarchy all happy. Point driven home
hopefully here is the general pattern
I'll leave you with the slide hopefully
you passed that challenge, and that general
pattern is pretty handy. Take a look
through the rest of those tips both on
Devmag and also on here, on Glenn
Stevens which has most of the same stuff
as Devmag but also some other
useful best practices. so hopefully that
was helpful for you and start doing that
in your games from now.