Hey guys. welcome back! So. in this video we're going to focus on
actually getting the world coordinates of
the mouse click. So. what's happening at the moment
is. we have these
things be able to be selected. when you click on them. but actually when we click
into the play-space nothing happens. There's no enemies
being spawned. So. we need to change that! I'm
going to start by confidently just deleting all the attackers in the scene.
defenders in the scene. because from now on we're
going to want to spawn defenders. Also. including that
rogue gnome that we had there. OK. fantastic!
So. in this video we're going to ensure
existing defender' colliders mask the square that they're over.
Calculate the world position of a click.
calculate to the nearest play-space grid center.
and then. spawn the currently selected defender. right there.
Right in the middle of the grid space or the closest
to the middle of the grid space. that we have clicked. So. let's
get on with that. Let's break the problem down into parts.
Where are we going to start? Well. we already have a
core game space unit. here in the UI. You can
see it there! It's under the Level Canvas. in your Hierarchy.
And if you click on it. you can see that it's 1.200
by 675 pixels wide.
So that's the object we are going to start by adding a script
to. So. there are some differences when
you start trying to add a script. of this type. to
a UI object. but let's do it! Let's be brave! Call it
DefenderSpawner. like that! So. a new script
attached to your Core Game area. And of course.
you need to tidy the script up as usual. There it goes!
OK fantastic! So. going into the script now. Let's
take a look and see what we need to do.
So. one of the first things we want to be able to
do is intercept a mouse click or a finger click. Remember. we're making
this game for mobile. so the method you need is On
MouseDown (). That also works for finger clicks. and it returns the
pixel coordinates of that press or that
click. So. why don't we just start by
making sure that method is being called. print ("clicked");
Now. if you're sharp and you've been looking at the docs. you'll notice
that we're missing something. but let's take a look at what happens if we
just try it. OK. so we print ("clicked") when the OnMouseDown
message gets called. Let's try and see what happens!
There it is. attached to the Core Game object! Hit play!
Click click click! Console! OK well. it's filling up
with nulls. which is fine. but even if we collapse the Console.
like that. there's no click going on right. I'm going to
remove the line that prints those nulls. I'm doing this just
by double clicking the null. that's coming up on the Console. That takes me
straight to the line of script that logs that thing out.
and I can get rid of it. So. we have a clear Console and we're
pretty confident nothing is getting called. Why?
Well. the reason is that you need a collider. The only
way that these clicks actually get interceptors is if you have
a collider. So. let's put a Box Collider 2D
on the course Game Space. There it goes!
Alright. you're getting an
error! Look inside the Box Collider Element. "The collider did not create any
collision shapes. as they failed verification." That's because on a UI
Element. the size isn't in world units it's in
pixels. So. we actually need to set the size of this Box
Collider to 1.200 pixels in the X direction.
like so.
To 675 pixels in the Y direction.
Now. this is different to how you normally do things. because they're
normally in world units. but this is a UI Element. so we're
showing you an alternative way here. Ah. now click is
being called! Great! That's fantastic! So.
remember you need that. Also. you might want to apply your prefab back to your
Core Game Element here. but generally we'll
update the prefabs later. So. we've done that bit. what next? How are we going to
calculate the world units of a click?
Well. our OnMouseDown method returns the pixel coordinates. We need
camera.ScreenToWorldPoint(). That's the method we're going to use!
So. let's take a look at how we're going to use that method to
make the translation. back
over in the Defender Spawner Script. Next.
thing we want to do is inquery this Input.mousePosition
thing. Let's find out what the mouse
position of where we're clicking or tapping
is. So. Input.mouse
Position returns the pixel coordinates
of where we've clicked. So. let's take a look at that. in practice.
instead of printing ("clicked"). let's just print
(Input.mousePosition)
I'm fighting a little bit here with
MonoDevelop's Autocomplete. but eventually I will prevail. and I
will type mousePosition! Fantastic! OK. so
print (Input.mousePosition); What do we get? Let's click around and take a look!
Cool! So. inside the square we're getting pixels numbers. that
seem feasible: 200 by something. 0 .of course.
on the end. That's because there's no Z coordinate of the mouse. It doesn't make sense
to the 2D mouse. And if we click outside the box. we get
nothing. so that is all kind of checking out! The question
now becomes. how do we actually get the world units. that we need to
work in? You may ask. by the way. how about if we did all
of this on a World Space Object. like a quad or a
plane. Well. you'd still have the same issue. because Input.mousePosition
will still return you pixel coordinates. So. the fact
we've done this on a UI Element doesn't really make much difference. We just have to
set a collider. of the appropriate size. So. what we want to happen is.
when we click this cactus guy. for instance. we want him to spawn in the
center of the nearest square.
So. how are we going to do that? We're going to use
camera.ScreenToWorldPoint(). That's the method
that translates the coordinates from
pixels into world points. but we're using an
orthographic camera. so perspective doesn't matter.
There is no perspective. and the distance from the camera doesn't
matter either. So. let's take a look at that!
If we go into our scene
and pop it into 3D View for a moment.
you can actually see the camera.
I'm just going to move the scene around a little bit. so I can get to the point where we can get
a camera and see that it's orthographic. I know those lines look like they're
diverging or converging down onto a vanishing point.
but that's only because the space is 3D. They're actually parallel lines;
you can see that when we switch the camera to Perspective. Now.
you see what a Perspective Camera looks like. Very very divergent
lines right. So. it doesn't matter how far we
are from a 2D space. With an Orthographic
Camera. it doesn't matter how far away the camera is. Wherever we
click. there's a one to one correspondence between where we click
and the world unit under our mouse. Does that make
sense to you? So. you click right in the center. it's always going to be
in the center. So. we have to provide the camera. because the
method requires it. but it doesn't matter what the distance is.
That's what I mean by distance from camera unimportant. Only
because we're using a single camera. and we're using a
Orthographic Camera.
So. how are we going to do that? Well.
take a look back in your script for
a moment. and let's start fleshing this out.
We're going to need a method that returns a Vector2.
which is your
world coordinates. And what are we going to call this method? Well.
let's give it a nice long descriptive name. Something like Calculate
WorldPoint
OfMouseClick ()
Pretty long right! And it's going to be responsible for finding out where the mouse
clicked and returning a Vector2 of world position.
Fantastic! So. that's the vector 2 it's returning there.
So. when this is working properly.
if you were to print the result
of that method. CalculateWorldPointOfMouseClick (). immediately after your
mouse position. then what we would hope to
see is the world point. So. let's just get the structure
setup for you. before I put you into the challenge!
I'm just going to return a flat Vector2
(0. 0); for the moment. just to prove the point
and make sure you're clear on what you need to be doing. So.
if we look now in the log. when you click Console.
when you click around... OK. the Console is collapsed. so you need to
turn collapse off. When you click around you're seeing pixel coordinates.
and then. immediately afterwards you are seeing world
units. on the next line. That's what we want. but of course we want the
real world units to be showing. not these
funny (0.0) that I've created here.
OK. So. here's a challenge for you! What I want you to do is actually
make that method. that is going to make that translation
for you. I want you to flesh out the body of the translation.
so that. for example. if you were to click on the lizard
there. then you would get a result back of
whatever his world coordinates are. 9. 3
I believe. Alright. instead of 0. 0.
So. that's what I want you to do! Create the
body of that method. You've got the signature! You've got the code that's going to
call it. you just need to make it work.
Cool! So. how did you get on with that? I'm going to
show you my approach to it! So. we're going to build up this
world space world point Vector2. in
bits. because C# likes us to do it that way. You've
seen that a lot before. when we were constructing vectors. So. float
mouseX. the mouse position in X. It's just Input
.mousePosition.x;
OK. so then float mouseY. Can you guess
what I'm going to type? That's Input.mousePosition.
...million dollar question.
.y; Right! OK! So. now we've pulled off the X and the Y
value into independent floats
of the mouse. So. what do we need now? This funny
camera.ScreenToWorldPoint method needs
a distance from camera. so let's give it one. Let's keep it happy! distanceFrom
Camera. There. another float. I'm just going to say 10. It's a reasonable number.
compared to our play-space. As I said. and distance doesn't matter.
So now. we're going to construct ourselves a
Vector3. because this method needs a Vector3.
It's a weird Vector3. and that's why I'm calling it a weird
Triplet. It's a weirdTriplet
because the first part of the triplet is an X coordinate.
It's a new Vector3 with mouseX.
The second part os a Y coordinate. pretty standard right.
So. let's put that in.
mouseY.
there we go! And then. the third part is a distance
from camera. Now. in our case. it happens to be a Z
coordinate. because our play-space is laid out in X and Y.
but in general. we could have tilted
our play-space completely differently. in 3 dimensions. So. it's not always
an actual Z coordinate. it's a kind of weird triplet.
It's an X. Y. comma distance from camera.
So. I'm just going to call it weird triplet. just to kind of
ring alarm bells. OK. so we've formed this weird
Triplet. that the method needs. So. let's make our
world point Vector2. the thing we're actually going to spit
out act the end of this method. myCamera!
We don't have myCamera yet. I know so shoot me. This is kind of
wishful coding here. We wish we had a myCamera. we're going to sort that out
later. The disadvantage of not having it of course is that it's
that Autocomplete doesn't work at this point. but that's OK. we'll
confidently type .ScreenToWorldPoint. pass it it's (weird
Triplet). And then. before we go any farther.
let's look at the Unity docs. by clicking on it and
clicking Control or Command and apostrophe. and see what
we mean by weirdTriplet. It takes an X. Y. and then this
distance from camera. So that's the weird triplet. and you can read all
about it at camera.ScreenToWorldPoint. if you're having trouble getting to sleep.
So. we're going to need to. of course. get
hold of the camera in question. So. how are we going to do that? Let's publicly expose
ourselves a camera. and we're going to call it
myCamera;
And in doing so. the code down on the bottom will no longer be
red. or course. because it recognizes that. and finally. we
need to return this world position.
OK. let's try running! Oh. it's moaning! Why
is it moaning? Let's take a look! I'm getting an error
at the bottom there. It's nothing to do with my collider.
Oh. hang on! I'm saying new! I shouldn't be
returning a new worldPosition. we've already constructed the worldPosition.
We just need to return what we've already made. Perfect! Great!
So. no errors now! Now. let's click away and see
what actually happens. once we've associated the camera.
Don't forget to drag your Game Camera onto
your DefenderSpawner Script and apply back to the
prefab. if you want to make sure you keep it. Now. let's click! Wow. that was lucky!
I hit 9. 3 on the first click! But if you watch the Console carefully
you'll find. as you click around. you're actually getting correct
world units. being logged out translated
from your pixel units. As I say. I was very lucky in the beginning
to hit exactly the middle of that square. but in general this is
working. The only thing that we're not quite doing yet is rounding
this figure. So. to finish off. all we're going to
need to do now is write a method that rounds
the numbers. so that what we get out at the end is
precisely on grid.
So. back in our
code. let's set you up for the challenge. Let's go log
crazy. and let's have a wishful method here that's
called SnapToGrid. OK.
So. I'm going to ask you to write this method in a minute.
The signature is this: Vector2
SnapToGrid. and it takes in
what? Well. it takes in a Vector2 and I'm going to call it raw
Position or rawWorldPosition. to be
even more explicit. So. it takes in a rawWorldPosition.
and it's going to return you
a new Vector2.
I literally put the word new in there! See
that was crazy. I literally typed what I said! It's good that
code is that close to English. that it's almost what you say but hey.
return new Vector2
and then. it's going to be some new X coordinate.
which I'll just put in there for you. And new Y
coordinate. OK. The question is.
how do we calculate that? How do we do the rounding? It's relatively
simple. and then. one you actually call (SnapToGrid)
on the...
Well. let's just wrap it around this method. We're not scared of
nested functions. Let's do this! Let's do SnapToGrid
on CalculateWorldPointOf
MouseClick (). Hopefully that makes sense to you. You're going to. Calculate
WorldPointOfMouseClick. will spit out a raw world point
without rounding. Like with 3.2.
4.3 or whatever. and then when we put that into the Snap
ToGrid method. we'll get a rounded value out hopefully. if
you write your SnapToGrid method properly. Alright. so
I'm going to make no apologies for nesting two methods. like this. I
personally don't like to see it. it's a little bit weird. but
you are going to see nested functions. when you go on the web and you start looking
at documentation. So deal with it. basically. [Laughs]
So. I want you to write the rest of SnapToGrid. Here's the slide for
the challenge for you. Write the method with this
signature. Round to the nearest whole-number. and by the way.
there's a method called Mathf.RoundToInt (). Check it out!
Cool! Welcome back! Let's make this guy work! Well. it's not too
tricky. I've given you loads of hints. We've got float
and then newX = what? Well. it's
Mathf.
roundToInt. And what are we going to take in?
If I can type straight. we're going to take in
rawWorldPosition. that we've got in here.
dot the X coordinate right. So. we take in the X coordinate and round it.
What are we going to do for the Y? I think it's
pretty clear that we use the same line of code with Y's in it
right. Cool! And we just returned that!
So. we take in a world point. say 3.2.
RoundToInt goes 3.2. you mean 3
friend. and newX becomes 3 and then so on for the Y.
So. that should do it! Let's try it. even with this funny nested
method thing. Let's try and see what happens!
We click here and however we try.
we cannot now get a nasty set of coordinates out
right. So. I get 1.0. 1.0. 1.0. until I get to the boundary. Then. I get 2.0. 1.0. Then. I get
3.0. 1.0. Awesome! We are nearly
there! Let's finish this off strong! What we need to do is just
actually instantiate our dude. for want
of a better word at this point. So look. we're so close!
OnMouseDown we already have practically everything
we need. So. remember our helpful static over
on Button? We have Button.selectedDefender;
That's pretty handy right! Button.selectedDefender.
That's a GameObject! So. can't we just go
Instantiate (Button.
selectedDefender. but
where? Where are we going to instantiate it? Well.
we've got that haven't we? That was the
actual world point. that we want to instantiate.
Now. you can do it all in one line. if you want. You can go
SnapToGrid
and then you can pass into SnapToGrid.
etc.. but I'm not going to do that. I'm going to break it down. So.
where do we want to instante this guy? We
want to instantie him at. just some
position right. or just call it pause if you want. But how do we
make pause up? Well. like this!
Vector2 is good enough for this!
pos =...
Well. why don't I say rawPos to start with? The
rawPos is the CalculateWorldPoint
OfMouseClick right. So. that's the raw position.
And then. we're going to have a new Vector2. rounded...
...pos. and that just simply = SnapToGrid
(rawPos); And then. we're going
to instantiate at roundedPos. Let's try it!
Yeah. le't see what happens!
Click play!
So. I've
obviously not looked at the docs for instantiate recently. so let's pop
into that and have a look and see what we get! If
you see it's two signatures. you either instantiate the object
and don't tell it the position. or if you're going to tell it the position. it wants
to know the roation as well. So. we're just going to use Quaternion
.Identity. which just means default rotation. no
rotation. So. it's just going to want that OK. so just bear that in
mind.
OK. let's try this!
We run here! Firstly.
if I click and I've not selected anything. the prefab you want to instantiate
is null and it's an error. It's OK. just about. We might want to handle
that better later. But look. cool! Let me see if I can
instantiate two on the same place. I can't! Why can't I?
Because these guys have got colliders
on them that are blocking the play-space below.
So. that is working a treat right.
Now. you may say. why are they blocking? How do you know they are blocking? What are the
Z depths doing? Well. if you're not sure and you want to be
sure. then go to the 3D View.
look at the Z depth of your Core
Game. it's just sitting there. and then. look at the Z depth
of the actual things that
you instantiate. So. you need to stick on a couple of
guys. pause the game. and then go and look at these
guys these gnomes. So. they should be
neatly here. And what is their Z depth?
Their Z depth is 0. What's the Z depth of
the Core Game canvas? Well. it actually also is
0. but the blocking is working fine. In
fact. if you look here. at the gnomes
they even though
they have a Z transform of 0. they are
still appearing in a different space to the Level
Canvas. because the Level Canvas' Master Transform
here is at Z = 1. in the
background. So. that's why they are actually sitting in front.
Just in case you're wondring. But that's it!
Here we go! We can click any of these guys and instantiate them.
We can't instantiate outside. they only land on the square. We can't double
instantiate. And look at that. we have made
what I would call significant progress. apart from
look at the mess we're making. You know I keep telling you about tyding
or keeping your Hierarchy tidy. Look at this disgusting mess! So.
what are we going to do about that? Well. you're going to do that.
exactly the same way as we did before. Exactly the same
pattern as we did here. over in shooter. We're just
going to call it defenderParent OK. So. I'm just going to
say that when we spawn defenders. let's take all
that code from the other guy. So. let's rename projectileParent
to defenderParent;
Or if we find ourselves doing this sort of thing.
why not just call it parent. at the end of the day.
The context will tell us everything else. but we do need
to name this ("Defenders").
and we can't use the rename
tool here. because it's a string.
It doesn't know how these strings related OK. So.
now if you were to come into here and start instantiating things.
it should be childed into defender.
but of course. we haven't yet told it to be childed into defenders.
Where do we do that? Immediately after we instantiate. we need
to child it to something. so we need to capture the GameObject.
So. Button.selectedDefender. What type is that? It's a GamebObject.
So. I'm just going to say object
for now. or defender.
OK. so I'm just going to replace this with defender. just to make the line
shorter. and I'm also
going to change
this Quaternion.identity. What type is that? Well. it's actually a
Quaternion. it's a unit of rotation. So. Quaternion
= Quaternion.identity.
And let's give it a name! Let's call it zero
Rotation.
Rot. I want to keep it short. The whole purpose of this is to keep the line short
and to give you some reinforcement on what the types of
these things are. So. now that we've got the line down to
that length. we can capture what we're doing. GameObject
newDefender.
Call it newDef = that. and then. we have to
because GameObject. Instantiate is going to return rather an
object. We need to cast it as GameObject. like that!
Now finally. after all that messing around. we can say newDef
.transform.parent
= parent; OK.
so all that messing around was just to try and get that line to fit on my screen.
So. a bit crazy but a bit of fun for you! So.
here we go! Let's just make sure it works. that the spawning works!
And of course. the problem is we don't mean parent. we mean parents transform.
So try that!
And let's take a look! Put some guys
down. Look they're all going into a defender's object. and if we collapse that
defender's object down. then our Hierarchy stays completely
sane. as all the projectiles are spawned in here and the defenders are spawned
in there. Perfect congratulations! Great job
on getting this far. and see you soon!