Hi welcome back! So, in this video
we're going to place our enemy spawners.
Decide how spawning of enemies is going to be controlled.
A bit of a word about the Flow Channel, that'll all come clear.
And write scripts to control the spawning.
So, what are our options, firstly, for controlling how
the spawning works. And what do I mean by spawning? Well,
what I mean by spawning, of course, is these enemies that appear
from the right hand side. They need to start appearing
automatically. We obviously cannot place... Well, we
could place them all at design time, that is one of the options.
But it would also seem there are other options,
for getting these enemies to come in from the right hand side.
So, one option actually would be to simply,
at design time, zoom out here for example,
and to go to our Attacker Prefabs
and to predesign the
layout of these enemies, by literally laying
them out, all to the right hand side of the screen. This is a valid
way of doing it, and you could store that information in the scene,
and then, what would happen is, when you hit play,
if you zoom out you'll see what's happening. The enemies will be coming
in from the right hand side, in a way that is hidden to the players. They don't know what's
coming next, but it's completely pre-organized. That
is a perfectly valid way of doing things. And if we look at our
slideshow, that is option one Manually Planned.
It gives you the most control, but it
can be very time consuming to do, and you may miss some interesting
ideas, some interesting patterns that
may come from more random or more procedurally generated
spawning. So, another option is
row two, Random Stroke Procedural At design-time.
So, what we could do is, we could write some scripts to
maybe even layout these guys on the right hand
side here, and then, to play test and see how
it's going. And then, maybe delete some and say well, actually that fox there comes
at an annoying time, so we'll delete that
one and, you know what, add a couple more in. So, this is a
semi-manual process, whereby you use a computer to help
you create, either random or semi-randomly, generated
patterns and then, you modify them. So, the
con of that is, it takes more time to do than runtime,
Or you could do Random Stroke Procedural at runtime. By the way, if you're
wondering what the difference between random and procedural is,
in simple terms random is not repeatable. You don't know
what you're going to get next time, whereas procedural is potentially
repeatable and can lead to much more intricate patterns.
If you want to find out more about procedural, look at Brice's Procedural
Generation course. Anyway, of you do it at runtime, it's very quick
and easy to setup, and it can help replay-ability because
the player never knows what they're going to get. Even the designer doesn't know what they're going to get.
Disadvantage, well it can lead to impossible play. You could
get a series of enemies that's not possible to defend against. It's much harder
to play tune, much harder to tweak the parameters
so that the game is just right, in the sweet spot, which we'll talk
about in a minute. And it can also be seen as less consistent
or unfair, if you've got a high score maybe you just got an easy run of enemies.
So, there's another option. That's, I think, the option we're going to
choose here, though, because it's the easiest to setup. And
then Adaptive, that would keep the player in the flow. Much harder to
implement, of course, but it would keep him in the flow. Briefly, what do I
mean by flow? So, let's just go back to the slide with this link.
If by the way, when you go to this link this Indie Dev
Stories blog article, it's not there for any reason, then
it's attached to this lecture under resources as a .pdf
for you. So, in this
blog it talks in detail, or they talk in detail about the flow channel.
Basically, it's matching the player's skill to their challenges, so as
they get better at the game, you need to challenge them more. And there are lots of ways of
doing that. One is introducing more difficult things to
do, more enemy types, more
defender types, etc., but there's also the idea that you could
actually up the ante according to how they're playing at the moment
adaptively. You could say well if they're playing really well, let's
spawn faster. If they're playing badly, let's spawn less faster. Anyway
lots of ideas there for you, and the basic point is here,
that there's not just one way to do it. There are several ways, possibly more than
there are on this table. We'd like you to try all sorts of
different ways for yourself. So, for simplicity, we
are going to just randomly spawn. So, I'm going to take away my Lizards
and my Foxes. All of them actually, in this case. I'm going to keep
the Attackers placeholder.
In fact, I'm even going to delete the Attackers placeholder, because
we're going to produce that Attackers placeholder,
in exactly the same way as we did in the defenders, just
by looking for it. OK, so let's just get this done quite quickly. What I want you
to do is create an empty GameObject called Spawner
or Spawners, because there's going to be
more than one of them. Transform at the origin, just like the buttons have a
transform at the origin. The Button placeholder does, but the buttons themselves
also are placed in the scene. That's fine! Now, we're going to create the
first spawner, so that's going to be childed to Spawners.
I'm going to number my Spawners by lane,
and so I'm just going to call this guy Lane 1. We've only got 5 lanes,
and Lane 1 is going to be at X equals
12, just off to the side of the play-space. And Y equals
1, and that's why it's Lane 1, because Y equals 1.
So, that gives us a very basic Spawner
Prefab. It's just a GameObject. We might as well
prefab it already, so rather than calling it Lane 1,
there the prefab, it's actually a Spawner.
And the benefit of this, of course, is if I now start dropping
the other four Spawners in, then any change we make to them,
provided we make those changes to the prefab, or apply those
changes to the prefabs we are all good. So, it's up to you
if you name them Spawner 1, Spawner 2, Lane 1, Lane 2,
or you just call them Spawner and maybe use the vertical position
in the Hierarchy to distinguish them. That's a perfectly valid way of
doing it, in which the bottom Spawner here would be
Lane 1 Spawner, and then, the next one up we would move to Lane 2.
That was lucky, on then Y coordinate! And then, the next
one up we'll move to Lane 3.
I'm going to need to use the Inspector for that one and so on. So, you get
the idea! They're laid out in the Hierarchy exactly the same as they are in the scene.
Nice and easy to see, there's another option for you, so
either way it works. I'm going to do it this way, because it's quick and easy!
Quick and dirty! And
Lane number 5. OK! So, I have 5
just points here, where I can spawn from.
So, a word on controlling
spawning. What is responsible for deciding
how often, on average, the enemy
is spawned? Is it going to be the enemy themselves, like the
attacker, or is it going to be a private variable
or public variable on the Spawner?
Well, either works right! If you put it on the Spawner
then each Spawner can have a different Spawn rate, but it's a bit more complicated
to make different attackers spawn at different rates.
I'm going to go for modifying the attacker, myself,
and give it a method called
seenEverySeconds. So, it's like how rare is
this fox? It's seen every 10 seconds on average, type of thing.
Alright, so that's actually per lane, or
depending on how we code it in the other side. So, what I want to do is
just simply go into the Attacker Script and
give attackers another property, and
it's going to be a float and I can put it alongside currentSpeed actually
and it can be seenEvery
Seconds, so it's quite clear what that is.
And that's it really.
If you want to tell the designer
a bit more about what this means, then you could use a Tool Tip.
To use a Tool Tip, you'd need to put that on another line,
so you would go private
float and then seenEverySeconds;
And then, if you put this annotation above, (Tooltip)
("Average number
of seconds between
appearances");
And we can leave whether that's per lane or overall
for the moment, until we decide how we do the Attacker Script. So, you
close your square brackets. And that Tooltip, look what it does! Pretty handy!
If we now go into the game, and we
look at one of our Attacker Prefabs now. Of course, because we've modified
the script we should, in a moment, get this.
We need to, of course, make this public.
There you go! We need to make the float every seconds
public, so let's just let the script percolate through.
Here it is, Seen EverySeconds! And if you hover your mouse over it,
look average number of seconds between appearances. Fantastic!
So, you could say that the Lizard is seen every 5 seconds,
for example, and the Fox is a bit more rare and is only seen every
10. And then, you can have each prefab
can have it's own kind of rarity value. Cool! Well, let's use that! So,
you've learned about Tooltips there, that's the format! Square brackets and
round brackets inside, and it pops up when you hover in the Inspector.
Fantastic! O.K. So, in a moment, we're going to need you
to do something, and what I'm going to want you to
do is to write a Spawn() method,
with this signature:
void Spawn (GameObject myGameObject).
And it's going to parent whatever you spawn to
the Spawner in question and test that it works. So, you've got your
Spawners. You just need to make a method that spawns
Game Objects at that point.
Don't worry about spawning them according to their spawn
rates yet, we're going to write a second method for that. So, just spawn
them every frame,
for example. Just get them spawning for now. Let's go ahead and do that!
OK, so how do we even make them spawn at all, before
we worry about getting the spawn rates exactly right.
So, you've seen this quite a few times now, this is
definitely not the first time you've seen spawning working, so
let's just get on and get it done!
Over in Unity, we take one of the Spawners, we add a new
script to it, and I'm just going to call it
Spawner. Deep hey! [Laughs]
OK. Goes untidy. I'm going to put the blinking
script in the blinking Script Folder. [Laughs] OK
there it goes! So, let's take a look at
this Spawner Script. What are we going to do with it? How
is this going to work? Well, the way that I'm going to do it is, I'm going to
take in an array of things that it can spawn, so I'm going to have
a public GameObject[] array called
attackerPrefab
Array; like that. So, that is all
the things that spawn point can spawn. So, if we look at this Spawner,
apply it back to the prefab, so that all of the
Spawners have this code on it.
We have an Attacker Prefab Array. Now, if I make
that of size 2, look what we get! We get
tell me two things I can spawn. Well, this lane
can spawn foxes and lizards. Now, the benefit of this
approach, of course, is that each lane can spawn it's own subset of attackers,
when you have more attackers. But I'm going to have this lane spawn
foxes and lizards, and actually, if I apply that back to the prefab all of the
lanes are going to spawn both foxes and lizards. Well, they
will when we write the code right. So, that's good! So, I've got an Attacker
Prefab Array! Now, the pattern I'm going to use is
the following. We don't need the Start () method. I don't see any need
for that right now. But every frame, what are we going to do? Well, I'm going to say
foreach. I love the foreach method, it just reads nicely.
foreach (GameObject myGameObject
in attackerPrefabArray) So, for
each of those attackers, in our case we've got two,
if... And I'm going to write a wishful method, for the moment.
if (isTimeToSpawn that reads nicely
right. If it's time to spawn (myGameObject)
this particular attacker...
Actually that's a
good name isn't it? thisAttacker, let's rename it!
There you go! foreach (GameObject this Attacker
in attackerPrefabArray), if it's time to spawn this attacker,
then Spawn
(thisAttacker);
Cool! Alright, so
we've got a couple of hopeful methods in there. Wishful methods,
whatever you want to call it. Neither of them exists yet, so lets
just write out my methods, firstly, the isTimeToSpawn().
Well, I said we could spawn every frame for now, so this isTimeToSpawn
is a bool, isTimeTo
Spawn. Now, you matey not have structured your code like this, you may have done it all inside
Update. That's fine! I'm just showing you a different way of
approaching this. OK, and isTimeToSpawn
will take in a (GameObject
and it will be an attacker
GameObject); It's important to keep track
of the types of these things, it is a GameObject. I'm just going to return
true; for now. We'll worry about getting that working properly later.
So, every time this is going to evaluate to true, so every frame, every
update it's just going to spawn. So, how is it going to spawn? That was your challenge
right, was to make yourself a Spawner
function. So, Spawn()
(GameObject myGameObject) was the pattern I gave you. So, void returns
nothing Spawn (GameObject
myGameObject) So, pretty general
spawning and parenting function. How is that going to work? Well,
GameObject = myEnemy...
Sorry, GameObject myEnemy or myAttacker
or thisAttacker again,
but we don't want to reuse the same thing. It's a bit confusing.
Is Instantiate myGame
Object, whatever I've passed in as a GameObject we have to cast it
to a GameObject. So, whatever we pass into Spawn we instantiate,
and then, we go myAttacker
.transform.parent
= what? What are we going to parent it to?
Well, just ourselves actually, just our own transform, because we're
going to parent ourselves to the Spawner. While we're parenting to the Spawner
but not the Defenders' projectiles to the
Defenders. It's because we destroy Defenders and
we don't want all of their projectiles to get destroyed, when we destroy defenders.
We're not going to be destroying
Spawners, so we do want a transform parent to Spawners.
Alright, so the other thing we need to do is just spawn at the
position, so it's just a question of myAttacker
.transform.position and then that just
equals what? = transform.position;
OK, so we say parent to the Spawner and parent
spawn at the Spawner. Let's give that a crack! Pretty simple
three line method, with a lot of wrapping around it!
We should end up with a lot of
guys coming now! Wow!
What's happening?
OK, I'll tell you what's happening! What's happening is they're being
spawned, but they're being spawned inside the Shredder.
OK, interesting hey! Interesting little bug that you can
get there! So, I'm going to move my Shredder over to the right.
And in fact, I'm going to be a little bit precise about where my
Shredder is. Let's put it at 16 and make it 3 wide.
So, if
the center of the Shredder is at position 16 and
it's 3 units wide, then 13
must be the left hand edge of the Shredder. So then,
are the Spawners clear of that? They are! So, let's try spawning
again. We'll get a very different result. That's better!
Now, we're getting an absolute ton, but at least they're being
chilled to the appropriate Spawners and you could
collapse down your whole Spawner Hierarchy and just get a crazy number
of enemies. Fantastic! So, congratulations on getting that far!
Now, what we need to do is tame the spawn rate, and guess
what? That is your job. We've already written the outline for the method.
I want you to complete the isTimeToSpawn method.
Return true, if it's time to spawn this frame,
return false if not, and as a bonus, log
a warning, based on "frame-rate cap". You'll find, when you write
this method, if you write it anything like Brice did in Laser Defender or
or in any kind of sensible way, you'll realize the the fastest
you can spawn in a simple method is the current
frame-rate. Now, generally that's not going to be a problem, but it's nice to catch the error.
That's a bonus but if nothing else, get it spawning
as often as your enemies
are set to spawn, so my fox, every five seconds
of... whatever it was. And
the way I tested this, when I set this up
in the first place, was to take out a stop watch. That's my Android phone
on the right. And I left it running for what? That's over half
an hour, and at the end, I looked at the log. So,
you may want to log out every time you spawn a lizard or fox,
and I could calculate that the spawn rates were as a set them.
So, in that instance, I set spawn rates
1 every 1 second and every 5 seconds on an average. That
agreed to within two significant figures or within 1%. So, you
may want to get a stop watch, leave it half an hour, and make sure it works. So,
there's your challenge! Get the different types of enemies
spawning at different rates and test it.
Awesome! So, let's get this finished off
then! Not too tricky! This isTimeToSpawn method, you just
gotta get your head around it. In fact, it's not too tricky at all!
So, obviously we don't want to just return true, that's kind of
rubbish. What we want to do is something along these
lines. Firstly, we need the
Attacker off the GameObject we pass in, so
Attacker attacker =
whatever we passed in, attackerGameObject
.GetComponent
&lt;Attacker&gt;(); And remember GetComponent
is a method. Cool! So, we've got the Attacker off it! Now what?
So, float meanSpawnDelay
I'm going to call this, is
attacker. and then what did we call it?
seenEverySeconds; So, we spawn this
guy in this lane, every second,
as often as this thing is seen. So, it's just playing
around with variable names
right. I'm just trying to make the math clear. So,
float spawnsPerSecond
= 1 divided by the meanSpawnDelay.
So, if the meanSpawnDelay is half a second,
then the spawnsPerSecond is what? 1 divided by a half,
which is 2. If the meanSpawnDelay is 2 seconds,
and the spawnsPerSecond is a half. Does that make sense?
OK, so if (Time.deltaTime, i.e.
how long this frame took, is
greater than the meanSpawnDelay)...
Yeah, so if this frame, which is typically going to be in tiny fractions of a second,
if it's greater than the SpawnDelay, so you've got a frame
of I don't know 1 second, because the game is frozen
to a whole but you're trying to spawn every half a second, but we've got a problem.
So, let's Debug.LogWarning. Just a warning,
it's not the end of the world, but I'm going to say something like ("Spawn
rate capped by frame rate");
You may want to pause the video and think about why that's the case.
Basically, you can't spawn any faster than the frame
rate, if you're spawning from inside the Update function. You can
but this current pattern won't do it. OK, otherwise
just go ahead without worrying about what could go wrong.
Actually, sorry...
It is else but for simplicity, rather than putting
else and then a big indented block, I'm just going to come outside this if
and start another piece of code, if that makes sense. We don't want to
work in indentation. So, let's create a new float called
threshold. And it's the spawnsPer
Second times
Time.deltaTime;
So, this is
just normalizing. It's just a threshold that says
if this value is above 1, then we spawn.
If it's below 1, we don't spawn. It's just a 1 threshold,
because then we can use if (Random.value,
which just produces a random number between 0 and 1.
Is less than threshold)
Then, you
return true;
else you return false; Now, there's a more compact
way of writing that, actually. You could just say
return (Random.value less than threshold), but I don't think that's
very clear to read, so I'm going to write it this way.
OK.
So, have a think about that! There are other ways to do it. You could certainly
write it in a lot lot less lines, but it may not be as clear to read.
Hopefully to you, it's clear to read what's going on and how
the math works. So, let's just test it works now!
Now, I haven't put a Debug.Log
item in here, but let's see
if this is working. What did we set on our Fox?
We said there should be a fox seen every 10 seconds.
Is that about right, on average? Per lane,
yes! What that means, of course, because there's five lanes
we're seeing about a fox every 2 seconds. That's right!
And then, the lizard, we are seeing every
5 seconds. seenEverySeconds... It really should be seenEvery
Seconds per lane, or to keep
everything else simple and keep it very simple, we just come in here,
and say well,
let's divide this threshold by 5
because we have 5 lanes. So, that's another reason
to have like a threshold intermediate variable. And now,
when you play, we're seeing lizards
about every 5 seconds
and foxes about every 10 seconds.
Now, of course, you'd need to run for a long time and count your lizards
and foxes, in the Console, or just
leave them in the scene. They'll all end up on the left hand side, and that
would prove it works. But that's it! The spawning is working how
we planned it! So, a final look at the code, make sure it's clear there.
The details of isTimeToSpawn and
Spawn don't necessarily matter, once you trust
them. This is the crux isn't it? void Update () foreach (GameObject
if it's time to spawn it, spawn it. Simple right!
It reads nice! isTimeToSpawn is quite long,
but still should be clear.
OK congratulations! We are spawning nicely!
See you soon!