So now. let's turn our attention to the Star
Trophy! We have a Star Trophy and they
have an Animator. but we have not at all finished
the way that this works. So currently. the way I've got it setup is it's
staying in the Idle State forever. and I have this grow
trigger. Considering maybe there was some script that was
going to call that. Let's do it a different way. Let's not have a grow trigger. we
don't really need a grow trigger. You can only remove
that. by the way. when you're not in Play Mode. And what I'm going to
do is. I'm going to say there's a transition from Idle to Star
Grow. after a certain number of
transitions. So. this will be where you encode how often
your sun producer or your star
producer actually produces stars. So. I'm going to say after 10 seconds
we go into Star Grow. and then.
Star Grow will finish and return to Idle.
after a single iteration.
after one cycle. Ok. and it's a
Atomic. it has to finish. So. let's just look at that
in operation. Let's put some
star trophies down in the scene. and watch their Animator.
It's going to cycle around
a few times. before then producing a star.
we can adjust this later. which then disappears. pops off. and
then it goes back to its Idle State. Alright. so
that's cool! Then. what I want to be able to do
is. at the end of the Star Grow. I want to call
a defender method. because this is a defender.
I want to call a defender method called
Add Stars and actually add stars to
some sort of global scoreboard. So. let's
make that possible. I'm going to lay your foundations for you.
And then. I'm going to ask you to write an entire class.
which is going to be called SunDisplay.cs. and that'll be the
first entire class you've made on your own. So Defender.cs.
it's no longer only being used as a tag. it's finally
going to actually do something. and the first thing I need it to
do is have a method called public void
AddStars. And
that's going to take an amount of stars that are being added.
Alright.
like so. Fantastic! And then. having that
method. even it it doesn't do anything yet. means that of course over in the Animator.
when we look at the prefab
for the Star Trophy
and its animation...
There's the Star Trophy there. In its
Trophy Grow state...
And actually I've spelled Trophy Grow wrong there.
That's OK. At the end of the Trophy Grow.
what we want to do is to have an event that actually
calls this Add Stars method.
So. why can I not add an event at the moment?
Because I don't have any instance in here to
practice on. So. what we need to do is pop an instance into
the scene temporarily. Now. we can add our event
flag. put it at the end just when the star finish
is growing. and we're going to add stars. How many?
Let's say 10. So. that's
going to call the Add Stars method. when the star gets to the
end of its animation. While I'm here I'm going to
fix up the spelling of this trophy. So. if I can just find
my Defender
Animations. in the Animations Folder.
And we have Trophy Grow missing an O!
We can fix that.
And you may want to go to the script and pop a log entry in. just
to say print. Just for now. we'll just print the number
of stars. (amount);
Alright. let's try all this! Let's make sure that when we run the game.
have the Console open and place a Star Trophy
down. like the one we've already got in the scene and maybe a second
one. Here we go!
Ten. you see it's being added when the star bursts.
Burst. 10. great! So.
that's happening! Let's get rid of the instantiated star trophies. so that they all
get instantiated run time.
And we have that bit done. So.
that's fantastic! Now. the Animator is calling into
AddStars on the Defender and getting it to actually add
stars. but we've got a lot more work to do to make this work.
in a nice way where the Model. the Viewer. and the
Controller are separated. It's called the MVC
Pattern. If you want to read more about the MVC Patter. well then
just type MVC. I always like the world wiki. because it
gets me to Wikipedia. and you can read about Model-View-Controller.
It's the idea of separating responsibility for
updating displays. keeping data. etc. We're basically
starting to follow an MVC pattern here.
So. I want a score display. That's a relatively
simple thing to put into place. We've got a Canvas already.
and inside that Canvas let's create ourselves a UI
Text Element.
There it is! And it's going to be Stars.
And here it is. I'm just going to move it.
up at the top.
focus in on it. get into the UI Editor Tool.
and just pop it right here. right next to everything
else. I'm going to vertically and
centrally. Ooh. vertically and centrally! Vertically and horizontally
center my text! I'm going to make the text
yellow. to represent the fact that this is
counting the number of stars.
I need it to be fully saturated for that to work.
There you go! That's just
fine! Wack up the Font Size a little bit.
Try putting in a four digit
number. I think is about as many as we're ever going to get.
There you go! That's fine! Adjust the Font Size for a four digit number...
... and that is just fine! So. we have a Stars component there.
I'm going to re-prefab the Level Canvas. so this stays with it.
in the future. There we go! The stars
have gone blue. and there is a Text component
sitting on there. So. what we now
are going to need is some sort of controller for this. to control
what's actually displayed. So. I'm going to add a script to the text element.
and I'm going to call it Star
Display.
And let's take a look at this StarDisplay Script.
OK. it's blank at the moment.
I'm only going to write one method. and then. you are gong to have to sort the
rest out. OK. so I'm just going to write the one
that receives the stars being added.
So. this is void AddStars. and yes. another
AddStars method. We need it in here as well. because remember
you can only call Defender scripts from the Animator.
And for now. we're just going to say print
Stars
(" stars
added to display")
They've not been added to the display yet.
but at least we know we're getting here. So.
let's look at the whole architecture. right. We have a Star
Display here. You're going to be writing the rest of this class. It
is going to go off and find this Text Element
here and be responsible for updating
this actual Text Element.
The Defender Script is going to find this StarDisplay
and call it. so let's wire that up. Wire that up
for you. and then. you're going to be on your own. So.
here in the Defender we need to do something else. We're going to have a private
SunDisplay or StarDisplay.
called starDisplay;
like that. OK.
Then. on the Start of our Defender Script.
we're going to go find it. How do
we find it? We've done this a thousand times now.
starDisplay = GameObject.findobjectOfType
&lt;SunDisplay&gt;(); and there should only be
one of them.
So there you go. it's found the &lt;SunDisplay&gt;.
and then. instead of just printing Add stars. let's say
SunDisplay... Sorry.
I keep mixing Star and Sun. It's &lt;StarDisplay&gt;.
dot now.
where is it? Public void AddStars.
and in a moment I'm going to talk
you through this whole architecture
and just pass the (amount) through.
OK phew! So. you have the framework you need.
Let's recap this from the beginning. for you. OK.
I'm going to make sure my code runs.
Alright. I place down a star
producer. like this. It has an Animator on
it. When the Animator.
after however many cycles you set. transitions into Star Grow.
at the end of Star Grow
on the Star Trophy. we have a method
call here. which calls the
Defender Script and in the Defender Script you have a method
called AddStars. So. we pass an (amount) straight through
the Defender Script. to the StarDisplay
class. and it then receives
the message. and it's going to handle actually updating that Display Element.
So. let's just check that it works. in that. that log
actually makes it through. Let's put a few stars in.
Check the Console. The Animator
should be messaging Defender. which should pass that message straight on.
to the Display. Here you go! And you see them being logged.
Fantastic! So. that is the architecture
I've gone for here. and what I want you to do. as a
challenge. is to flesh out the entire class
of StarDisplay.cs.
Remember. you're going to require UnityEngine
.UI at the top. so we can access this
Text component that we created. Find the Text component
on Start(). Write an AddStars (int
amount) method. I've already started it.
but it wants to actually update the display. Write a
UseStars (int amount) method. which is going to subtract.
which we'll use later. And then. Update
the Text component. only when the above
are called. Not every frame. let's only Update the Text
when these methods are called. And if you get
all this done. you've written your first entire class from scratch.
apart from I've written a single line of Debug in it for you.
OK guys.
so let's get this Sun Display class written then.
It's relatively simple. I believe it's just
wiring things together. So. let's just take
it one step at a time. Firstly. for it to
even work. the Star Display. it's going to require a Text
Element. so it's a good habit to start getting yourself into now. of using this
RequireComponent annotation here.
And that makes sure. that at editor time. if there is no
component that is of type (Text). then it
will give an error. Why am I giving red here? Because of what I said.
we need the namespace UnityEngine.UI;
Now. it may be in a future version of Unity. like 5 or beyond
that that's not the case. but for the moment we still need to be
doing that. OK. on the Start. Well firstly.
what member variables do we need for the StarDisplay? I think it needs
two things. I think it needs private
Text
starDisplay or starText;
OK. so that is the actual text.
And then. it's also going to need a private int
stars. which is the
number of stars. and let's initialize it to 0. You might say
why don't we just use the Text Element itself. to store the number of stars?
Don't do that. Only use Text to
display stuff you're going to display on the screen. Don't
go and reach into the Text Element and convert its text into an integer
or something. No. let the class member variable
here keep track of how many stars there are.
in the StarDisplay. and then. we just do the translation
to text. never back from text. it's just bad practice.
So on Start. we're going to go and find this starText
OK. So. the starText =
GetComponent. Now. why not GameObject.? Why just Get
Component here?
Because. if you look over in Unity.
you'll see why. Let's just take a look.
Because remember. we're on the Stars object here. It
has a component called Text. of type Text.
so it's this component talking to this component.
Yeah. we're not looking for another GameObject
in the scene. like the Trophy or whatever. We're just looking for a component
on ourselves. so that's why we just say GetComponentText.
Great we've got the text! So. do we
do anything on Update? No. we don't do anything on Update. This
method is only being called when the text is
updated. so only when you add stars. So.
how do we actually add stars? Well. we don't need a Debug statement.
We'll find out if it works by whether the display changes.
stars +=
amount;
simple enough. Then. some wishful method called UpdateDisplay.
There it is! OK. we'll make Update
Display in a moment. but just for now make the other
side of this method. which is the UseStars.
and it's just a -=.
Fantastic! So. how does Update
Display work? Well. it can be private. only this method needs to call it.
We want it to be private. we don't want any other methods updating the Display.
We just want methods saying. to the StarDisplay. add them or remove
them. If there's another API. another way that you can talk to
the Star Display. well then write some public methods.
void UpdateDisplay
So. what's in the Update Display method? Well.
we simply go starDisplay
or starText. in our case
.text. which is the actual text in it.
=stars.ToString();
Remember. stars in an integer. The .ToString(); will change the integer
that's stored in stars. the member variable. change it to a string
and set the actual yellow starText to it.
Wicked! OK. let's see if it works!
Remember. we're only creating stars.
we're not using them at the moment. Now. this says 9999.
because that's how I left it in the Inspector. I'm hoping
that on the first production of a star. it'll go to 0
or 10 rather. because it goes straight to 10. Perfect!
It's working and as they burst they're adding. So. the
last thing I need to do is. go to this actual Stars Element. set its default text
to 0.
and we are working! Fantastic!
Congratulations if you created that entire class on your own! It is
now... We now have Sun Currency to spend!
So. next it's going to be. let's make these things cost something.
because right now it's far too easy. Right. we can just keep putting defenders down
willy nilly. We need to have a cost to the defenders. so
that's what's coming up next. See you soon!