So welcome back! As you can see.
we have no way of losing right now apart from clicking
this button down here. Our attackers. rather. are
just disappearing off the left of the screen and completely
taking over our Garden. our life. without
any regard. So. we need a simple lose condition
and handling. So. let's go ahead and do that! What we're going to do in this video
is. number one. remove the Lose Test
Button or the Lose Condition Button. We are going to
create a lose collider. setup lose triggering and
transition. into the next level
or the Lose Level at least 30b lose.
and improve the Lose Screen itself. I've got a couple of gripes with it.
Now look. before we go on and I start showing
you how to do this. I would like you to consider stopping the video
now even and doing this entire video on your own.
because you've done lose colliders before I
think you can do all of this. So. if you feel ready. stop the
video now. and get the whole automatic loading
of the Lose Screen organized. If you don't
feel ready. keep watching and you'll have a smaller challenge midway
through this video. OK.
so whether or not you're still watching. I'm going to show you how I'm thinking of
doing it. So. here's our scene. We already have
something very similar. I always think. do we already have something
in the game that we could copy. to save ourselves time? Well. we kind of
do. There's our shredder. you see it on the right hand side here.
It has practically everything we need. a Box Collider and
well a Box Collider. So. I'm going to duplicate it.
in this case. just as an example. I'm going to leave it
as it is and just call it a Lose Collider.
I'm going to give it a different script.
so I'm going to remove that Shredder Script. because clearly it's not a shredder.
and I'm going to give it a new script
called Lose Collider.
I normally call my scripts the same thing as the
object. because it's the behavior of the object. It needs to be moved
across. across to the left hand side. I'm going to use the red arrow.
because it'll take it to the right place. and I think that if they've got
about there we've lost right. If they
get that far we're done for.
Why leave it this thick? Don't have to but being
that wide means. if they were traveling really fast. there's not chance of them
passing through it on a single frame. because if you do have a frame
here and then a frame here. then you'll never detect the lose condition.
Cool! So. we have a Lose Collider Script! Let's take a look
at that Lose Collider Script.
Now. it's a trigger. so the method that I need to call.
when the lose condition actually happens. is
OnTriggerEnter2D. So. let's
just make sure that happens. and set you up with the peripheral
information you're going to need and then we'll set you
straight into the challenge. So. void OnTriggerEnter.
Now. you have to spell
these properly. because you get no Autocomplete on these messages.
Now. do we need to gather any information from what you're
colliding with? Not in this case. so I can actually leave no parameters.
and I can prove this is working by just...
I'm just going to say lose. actually.
So. I'm just going to check this works. before we
throw you into the challenge. Tidy up the script.
and then. get to the lose
condition. Let the defenders arrive on the left hand
side. Make sure we get a log entry saying. lose condition.
Then. at least we know
that method is being called here.
and then. I'm going to challenge you to finish this off.
So. I'm going to
grab this dude and help him along his way.
If I can. if I can get to him in time. It's going to be quicker to wait. You
can move the transform of things. while they are actually moving.
If you want to by the way. you could grab a lizard and drag him
across. Lose Collider. to my eye that Lose Collider trigger went
off before he hit the Lose Collider.
So. I need to just check the position of that Lose Collider.
Maybe it didn't? Maybe that was just
my imagination? I'm going to assume it was my imagination
and carry on! So. here's your challenge for this
video then! You need to. in the Lose Collider.cs
class. find the LevelManager by script would be better
than dragging it in. So. use a private LevelManager Level Manager.
Then. go ahead and find it in the Start.
Use the OnTriggerEnter2D method to detect the loss
condition. and then. call Level
Manager.LoadLevel on the ("03b Lose"); level.
and make sure that it actually works. that you can actually lose the game.
So. go ahead. pause the video. and do that
now!
How long do I wait? [Laugh] That'll do! You're back!
Fantastic! So. let's make this guy happen! Let's get into this
Lose Collider Script here!
So. I said we needed LevelManager. but want to do it in
script. so I wire it together in script like this: private LevelManager
levelManager. So. it's of type LevelManager. it's called levelManager.
with a small l. On the Start. we go and find it.
This is becoming very wrote. we do this a a lot. GameObject.Find
ObjectOfType. Not Objects
but Object. There's only one of them in this level. I hope there is.
There you go! It's a method. so it needs the squigglies.
then semicolon. Fantastic! We're not going to do anything on Update.
on this. So. all we're going to do here
is levelManager
.Loadlevel. And we need to
give it a name. Now. we need to make sure we did the name properly.
I think it's ("03b_Lose"). but I'm going to go check that string
value. because anything that's a string is not going
to get changed by the Refactor Tool if we ever
use it. So. this is a little bit dangerous. in a way.
because if you decided to rename your level. the lose condition won't
work. So. what we might want to do is check the docs
for LoadLevel. and see if it's going to tell us
why return...
It doesn't tell us whether it's successful or not. by return.
So. if you wanted to put a catch condition in here
you would need to say. if there's a
level loading or write some script around this to say.
if I call ("03b Lose") and it doesn't exist. maybe I want to
report an error. I'm not going to bother with that for now. I'm just going to
check that 03b is the correct scene
name. But do understand that if your designer came in and
innocently changed the ("03b Lose") to something else.
that this piece of script will fall over. and it's an exercise
for the reader to guard against that. if you want to.
by simply seeing whether the level was loaded or not.
But I'm going to leave it at this. Let's try and see how that
goes. I'd like to keep this video brief. partly because I want to go to lunch and partly
because you've had a lot of long videos lately. So. let's
see what happens when Mr. Fox gets to the left hand side.
They're really fast. these foxes! This game is going to be
mental compared to Plants Versus Zombies! OK.
so what's happening here is. we don't actually have a Level
Manager in the scene at all. If we remind ourselves that the
Splash Screen does have a Level Manager on it. it's a prefab.
you can see it's blue and it's autoloading the next
level. after three seconds. The Start Scene.
while we do not persist the LevelManager from the
Splash Screen to the Start Scene. let's see it not persisting.
There's the Splash Screen with it's LevelManager! We end up in Start.
and there is no LevelManager in here and yet we can change level. How come?
The reason we can change level in this scene is.
if we look at it. the UI buttons that do all the level
changing. like the Play Game Button is
connected to the LevelManager Prefab. You see it there?
If we click that little Explore Icon.
under the OnClick event of the button. you see it's
connected to the LevelManager Prefab. so the prefab is always available.
So. what we haven't done yet. simply because we haven't
needed to. is in our level 2 here in our actual
level. or level 1 rather. there is no LevelManager Prefab.
We need to drop it in and that's fine. because we're likely
to need to drop all of these things in. when we create a new level.
So. give yourself a LevelManager. that's going to help!
Not autoloading on the next level. and now. when
we look for a LevelManager. in this scene. it should exist. Let's
see what happens! Here you go. the Console is logging Level
Manager (LevelManager).
It's telling us that Level Autoload is disabled. Good!
And the game wouldn't be much fun. if we were autoloading.
And now. the enemies come in. and I'm confident that now
that we've found the LevelManager. that we will actually get
the behavior that we want. Please
I want to go for lunch!
There he goes. you lose! Fantastic!
So. the final thing to do here is. I just don't like the look of that
Lose Scene. The only thing that jars me on it
is that the Start and the Quit is...
Firstly. I don't want to say Start. I think I want to say Start Again.
which means I need to use the UI Tool to make
my text a little wider.
There we go! And then. I want it to just be lower.
And I will just say
Lose! You Moose is crazy! A bit of
fur for a while. wasn't it? But "You Lose!"
OK. so "You Lose!". "Start Again".
and "Quit". nice and clear. Fine. I've made all the changes
I need to make. so hopefully you managed to do this whole
video on your own! It's relatively simple. Just as a quick
recap. all we did here is we
didn't touch the LevelManager. actually. We didn't change the LevelManager at all.
we just went and found it in the LoseCollider.
well made space for it. I declared it at the top.
found it in the Start. I don't need to print it anymore.
and then we simply call loadlevel  on (03b)
lose. nice and simple. So congratulations
and I shall see you soon!
=======
So welcome back! As you can see,
we have no way of losing right now apart from clicking
this button down here. Our attackers, rather, are
just disappearing off the left of the screen and completely
taking over our Garden, our life, without
any regard. So, we need a simple lose condition
and handling. So, let's go ahead and do that! What we're going to do in this video
is, number one, remove the Lose Test
Button or the Lose Condition Button. We are going to
create a lose collider, setup lose triggering and
transition, into the next level
or the Lose Level at least 30b lose,
and improve the Lose Screen itself. I've got a couple of gripes with it.
Now look, before we go on and I start showing
you how to do this, I would like you to consider stopping the video
now even and doing this entire video on your own,
because you've done lose colliders before I
think you can do all of this. So, if you feel ready, stop the
video now, and get the whole automatic loading
of the Lose Screen organized. If you don't
feel ready, keep watching and you'll have a smaller challenge midway
through this video. OK,
so whether or not you're still watching, I'm going to show you how I'm thinking of
doing it. So, here's our scene. We already have
something very similar. I always think, do we already have something
in the game that we could copy, to save ourselves time? Well, we kind of
do. There's our shredder, you see it on the right hand side here.
It has practically everything we need, a Box Collider and
well a Box Collider. So, I'm going to duplicate it,
in this case, just as an example. I'm going to leave it
as it is and just call it a Lose Collider.
I'm going to give it a different script,
so I'm going to remove that Shredder Script, because clearly it's not a shredder,
and I'm going to give it a new script
called Lose Collider.
I normally call my scripts the same thing as the
object, because it's the behavior of the object. It needs to be moved
across, across to the left hand side. I'm going to use the red arrow,
because it'll take it to the right place, and I think that if they've got
about there we've lost right. If they
get that far we're done for.
Why leave it this thick? Don't have to but being
that wide means, if they were traveling really fast, there's not chance of them
passing through it on a single frame, because if you do have a frame
here and then a frame here, then you'll never detect the lose condition.
Cool! So, we have a Lose Collider Script! Let's take a look
at that Lose Collider Script.
Now, it's a trigger, so the method that I need to call,
when the lose condition actually happens, is
OnTriggerEnter2D. So, let's
just make sure that happens, and set you up with the peripheral
information you're going to need and then we'll set you
straight into the challenge. So, void OnTriggerEnter.
Now, you have to spell
these properly, because you get no Autocomplete on these messages.
Now, do we need to gather any information from what you're
colliding with? Not in this case, so I can actually leave no parameters,
and I can prove this is working by just...
I'm just going to say lose, actually.
So, I'm just going to check this works, before we
throw you into the challenge. Tidy up the script,
and then, get to the lose
condition. Let the defenders arrive on the left hand
side. Make sure we get a log entry saying, lose condition.
Then, at least we know
that method is being called here,
and then, I'm going to challenge you to finish this off.
So, I'm going to
grab this dude and help him along his way.
If I can, if I can get to him in time. It's going to be quicker to wait. You
can move the transform of things, while they are actually moving.
If you want to by the way, you could grab a lizard and drag him
across. Lose Collider, to my eye that Lose Collider trigger went
off before he hit the Lose Collider.
So, I need to just check the position of that Lose Collider.
Maybe it didn't? Maybe that was just
my imagination? I'm going to assume it was my imagination
and carry on! So, here's your challenge for this
video then! You need to, in the Lose Collider.cs
class, find the LevelManager by script would be better
than dragging it in. So, use a private LevelManager Level Manager.
Then, go ahead and find it in the Start.
Use the OnTriggerEnter2D method to detect the loss
condition, and then, call Level
Manager.LoadLevel on the ("03b Lose"); level,
and make sure that it actually works, that you can actually lose the game.
So, go ahead, pause the video, and do that
now!
How long do I wait? [Laugh] That'll do! You're back!
Fantastic! So, let's make this guy happen! Let's get into this
Lose Collider Script here!
So, I said we needed LevelManager, but want to do it in
script, so I wire it together in script like this: private LevelManager
levelManager. So, it's of type LevelManager, it's called levelManager,
with a small l. On the Start, we go and find it.
This is becoming very wrote, we do this a a lot. GameObject.Find
ObjectOfType. Not Objects
but Object. There's only one of them in this level, I hope there is.
There you go! It's a method, so it needs the squigglies,
then semicolon. Fantastic! We're not going to do anything on Update,
on this. So, all we're going to do here
is levelManager
.Loadlevel. And we need to
give it a name. Now, we need to make sure we did the name properly.
I think it's ("03b_Lose"), but I'm going to go check that string
value, because anything that's a string is not going
to get changed by the Refactor Tool if we ever
use it. So, this is a little bit dangerous, in a way,
because if you decided to rename your level, the lose condition won't
work. So, what we might want to do is check the docs
for LoadLevel, and see if it's going to tell us
why return...
It doesn't tell us whether it's successful or not, by return.
So, if you wanted to put a catch condition in here
you would need to say, if there's a
level loading or write some script around this to say,
if I call ("03b Lose") and it doesn't exist, maybe I want to
report an error. I'm not going to bother with that for now, I'm just going to
check that 03b is the correct scene
name. But do understand that if your designer came in and
innocently changed the ("03b Lose") to something else,
that this piece of script will fall over, and it's an exercise
for the reader to guard against that, if you want to,
by simply seeing whether the level was loaded or not.
But I'm going to leave it at this. Let's try and see how that
goes. I'd like to keep this video brief, partly because I want to go to lunch and partly
because you've had a lot of long videos lately. So, let's
see what happens when Mr. Fox gets to the left hand side.
They're really fast, these foxes! This game is going to be
mental compared to Plants Versus Zombies! OK,
so what's happening here is, we don't actually have a Level
Manager in the scene at all. If we remind ourselves that the
Splash Screen does have a Level Manager on it, it's a prefab,
you can see it's blue and it's autoloading the next
level, after three seconds. The Start Scene,
while we do not persist the LevelManager from the
Splash Screen to the Start Scene, let's see it not persisting.
There's the Splash Screen with it's LevelManager! We end up in Start,
and there is no LevelManager in here and yet we can change level. How come?
The reason we can change level in this scene is,
if we look at it, the UI buttons that do all the level
changing, like the Play Game Button is
connected to the LevelManager Prefab. You see it there?
If we click that little Explore Icon,
under the OnClick event of the button, you see it's
connected to the LevelManager Prefab, so the prefab is always available.
So, what we haven't done yet, simply because we haven't
needed to, is in our level 2 here in our actual
level, or level 1 rather, there is no LevelManager Prefab.
We need to drop it in and that's fine, because we're likely
to need to drop all of these things in, when we create a new level.
So, give yourself a LevelManager, that's going to help!
Not autoloading on the next level, and now, when
we look for a LevelManager, in this scene, it should exist. Let's
see what happens! Here you go, the Console is logging Level
Manager (LevelManager).
It's telling us that Level Autoload is disabled. Good!
And the game wouldn't be much fun, if we were autoloading.
And now, the enemies come in, and I'm confident that now
that we've found the LevelManager, that we will actually get
the behavior that we want. Please
I want to go for lunch!
There he goes, you lose! Fantastic!
So, the final thing to do here is, I just don't like the look of that
Lose Scene. The only thing that jars me on it
is that the Start and the Quit is...
Firstly, I don't want to say Start, I think I want to say Start Again,
which means I need to use the UI Tool to make
my text a little wider.
There we go! And then, I want it to just be lower.
And I will just say
Lose! You Moose is crazy! A bit of
fur for a while, wasn't it? But "You Lose!"
OK, so "You Lose!", "Start Again",
and "Quit", nice and clear. Fine, I've made all the changes
I need to make, so hopefully you managed to do this whole
video on your own! It's relatively simple. Just as a quick
recap, all we did here is we
didn't touch the LevelManager, actually. We didn't change the LevelManager at all,
we just went and found it in the LoseCollider,
well made space for it. I declared it at the top,
found it in the Start, I don't need to print it anymore,
and then we simply call loadlevel  on (03b)
lose, nice and simple. So congratulations
and I shall see you soon!
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1:Unity/Section7/GG40 Handle Lose Condition.srt