Hi and welcome back! In this video. we're going to do a lot of
tidy up. We're going to make a quick change to the logic in the
Spawner.cs file. We're going to adjust the
colliders. so that our attackers actually hit our defenders.
We're going to fix the gravestone animation
transitions. so that they are in their under attack state.
at the right times. And then. we're going to make sure that all our
work is properly prefabbed. so we can create other levels.
So. first thing is to look at this
Spawner.cs Script and see what is up
with it. Nothing wrong
with it. it works. but look at the logic at the bottom here. I
ought to be sent to code prison for writing that. because all of
that can be written in a single line. Can you see what the single line could
be? Well. this return
true. we're never going to reach return true right. because
these two are jointly exhaustive. It's tempting to say
mutually exclusive. but I get told off by philosophers when I say that.
So. they're jointly exhaustive. between them they cover everything.
but this return true is completely unnecessary. Also. you'll
notice that this thing in brackets. either evaluates to
true or false. so why don't we just return it.
Return. I like to use brackets. You don't have to but I prefer to.
for my logic statement. and just need a semicolon.
How's that? return
Random.value is less than threshold.
It may not read quite as clear. but it's certainly a lot more
compact. and I wanted to give you this option where you just return something
that evaluates to a Boolean. Let's make sure it works. before
I get too excited about my new plan. Always check your plan.
because it may seem like a cunning plan. at the time. but may not
work. So. I've lost so quickly
because of the game time. So. I'm going to change my
game time. right now. into Level Canvas. onto your
slider. Now. I don't think slider is a good name. I think it's not
descriptive enough. Something like Game Timer would make
more sense. so I'm renaming my Slider object to
Game Timer. I'm also going to. on its script.
change the default time for this level.
because it's far far too short. So. where's the script?
Here it is! Level Seconds. and I'm going to go for 100 seconds.
Now. we're going to have a sensible time. So. let's just check
nothings broken.
Let's keep going!
So. hopefully we are now continuing
to record. and I'm just playing to make sure stuff is working.
So. we have a countdown timer. counting down
here. and hopefully. in a moment. some
spawning is going to happen. Here we go! This is just check that. that code
changer made to the Spawner. And we've go the parenting. and everything is working
hunky dory! Fantastic! On to the slide. let's
see what the next thing to do is. Adjust
the colliders. so attackers hit defenders. Right.
very true. If we look at the game. as it is.
and we place down some stones. for
example. Now. they're not working! My Defender Prefab Button is not
assigned. so let me just fix my buttons. It's simply
a question that the buttons do not have the
appropriate prefabs linked to them. The Gnome here is just missing
the Gnome. so let's connect to the Gnome.
The Stone is probably missing the Stone. I don't know when
these got disconnected. but if you see something like that. just reconnect
it. And then. for future. let's also make sure
that we have it prefabbed right. There's your Star
Trophy! So. all the buttons. it would make sense to prefab
the buttons. Now. some time I created a Buttons Folder. but we've never used it.
So. I'm going to delete the Buttons Folder under Prefabs.
and just prefabs the button's
GameObject. which will then come with a bunch of Sub-objects.
so they're all blue now. Eventually. we want to prefab practically everything.
See the Level Canvas. for example. that's not
prefabbed either. There is a prefab for it.
but it's disconnected. because it's black. so let's
delete the Level Canvas Prefab and re-prefab
our Level Canvas. This is better. I want practically
everything to be blue. I don't
need my placeholder Defenders and Spawners. that are created at run time.
to be blue. but everything else I pretty much
want blue. Fantastic! So. let's see if it works now and get onto this
issue of... Yeah that's cool!
Just going to check all my Defenders.
Fantastic! So. what I want to do is wait till somebody comes along and hits this
gravestone. and make sure they're actually colliding with
the gravestone. The gravestone animation is wrong. at the moment. That's
because it's animation state is just not correct right
now. It is
just sitting in the Under Attack state. but we'll deal with that in a minute.
For now. what I'm interested in is. if we were to pause and look
at this lizard up here. we will find
that he's not quite touching the gravestone.
In fact. he's doing quite a good job. right now.
Yeah. he's doing an OK job! Let's take a look at our lizards.
And his
collider and let's look at the gravestone as well.
So. there's the gravestone's collider
and then. here is the lizard's collider and then there's the
lizard behind him. Let's see what happens when this lizard behind comes in.
He stops there. you see. That's
the problem. he's stopping short because of his collider. So.
all we need to do is move the lizard's collider. So. stop the
game. go to your prefab.
in my case. and just make sure that for all your
characters. their colliders lead
to a believable sort of behavior. I know it's going to be about a
third of a block across. just from I.
So. let's just check that this guy appropriately
stops. when he get to the... Yeah. he
does. but he chews the back of it and I prefer that he chews the front
of it. So. we simply bring the lizard.
on his body the sprite itself. we
take the Order in Layer to 2. And now. the lizard will be in
front of the stone. So. let's just check that the lizard.
impacting the stone. looks good now!
There he is! And if we look at it. in the Scene View. we can see he's
actually making contact with the stone and making it wobble.
As extra credit. you might want to add a particle effect or something like that.
Fantastic! Now. let's sort out the third thing on
our list. which is that the... I'm going to
check the list. [Laughs] Yeah. the gravestone animation transitions. We need to make
sure that they are working properly. So. what's up with this gravestone
right now? It's complete rubbish right now.
So. let's have a gravestone. in the scene.
and inspect it and look at its Animator. Now. what's going on
with this particular gravestone? It's in the Under Attack state. all the
time. Why? Well. in my case. it's because I just got
my transition logic wrong. I've got Is Attacking False.
is taking me to Is Attacking. which is around the wrong way.
But actually. I don't want to be using a ball here at all. I'm going to want
to use a trigger. So. the general architecture
is going to be as follows. When the
attacker hits the defender's collider.
it's going to continually call the OnTriggerStay2D
message. While that's happening. I
want to keep pushing a trigger into the Attack state. In fact. I'm going to
swap Idle and Attack around. So. all the time the collision is happening.
I want this transition to happen. from Idle to Attack.
and then. I want it to automatically. at the
end of the current Attack animation. go back to Idle.
And of course. if we continue to push it. because the collisions keep happening
or stay in Attack until a collision stops happening.
So. how do we make all that work? We're going to remove the
Is Attacking parameter
altogether and add a trigger.
And I'm going to call it under
Attack trigger. I like to use the word trigger. so it's really clear
in the Inspector down here. in the Parameter Inspector. that it's a trigger
because it looks just like a Bool.
And what I want to happen is. Idle is the default state. that
is the orange. I want to go into Under Attack based
on the trigger. but I want to come out based on a single
cycle. an exit time of one loop.
and I leave both of these transitions as Atomic. so
the animation is complete. We can test it. actually.
before we go and wire up the code.
like this. In fact. the code may fail. Let's just look.
The code is OK. which slightly surprises me.
because I thought that we called that already but maybe we didn't.
So. place yourself a defender down
and inspect it. and of course. it's
not working. Why not? Why does it keep going
into this Under Attack state?
Good question! Maybe the code has actually renamed itself.
Let's go and look at the script. for the stone
and see what we've got. Absolutely nothing. so it's not
the stone. So. before we code anything. we need to work
out why this guy is
flitting between states. Even though in his
Animator we have a Default state here and a Transition
condition of the Under Attack trigger. is not true right now.
If I set it to True. it stays in Idle.
See that's a bit weird.
it's doing the inverse to what you'd expect.
So. let's
Reset this condition. in case there's some bug.
Idle is the default state.
It would change to the Under Attack state. when the
trigger happens. presumably when it's true.
and then. it will come back after one cycle.
That all sounds sensible. So. what I need to do is go to Mono
and I need to do a search
to Find in Files. here.
and I'm going to look for Under Attack.
in the whole solution.
And it's not there. so it's not code doing this.
So. let's just look again.
There you go! It's behaving now! Just some
weird bug. So. I had to just cycle the transition
in the Animator. So. if I now turn that on.
it goes into that state. but it comes off
again. But the OnTriggerStay would have the effect of what I'm
doing. It'll keep clicking on Attack Trigger and it should work. So. let's
go and give it a go! Into the Stone Script.
and it's no longer only being used as a
tag. wer'e actually going to put some behavior in the Stone Script. And
you can see it coming. can't you? I'm not going to show you how to do this bit.
OK. so here's your challenge. Write the Stone.cs
Script. When the Attacker is actually colliding
with the Defender. I want you to continuously set the Under Attacker trigger.
You're going to need to find the Animator. of course.
Ensure the projectiles don't trigger this.
Check the animation transition happens
as expected. And
here's a hint: Use OnTriggerStay2D ().
So. that's the message you're going to want to intercept.
inside the Stone.cs. So. have a go at that now! And
see if you can get it so that. when foxes
jump over the stones or lizards meet the stones in my game.
the stone starts wobbling. and when
they're no longer under attack. they stand still. or whatever
the equivalent is in your game. Fantastic! So. how are we
going to make this happen? One of the first things
we're going to need is a private access to an
Animator.
And as we've done many a time.
we need to go find that Animator. which should be relatively simple.
Well. now where is the Animator? We're on the Stone.
What method do I use to find the Animator?
Well. if we look at a Stone Prefab.
the script that we're writing is at the same level.
it's on the same GameObject as the Animator. so it's a Get
Component call we need here.
Of type Animator.
method. end line. OK cool! So. we
have access to an Animator. Now. it's a question of the
logic. What is the logic by which we decide
what state we need to be in? So. it's going to be done every frame. We're going
to need to query. every single frame. And then. how are we going to
do it? Well. we've done this before. When did we do it before? I
believe it was for the projectiles. They need to decide
what they're banging into right.
Let's take a look at the Projectile Script. Here we go! And in fact. it's
exactly this line. where we say Attacker
attacker = collider.gameObject.GetComponent&lt;Attacker&gt;();
So. these two lines are pretty much exactly
what are going to want
to have working. alright. It's just that we're going to be using OnTrigger
Stay. rather than OnTriggerEnter. So.
let's get the body of it
there. Instead of OnTriggerEnter it's OnTriggerStay2D.
So. all the time that the collision is happening.
we find whether or not it's an attacker. We
say. if it's an (attacker). otherwise it would be null.
Then. what are we going to do? Well. we go animator.set
Trigger. Remember. this only takes one parameter.
and it's called ("underAttack
trigger"); Now. is that spelling
perfect? Let's go over to Unity.
and let's check the
Prefab for the Defender.
So. Animator. underAttack trigger.
If you're not sure. copy and paste it. Make sure you
don't get it wrong right. OK.
so if it's an attacker we're collding with. then set
the trigger. otherwise do nothing.
Maybe that alone would do it? Let's try!
Let's place some defenders.
Yes. some defenders! A whole line of the stones.
Watch this guy. he's shaking! Awesome! And this guy is shaking!
Now. we just need to make sure that
when the stone dies that it disappears.
and also whether the fox triggers an attack.
Well. that's a game design decision. I don't really mind whether
the fox does or doesn't No. I need to stop this fox.
because otherwise. the game is going to end before we get to find out what
happens to our stones. I think the top stone should
die before anything else. because
it's being
chewed by at least two guys right now.
Come on stone! You can always just go...
When you're play testing like this. you can always just go in and artificially
remove their
health. You can just
reduce the health. OK. didn't really test anything. because the stone disappeared.
Everything is working fine. but our other question is.
what happens if the
attacker dies.
before the defender disappears? So. let's put
several guns in this lane. This is why I'm doing all of this before play tuning.
It would actually be difficult during play tuning. And
let's see what happens to this bottom stone here.
Does it? Yes. it stops! Perfect! Final thing. do these projectiles
trigger the stone? No! Why not? Well. because the code
just says. if it's an attacker. otherwise it never sets this trigger.
and then. then Animator is taking care of the rest.
OnTrigger it's going into the Attack state. After one animation
it comes back. but if we continually trigger this. it
appears to stay in the Attack state. So. that's it! We have completed
the challenge as we wanted.
basically. Fumbled mouth. So congratulations!
We've done all the tidy up that I want to do. at this stage. and the game is
basically working. We just need to play tune it. which is what's up
next. See you soon!