Hi. Sam here again. and I am going to be showing you how to upgrade
to Unity 5. in this lecture. for Glitch Garden.
But first.
a challenge! You guys should be fairly used to
upgrading. by this point. We've done it a couple of times. and I'd like you to have a go at doing it
yourself and doing the Web GL build and sharing all by yourself.
So. check your game in Unity 5. carefully. as usual.
and then. make a Web GL Build. all using the instructions
that we've done in the past. and share using Game Bucket.
OK. so pause the video and have a go at that. and if you get stuck. you can come back
and watch the solution.
OK. welcome back! We're going to dive in
and have a little play around and see what has changed.
what Unity 5 upgrade will do to change our Glitch Garden project.
So. you guys know the drill. We are going to open up Unity
5. and then. when we have this open.
we are going to go and find our Glitch Garden folder
and open that. And as usual.
we will be prompted to upgrade. and as you can see. it's
not warning us about changes to the API we're needing to backup and that's fine.
Basically. the code in Glitch Garden is ready to go as it
stands. It's ready to be upgraded to Unity 5. there's no API changes.
and so really it's not changing a whole lot.
We just have a few asset files that it will change
and so on. So. we'll see that in just a second. when we take a look
at the SourceTree for this project. So. in fact. let me just go amd
open up SourceTree now. and I'm going to
open up the Glitch Garden. which is what we have here. Just
make sure it is the right Glitch Garden folder.
Yes! And we can have a look
at the uncomitted changes. So. I'll bring the Unity over. As you can see.
it's on the blank scene at the moment. so if we go and
select our splash screen and hit play...
[Background Music Plays] There we go. we have our splashscreen sound. and
then. the game starts and we can select
our defenders and place them in. ready for
the attackers. which will soon be arriving. There
we go! As we can see. perfect! So. everything seems to be working
properly. Obviously. test it more thoroughly than that. before releasing it
with your own version. Let's go to Source
Tree and see what has changed. So
here. as you can see. it's mostly just the asset files and the Project
Version.txt. as we have seen in the past. So. nothing
huge. no big changes here. So. what we can do is
head on back over into Unity and go into our build.
And I'll bring it over from the other screen.
WebGL and then we just hit
Build. As usual. we'll need to create our Build folder.
and give
this build a name
and hit Save. And then we have to wait
for the build to run. Once that is finished. we can zip that
up and uplaode it to Game Bucket or any other sharing service
that you're going to be using. And you cna share it on Facebook. we can share it in
the Q & A. etc. OK. so we'll leave it there and leave the
last few steps up to you and see you in the next video!
=======
Hi, Sam here again, and I am going to be showing you how to upgrade
to Unity 5, in this lecture, for Glitch Garden.
But first,
a challenge! You guys should be fairly used to
upgrading, by this point. We've done it a couple of times, and I'd like you to have a go at doing it
yourself and doing the Web GL build and sharing all by yourself.
So, check your game in Unity 5, carefully, as usual,
and then, make a Web GL Build, all using the instructions
that we've done in the past, and share using Game Bucket.
OK, so pause the video and have a go at that, and if you get stuck, you can come back
and watch the solution.
OK, welcome back! We're going to dive in
and have a little play around and see what has changed,
what Unity 5 upgrade will do to change our Glitch Garden project.
So, you guys know the drill. We are going to open up Unity
5, and then, when we have this open,
we are going to go and find our Glitch Garden folder
and open that. And as usual,
we will be prompted to upgrade, and as you can see, it's
not warning us about changes to the API we're needing to backup and that's fine.
Basically, the code in Glitch Garden is ready to go as it
stands. It's ready to be upgraded to Unity 5, there's no API changes,
and so really it's not changing a whole lot.
We just have a few asset files that it will change
and so on. So, we'll see that in just a second, when we take a look
at the SourceTree for this project. So, in fact, let me just go amd
open up SourceTree now, and I'm going to
open up the Glitch Garden, which is what we have here. Just
make sure it is the right Glitch Garden folder.
Yes! And we can have a look
at the uncomitted changes. So, I'll bring the Unity over. As you can see,
it's on the blank scene at the moment, so if we go and
select our splash screen and hit play...
[Background Music Plays] There we go, we have our splashscreen sound, and
then, the game starts and we can select
our defenders and place them in, ready for
the attackers, which will soon be arriving. There
we go! As we can see, perfect! So, everything seems to be working
properly. Obviously, test it more thoroughly than that, before releasing it
with your own version. Let's go to Source
Tree and see what has changed. So
here, as you can see, it's mostly just the asset files and the Project
Version.txt, as we have seen in the past. So, nothing
huge, no big changes here. So, what we can do is
head on back over into Unity and go into our build.
And I'll bring it over from the other screen,
WebGL and then we just hit
Build. As usual, we'll need to create our Build folder,
and give
this build a name
and hit Save. And then we have to wait
for the build to run. Once that is finished, we can zip that
up and uplaode it to Game Bucket or any other sharing service
that you're going to be using. And you cna share it on Facebook, we can share it in
the Q & A, etc. OK, so we'll leave it there and leave the
last few steps up to you and see you in the next video!
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1:Unity/Section7/GG48 Unity 5 & Web GL Sharing (Optional).srt