So you made it to the end of Glitch Garden
and congratulations! So. Brice. there's a summary of what they have
learned? So. you've learned lots of really cool stuff in Glitch Garden!
Firstly. you've gone through the animation framework. You know how to
animate positions. which we've learned previously. and
also use sprite animation in the Animator.
That's awesome. that lets you do lots of cool stuff for
your 2D games. You've also learned a lot more about structuring your
game. how to use different ways of putting components
together. how to refer back and forth between components inside your game.
So. lots of really cool coding stuff that you've learned
in Glitch Garden. So. what's the next action?
Ben. what should they be doing now with their new glitch game? Well. hopefully you've
already shared it on gamebucket.io. and all the people
on Udemy are going crazy about how cool your game is.
Hopefully you're going to go and find some other art assets. and if you're really ambitious
make your own art assets and really customize up the game.
We'd love you to make new animal types. new attacker
types. and new defender types as
well. Add them to the game. give them new types of behavior. Let's give
you a couple of ideas. We have a fox jumping over. Maybe we have something
that burrows under and you make an animation for that. Maybe you have a
whole new type of attacker. maybe somebody that can fire over.
Lots of different things. Have a look at Plants Versus Zombies for inspiration.
I'd love to see a land mine that
blows up people that walk over it. as a defense. as well
as a flying creature that can avoid the land mine. when you attack
with it. Awesome! There you go. two more ideas! So. really mix
it up. use the component architecture we've shown you. really make
this thing extendable and pretty cool! Hopefully you've already
deployed it to the web. I would like you to try and deploy it to mobile.
That's whatever suits you. so if you haven't got a Mac you're
going to be better off trying to deploy to Android. If you've got a Mac
Android or iOS. At least get it as far as the iOS Simulator.
if you can. if you have a Mac. If you
can't do either of those. or you don't have the development environment
setup where you don't want to. then check out the Unity Remote on
the app store. for both Apple and Android. and that's going to allow
you. with a bit of fiddling. to go in as we've shown you and
play from the editor straight to the phone. It kind of streams the game
to the phone. The frame rate is a bit low. the interactivity is not like a native app.
but it's a great way of previewing how your game is going to look. It's really important
actually. It's really important to test your game on the platform that you're going
to be running it on. It's very difficult sometimes to be in the simulator
on your PC and figure out really. is that how the
experience feels for the player. So. you've got the PC and you can click
with your mouse. but the experience isn't the same as when you've got it in your hand.
so try it out and have fun doing it. Absolutely. only one of the
things you immediately come up against is the size of this right. the end of your finger.
You may have to adjust buttons. adjust the UI Elements around buttons.
etc. Sausage finger. Sausage finger people.
This is the last 2D game that we're doing
in the course. then we're moving into 3D with Hyper
Paddle. and then beyond in other courses. So. thank you for
getting this far! It's an awesome job if you've got this far. especially
if you started from nothing. Wherever you started. Well done
and we'll see you soon! Bye.