Hey guys! So, in this video I'm going to give you an overview of
the development process. I'm going to talk about all the different
ways that we can do it, and then, we're going to go ahead
and ask you to decide how you want to take this section.
So, we'll build a diagram, looking something like this,
which will show you the options, and then, I will give you a
challenge. So, let's take a look at our
options for developing an multiplayer game, whether
or not you have one or two machines.
I'm going to draw two scenarios. This is if we only have
one PC available, and this is if we have
two PC's available. Now, I'm only talking about PC's here
to speed up the development. Of course, you can be testing to
the mobiles, as well. So, in one
PC, then what do we have as an option? So, here's your PC
sitting there, and let's just draw some little
triangly bits. There we go! And of course, one thing to remember is
that this, key see, has a keyboard,
keys, and a mouse. Let's just draw a little mouse
here, with a little cable going off into the PC.
OK. So, in this PC
we can of course run the Unity editor.
That's one thing we can run. And what can
we test? What could we test that against? Well,
we could actually test it against a build, that we've spat
out, a B for build, and then, you could have a stand alone
app, running on your PC, and then, you can have a two way
game between the build and Unity.
So, I hope that makes sense. What I'm talking about is, you literally
have the Unity Editor open, with your project.
So, I'm just going to open Ahoy Matey here, which has nothing
in it yet, because well we've done nothing.
And in one instance, you'd be playing in here and
in the other instance you'd have gone to build, and you'd
actually built yourself a stand alone version and that would run in another window.
Now, that works but hey it's not very convincing, because
you don't really know anything that's going over
the network, it's just going to something called local host. And secondly,
the major challenge is that the mouse and the keyboard are
plugged into the same machine, so
any movement you make of one character moves to the other. Indeed,
even if you want to go through the menu systems of one
of these games, the other will respond, and that creates us a real pain.
So, it's possible to do it that way, if you're really stuck for PC's,
but why not team up with a mate and go for the second
option, which is my two PC's option here. This is the one I'm going
to go for. I'm going to put it in green, to signify that it's
that I prefer. So, there are two different
machines; I'm going to be working on a Mac on
the left hand side. That's where I record the course and that we have
PC on my local area network,
on my LAN like that. OK, so they're connected together.
And then, of course, each one then has its own
mouse and let's say track pad, in the case of the Mac,
because they're super sophisticated, and in the case of clunky old
PC's then we have a horrible only fashioned mouse.
OK. I'm just being prejudice just for fun.
OK fantastic! So then, we have
a simpler, much simpler, way of doing things, but of course you need a
second computer, but it has the benefit that we have separate
control mouse and keyboard plugged into
each. Now, I'm actually going to use a remote control software, so I stay
on the Mac and I remote control the PC. What I'll be
doing is swiping across, like this, into a Windows environment.
So, this is Windows, remote controlled from
my Mac. You'll notice it's a bit fuzzy and
that's simply because the resolution of the screen over on the
PC is 720 p, and it's about as good as I can get
it. But it doesn't matter, it'll be actually a very easy way for you to
tell that I'm on the PC there and I'm on the Mac here.
OK, so that's the architecture, that's how we're going to be doing
things. You will be able to follow along, if you decide to
go to local builds. The only thing that you're going to need to notice,
that's going to be a little bit different, is that in the case
of a local build, when we talk about IP addresses,
let me just show you what happens. So, over here with a local
build, you address something called Local Host,
and you use that instead of
the IP address of the PC or the Mac.
So, when I'm doing things, my Mac for example,
will have an IP address of something like 192
.168.0.44 maybe.
And the PC may have an address of
192.168.0.
something else, OK. And they will need to be
setup inside Unity, so that you know what's
the Host or the Server and
what is the Client. We'll talk about the difference between a Host and a Server and a
Client, in a moment. But generally,
the PC will be set up as the client, as the person
playing the game, and the Mac will be set up, typically, as
a Host. Now, what a host is,
is basically, is if this is a box... Let me just give
you a different color to keep things a little bit separate. The
idea with the host is that it's both a Server and a Client, in the
same machine. So, if this is a Host here,
then it has both a Server
and a Client in it. So,
that means I can play the game on the Mac, and the Host Server runs on the
Mac, and then, the PC is acting purely as a Client.
Now, this is how you often play, when you do a multiplayer game with your friends.
You often setup as the Host, and that means you play the game
but you also host the game. So, that's the typical environment
we're going to be working in. And if you are going to
be doing things from different machines, instead of using Local Host,
you're going to be using the appropriate IP address, which would
depend on your machine, and I'll show you how to find all that out,
just in case you don't know. So, there's a brief overview
of how we're going to be doing things. We'll go through the course in the right hand
scenario, so that we don't have these Control System issues. If you've got just
one machine, then you're going to have to test against a Local
Build or possibly a Mobile Build.
So, here's another final option for you,
is you could go against a mobile of some
sort, so I'll just represent that like that. You
could go over Wifi, which I'll represent like
that, it's like a little Wifi symbol, to a
mobile, that is possible, it's still via the LAN.
OK. But I'm not going to be showing you all how to do this. I'm
going to assume that if you've got this far in the course, and you're pretty serious,
that you're going to be able to get hold of a second machine or you're going to be able to
team up with a friend or even go into the
course discussions and ask another student, if they
want to team up with you. And you could talk to them over Skype,
at the time of your arrangement, and actually arrange to
develop this together and to through the section together, possibly. So,
that is my challenge of you, in this video.
So, I want you to arrange your environment. See if you can
access a second machine locally. That's ideal! If not, ask in the
discussions for somebody to work with, and include your time zone
and some times that you could work. If not that, then consider building
to mobile, but I won't be showing you in detail how to do that. It just
slows the development down a little, and the worse case is, you build to a PC, Mac,
Linux stand alone, on the same machine, and you just have
to deal with the control system differences. Perhaps using W,
S, A, D, for one play, and I don't know I, J, K, L,
for another. So that's it! Arrange your environment, get in the
discussions, and tell us how you're going to be taking this multiplayer
section. Ask for other students, if you need to.
And I look forward to seeing you in the next lecture, where we'll crack on and
start making things work!