Hey hey! So now. we're going to be talking about deploying our game
locally. that is how to deploy the same version of the game
into two machines. Of course. you could use Version Control.
such as GIT or SVN. You could use a shared folder.
you could setup DropBox sync between two PC's.
That's what I'm going to be doing. I'm going to be using DropBox.
but the thing to remember is to be careful to just have
one master. We're going to make all our changes on one machine
or in just the Unity Editor. which will also be the Host
Machine. and then. we're going to push those changes either to
your Local Build or using one of the methods I just mentioned
over to the other machine. So. as a
quite summary of what I just said. this is what we're going to be doing in this video.
So. remembering this diagram from the
last section or the last video. we're going
to be using the right hand column. the two PC scenario.
but what we didn't talk about yet is how we're going to get the file
from the Host. the Mac. to
the PC. the Client in my case. You might be using a different
combination. of course. you might be using two Macs or two PC's or
whatever. But we're going to be developing on the Host Machine.
and then. we need to push a version of the game over to the
Client. that's exactly the same. so that all of the
resources and all of the assets. everything must match.
Just like when you're playing a multiplayer game with other people. you
need to make sure you have the same version of the game. So. I'm going to
talk about how we're going to do that! I'm opting
to use DropBox. but as I said
in the overview. there are other options. You could use Version
Control. such as GIT or SVN. etc.. and then. check
in and check out on the other machine. You could use a shared
folder or a network drive. but the important thing is
that you make all your changes on your master. the machine you're coding on.
which will also be the Host and then that you are
aware of when those changes propagate over to the Client
Machine. So. I'm going to use DropBox for this. so let's see
how I do that. So. here in Unity I'm going to quit. make sure
Unity is fully closed. before I go and move it's project folder.
Then. I'm going to go and find it's Project Folder. Now. in my case. that's
in Repos. UnityCourse. 11 Ahoy Matey.
There it is! OK. and I'm going to move that project folder.
simply move it into DropBox. So. there it is!
Now. it is in DropBox now. Ahoy Matey.
and it is syncing. If we look at the DropBox Sync Client. it says downloading
the files list and various other things.
but you can see that there's a logo here that suggests it's still syncing.
So. before I go over to the PC. I want to
check a setting. I want you to go into Preferences of DropBox. if you're using DropBox.
and just make sure under Network that LAN Sync is on.
on both machines both PC's both Macs. both machines.
because that will allow the files to not only
be sent up to the web but to be synced over the network.
Now. I actually have this under Version Control. all this stuff.
there is a GIT repository here as well. and it's not the best
idea to have a GIT repository also in DropBox but I've done some testing and
it seems to work fine. So. we're just using DropBox to get this
file from the PC here. and the Mac rather. over to the PC.
So here I am. on the PC! Ooh! Hah! Two sets of
Start Menus. let's try and get the PC Start Menu.
It's going to be tricky. this is going to be fun! OK. so there we
go! Maybe I'll put the PC's Menu along the side of the screen. for
future videos. You can see on the PC that the DropBox is still
syncing. Remember on your PC to check
the DropBox settings. to make sure that you actually have your
LAN Sync enabled on the PC as well.
So. that would be over here on a PC. if you're using DropBox
Preferences. and I'm not sure
where. Probably Band Width and then Enable LAN
Sync. There you go. that's the PC! Perfect! So. once this
is finished. we can have the project
open on both machines. So. I'm going to go to the Mac and just open
it on the Mac first. I've got a Game.unity file.
So you. as a minimum. need to just have an empty scene with
the name and that's what I want you to sync across.
So. I've got this thing called Game here.
And what I'm going to do is wait over on the PC for the DropBox
sync to finish. it shouldn't be very long. Then. open the project.
There you go. it's finished! Assets. Game.
and here comes Unity. opening up obediently
for us. and we see the same thing! Great!
So. we have the same file
on both machines. the same Unity Project. Let's try just adding something.
You don't necessarily need to follow along with this right now.
by the way. you can just watch me. I'm going to give you a challenge to do
all this. in just a moment or to catch up. So.
I'm going to put a cube at the origin. quite simply. in my
project over on my Host my Mac. I'm going to save it to the disk.
the little dot has gone away. I'm going to go back
to the PC and see what happens.
So. Unity is quite good at detecting
changes in the File System and actually updating the project.
So. if we watch over here in DropBox.
we should find that this syncs through
and changes. Let's see how DropBox is doing. OK.
there you go! Unity says "The open scene has been modified"
reload. And that's fine. there's our cube! You see
what I've done there? I've just added a cube on the Mac.. it is saved to the File
System. DropBox has synced it across. or you could use your shared
folder or you could make a commit. and here over on the
PC or my Client version. the cube has
appeared. So. what I want you to do now is. simply to make sure this is
all working for you. I want you to get your Client copy working. Setup your Client.
this can be a build or a different machine.
If you're going to do a build. then I'll show you that in the solution
briefly. And then. add a second cube to the scene and check that
this change propagates to the Client.
So go ahead. pause the video. and make sure you can propagate changes
to your Client version.
Cool! Welcome back! So. let's just check this. I'm very confident this
will work. so let's just add another cube. It can
be maybe at a position of. I don't know. maybe
two meters away three meters away? That'll do! As long
as I save to the disk and then go back to the PC and wait.
We're waiting firstly for the Host Machine. the
Mac in my case. to upload to DropBox. Now. it
doesn't have to get the file entirely to the web. because LAN
Sync is on. Hopefully it will come across the LAN quicker.
And then. in a moment. it'll arrive
on the PC. then Unity will go hey. something about this file
has changed. It's important that you don't change anything on the
Client version. we just do testing on the Client.
You do all you're coding over here. on the Host
Machine. that's really important! So there's a one way flow of
file information and game distribution. if you like. from the
Host to the Client. So.
is this going to notice the change? It should do it
in a moment.
Try playing. see if that knocks it
into noticing. No. So. if you're not sure. of course. you can check the
status of the DropBox sync here.
Here it is! I have ticks. I'm
not seeing any changes. So. this could... There you go!
So. I don't know whether looking at the file prompted it
to action or whether it was just time. I think it was just time!
Great! So. you may be better off using a shared folder. for example.
Well. that's another option for you. So. we're in sync.
that's fantastic! What's this business about working into a build?
Let's just try that! Let's make a build
and we'd add the current scene and it'd be a Mac PC Standalone.
for example. And I could make a folder
called Builds and I could call it Mac.
just Mac
or Ahoy Matey
Mac. There you go!
So. in this case. if you're going to be working to a
Local Build. then clearly
anything that you do when you do the build will
arrive in the build. right. So anything I've done to this
scene. after I've said build. will
go over to the Build Folder and work. So. if I now go and run this
Ahoy Matey Mac. at any resolution.
Then. I need to just get this on a different screen.
That'll be a second.
Let's try again! Ahoy Matey Mac.
Windowed.
and that allows me to bring this down. "made with Unity".
And of course. there is my scene.
only in Game View of course. So now. if you were to make
another change. over in your Host. like say delete this cube.
which I'm going to do anyways. so go ahead and delete your second
cube. Then. of course the way that
you get that to your Client. if you're using this way of working. is
simply Build & Run again. and then. you create
a new Client. without the cube.
Alright. which stands to reason. So then. your build goes away.
and when you rerun it
of course. the cube isn't there. which is
fairly obvious that if you rebuild the game without the cube. I just
want to make you realize that these two things are equivalent . I'm going
to be working Unity Editor to Unity Editor.
because that is much quicker and easier than constantly building. so I'll be
working from here. over to the PC. Talking about the PC is
the final thing. before I go away. I want to make sure that now that I've saved
this. Have I saved it? I have now! On the
Mac. I want to make sure that change propagates to the PC. without me
doing anything. I'm just going to take my hands off and let that happen.
In the mean while. get your environment all setup.
and make sure that you can effectively deploy your game. That's what we're doing
here. we're just manually deploying our game for testing purposes.
so that we have the same thing on the Mac and the PC or the Host
and the Client. You may wonder why it matters that we
have the same thing. The reason is that in a multiplayer
game. the assets aren't actually pushed over the Network.
so if you have some complicated animation or music
or anything like that. they're not pushed over the Network. They need to be
available in both copies of the game. which is why
two discs when you buy a PS4 game. for example. have
you know the same amount of stuff on them. It's not as if you host the
game and you send all the assets streaming down the network. it doesn't work like that.
What you do is you send Network ID's. which we'll
find out about later. streaming down the network.
and those Network ID's tell the Client.
this thing over here on the PC. what assets to load
into the game. So. that's why we need to have an
identical copy of the game on both machines. It
means that we can send just information about how things are changing. down the
network. not the whole lot. So. I've talked
about that for a while. and the Unity over on the PC
still hasn't updated. so something has
to kick this into action. by the looks of it. It seems that just
going to the folder on the PC and just having a look at it.
seems to kick DropBox or Unity into
action there. So. maybe you have that quirk as well.
that you just need to go and have a look at the folder. I don't know
perhaps that's what you need to do. So. that's it! Hopefully you're
up and running! Share in the comments to say. yep I've got it working.
and I can deploy a version between two machines. And then. we'll crack on
with actually making behavior work over the network! See you
soon!