Hey. welcome back guys!
So. in this video I'm going to introduce you to the concept of a
stack of API's in networking. We will
have a quick look at Unity's Network Stack. find out where to get
started with networking. and by the end we will have a very simple Network
Manager. in our scene. and an ugly Player prefab
and we will be able to start playing and actually launch a
host and have our player spawn. So. that's the objective of this video!
So. as with a lot of things in life. a good place to
start is with a simple Google search. So. here we go!
I've searched for Unity Networking. Oh. by the way. you can use
whatever search engine you choose. I'm not particularly partial to Google.
You could use one to of the other major search engines. [Laughs]
Anyway. so here you go. "Unity - Manual: Multiplayer
Networking". So quick overview basically suggests
that you can do it on multiple platforms. which is one of its strengths.
If we then dive into Networking Overview. at this
URL up here. UNetOverview.
you'll see "Users making a Multiplayer game"... "should start with NetworkManager
and the High Level API." Alright. well there's a couple of hints there.
Let's open those two up. NetworkManager and High Level API.
So. NetworkManager has got a lot of information
about it. and it's a component you can add and we'll look at that in a moment.
And then. the High Level API. I just want to
show you this diagram. So. I want to explain the concept of a
stack. What's happening here is all these different layers. from the physical
kind of transport layer. at the very bottom. as to how
the packets are sent and received through. The network.
all the way through Connection and Clients and Identities and scenes. right
up to NetworkTransform. which allows you to
lock the transform of two different itmes in the game and move them together
and to sync animations over the network. etc.
There's a whole load of different layers that all talk
to each other. so that's a stack. a stack of layers. And we'll actually be
diving in at various different levels of this stack. We won't be
concerning ourselves with this bottom layer here or even really too much
with the connection layer. but we will be talking about NetworkIdentity and
NetworkManager and a few others. So. there's an
overview of how it all stacks together. The question
is. back in Unity. how do we even start? Well. I want
you to have a go at starting. now that I've given you a very strong hint as to
where to start. I want you to do the following. Add
an empty game object. positioned anywhere.
Add a Network Manager component. Also. add a Network
Manager HUD component. temporarily. And
then take a look around those components and see if you can get the game
to run. without errors. You will have to do one or two things. just
be guided by the errors until you can get the game to just run.
It wouldn't do anything. it would just be able to keep sitting there. but see if you can get it to run without
errors. So. pause the video and have a go at doing this early bit
yourself now.
So welcome back! I'm going to
crack on with exactly that! So. an empty GameObject goes into the
scene. I'm going to put it at Y = 100. just to get it
well up in the air. out of the way. so that the transform gizmo.
these little arrows. don't get in my way.
Fantastic! So now. it actually turns out that if you put a NetworkManager
HUD on that it has a dependency of a Network
Manager. Let's collapse those down. So. I've added the HUD
and you'll see what that does. in a moment. And that has a dependency of a NetworkManager.
So. let me just show you what the HUD does. so you're not wondering. If we
play. I think it's actually using the old UI
or GUI methods to draw these pretty ugly
buttons. and we're not going to use these for long. because
I want you to know how to make these method calls yourself.
because if you don't then well you're stuck with these ugly buttons. which we don't want.
So. that's what the HUD does if we
disable the HUD. Then. when you play. you just get nothing whatsoever
it's just as if nothing exists.
Alright! So. if you play the game. then
it works fine and you may not have had any errors. Now.
if you'd have gone and said. I want to be a LAN Host.
which means that you are both being a player and a
Server. then you will bet these errors. The Player prefab is
empty. on the NetworkManager. Please setup a Player Prefab
Object. OK cool. so let's do that! Firstly. I'm going to
name
Network Manager to Network
Manager. and then. I'm going to create another empty object.
I'm going to call it Player.
and it really has to have
nothing on it at the moment. it just needs to be a
prefab. So. let's move the Player just
a little bit. say in Z. just so it's in a different position.
And I think just for
simplicity I will add. from scratch. a
Cylinder. so I need a Mesh Filter.
and then. I'm going to make a Cylinder Mesh on it. This is
a slightly strange way to build up a Cylinder. I'm just showing you that you can do it from
scratch like this. And a Mesh Renderer.
OK. and then. we've got a basic Player there. He's
orange. he's ugly. that's fine! So. the point
that we needed is we needed a Player prefab. so of course. you
prefab that Player and now we have a Player prefab. So
finally. let's go look at the NetworkManager. briefly! Don't
destroy on load. that means it'll persist through to another scene. It's running
in the background. That's what we want! Well. I won't go through the details of the
rest of these. for the moment. Bear in mind. that we are going to need to change
Network Address later. when we come to talk to another machine. You'll leave it as Local
Host. if you're running against a build. and you will change it
to the IP Address of the other machine. if you're doing it that way.
So. what we do need though is a Player prefab. to stop that error
message. So now. when you try and drag the Player
prefab. what do we get? We get "playerPrefab must have
a Networkidentity." So. this is where we bring in the
concept of Network Identity. So. the Network Manager
must have a Player to spawn. when the game starts. right.
and all objects that we're going to use
in the multiplayer game. that are going to communicate over the network. must have a Network
Identity. And if we add
that component. we won't worry about what
the options are. for the moment. but that gives this thing an ID.
that the Networking System can use. alright. Now of course.
I've added it to the instance. I haven't applied it back to the prefab. So
now. I have applied it back to the prefab. and we can check that in the
Prefab. So. what we're doing is just adding a
simple object. that must have at least a Network Identity
on it. to the Player prefab.
Ah hah! And this is an old error. let's try running!
Here we go but we don't know that it's working yet. because
we haven't tried to create a Server or a Host. So. I'm going to make a Host.
There you go! Now. what's happened here
is it's actually made a new Player at
the central position. So. we have our Player prefab. that we left in the scene. and
a new one right over the cube
there. So. because the Player is going to be spawned
for us. when we start playing. we don't actually need
the Player instance to be in
the scene. from the beginning. So. we can remove that now. so
all we've got is a scene that has a cube in it. just so that it's got something
in it. and NetworkManager.
which is going to sit there and persist and provide us with some
Heads Up Display HUD. to control it.
And then. a Player prefab is linked into
that. so that when we play the game. then
you launch a Host. the Player gets spawned.
Also. if you play the game and launch as a
Server. the Player does not get spawned. because servers don't
have any players in them right. they are just pure Servers.
And if we launch as a Client.
then what's going to happen? Nothing! So. we'll
see later. why when you try and launch as a Client.
we don't get a Player appearing. OK. we're only
going to get a Player appearing when there's a Host. because
in simple terms. you can't have the Player or the Client without
a server. So. a Host is a Server plus a
Client. these two together. So. that's why the only thing
that currently works is clicking Host. Server comes up.
the Player gets spawned. and we're good to go.
Alright. so that's fantastic! In the next video I'm going to show you how
to make the API calls that these
buttons make. yourself OK. so that we don't rely on this
hidden functionality. Let's start breaking down how this stuff works!