Hey guys welcome back! So. in this video we're going to make
our own Start Host Button. something like this.
And that is going to be wired through. to our own methods against Network
Manager and allow us to start the host and get a log
in the Console. without needing the ugly
default HUD Component. that kind of works
magically without us knowing what it does. So. that's what we're
going to be doing. We'll also have a quick look at the API documentation
of a couple of methods. OK. so that's
what we do. So the reason we want to
replace this default HUD is. because we don't really know what it
is doing. We click a button and stuff happens. but
that's not great. How about if we want our own User Interface.
how are we going to get behind the skin of that button? If we try and inspect the button.
then there's no information really.
and you can do some offsetting on it. You can say GUI
Vertical and Horizontal offset and some other runtime
controls. which are just a repeat of these buttons. like LAN
and Host. etc. But it's really not very
helpful. and if you try and search to see if we've got a HUD script
we can inspect. we haven't even got a HUD Script we can
inspect. So look. we need to get under the skin of this guy and start
creating our own functionality.
Initially. for this video. just getting the Start Host Button working.
and then from there. its an easy job to add other buttons as
we need to. So. what we want to do is just
create a button to start with. so I'm just going to add a UI Button.
and that will bring all the normal stuff with it. the Event System and the
Canvas. of course. And I'm just going to call that button Start Host.
And give it a label
of Start Host. of course. which is in the Text Element. all standard stuff
alright. We'll leave it a screen space for the moment.
The idea is that we just have a button. I will get it as
2D. pop into the UI Control.
zoom to the Canvas. and then. move the button into the
Canvas carefully. up there
on the top right to differentiate it. So now. if we click play.
obviously our Start Host does nothing. because it's not wired to
to do anything. So. the question comes. how do we even begin to find out what
methods to call to start this host. Well. I think a good old
Google search will be good again: "unity network manager start host".
and this is looking pretty promising. NetworkManager.StartHost
there. Alright. so that
is what we are dealing with. the NetworkManager.StartHost.
I am going to suggest a slight
architectural addition. and then. I'm going to challenge you actually
get the host starting. from the button. So. the thing that I want
to do to make that possible is.
to have a script of my
own. my own NetworkManager. which is going to allow
me to actually make a
call from this button. Remember how buttons work. if we go to the button.
come down here. and say On Click (). it's going to want an
instantiated object to call alright. So
we can talk to the NetworkManager here. but you'll find that if
you look at NetworkManager and
inspect it. you don't have Start
Host. it's just not an option. You've got Stop Host but not
Start Host. so you can't even call the existing
NetworkManager. because for some reason they haven't publicly exposed the
Start Host method. Now. that may change in the future. but that's how it is right
now. It's not available by the Network HUD either.
so we need to create ourselves an interface
in between the two. So. back at the NetworkManager.
instead of using a NetworkManager HUD Script. I want you to remove
the NetworkManager HUB Component off your NetworkManager.
Alright. so we've just got a NetworkManager on there.
so this thing is really of type NetworkManger now.
among other types like transform. Now.
what I want to do is just make my own MyNetwork
Manager or MyHUD for now
Let's just call it my HUD. So. create a script called MyHUD.
Alright. and that's attached to the NetworkManager
and let's pop into that script.
And I'm going to set you a challenge. of course. because
I think that you can manage this bit.
So. what I want you to do is make the button start the Host.
in MyStartHost() method in
that script we just created. Start the Host and log to the Console.
with a meaningful time stamp. OK so. you're going to click the
button. wire it up. call my start. call the appropriate
method. which I showed you in Unity's docs earlier. the NetworkManager.
StartHost. and then make sure the Host actually starts from your button.
The more experienced among you. may have noticed that we are
inheriting. in our script. from MonoBehavior by default.
and maybe that's not what we want to do but for now. just leave
it inheriting from MonoBehaviour. Follow along with me. just for this video.
and in the next video I'm going to talk about override and
other things that are going to get the structure of this right. I just want to
take people down the path they're likely to go down. on their
own to start with. So. go ahead. pause the video. and
do that now!
Welcome back guys! So. let's have a look at how
we're going to do this! We have a my HUD Script.
which is just loading up in Mono now. Here it comes.
on the other screen. Fantastic! So. the first thing we're going to need to do is go and
find ourselves the NetworkManager. I want to do this privately. I
don't want to drag it in. This is something we don't want the designer doing. so
we have a private NetworkManager.
Now. it's not there! The name space you're going to need to import
is UnityEngine.
Networking; now. you'll have a Network
Manager.
There we go! So. private Network
Manager networkManager; OK. and then the
standard old stuff. for us to go find it. So. networkManager
= GetComponent.
Now. we can just GetComponent. in this point
because it's on the same GameObject right. We are
sitting here. MyHUD Script. it's
on the same GameObject. If we want our HUD Controller.
for some reason. to go on a different GameObject. which we might do later. we'd use a different
find method. we'd find object of type. If we're going to GetComponent
of type
and that's it! Now.
I'm going to provide a method. I said in the challenge that we want
a method called void.
oops! MyStartHost
returning nothing. What's it going to do? Well. it's
just going to go NetworkManager the instance dot start
Host. Now you see that's the
autocomplete. on my system at least. here in Mono. It may be
different in Visual Studio for you and it may be different in the future. but look. if I go start
it's not there. So. you have to confidently continue to
startHost. Alright. that's great!
And then. what I want to do is Debug.Log
("Starting
host at...
I'll put a capital H. why not. ...Host at " and then
I'm going to concatenate it in Time.time since level load.
Fantastic! And then. there's also
a method or message rather that is passed.
when the Host actually starts. Let's go to the docs and have a look.
So. you've got StartHost. If we go back up to Network
Manager. script reference NetworkManager.
let's see what we've got under Host. We've got a whole
Host. excuse the thing there the pun. there
of things mentioning Host here. and then. we have OnStart
Host hook or message. So. I'm going to just
intercept that OnStartHost. void OnStart
Host. Normally. you'd cut and paste those. be very careful that you
spell it right. If you're not sure. just cut and paste from the docs.
because message is no error. but be careful of your syntax.
And we're just going to Debug.
Log ("Host
started at " and then
just put in this Time.timeSinceLevelLoad):
OK. let's see how all that works! Let's go into
Unity. let's play. and when we
play. of course. there's not heads up display on the left anymore. because we
disabled the component. If we click Start Host and
look in the Console. what happens? Nothing! Why not?
Simply because I haven't wired this button to any method. So.
the object I want to operate on is the NetworkManager.
but the function I want to find is MyHUD
and then Start Host. Now. it's not there!
Final rookie error. of course. is that this needs to be
public void Start Host. Save that script. back in
here. Now. when we inspect through
to here. we've got MyStartHost.
Now. why did I call it MyStartHost?
That's OK! The reason I called it
MyStartHost was to differentiate it from the built in method.
so that we're clear that it's me then going on to call
the Start Host. Fantastic! So. we're looking
at the NetworkManager. this instance here. We're looking through
the NetworkManager to the MyHUD Component.
and then. we're calling MyStartHost. with no parameters. See
if it works! Ah hah! "Starting Host at
1" second .3333. You'll notice that we
are not seeing our other log entry.
which if we pop back into MonoDevelop. If I can
find it. somewhere along here. This On
StartHost has not worked. Now. that's going to be the
subject of the next lecture. because for the first time we're needing to do
something called an override. So. we'll talk about what overriding
is in the next lecture. So congratulations if you got this far! At
least you've got your Host starting. with your own button! And we will explore
what we need to do next!