Hey guys! So. we're going to talk about the Override
Keyword! So. in this video. we're going to have a little recap
of inheritance and how that works. We're going
to talk about what the Override Keyword
does and why we need it and explain some code
we're going to be writing. so at the end of the day when you
click Start Host. Host Started appears. but there'll be
quite some dramatic changes to our script.
because there are some lessons to be learned here about
what it all means. So. why isn't this working?
We click play. Start Host. and we get no
log entry. This seems like a simple thing. I'm not getting a log
entry. but there's actually a much much deeper problem. with the way
that I've made you write this code so far. It's actually completely
the wrong approach. and in seeing this it's going to
help you understand what the right approach is.
So. this is the line that's not working. void (OnStartHost) ().
Let's look at the documentation. The thing to notice. that
OnStartHost is a method of
NetworkManager. It's a public void method of
NetworkManager. NetworkManager. in turn.
inherits from MonoBehavior. which inherits from Behavior.
and so on. up the stack. Let's look at that in a diagram.
Just get rid of my pretty pencils
and bring up the slide. So.
we made MyHUD there in red. It inherits from
MonoBehaviour right. takes all the methods of MonoBehaviour
and allows you to add more. MonoBehavior inherits from Behavior. then
Component. then Object. What we actually wanted to do
is to understand that NetworkManager itself inherits
from MonoBehaviour. And what we're really trying to
do here is create our own NetworkManager. with it's own
behavior. for example. our own buttons.
So. we don't want MyHUD at all. Instead of MyHUD. we want something called
MyNetworkManager. which inherits from
NetworkManager.
and then. we will be able to do something called a override.
Now. let's talk about what an override is. briefly.
An "override modifier is required to extend or modify the abstract or
virtual implementation of an inherited method. property. indexer. or
event." OK. So. that sounds like a lot of bumf.
but what it's saying is that when we do this
inheritance here. when we create a MyNetworkManager. at the bottom.
inheriting from NetworkManager we are
able to override its method. So.
NetworkManager. as the documentation says. has a NetworkManager
dot. if we just
go back a few. OnStartHost.
OK. So. what
we're wanting to do is override the behavior
of OnStartHost. Whatever OnStartHost is doing now. we
need to intercept it. but how do we do that? Well.
the way that we do it is we say
override void OnStartHost().
But this is only going to work if
we're talking about a class. i.e.
this class name here needs to be a child
of NetworkManager. not of MonoBehavior.
So. we need to make MyNetworkManager
a child of NetworkManager. Let's do that first!
So. instead of getting called MyHUD. I'm going to rename it with
Controller Command R. MyNetworkManager.
OK. that's a more sensible name and save it.
Then. it's not going to inherit from MonoBehaviour. but it's
going to inherit from NetworkManager.
Ah hah!
OK. now we don't actually
need these bits. but I'll challenge you
to tidy that code up in a moment. bits of that! Leave those where they are!
What we want to do is understand this override On
StartHost. So. now OnStartHost is a method of Network
Manager. and we're trying to override it. It's not quite right yet.
and I'll show you why. Let's try and do that override.
And it says. "virtual abstract members
cannot be private." OK.
so that's because the access properties
of OnStartHost here need to be public.
the same as OnStartHost actually
is. Now. if you look in Unity's docs. it
says that it's a public method. OnStartHost. Furthermore. if you look
in Microsoft's documents here. about overriding it.
say somewhere down here: "An override declaration cannot
change the accessability of a method."
So. what we're doing. as a recap. is we are
replacing the behavior of the NetworkManager's
OnStartHost method. with our own in
MyNetworkManager. and that's where the override comes from. It's public because
the one in NetwormManager is public. It's a void
because it's the same signature as the one that NetworkManager
already has. but we use override to override it's behavior.
Let's see what happens!
Now. there's a script missing and
the reason there's a script missing is. because we've still got the
old NetworkManager attached to our Network
Manager. Remove that standard Unity component.
and when you put your new MyNetworkManager on.
look. it actually behaves just like a NetworkManager. because it is a
NetworkManager. it's a child of one. OK. Of course. you'll need to
rewire your player. so let's rewire our player.
and let's see how we get on.
OK. into the Console and click Start Host.
and that
actually is logging the Host started. so that has worked.
That's good news! So. well done getting that far.
if you have. And what I want you to do
now is I want you to refactor your script. So. here's a script.
There's a problem with a few of these lines. We don't need to go and find components.
because we are a NetworkManager now. So. I want you to
remove the GetComponent line. change the call to
Start Host so it is simpler. rewire
the Player Prefab. I've done that for you as a bonus. test that logging works
still. and ask yourself if you understand what's
happened. So. go ahead and just simplify that script
now.
OK. so let's have a look. We don't need to find a Network
Manger. because we are a child of the NetworkManager. So. we don't need to
do this go and find the component. OK.
so the only thing that's not going to work is this NetworkManager.StartHost (); we don't
have a local member variable called
NetworkManger anymore. because we don't need it. We just call
StartHost. because StartHost is now in scope. it's a method
of NetworkManager. So. we make our own NetworkManager.
which extends NetworkManager.
we make our own method called MyStartHost. we log out.
and we call StartHost (). which is NetworkManager's one. This just provides
the path through for our button. Remember that our button couldn't
see... When we clicked on this button. it couldn't see
when we looked at the NetworkManager. and then. we
looked down. we couldn't actually see a Start Host but we
now can. MyStartHost. that's what we wire it to!
And then. here we're saying. OK when the
OnStartHost method gets called. of the NetworkManager.
then I want to override it and just log out what's happened.
So. when we do that and click the button
and it says Starting Host. and immediately as it happens
it says Host started. Not surprising! What does it need to
wait for? So. that's that! I hope that all
makes sense. I think we need to stand back from that a little bit. because there's a lot of
new stuff in there. Basically. remember that
the mistake we made was inheriting MyHUD. without
thought for MonoBehaviour. when it should have been a different name.
MyNetworkManager. and it should have inherited from NetworkManager.
OK. and as a test as to whether you do understand
this. why don't you go ahead and explain override to someone.
as a challenge. Call a geeky friend. who would understand. or even
better still. simply go to the discussions against this lecture and just
explain what you understand by overwrite in a paragraph.
if you can. And if you possibly
can. just in 5 words or less. What does override do in a nut shell?
Good luck and I'll see you in the next video!