Hey welcome back! So, in this video we're going to briefly
talk about Local Host and IPv4 addresses.
Basically, 127
.0.0.1 is your Local Host
address. You can find out more about Local Host at Wikipedia
on the link at the bottom of this slide, if you want to.
I'm going to show you how to find your own machine's IP Address.
You are going to temporarily use the HUD again, the built
in Networking Hub to connect the Client
to the server,
and then, we will
also connect a Local Build by a Local Host.
So, by the end of this, what you'll be able to do is
come in here and click, for example, Start Host
and you will get information about this client start having been
rquestied. We've moved the time stamps to the front. You'll get dots
up here, until it's connected, and then, you'll be told when it's connected.
And that will also work over on the
Client Machine. You can see my Client Machine is actually connecting. So, I'm going to
show you how to do that right now.
I want to log out some information about what the Client
is doing, so I'm going to go into my
NetworkManager Script, and I'm going to
look at another method. There's another method called OnClient
Start, and we have to do exactly the same thing: public override
void, because that's it's method signature,
OnStartClient.
Now, if I just certainly in
Mono go to the end of that line and go Command or
Control on a PC and Apostrophe, that will do a search
to the Google docs, which is very helpful. And it's Network
Manager.OnStartClient. How do I know that?
Well, I'm working inside a NetworkManager, at the moment,
that is the whole class we're working in. And you'll see that when that
message is called, you also get passed
in a NetworkClient.client. So, let's just copy that
and come back over into our script
and paste that in, but we don't need
Networking dot, because we've already imported the Networking name space, so
let's get rid of that. And also, Client sounds like a
reserved word to me, so I'm going to use myClient.
OK!
So, what happens is this method is called,
when the Client start is requested. In fact, let's just look at
the docs and see what the docs say.
This hook is invoked when the Client is started OK.
So, it's actually really called when the Client
start is requested, so let's log that.
Let's put a log entry that says, Client's
start requested. In fact, why don't you just do this! I want you to do
two things. I want you to just log Client start requested, but also
switch these time labels to the front of all these lines
for me, so that they appear in the log a little bit better. So,
go ahead, micro challenge! Pause the video and just say time,
client log, and say client start requested.
Welcome back! So, I'm just going to
take these timeSinceLevelLoads and start putting them at
the start of the lines. You'll see why when you see the
log. A bit of a space, " Client
start requested."
And I'm just going to take the rest of these and put them at the beginning
of the lines.
And I can copy all that. Finally, I could do
a find and replace, arguably here, but
it would take longer with three instances than just doing it.
Starting Host.
Starting Host. Now, we don't need these app bits we just,
you know, say Starting Host, host started,
" client start requested". Let's try that!
Now, how are we going to try it? How do we request a client? Well, one of the
easiest ways is to go back to the NetworkManager and add a HUD back in.
You can add this HUD and then replicate its functionality and take
it away again and add it again, that's all fine. So here
we go, we've started! Now, if I click Start
Host, let's see what happens! We get a
3.53, etc. seconds, since the game started, "Starting Host".
"Host started", at the same time, because it's local, and then,
"Client start ruquested." Great! So, it's the Host that's
created both a Server and
a Client.
OK, we don't know if the client was actually created, we'll find out in a minute.
Let's see if it works the other way. Try play and just
go LAN Client Local Host. "Client start requested." Great!
So, we have logging information
about the fact that the Client start has been requested. Now,
what we need to do is know what happens when the
start actually happens. So,
we've got another method, which is public override. You're going to get
used to writing public overried void. On
ClientConnect. Now, again, we can go to the docs for that.
It's called on the Client,
when connected to a server, and it passes on
a Networking Connection conn OK.
So, let's go and take that parameter
with its in
and take a look. So, now I'm just going to log out.
I'm going to put a time stamp in to
start with, so that we can see the delay, and there'll be no delay on the local machine but you'll see
the delay on the remote machine, in a moment.
So, we want to say that the Client is
now connected to, and I'd like to
to know the IP Address its connected to. Now, where did you get the
IP Address from? Well, now that there actually is a
connection, we can query this conn
variable here. So, we go conn.address.
Let's see how that works, locally.
Play.
If you start a Local Client,
"Client start requested." And
the Client is not connected to anything, because
there is no Server. OK, let's try the other
thing, let's try starting a Host. Now, the Host is
requested to be started, immediately it starts,
the Client start request happens, and then, the Client is connected to IP Local
Server. Great! I think we have all of the logging
that we need now, to be sure that
we'll know when we are connected. So, let's
go ahead and get this working on the other machine. So,
this code once saved and once the Unity project is saved,
I can safely go over to my Slave Machine,
you know the machine I'm distributing the software to,
make it refresh. In my case, I just have to look at the
drop box folder and come back in here, let Unity refresh,
reloading everything. OK, so
on the Host Machine, let's play and start
the Host. Now, who remembers what my IP was? I think it was 0.39?
Let's go find out! over on your
Client Machine, we play. Now,
we've got this GUI here now.
We replace Local Host, unless you're doing a Local Build. If you're doing
this out to a Local Build, leave it as Local Host. It won't be as satisfying as
this, because this is actually going to do something over the network in a moment.
192.168.0.39. "Client
start requested." And then, there was a gap, which is a good sign.
There's a gap of what, 0.4 of a second or
something like that, 0.04 of a second, 40 milliseconds.
And it's actually connected to 192.168.0.39
Remember what you're seeing here is a different computer, sitting on
the end of a LAN cable. I'm just using
team viewer to view it. So that's it, they are actually connected!
You've just got to believe that for now. [Laughs] So, in the next video, we're
going to actually get some movement of
GameObjects, over this connection that's working.
If it isn't connecting for you, for example,
you put the wrong IP Address in. Let's just put some
bogus IP Address in. I don't know,
maybe .23? I hope that's not my other IP Address by mistake.
And if I click LAN Client now, it'll just say "Client
start requested" and it'll just sit there, saying "Client
start requested." Now, how do you know it's doing anything?
Well, that sounds like a good exercise for the reader.
So, what I want you to do is invoke dots! I want you to print a
dot on the Console until it's connected. So, between the
Client's start request
and the actual Client connect, I want you to just print a dot!
Hint, just the InvokeRepeating() method. So, go ahead and
see if you can get that working now!
OK, so welcome back! Let's have a look at a simple
piece of code, just to give ourselves some feedback that this
connection is trying to happen. Remember when you use Invoke,
you have to write your own method, so void print Dots ().
It doesn't need to take anything in, for the moment,
and it's simply going to Debug.Log
a dot.
Simple. Now, when OnClient
Start, when we request the start,
we want to, after we have
printed the Client's start is requested, we want to InvokeRepeating.
The name of the method
is ("PrintDots"). It's a bit clunky, this isn't it passing in a method
name as a string? Ah! Anyway, 0f is the
pause. We want to start, sort of one second, as a
float, is the delay, and then, what you do once you are connected is,
you simply cancel Invoke. So,
CancelInvoke (); it doesn't need any parameters,
it cancels Invoke the entire
scope that we're in at the moment. OK, so let's
have a go!
I've got to play on the machine here, start a
Host, you get a single dot there. If I go over to the
other machine, make sure that the file is updated by
looking at this folder. I'm not sure why DropBox needs me to do that, but it does
bless it. Let's purposefully put the wrong address
in... something like 19
2.168.0.24,
start the Client, and it's saying
dot dot dot. And if we choose the right
address, which is 0.39,
then it should work
and we are done! And you just
get one dot and it connects. Perfect! Alright, so we have some sort of
wait state now, showing us what's going on. So that great! I'll
see you in the next video, where the cube will actually move over the Ethernet!
[Laughs] See you soon!