Hey. welcome back! So. in this video. we're going to use something called
a Network Transform on our cube.
one of these things. and it's going to allow us to actually send
the movement of the cube across from the Host
to the Client. So. I'm going to explain what a Network Transform does
for us. I'm going to tell you about this network
identity thing that comes along. We're going to make movements travel over the Network.
test it over the LAN. also. with
a local build and optionally you can go off and try
it to a mobile. on your network as well.
OK. so to make this work. we're going to need something called a
Network Transform. so go to your Cube on your
Host Machine. in the primary version of the game. and then
look for a Network Transform.
When you do that. it'll also add a Network Identity. so
the Network Identity is an ID that allows
the system. at either end of the game
or any of the Clients. to access a particular
asset. in this case a cube by an ID.
So for example. you're playing Grand Theft
Auto. and suddenly a brand new car you've never seen before
appears on the horizon. What's going on there is. that car asset
of course. is already on your game disc or in your game download. and
it's an ID that is being passed over the network. to say that this
asset needs to be pulled from the Assets and
spawned. So. that's what the Network Identifier does; it allows you to
uniquely identify particular assets. So. adding it to the
cube here of course means. it will also be added over on the
Client version. when it all updates.
Alright! And the other thing we're going to add is a Network Transform.
And what that does is. according to this rate that you set here...
I'm going to set this to 10. so 10 times a second is going to send the
transform of this cube over the network to the
Clients. Alright. so let's see if we can
make that work. By the way. I warn you that the player not having a material
on it is probably going to cause an error. but let's
let that error come up and solve it. when it comes up. Then. you'll have the experience
to recognize that type of error. because it's not particularly
clear. when it does come up. So. let's go for it! Let's
add to the Cube. this Network Transform.
which will come with an identity. which is a dependency.
Save it. go over to our Client...
I need to look at my Dropbox folders
and make it sync. for some reason. which forces a reloading
Unity. OK now. back to the Host!
Let's get the Host up and running. so Start Host.
In fact. hang on stop! I am fed up with typing
this network address. so in my very Network Manager.
under Network Address. I'm just going to put the address
of the Host. for myself. OK.
Over here. Network Manager. under
Network Info. Just put it. save it again.
and then. let your client version refresh.
and then. in Network Manager you'll see that there's
a default address there. which means that when we start
the Client. we will get
that as a default address. So. I've started the Host.
Let's go over to the Client; you can click LAN
Client now. and it'll have the address defaulted.
OK. Now. the Client
is connected. so the machines are talking to each other. What we need to do now is click
Client Ready. OK. this means the Client is finished loading all its
assets and it's ready to go. There you go! So. you're seeing both the ugly player.
with no material. and the Cube. Let's move back over
to the Host. We're going to go to Scene View and
I'm going to try just translating that Cube.
OK. I can see that that's working. but you probably don't believe
me. so let me show you that's working. by doing a
Split Screen. So. I'm going to make Team Viewer. rather than Full Screen.
I'm going to make it somewhat smaller. I will
make just the Game View visible.
By the way. this machine is called Bertie. because I couldn't think of a better name when
Windows surprised me. by asking me for a name. so
just in case you're wondering why you're seeing Bertie. So. what I have on the left
is my Unity. On the
Host. which is on a Mac. and on the right. we're Team Viewing into a
separate computer. a PC over on the network. Watch this!
Wow! It's amazing. it's a miracle. it moves. and if we grab
the Rotation Tool. then it's a little slow.
but Rotation works as well. So. that
is great news! We actually have movements
working over the network. which is really cool!
So. I haven't actually seen
this error yet. so I'm going to leave that ugly
material-less player. until we see an error. but
at some point we'll probably get a complaint. about something not
being initialized or some prefab not being
available or something like that. And at that point. we can be on our guard
to just give this player a material.
OK cool! So. that's working! Now. what I want to do is try
doing it to a local build. so I'm going to leave that to you as a challenge.
And what I want you to do is test to a local build. Creat
a local build of your game. run this build as a Client.
ensure that movement works between the two on the same machine.
and as a bonus. you can create a mobile build and try
building to that. as well. You can simultaneously have your cubes moving around
both. on the same machine. and another machine and
a mobile if you want. if you really want to go crazy. Have a go
and I'll see you on the other side.
Cool! Welcome back! So. let's make this
happen! It's simply a question of going to Build Settings.
making sure that the scene is in there. building for Mac
and Linux. and let's just build and run. Ahoy Matey Mac. I've
already built before. so I'm going to replace the Ahoy Matey Mac Build.
In your case. you may be on PC or Linux. Now. you probably
want to run it windowed and then just play. The resolution is
pretty irrelevant. Here it comes!
So. what I want to do is run this as a Client. but not yet. let's get the
Host going first. So. I'm going to make my
windows a little bit smaller so we can see what's going
on. And
let's run over here. It's setup as a
Host. that's fine.
I'm going to go to Scene View. with my cube selected.
Now. let's go back over here. set this guy up as a Client.
and say Client ready. OK. so on the right hand side. you're seeing the local
build. On the left hand side. you're seeing the Host in the Unity Editor. Let's
move the cube and it works! Great! So. that's
challenge one done! How about if we wanted to continue
to talk to the Client machine. over here on the
network. Let's try spooling that up. at the same time!
See if we can get two Clients coming in. at the same time. Let's launch a
Client and say that we're ready. OK.
Now. again I'm going to have to do some jiggery pokery. as
we call it. with the windows here. So.
what you've got now is. let's just maximize on
the PC. on the Client. There you go! So. you have
PC down on the bottom right. you have a Local
Native Mac Build. at the top
right of the screen. and on the left
hand side. we have the editor. Let's see if this works.
Can't really see can we. because I've go too much stuff.
Here you go. look at that! So. we now
have two Clients receiving the same information. one across the network.
one on the same machine. Pretty nifty hey! So. this
is what we covered in the video. and I look forward to seeing you in the next video.
when we continue to build out our multiplayer game.