Hey welcome back! So, in this video
what we're going to be doing is adding a camera
as a child of the player, so that we can move around,
like this and do an over the shoulder view. We are
going to find out that we have an issue, when we try doing that
and that we have a camera conflict problem. We'll find a simple
way of solving it, and then, I will show you
that ultimately we can make this work. We can actually have a
camera on two different objects, and they can both move around and
even on the Client we can see a different perspective to the
Host. So, that's what we want and it will scale three ways, as well. We'll also look at
building this to a Local Build. So, that's
what we're going to be doing in this video, it's going to be fun! By the end of it, you'll really feel like you're making some
multiplayer progress! Let's crack on!
So to make this work, our player is going
to need a camera, of course, as a child.
So, I'm going to get rid of, boldly, the Main Camera in the scene.
If we play now, we're going to get a warning, that there are
no full screen cameras. That's OK, we are actually just in a menu system
here. By the way, while we're here, I'm also going to temporarily disable
my own Start Host Button. We know now that we
can reach in and do anything that this does, but I may as well use the test button,
for now, rather than doing two things at once. So, I'm just going to go to Canvas,
Button. I'm just going to call it My Start
Host Button but then disable it like that,
so when we play we've got a very simple
UI, like that. I may, even while I'm here,
on the Network Manager Component
remember what is creating this. What is creating
this UI here. Well, it's the Network Manager
HUD OK, and then, you can use the vertical and horizontal,
offsets there. Now, if you're ever not sure
whether a change is going to propagate, once you leave play mode, of course
remember you can copy the component. And if we leave Play Mode
and then re-enter it and find it's forgotten what we've
done, then we can paste component
values, OK. And that's a way of getting changes from
Play Mode out, so there you go, I've moved it slightly and it has remembered it. So, a little
hint for you. Alright, so where do we
want this camera to be? Well, let's put a player in the
scene, our prefab, there he is. And let's stick
a camera, as
a child, to the player.
Alright, so I've childed the camera to the player.
The problem with the way I've just done it, of course, is look at the distance. You've got the player
player here and the camera up there. So, we need to just Reset
the transform. Now, the camera is right on the player.
We zoom to the player, the camera is right in the player. Now,
I don't really want that. For now, I want to be able to see the player,
so I'm just going to move the camera back a little bit so we can see the player's head.
Alright, so let's try that firstly, but
of course, the Player Prefab I've just modified. Look at the Player
Prefab, down here. It's not updated,
so of course, you click player and apply. Now, it's got a camera
and we don't need an instantiated player yet.
So now, the game has a cube,
which is just representing an enemy or something,
and it has no player, which is normal. We launch the Host, nothing happens. We make the
Client. Ah hah! Now, it instantiates a player, with a camera
childed to it, and I can actually move
this player around and that cube just provides some sort of reference in our scene.
Alright, so there's our player, and let's look at that in
Scene View. There's our player, with the camera
attached to it. If we move the camera, the player goes with it. Cool!
Alright, now let's see what happens if
we propagate this change over to the Client, and see whether all is
hunky dory. I bet you can guess that all is not quite
as we'd hope it would be. Our
challenge is before us! So, let me just save over
here. Skipitty beepy dee! Let it sync
to the Client copy. It's like distributing version
53 of our multiplayer game. Reload!
the smoking gun will be that there is a camera charted
to the player over here. Cool! Now, let's just go!
Launch a Host, make the Client, go over here!
Launch a Client, make it ready!
Client Ready! Cool! OK, so firstly let's look on the Client Machine. What happens
when I move around? Well, it's OK!
That's fine! I am the Client, I can see the other
player, the Host Player there, sitting under the cube. OK now, let's go
back to the Host. Now, let's try moving. Oh,
what's going on there! Well, if you're not sure, click
on the player, and look at it's transform up at the top right
here, in the Inspector. And you can see that what's happening, when you're
clicked clicked into the Game View, of course, is that I am moving
the correct player, because of
course the keyboard commands are being sent to all the player objects, but the Player
Script, if you remember is doing that cleaver thing where
it says, if it's not a Local Player then get out of here.
So, that's all working, but the problem is there are two cameras in the scene.
In fact, also because there are two cameras, if you look at this warning down at the bottom
here, there are also two audio listeners in the scene.
What's happening, if we look in the Scene View, is that if I
move say the Client here, it's
moving with its camera, but the camera that is being
rendered to the Game View is the camera of this other player,
of the Client player. So basically, we don't want two
cameras in the scene. What we need to do, and what you're challenge is going to be is to
make sure we only ever have one Client in the scene, regardless
of how many players we have. So, I want you to
disable all but the player's camera. I suggest you do something
inside Player.cs. I suggest you use OnStart
LocalPlayer() method. Care with it's signature,
it's an override again, and have a go, see if you can make this work!
Remember that you can enable and disable things in the Editor,
by default on the prefab, and have a go, this is quite a simple
solution to this. And I'll see you on the other side, once you've had a
good go!
That was me clinking my pen against my tea! So I'm back!
Let's see if we can make this work! So, remember
what we're trying to achieve here, we are trying to get only one
camera. So, one simple way is to go to the player and
into its camera, and you could consider disabling the Camera
Component, Camera Object, altogether. The problem with that
is you then can't find it, because it doesn't exist. So, I'm
going to disable the Camera Component of the Camera Object,
just by disabling it in the Editor.
Yeah. Then, in the Player script, let's
intercept a new message. There's actually a message
called OnStartLocal
Player. Now, if I just go to the docs for that, Command and Control
and apostrophe and then, bring the new doc window in,
let's see if it's going to come and tell us.
There you go! NetworkBehavior, which is what we are,
remember that our player is a NetworkBehavior.On
StartLocalPlayer, and it's called when the LocalPlayer Object has
been setup. But it is a public
void signature type, but also
we're overwriting the inherited OnStartLocalPlayer,
because we've already inherited an OnStartLocalPlayer method from
player. So, we want to go public,
because we need to match the accessibility, void because...
Sorry, public override void I believe.
Let me see what I've wrote before. Yes of course, that way around, so
public override void
OnStartLocalPlayer(). Alright, and then we are matching
the accessibility, we are matching the return type, but we're
overriding. Now the question is, what do we do?
Well, we can GetComponent in children,
of type Camera. Now, let's see
what we're doing there, before we go any further. Get
Component of children in type Camera. We're on the Player,
we're looking into the Player's children camera, and we're finding
this guy here. This is the component
of type Camera on
the child. And then, what we want to simply do
is enabled = true;
So by default, any player that is created will come with
a disableed camera, and then that script should enable it, only for the
Local Player. Let's check that it works. Actually, let me just save, so
DropBox can be syncing. OK, so we play,
we launch a Host, and we create a Client. Let's have a look at the one player
that's in here. It has a camera and it is enabled,
and it's enabled because this script that we just wrote
has enabled it. Let's see if
that's true! Let's have a look on the Host over here,
on Client rather, on the other machine. Let me let DropBox
sync, come back
in, let it reload, check
our Player script, so you can click on the Player script
and just look here. Yep, that code has come through!
Let's play, launch a Client, and go Client Ready.
Now, from the Client's perspective, let's have a look at these two players. We have this
player, which is the Host, and it's camera is
disabled, because on the prefab it's disabled. And this
Player, which is us, it's camera is enabled because our script
enabled it. Wicked! So does it work? That's the
question. Well, let's move around and have a look. So I as the
Client here, on the machine that I have on the network,
have stood back from the Host Player, and the
Host Player is sitting under the cube. Now, let's go to the Host,
go back into Unity,
and let's use my local keyboard to move around. Ah hah! Now,
you see I have the correct perspective. I am now the Host standing back
from the Client, who was looking at me under the cube. [Laughs] You get the idea!
And then, if I reach over to the other keybaord that's it,
we have First Person Perspective,
or of course, for this game it's going to be eventually a third person. We
actually have a Third Person Perspective. What's the difference? Well of course, it just depends how
far away you are. Is this first or third, well this is over the shoulder,
so it's kind of half way in between but you get the
idea. So that's it! That's pretty cool! Right now, I want
to just give you a couple of warning signs, before we carry on.
That is, you may in your exploration have found this little guy
here, which is view, Network View component.
If you add that, you'll find it's deprecated. It'll still be
in the docs, it'll still be all over the web, when you do these searches, just don't use it.
It's deprecated, deprecated means don't use me, because I'm
going out of fashion, a bit like tie-dyed
clothing or something. I hope I haven't offended anybody. I think I've worn
that at some point. So that's that!
I don't think there's anything else particularly to tell you about that. I think we've achieved
all of our objectives for this video.
So just to reiterate as well, be careful that you disable
the Camera Component, not the
Camera itself. If you disable the Camera itself, let's just see
what happens. When you
launch your Client, you're going to get an "Object reference not
set to an instance of an object." And if we look at that,
that's on line 24
which is here, and that's because it can't
find a component in the children of type Camera, because
the child is completely disabled,
so the GetComponent won't reach into it. And that
is why, on my prefab, I disable not
the Camera Object alltogether but the
camera itself, the component.
Alright, so that is a way of getting it working! You know what I'd like to do before
we just move on finally, is I'd like to run this three
ways. So, let's make a Local Build and just convince
ourselves that this works three ways, and then, I think after that
it's going to be a question of identifying our players, because it's getting
confusing now, to me at least. So, let's make a Mac
OS Build. Ahoy Matey
Mac, I'm going to replace my exising build.
I'm going to Allow network access and make a
windowed version of it, at a reasonable resolution. Here it is!
So, this is my Local Build! Alright, so before we get too
excited, let's get the Host up and running. So, the Host is my Editor
version, in this case. LAN Host, Client Ready,
good to go. Now, let's tab over to our
Local Build. Let's make a Local Client to Local Host.
You could probably use the IP Address, as well.
Client Ready. OK, so let's move this Client around. This guy
is working, so I'm going to stand off and to the right, with my Local
Build. Now, let's come back. Can I see
the other player? I can. Cool! Now,
let's go over to the PC version, the Client
version on the network. Launch another Client, get it ready,
and then, view it from here. Ahh look! Three different
people, all of which have their own perspectives
on the game, and this is good, because this proves
that we can scale our solution now and here's the
third one, which is my Local Build. Fantastic! So, it's a
simple scalable solution to getting them all talking to
each other and all the camera's independent. So contratulations on
getting this far! I will leave you on the screen, with the
code that we have just generated. It was simply this
overriding the OnStartLocalPlayer behavior
of our player, to enable the camera, whcih we've
left disabled by default. Much better than going through and looking for all
the cameras in the scene or in the game and disabling them all
or something. Why not just enable? Opt in is better than opt out,
we know that from e-mails. [Laughs] OK guys, see you soon!