Hey guys! So, in this video, we're going to
talk through Unity's Network System concepts,
ask ourselves what's not fun about the current game, you can't even really call it
a game at this stage, and then, I'm going to challenge you to make a basic game
from here. So, let's start off by having a
recap of what we're doing with the Network System concepts. So, you click that link,
you come to this page. So firstly,
we covered the concept of a Server and Host.
So, remember that your Host contains the
Local Client and the Server. Now, you could make a single
player game like this. If you're going to have a game that's both multiplayer
and single player, this architecture of just running the
Server locally is just fine, there's not too much of a performance
overhead of this. So, you can structure your
whole game like this, that you always have a Server running.
So, that's what happens when we spin up a Host. And then,
we've also had a couple of remote clients haven't we? One was my
PC, over the Local Area Network, and the other was a
local build on the same computer, all
plugging into the Host, actually really plugging into the Server.
So, there's that, hopefully that was clear for you.
And there's a lot more information on this page, obviously, I'm not going to
read it out to you, you can look for yourself. So, then
the next concept was about Local Player Authority and players.
So, there's a box kind of
drawn around by the Client 1 and the Server, which together,
as per here, make the Host. So, Server and Local
Client, in this diagram, relate to Server and Client 1.
So, Player 1's transform changes are
sent up to the Server and then propagate down to
Client 2. And then of course for Client 2,
Player 2 is set as the local player, and it
has authority, which means that changes made on Client 2 get
sent to the Server and then back down. We also had in our
scene a cube, which represents an enemy and
that doesn't have any Local Player Authority, and all
that happens there is that when the Server moves this
Enemy, or the cube, then the transform
component, the Network Transform Component,
pushes that change down to both of the Clients.
So, hopefully this diagram now is a little bit clearer in as
to who controls what. So, Player 1 has Local Player Authority,
here, Player 2 here, and the Enemy up on the Server.
Again, some good information on this page. Don't let
yourselves get too confused by it, but reading through Unity's
Networking over High Level API is a good idea,
in conjunction with doing the course, because it's going to help you.
understand. So, where can we go from here with this
game and this section. Well, one of our students,
Marco Vale, has very kindly provided us with this
fantastic ship! Look he's created this, modeled it,
and animated it, and there are also several animation states.
Now, I left the cube in the just for posterity, but what I've
done here, as just an example for you, is I've grabbed a Sky-
box from the Assets Store. I've just said
Skybox, and I've gone to Assets Store and looked
for a free Skybox.
Maybe you need one word, and I think the one I'm using
is WispySkybox, over here. So, I've imported a
free Skybox, which makes things look prettier. Now, I'm
for water using the same water as we used in Zombie Runner, which is the
Water Pro Daytime Asset, from the Standard Environmental Pack.
And then, that gives you reflection and refraction, not that there's
anything to refract from under the water. And then,
we have an Animation Machine, we have a Skybox,
and then, you can decide what are you going to do with the game from here. Are we going to have a
Top-Down Perspective, like this? And maybe be
right up in the sky and point and click around, to make these ships
move, or do you want more of a First Person Perspective? So,
before I go any further, and indeed if I go any
further, I want you to have a good go at using all of the knowledge you have,
from the courses so far, to now go and make
this work, because really this is the end of the course and you
are very able to produce a
huge amount yourself, and I want you to get confidence in that. So, we've
broken the back of the difficulties of Multi-Player,
and you can see the process by which you go through and
work out, well how do I get the next thing working,
you know? You're going to find that when you go to your
player and you start typing network in here,
some of these things are deprecated and it will say so if they are,
and some of them aren't, like Network Animator, for example.
So, you're going to need to use a few
more components, to transmit things like Animations
State, and if you want to do things like
match making, which we're not going to cover in
this course, because it's too advanced, then you're going to need a
Network Matchmaking System, which is against the Network Manager
but again, too much for this course. So,
most of what you need is there. You will run across other multi player
challenges. My challenge to you really is to
make a basic game, use everything you've learned in the course so
far. Incorporate some player assets, use Marco's
please credit him, say thanks to him on Twitter.
Now, the name of his Twitter Handle by the way, you go to
the video at the start of this section,
the first video the Intro Assets and Notes, and then, you download
his package and what you'll end up with is
this thing called Ship and Sea here.
And if you double click Ship and Sea, you'll have a folder
that opens up, because we need a subfolder anyway, called Thanks to @MarcoVale
Kaz. Please thank him on Twitter for providing it. And then you can go
in there and open the Ship and Sea package, as usual.
Now, there's nothing particularly unusual inside that
asset pack. Let's just have a quick look at it,
it has animations, it has
prefabs for the sea and the ship now. I
would prefer to use Unity's Standard Assets
for the water, just because it's a little prettier and it's reflective, but
Marco has a very great and high performing solution in there, as well, just by
scrolling some textures. So, you've got that, you've got an Animation Control,
you've got serious animation states. So, you
should be able to put all that together, create some simple game play.
Again, you've learned kind of point and click type game play,
from Glitch Garden;
you've learned, I think all the basics you need. See what
multiplayer challenges you've face, share the challenges that you face
in making your game, in the discussion. And when there's
a reasonable amount of challenges built up, and I've got a picture of
what you're struggling with, that will tell me what the gap in this course is,
and of course, I'm committed to the long term development of this course, as you've
seen I have to constantly revise it. So, as I start to see people's
challenges build up and players make it... uh players! [Laughs] ...students make
it through to the end of the course, I will start to consider making
further content to help you solve those issues, but I want to
be solving the real issues you're having. So, go ahead and make a basic game,
share what you can, get stuck when you get stuck, tell us in the
discussions, and let's move onwards and upwards! So,
see you soon guys!