So. how did you get on with the
huge challenge of turning what I've shown you. and everything else
in this course. into your own multiplayer game?
Now. I'd expect that challenge to take days and weeks. not just
hours. So. I hope you've done it. I hope you're
doing well. Let us know in the discussion where you're
stuck. I would say right now. that if I see a recurring
theme come up. where you don't feel you're fully equippedt to make a game.
then I will add to the section. because of course. I'm committed for the long
term to maintaining this course. and the Physics course. and the Blender
course. and any other courses I've made. It's my job
to keep those up to date. keep them fresh. so that includes adding
to this section. as and if required. But what I'm going
for here is a tapered structure. so the very early sections
of the course are very small. and then. they got bigger and bigger and  bigger.
culminating with Glitch Garden and Bowl Master; very
large sections and then we taped down again. Zombie Runner was a little
bit incomplete. Twin Sticks was very incomplete. and this
section is purposefully also incomplete and really
focusing on the core knowledge that you need to make multiplayer games.
so that you can use everything you learned previously in the course.
to turn it into real games. Now. you're going to need this sort of
independence. when you're working for yourself
and you're making your own games. of course. Somebody is not going to be there. to tell you
how to make every aspect of it. So. please persist.
please keep learning. keep exploring. keep supporting
each other. and see if you can't make your own multiplayer
networking game. and ship it into the Assets Store. At least.
a local multiplayer game. just with what you've learned. Let me
know how you get on. in the discussions. and I will see
you in the Final Section. where there are fewer extra resources.
and of course on with my other courses.
=======
So, how did you get on with the
huge challenge of turning what I've shown you, and everything else
in this course, into your own multiplayer game?
Now, I'd expect that challenge to take days and weeks, not just
hours. So, I hope you've done it, I hope you're
doing well. Let us know in the discussion where you're
stuck. I would say right now, that if I see a recurring
theme come up, where you don't feel you're fully equippedt to make a game,
then I will add to the section, because of course, I'm committed for the long
term to maintaining this course, and the Physics course, and the Blender
course, and any other courses I've made. It's my job
to keep those up to date, keep them fresh, so that includes adding
to this section, as and if required. But what I'm going
for here is a tapered structure, so the very early sections
of the course are very small, and then, they got bigger and bigger and  bigger,
culminating with Glitch Garden and Bowl Master; very
large sections and then we taped down again. Zombie Runner was a little
bit incomplete, Twin Sticks was very incomplete, and this
section is purposefully also incomplete and really
focusing on the core knowledge that you need to make multiplayer games,
so that you can use everything you learned previously in the course,
to turn it into real games. Now, you're going to need this sort of
independence, when you're working for yourself
and you're making your own games, of course. Somebody is not going to be there, to tell you
how to make every aspect of it. So, please persist,
please keep learning, keep exploring, keep supporting
each other, and see if you can't make your own multiplayer
networking game, and ship it into the Assets Store. At least,
a local multiplayer game, just with what you've learned. Let me
know how you get on, in the discussions, and I will see
you in the Final Section, where there are fewer extra resources,
and of course on with my other courses.
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1