So hi, and welcome to laser defender. Laser defender is a brilliant new game.
Ben, what was laser defender all about?
So laser defender is a classic old space shooter. You are at the bottom of the screen.
The bad guys come in and try and shoot you from above.
It’s a great great game. It flows really nicely, and there’s a load of new things you are going to learn in there.
So, Brice, what are the three or four major new things they’re going to pick up?
Yes, some really exciting things actually.  It’s the first time you are going to meet the animation framework.
So Unity’s got this really powerful behind the scene animation framework, that you can do lots of cool stuff with,
and it’s the first time we are going to be playing around with it.
To firstly move stuff about, move stuff around, and things like add effects as well.
So that’s going to be quite interesting.
In addition to that, we’ll be meeting trigger colliders for the first time,
and we’ve been doing a lot of non-trigger colliders.
Just normal colliders before, but now we’ve got a different type of collider.
And they give you a little bit more power to do certain things in the code, rather than let the engine resolve it.
And thirdly and lastly, we’re going to be using particle effects, a little bit more,
to do some cool stuff with the backgrounds of our game,
and to make it feel more alive and to give some depth in a 2D setting.
And of course again, we want you to create your own variations on this, from the start.
Even as you’re going through the videos, you don’t have to use the assets Brice is using:
sound, bit graphics, animations, any of it.
You can change it for yourself, either at the end, or I suggest as you go through.
So enjoy the section, it’s going to be fun!
You’re going to have a great game and a load of new tools at the end. And We’ll see you soon. Bye.