So hi, and welcome back.
In this video, we’re going to be importing our menu system, to set up our Laser Defender game.
So what are we going to do?
Well, we’re going to grab a Unity package from either A). another game,
or B). from the bundle downloads at the beginning of this section,
and we’re going to create our Laser Defender game, with a menu system.
To get started and be ready to start developing the game itself.
So how are we going to do that? Well you have a choice.
You can either grab the Unity package, the one that we’ve put in the download section,
or you can  go to one of your old games and grab the menu system from there and export as a package.
I’m going to be showing you how to use the one from the downloads.
Feel free to do exactly the same steps, but with a package you have created yourself.
So that’s actually exactly what I want you to do now.
I want you to pause this video, and create a Unity package, and import it into a new project called Laser Defender.
So pause the video now, and import your package into your game, to start your menu system.
So here's how I'm going to do it.
I’m going to open up a new Unity project;
create a completely new project.
I’m going to set the mode to 2D.
I’m going to choose my location,
and you can choose whatever you want and makes sense to you.
Personally I’m going to call it Laser Defender.
I have a special folder for all my Unity games,
and don’t worry about the extension on the folder name.
And here we go, we’ve got a 2D project.
I’m creating my project, and here we are.
If you haven’t created your project as 2D, don’t worry too much about it,
that can always be changed later, so don’t worry at all about that.
So now I’m in my project. I can import a package by going to Assets.
Import Package. I’m going to import a Custom Package.
And as you can see, I’ve already navigated to the right place.
This is the menu package that comes as part of the downloads,
and if I click this and double click it and select it, I can import everything.
And Unity will take time to look through all the assets and import them into its library.
And while it’s doing that. Here good brilliant!
So now I’ve got a start scene.
And if I look at the start menu as a whole, we’ve got the…
well you can probably…
if you’ve been looking at this course and other sections of this course you have probably seen this before.
So we’ve got a Start Menu. We’ve got a Win Screen.
The first thing I’m going to do actually is,
I’m going to open my Build Settings,
and I’m going to add my scenes to my Build Settings.
I’m selecting my scenes and dragging them into the scenes in build in my Build Settings.
And that’s so that Unity knows that these scenes are actually going to be available while the game is playing.
So now I’ve got my scenes in. Let’s try and play the start scene and see what we get.
[Game Music Playing] So as you can tell, the background music is coming on.
I press start. I go to the end scene.
I press play again. Brilliant!
So, now the next step is to add a intermediate scene from that start scene.
To move into so I’m going to create a new scene,
and from that I’m going to save it, and I’m going to call it Game.
And that’s going to be the game scene.
My game scene is saved into Assets by default.
I'm just going to move it into my Scenes.
My Scenes folder.
So Brilliant! I’ve got the game scene here.
Now, there’s nothing in the game scene.
I don’t really want anything for now,
so I’m just going to jump into my Start Menu and make my Start Menu’s Start Button actually move me to the Game Scene.
And to do that, I go into the Inspector.
When I’ve got my Start Button selected,
I look at the buttons on the Click Handler, and I look at the Level Manager dot load level.
And instead of  loading the Win Screen, I change the Win Screen in the Inspector to the Game Scene.
And if I press play now, we should see that when I press start.
I can’t load the scene. Why is that?
Well, because I forgot to add it into my Build Settings.
So, File. Build Settings. This seems vaguely familiar.
Drag your scene into it.
I’m going to put it up here, into my Build Settings, in the second scene.
I close my Build Settings, and I try again.
So now we’ve got a Start Button that takes me to the right scene.
So great! Brilliant!
We are now set up and all ready to go for the next step of building this game.
So thank you for watching, and I will see you very shortly. Bye.