Hello. and welcome back! In this video
we're going to be building a spaceship.
So what about our spaceship? Well. we just want a spaceship we can control.
that's going to be our defender. He's going to be moving in the play space from side to side.
and that's what we want to do. So what's the first step in building a spaceship?
Well. the first thing I'm gonna do is I'm going to grab
some assets. and I found some brilliant
assets on a place called open game art.org.
and in fact. it's a great website for
your asset needs. In fact. we've bundled
all of those assets in our download at
the beginning of the section. If you want
to get ahold of it. Also if you want
to grab them yourself. they're all on this
website called open game art .org. and
we're talking about the space shooter
redux. and there's a whole bunch of space
assets and our laser defender is going
to be our little space ship right here. So
let's do it. Let's jump straight in and
get that done. We want to add the asset
and we've got it from Unity so I'm
just going to jump back into Unity. and I'm going to import some assets. so the way
I'm going to do that. I'm going to find them in my browser. I've got my finder here.
I'm going to go to the right place on my desk and grab the assets. so got laser
defender and it's going to be in the
bundle. And that's the bundle you download and it's
going to be in space shooter redux. Why it's all the way there on the right I have no idea.
So let's take a look and what assets do we want for our spaceship?
We're talking about the players spaceship. and I kinda like the look of the blue dude.
That blue guy is the one I like. so I'm
going to grab that and I'm going to drag and
drop it into my Unity editor. If I
grab it and drop it on the Asset Pane.
it'll create a sprite. I can actually bring it to
Assets. Let's jump in there. Let's see? Has
it been imported properly?
Yep. sprite 2D in the UI.
if it hasn't been imported as a 2D
sprite don't forget you can always
change that by going to the Inspector
and you've got the actual item selected
So I don't actually care about this scene
right now. so I'm going to jump back out
into my game. Save whatever changes I've made here. Let's get started with our 2D game. So the first thing we're going
to do is grab our sprite and drop him in.
So. we've got him in the play space. Let's zoom in a little bit. so we can actually see it.
Have we got a player ship here?
Yes we do. It's not huge. It's fine. We can deal with that. We'll recenter it. to make sure
it's all at the origin. and if I've got
that right and then I can
just double-click the ship. and here we are. So that's our player ship. So we've got this player.
He's going to be our little space ship. and our job is actually now to make sure we can
control him. We can actually get him
moving the way we want to. and in fact.
that is once you've downloaded his assets and imported them to Unity. that's your job.
and that's your next job. I want you to
add a script to your ship so drag and
drop a script or create a new script onto
your script. Call it PlayController that
script. and get it to move the ship left
and right with the arrow keys. You need
to make the speed adjustable in the
editor. because that requires a lot of
tuning. So pause the video now. and add a
controller script to your starship. To your
little starship sprite to make sure it
can move left and right. based on your
arrow keys. Now. I know this is a little
bit of a bigger step and challenge than
we're used to. but don't worry too much
don't stress out take it slow. Remember
to break it down into smaller problems. So add a script; add a function inside  your
update. Rather add an if statement inside your update that checks whether the right and left arrow keys
have been pressing. and if you're not quite
sure how to. Go back and have a look
at the Text 101 game we made. which uses the keyboard. and you'll need to find out
the key code for left arrow and right
arrow. And then once you've done that
it's a simple matter of changing the
transform's position. Modifying the
transform's position. the way we did in
Block Breaker for moving the paddle. so
take a look at Block Breaker code for
moving the paddle if you're not sure
and take a look at the Text 101 code for
grabbing the keyboard input if you're
not sure. And once you've done that.  I will see you and we will go through it together. So see you soon.
So here we are. we have our ship in our editor. How do we get a script on and get it to
move from side to side
based on the arrow keys? Well I'm going
to just add a component to my...  I've got
the ship selected. Actually I'm going to
rename it player ship one blue doesn't
sound good. so I'm just going to call it Player. Oops not play. but Player. So I've
got my player. and I'm going to add a component to it. That's going to be a new script.
there's going to be a player controller and that's the script responsible for controlling the player
and I'm going to edit that script now. so
here we are we have mono coming up. and
let's get this ship moving. So how are we
going to do that? Well you've seen this
before. We just go: if Input.GetKey
and we're going to go left and right arrow.
That's KeyCode with a capital K.
KeyCode. And it'll give you left arrow. so
that's moving my ship left. I want my
transformed.position to be  +=
a new. So I'm changing my position
by a vector. so that's X. Y. &amp; Z. And I really want to move it in some distance in the
X-direction. so I'm going to have. lets
say if I'm moving left I want a negative
X direction. so that's minus. and
that's going to be my speed of my
little star ship. And I don't
have this defined just yet but that's
ok. I don't want to move up. I don't want it
to move down. and I do not want it to
move in and out of the actual game world. So that's it. Our speed isn't defined. so
let me to define that now. Publicly expose a speed variable. I've got a public speed
and that's going to be a float. and I
want to start with a speed of say five.
And don't forget the f if declaring float
variables. And I'm going to do exactly
the same thing for the other direction.
and in fact if you want to pause now and
get that done. feel free to. Really it's
identical. GetKey now on the KeyCode. Now on the right
arrow. and once they've got that key code
sorted. I want to change the position of
my ship. with a positive speed in the
X-direction this time. So let's save that.
See what happens. so we can remove all the
stuff we don't need yet. We have an update function.
You move your keys. it'll move your ship
left and right. So we can adjust the
speed in the editor. and I'll show you a
little trick in just a sec to make that
speed frame rate independent. So let's
jump back into Unity. We've got a ship.
Let's play the game... [Fumbles Words] I did a boo boo here.
Yep. what else? Yeah. I forgot my if. it's
else if not just else. So I save that.
jump back into Unity. and try again.
And whoa. that's rather fast! Great. so we've now got our ship moving left and right.
We really need to be able to tune that. and
we thankfully have a speed.
Let me tune it in RUN Mode. and save that. Go back into my game and it's a lot more
reasonable. now. So we've got the ship moving left and right.
Let me jump back into my scene. to pause the game.
I might move it down a little. so it's at the bottom of my screen. If I go back to my game that's perfect!
If I play again... let's set the
default speed to 1. shall we. So jump back
into our code. Now. actually I'm going to do a little trick here. I'm actually going to
multiply my speed. I mentioned that I
would make its frame rate independent by
Time.deltaTime
And that means that's the time it
takes between frame updates. That way
if the frame takes longer to
render then. it'll always have a higher
speed. and if it takes less time to
render. it'll move by a lesser increment.
So let's try that to make sure that
we've got the right factor. given that we're multiplying
now by the Delta to the time between
frames. So if we jump back into Unity and press play.
We might find that that's now a little bit
sluggish. In fact. because we're now multiplying
by a small number.
Frames render really quickly. so let's change that default to something a
little bit more friendly for us. We jump
back into MonoDevelop and I'm going to put a
default of maybe say 15. Jump back into
Unity. Let's  test it out. Don't forget that if you
update the default but you've changed it in the editor itself it''ll not update.
So you'll need to update it here as well
Alright. ok that seems more reasonable. So let's do a quick recap. We have created a
player controller script. which controls
our little star ship which we just created.
and we've used the key getting and we've changed the transform to move it about
We've also made sure that
the position and the movement
speed is independent of the frame rate by
using Time.deltaTime. So we now
have a player controller script that moves our player about. So well done for
getting this far. Congrats! Hope you enjoy the video. and I will see you in the next one.
Bye for now.
=======
Kind: captions
Language: en
Hello, and welcome back! In this video
we're going to be building a spaceship.
So what about our spaceship? Well, we just want a spaceship we can control,
that's going to be our defender. He's going to be moving in the play space from side to side,
and that's what we want to do. So what's the first step in building a spaceship?
Well, the first thing I'm gonna do is I'm going to grab
some assets, and I found some brilliant
assets on a place called open game art.org.
and in fact, it's a great website for
your asset needs. In fact, we've bundled
all of those assets in our download at
the beginning of the section. If you want
to get ahold of it. Also if you want
to grab them yourself, they're all on this
website called open game art .org, and
we're talking about the space shooter
redux, and there's a whole bunch of space
assets and our laser defender is going
to be our little space ship right here. So
let's do it. Let's jump straight in and
get that done. We want to add the asset
and we've got it from Unity so I'm
just going to jump back into Unity, and I'm going to import some assets, so the way
I'm going to do that. I'm going to find them in my browser. I've got my finder here.
I'm going to go to the right place on my desk and grab the assets, so got laser
defender and it's going to be in the
bundle. And that's the bundle you download and it's
going to be in space shooter redux. Why it's all the way there on the right I have no idea.
So let's take a look and what assets do we want for our spaceship?
We're talking about the players spaceship, and I kinda like the look of the blue dude.
That blue guy is the one I like, so I'm
going to grab that and I'm going to drag and
drop it into my Unity editor. If I
grab it and drop it on the Asset Pane.
it'll create a sprite. I can actually bring it to
Assets. Let's jump in there. Let's see? Has
it been imported properly?
Yep, sprite 2D in the UI.
if it hasn't been imported as a 2D
sprite don't forget you can always
change that by going to the Inspector
and you've got the actual item selected
So I don't actually care about this scene
right now, so I'm going to jump back out
into my game. Save whatever changes I've made here. Let's get started with our 2D game. So the first thing we're going
to do is grab our sprite and drop him in.
So, we've got him in the play space. Let's zoom in a little bit, so we can actually see it.
Have we got a player ship here?
Yes we do. It's not huge. It's fine. We can deal with that. We'll recenter it, to make sure
it's all at the origin, and if I've got
that right and then I can
just double-click the ship. and here we are. So that's our player ship. So we've got this player.
He's going to be our little space ship, and our job is actually now to make sure we can
control him. We can actually get him
moving the way we want to, and in fact,
that is once you've downloaded his assets and imported them to Unity, that's your job.
and that's your next job. I want you to
add a script to your ship so drag and
drop a script or create a new script onto
your script. Call it PlayController that
script, and get it to move the ship left
and right with the arrow keys. You need
to make the speed adjustable in the
editor, because that requires a lot of
tuning. So pause the video now, and add a
controller script to your starship. To your
little starship sprite to make sure it
can move left and right, based on your
arrow keys. Now, I know this is a little
bit of a bigger step and challenge than
we're used to, but don't worry too much
don't stress out take it slow. Remember
to break it down into smaller problems. So add a script; add a function inside  your
update. Rather add an if statement inside your update that checks whether the right and left arrow keys
have been pressing. and if you're not quite
sure how to. Go back and have a look
at the Text 101 game we made, which uses the keyboard, and you'll need to find out
the key code for left arrow and right
arrow. And then once you've done that
it's a simple matter of changing the
transform's position. Modifying the
transform's position, the way we did in
Block Breaker for moving the paddle, so
take a look at Block Breaker code for
moving the paddle if you're not sure
and take a look at the Text 101 code for
grabbing the keyboard input if you're
not sure. And once you've done that,  I will see you and we will go through it together. So see you soon.
So here we are, we have our ship in our editor. How do we get a script on and get it to
move from side to side
based on the arrow keys? Well I'm going
to just add a component to my...  I've got
the ship selected. Actually I'm going to
rename it player ship one blue doesn't
sound good, so I'm just going to call it Player. Oops not play, but Player. So I've
got my player, and I'm going to add a component to it. That's going to be a new script.
there's going to be a player controller and that's the script responsible for controlling the player
and I'm going to edit that script now, so
here we are we have mono coming up, and
let's get this ship moving. So how are we
going to do that? Well you've seen this
before. We just go: if Input.GetKey
and we're going to go left and right arrow.
That's KeyCode with a capital K.
KeyCode. And it'll give you left arrow, so
that's moving my ship left. I want my
transformed.position to be  +=
a new. So I'm changing my position
by a vector, so that's X, Y, &amp; Z. And I really want to move it in some distance in the
X-direction, so I'm going to have, lets
say if I'm moving left I want a negative
X direction, so that's minus, and
that's going to be my speed of my
little star ship. And I don't
have this defined just yet but that's
ok. I don't want to move up. I don't want it
to move down, and I do not want it to
move in and out of the actual game world. So that's it. Our speed isn't defined, so
let me to define that now. Publicly expose a speed variable. I've got a public speed
and that's going to be a float, and I
want to start with a speed of say five.
And don't forget the f if declaring float
variables. And I'm going to do exactly
the same thing for the other direction,
and in fact if you want to pause now and
get that done, feel free to. Really it's
identical. GetKey now on the KeyCode. Now on the right
arrow, and once they've got that key code
sorted, I want to change the position of
my ship, with a positive speed in the
X-direction this time. So let's save that.
See what happens, so we can remove all the
stuff we don't need yet. We have an update function.
You move your keys, it'll move your ship
left and right. So we can adjust the
speed in the editor, and I'll show you a
little trick in just a sec to make that
speed frame rate independent. So let's
jump back into Unity. We've got a ship.
Let's play the game... [Fumbles Words] I did a boo boo here.
Yep, what else? Yeah, I forgot my if, it's
else if not just else. So I save that,
jump back into Unity, and try again.
And whoa, that's rather fast! Great, so we've now got our ship moving left and right.
We really need to be able to tune that, and
we thankfully have a speed.
Let me tune it in RUN Mode, and save that. Go back into my game and it's a lot more
reasonable, now. So we've got the ship moving left and right.
Let me jump back into my scene, to pause the game.
I might move it down a little, so it's at the bottom of my screen. If I go back to my game that's perfect!
If I play again... let's set the
default speed to 1, shall we. So jump back
into our code. Now, actually I'm going to do a little trick here. I'm actually going to
multiply my speed. I mentioned that I
would make its frame rate independent by
Time.deltaTime
And that means that's the time it
takes between frame updates. That way
if the frame takes longer to
render then, it'll always have a higher
speed, and if it takes less time to
render, it'll move by a lesser increment.
So let's try that to make sure that
we've got the right factor, given that we're multiplying
now by the Delta to the time between
frames. So if we jump back into Unity and press play,
We might find that that's now a little bit
sluggish. In fact, because we're now multiplying
by a small number.
Frames render really quickly, so let's change that default to something a
little bit more friendly for us. We jump
back into MonoDevelop and I'm going to put a
default of maybe say 15. Jump back into
Unity. Let's  test it out. Don't forget that if you
update the default but you've changed it in the editor itself it''ll not update.
So you'll need to update it here as well
Alright, ok that seems more reasonable. So let's do a quick recap. We have created a
player controller script, which controls
our little star ship which we just created,
and we've used the key getting and we've changed the transform to move it about
We've also made sure that
the position and the movement
speed is independent of the frame rate by
using Time.deltaTime. So we now
have a player controller script that moves our player about. So well done for
getting this far. Congrats! Hope you enjoy the video, and I will see you in the next one.
Bye for now.
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1:Unity/Section6/03-A-Starship-We-Can-Control.srt