So hello, and welcome back. In this video
we're going to be looking at how to add
enemies to our scenes, spawn an enemy, because we've got a player ship. If we take a
look at our game right now, we have a
player ship we can control, but we have
no enemy on the play space. So I think
it's time we added some. So what are the first
things we going to do? Well, we're going
to create an enemy prefab. Create
a spawner that will generate an enemy at
runtime or created an enemy when it
starts, and that's pretty much it. And in
fact, your first job is to create the
prefab. So go and dig into the bundled
artists download you got at the
beginning of this section, and make me an enemy prefab. So that will be whatever
ship you choose, whatever enemy ship
you'll choose as a prefab, that I can
dump into my game and use later. So
do that now. Pause the video and create
an enemy prefab.
So how about that enemy? How did it go? I'm going to create my enemy
prefab just about now. So the first thing I'm going to do... I'm going to grab import assets so [Humming]
I want to grab my new enemy sprite,
which I'm going to get from my assets. I can
look at that in the right repository. I
have got all my assets loaded in a
special repository down here.
My bundle of assets, in space shooter redux.
I go to my PNG folder, and which
enemy do I want? I've got an enemies folder. I think the
look of the black... the enemy black too looks quite threatening. I kind of like
that one. So that's going to be my enemy. And to bring it into our game, what do I do?  I drag
and drop it into my assets, and here
we go.
It's come in. It's come in as a sprite,
which is what I had needed. Which is
exactly what I want. I drop into my game,
and I've got an enemy. I'm going to rename it, this
dude, instead of enemy black 2, Enemy, to make it very clear. No confusion. And I want
that as a prefab. Drag it back, and I've
now got a prefab. I'm going to do some
organization now. I think it's getting a
little bit messy. I'm going to show you an
alternative way of ordering your folders
around. I'm going to create a new folder,
which is named Entities; if I can spell that
right. If you haven't thought... if you
haven't figured it out, yet my spelling
is pretty bad. I'm going to create a new
folder inside Entities, which is my Enemy. And I'm also going to create a folder
inside my Entities, which is going to be
my Player. So that's just an alternative
way of organizing your CEO assets, and I've got to grab everything that's to do with
my enemy. So that's my enemy prefab and my enemy sprite and everything else, and I'm going to put them
in my Enemy folder.  And I'm going to do the same with stuff that's to do with my player. I'm just gonna
grab all of that and put it in my
player folder.
Here we go! Cool! So now, we have an Entities folder,
with a player and an enemy. I've got my enemy prefab. So how about we get an enemy
spawning at the beginning of the game?
Create an enemy, an enemy spawner.
What's the first thing I'm going to do? Well, I'm going to create an empty game object. So in
my empty game object, I'm going to rename this guy. I'm going to rename him
to enemies or Enemy Formation, which is a way of saying that's the enemy that's now going
to attack me. And so my enemy formation, we want at the beginning of this game. We don't want
an enemy in the actual play space. I can delete that one. Remember, it accepts delete because
it's a prefab and you can tell because
it's blue. So I'm grabbing my enemy and I'm
deleting it, and I've got an enemy formation and the first thing I want to
happen in my game, is an enemy arrives at the enemy formation. So let's check out
where the enemy formation is. Well its at
00. That looks about right to my eye, to compare to my here ship, so that sounds
ok. And I want to export an enemy
so I'm just going to create a new component
called EnemySpawner. It's a script. It's a
C# script. Create and Add. And I'm
going to spawn an enemy at runtime. The
first... the only thing I want to do
is create an enemy. No auto-save has been found for this file. Wow, what is going on!
Well, I don't know I [Mumbles] use original file. That sounds about right. So here we go,
we've got an enemy spawner. On start I want to create a new enemy. So what I'm going to do...
use to create my enemy, is the Instantiate function, and this Instantiate function... If I can
spell it. Here we go, Instantiate. The first
thing it takes, and you can check it out
by opening the parent, is an object. And
I'm going to take in an enemy
prefab object,
which I don't have yet. I don't have that
defined... what that is or where that is.
I'm going to take a position and a quaternion. Now, you don't need to worry too much.
about what a quaternion is. It's basically about the rotation of the thing, but we don't
need to worry about that too much.
The vector 3 position is going to be a
new Vector3, not vector 2, and I'm
going to put it at the origin and my
quaternion I can put in, Quaternion.identity
And that will not have any rotational
effect. So what's this enemy prefab? Well,
I'm going to pass that into my editor,
through my editors, through drag-and-drop. So I want a public GameObject enemyPrefab.
Right! Awesome! So now I've got this enemy prefab. I can save it; save my script.
And no special characters coming randomly, because I'm typing the wrong thing on
my keyboard. So I've  got my enemy prefab. I go back into my editor, and that should
appear shortly. And then I can drag
and drop my enemy prefab into my script,
and on start i should see that. When I
play the game right now, there's nothing
there, but when I press play, drum roll,
yeah an enemy appears. Brilliant! So now, we've
got an enemy coming up in our scene.
Hopefully you managed to create the
prefab yourself. You've got so far, we
are asked to get the enemy appearing on
start. I want to make sure that, instead
of being at the top level here, my
enemy is under my enemy formation. Enemies are in a formation, and I want to keep my
scene hierarchy tidy, and so to do that
I'm going to change my scripts. So stop the play..
Jump back into my script. So I'm going to get my enemy, I wanted to be under enemy
spawner. So under the enemy formation,
remember the enemy spawner script is
attached to the enemy formation.
So the transform I've got access to,
within my enemy spawner, is the
transform of my enemy formation, and so
what I want to do is make sure that the
enemy gets instantiated inside the enemy
formation and to do that I once have... What
I can do is get my enemy out of
instantiate. So I want a GameObject
enemy, and that's the actual enemy that
we've just created here using instantiate.
And I have to here type, as GameObject,
because what comes out of instantiate is
actually an object and not a GameObject. So we need to tell it,
hey dude, this instantiate function is a
returning object. But actually I'm just going
to consider it a GameObject, and this is
what this as GameObject does. And the
syntax highlighting will catch up with
us I promise.
Space sheep [Laughs]. Here we go, the syntax highlighting has caught up with us now.
So transform, to change the enemy's
parent in the scene... in the scene graph.
Right, we can do
enemy.transform, and it has a dot
parent property and we can set this to
be equal to our transform. So that's
the transform of whatever this enemy
spawner script is attached to. In our
case that would be the enemy formation.
So if we save it now, and we jump back
into our scene and press play, we should
see that the enemy is spawned within
the enemy formation, neatly keeping
everything in its place. We've got an enemy formation and an enemy clone there. So brilliant! What
have we done? Let's take a look at what
we've done so far. Have we've built a spawner
that is attached to a GameObject and
that as a reference to an enemy prefab,
which it uses inside instantiate, so the
beginning of instantiate we pattern the
enemy prefab and create a new enemy? Yes, we have. We have built a spawner that takes in an enemy
prefab and creates it. Have we made sure that the new enemy we've just
created from the prefab template
is childed properly to a GameObject, so
that we keep our scene tidy and we know
where all the enemies are? Yes, indeed, we have. We've used the transform.parent
property to make sure that the enemy has
a parent of the enemy formation. So
that's it for now, in this video. We've now
happily created a spawner that will create
one enemy at the start of the game. We'll
be expanding on this a lot in other
videos, but for now, we've got this far.
It's a great starting point, so well done,
and I'll see you later! Bye for now!