Hi. and welcome back! In this video we're
going to be creating our enemy formation.
using position objects to define how our
enemies are going to form together. to
attack the player in our little Laser
Defender game. We'll also show you how to
use the OnDrawGizmos() function to show
the positions. which are virtual objects.
you know that don't already have a
physical embodiment in your editor.
while you're editing. so you know what
you're changing and what you're moving around.
So great stuff. we're going to start with
creating our position. and that's just going
to be an empty GameObject added to enemy formation. so the formation is a set of
positions within the formation. and then
we'll show those formations for you. So
let's do that now. If we jump into our
editor. let's remind ourselves of the
game we're working with. We have our
spaceship and when we have the enemy
formation. which has an enemy spawner
script which automatically creates an
enemy. when you press Start. and then we
start the game and we can see the enemy
on the screen and we can move left and
right and obviously our movement is
clamped to the side so that we don't go
out of bounds. So great stuff! So what are we
going to do next?
Well. I'm going to create an enemy
position inside my formation. and that's just like
creating an empty GameObject here within
my enemy formation. I'm going to rename that
dude. Position. and that's going to be one
of my position objects. within my
enemy formation. Now. I'm
going to do it a little trick here. which is
using the OnDrawGizmos function. to reveal that position to us. So right now. we
can see this position here. That's the
thing I'm moving here. but if I select
anything else in the play space of my player. the position immediately
disappears. Now. that's not where we want our enemy positions. We don't know
yet. So we want to show that position to
us while we're editing. and to do
that. we're going to use OnDrawGizmos and that's going to be in a script. A new. script.
which I'm just going call it
Position. and this  position script. if we
edit it
will have... and MonoDevelop is just
waking up. so be patient with it.
Here we go! So MonoDevelop will have a very simple script. We're not going to have anything on
start. We're not going to have anything on the update. The only thing we're actually
going to have is a void OnDrawGizmos function. And now what are gizmos.
you're saying? We've got gizmos!
What are gizmos? Well. if we jump back into
our editor. we can see what gizmos are.
If you click the little gizmos drop down in
your scene view. you'll see that there's
a bunch of different gizmos here.
shown to you in the editor. One of the
most obvious ones is the camera gizmo. If you
un-tick that box. you'll see the
camera gizmo is no longer here. and when
you press on the camera. it's just the
position and no longer the cursor. So you
can show all this stuff. so for example you can switch off the camera icon. as well as
hide the camera gizmo. And you can see
the difference in what happens. when I
click Yes or No for the camera gizmo and what happens when I click Yes or No for the
camera icon. as well. So those gizmos are
basically useful things within your game.
that are attached to objects within
your game. that are shown in the editor
but not in the game itself. And that's to
help you as a game developer. as an
engineer to design the game better; to
be able to say if you have way points. for
example those things are completely
invisible to the player but the enemy AI
will be taking them into account. and you
want to be able to manipulate them and
move them around. And that's what gizmos
are for. to show you things you want to
see as an editor and a game developer but
that you don't want to see in the game.
basically. So. OnDrawGizmos is where all the magic happens. Let me jump back into
OnDrawGizmos. and I jump into MonoDevelop. So this is the function that you need to do something
in to draw the gizmos. and I'm going to
call Gizmos. and you've got this in the
autocomplete. Dot! I'm going to draw a sphere. a wire sphere... Draw a wire sphere. and it'll ask
for two things. the vector 3 center.
which is a position for the center of my
gizmo's sphere and the radius of the sphere.
So my center for my gizmo is actually going be the origin of my object. the actual
position object. and the radius. I'm just
going to leave to 1 for now. And if I save
that script and then jump back into my
Unity editor. you'll be able to see that my
position gizmo now has a sphere around it. Can you see that's sphere? And so now. that lets us
show the actual position. even when we
don't have it selected. When I select the
player. for example. or I select the camera.
the sphere is still showing in the
scene view. but it will not show in the game view. So what's next? We've got this position.
Well. its challenge time! It's challenge
time! It's now your job to turn this
position I've just created. and then
you'll just create. into a prefab.
and then use the prefab to create a
bunch of different positions within the
enemy formation. Now. be creative about
how they're laid out. These positions
are how your enemies are going to be
forming up as a squad of enemies to hound
the player. to attack the player. So take
some time now to kind of create. let's say.
a W pattern or something interesting from
how the enemies are going to form up. So pause the
video now. turn the position to a prefab.
and then use the position
prefab to add several positions into the
enemy formation.
Cool! Let's get our positions
turned into a prefab. So the first thing
I'm going do is I'm going to grab my
position from my hierarchy. drag it into
my assets. and turn it into a position
prefab. Now. I've got this enemy spawner.
position position prefab. All those
things really belong into the enemy
formation entity. So I'm going to create a
new folder within an entity. which is going
to be a... my Enemy Formation folder. and all the stuff about the enemy formation. I'm
going to drag and drop in there. So I'm
grabbing all my things. and you can use
command or control click. to select
multiple items. and I'm dropping them in
my Enemy Formation. So that's great! So I've got the enemy formation. I've got the position.
Let's have a look at it in the scene. Let
me add a couple more positions for my enemies.
This is where they're going to be. I'm going to create a pattern. You can also duplicate
an object. and don't forget to put them in the enemy position GameObject. You can also
duplicate an object. if you've got it
selected. by typing Control + D or Command + D
on a Mac. And you can see another
position has been created. and how about
something like that. I think that Is a
good formation. that will attack my player.
and it'll looked quite interesting. I can
always move him about a little bit. Here
we go. So that's my formation. I've got a formation of six enemies hounding the
player. in this manner. So now I've got my
positions. I want to spawn an enemy on
top of every position. That kind of makes
sense now. doesn't it?
So let's jump back into our code. Here we go.  So we've got our new spawner. Right now it's not doing
much. except spawning a single enemy.
What I want to do is spawn an enemy on top of
every position. So how am I going to do that? How do I get the child objects of the...
the formation... the enemy formation from my code?
Well. the way I'm going to do that is to use the transform objects. So every game object
you've got has a transform. so that's...
You can access that transform via this.
We've seen it before when we've moved...
For example. above here we set the
parent of the enemy to be our transform.
so that's the transform of the enemy
formation. But what we can also do with our
transform. so that's the transform of the enemy formation. is to go over it for every child.
and the way to do that is for each. And
our children are actually going to be
transforms too... transformed too. We're
considering them to be transforms. For
every transformed child in. myself. my
transform. I want to do something. So you
might not have met this. for each. looping
construct before. but that lets you go...
Well. it's calling at the docks right now for
us. So it's for every item in the
transform. for the expression. You're
going to be able to... Your going to have a loop of
every item in a collection. essentially.
So if we... if we want to spawn an enemy. we
already have the code to spawn enemies
just above us. We can grab that code and
move it into the loop instead. So we delete it. and put it in our loop. and tidy this up a
little bit. And now. I'm instantiating
an enemy. for every child transform
in myself. So those are going to be my
positions. and I want to re-parent my
enemy to the child itself.
So instead of putting the parent of the
enemy to be myself. I want
the parent of the enemy to be the
child. So the actual outcome you want. if
we take a look at our Unity editor. is for
enemy prefabs to be spawned underneath a given position. within a position. So you
can see that. We've got the position here. and we've got an enemy inside the position itself.
That's what we want. That's the
behavior we want. So let me take out my
enemy. And do I still have six positions? Yep! And why... So why did the the enemy come up?
Take a look at what happens when I bring
the enemy to that position. Look at the
enemy. It's not on top of the position.
and the reason for that is. it has a
non-zero X and Y transfer value. And now it's
on top of the position. So let's double check that our enemy... Yep! If we have a look at
our enemy prefab. for some reason I
reverted it back to something to be
non-zero. I want my enemy prefab to not
have a position by default.
Cool! So now. when I put an enemy prefab on top of a position. on any position here.
it should be on top of the position.
which is great. That's exactly what we
want. So that's the behavior we want. So let me remove the enemy I've got here. jump back into the
code. and do that in code this time. So I
want the parent of the enemy of the
spawn to be the child. instead of myself.
Remember this is being called from the
formation and not from the position. So
if I save that now and I jumped back into
my game. I should be able to just press
play and see what happens.
Hmmm.. Not quite what we were expecting. Why have we got an enemy here. but none in...
any other place? Well. if we take a look
at the... hierarchy. we
can actually see that enemies have been
spawned absolutely everywhere. and really.
they're just only being spawned. if we have
a look at the hierarchy again. on top of each
other. That's the problem. So if I select this one. it's still the same enemy.
They're all spawned at 000. So why is
that? What's going on here? Why are we getting
enemies spawned in the wrong place? Well. if we take a look at our code again. So let's
pause the game. and jump into our code. We can see that here. we are instituting an
enemy at 000. which is the absolute 00.
That's the game space's 000. So really we we want
to instantiate enemies on top of their
actual parent objects. because once we
re-parent the enemy. which is what we do in
line 11 just down here. when we re-parent the enemy.
That will change the relative position or
change compared to be relative to the
parent now. So really we want to change that. So instead of spawning at the origin
of the games space. essentially the entire game space. we're going to spawn them at
the child's position. So that's going to
be child.transform.position. and
now if we jump back into our game. they
should let me jump back into Unity. And
if we press play again. we can see that
all the enemies have been spawned at the right... at
their right position. So that's great!
We've got enemies spawning in the right
positions. We should be quite pleased
with that. We've got the beginnings of
the game. They look quite menacing.
attacking the player in this formation. and so we are finished with this video. so
far. So let's take a look at what we've
done. Let's do a little recap of what we've
just done. We have looped every child
object within a given game object.
and thats by looking at the full reach
transform of our transform. which is how
you... the hierarchy of objects in the
scene is represented in code. that's
through the transforms and their
children. We've grabbed the transform to
position our enemy. and then we spawned
an enemy on top of every position we had
within our formation. So great stuff! Just to give an overview of the
entire video. we've now got an enemy
formation. which we can see with our eyes
in the editor. You can't see with your ears . so that was a little bit redundant. but we see it in
the editor by using the gizmos. We've got
a position prefab. and we've got it so
that we can spawn multiple enemies in a formation. So well done for getting this
far! Well done for watching. and hopefully you can see how we'll be turning this little
formation into a lot more menacing
formation of enemies that start shooting
the player in another video. But that's
all for now. Thank you for watching! I'll see you later! Bye.
=======
Kind: captions
Language: en
Hi, and welcome back! In this video we're
going to be creating our enemy formation,
using position objects to define how our
enemies are going to form together, to
attack the player in our little Laser
Defender game. We'll also show you how to
use the OnDrawGizmos() function to show
the positions, which are virtual objects,
you know that don't already have a
physical embodiment in your editor,
while you're editing, so you know what
you're changing and what you're moving around.
So great stuff, we're going to start with
creating our position, and that's just going
to be an empty GameObject added to enemy formation, so the formation is a set of
positions within the formation, and then
we'll show those formations for you. So
let's do that now. If we jump into our
editor, let's remind ourselves of the
game we're working with. We have our
spaceship and when we have the enemy
formation, which has an enemy spawner
script which automatically creates an
enemy, when you press Start, and then we
start the game and we can see the enemy
on the screen and we can move left and
right and obviously our movement is
clamped to the side so that we don't go
out of bounds. So great stuff! So what are we
going to do next?
Well, I'm going to create an enemy
position inside my formation, and that's just like
creating an empty GameObject here within
my enemy formation. I'm going to rename that
dude, Position, and that's going to be one
of my position objects, within my
enemy formation. Now, I'm
going to do it a little trick here, which is
using the OnDrawGizmos function, to reveal that position to us. So right now, we
can see this position here. That's the
thing I'm moving here, but if I select
anything else in the play space of my player, the position immediately
disappears. Now, that's not where we want our enemy positions. We don't know
yet. So we want to show that position to
us while we're editing, and to do
that, we're going to use OnDrawGizmos and that's going to be in a script. A new, script,
which I'm just going call it
Position, and this  position script, if we
edit it
will have... and MonoDevelop is just
waking up, so be patient with it.
Here we go! So MonoDevelop will have a very simple script. We're not going to have anything on
start. We're not going to have anything on the update. The only thing we're actually
going to have is a void OnDrawGizmos function. And now what are gizmos,
you're saying? We've got gizmos!
What are gizmos? Well, if we jump back into
our editor, we can see what gizmos are.
If you click the little gizmos drop down in
your scene view. you'll see that there's
a bunch of different gizmos here,
shown to you in the editor. One of the
most obvious ones is the camera gizmo. If you
un-tick that box, you'll see the
camera gizmo is no longer here, and when
you press on the camera, it's just the
position and no longer the cursor. So you
can show all this stuff, so for example you can switch off the camera icon, as well as
hide the camera gizmo. And you can see
the difference in what happens, when I
click Yes or No for the camera gizmo and what happens when I click Yes or No for the
camera icon, as well. So those gizmos are
basically useful things within your game,
that are attached to objects within
your game, that are shown in the editor
but not in the game itself. And that's to
help you as a game developer, as an
engineer to design the game better; to
be able to say if you have way points, for
example those things are completely
invisible to the player but the enemy AI
will be taking them into account, and you
want to be able to manipulate them and
move them around. And that's what gizmos
are for, to show you things you want to
see as an editor and a game developer but
that you don't want to see in the game,
basically. So, OnDrawGizmos is where all the magic happens. Let me jump back into
OnDrawGizmos, and I jump into MonoDevelop. So this is the function that you need to do something
in to draw the gizmos, and I'm going to
call Gizmos, and you've got this in the
autocomplete. Dot! I'm going to draw a sphere, a wire sphere... Draw a wire sphere, and it'll ask
for two things, the vector 3 center,
which is a position for the center of my
gizmo's sphere and the radius of the sphere.
So my center for my gizmo is actually going be the origin of my object, the actual
position object, and the radius, I'm just
going to leave to 1 for now. And if I save
that script and then jump back into my
Unity editor, you'll be able to see that my
position gizmo now has a sphere around it. Can you see that's sphere? And so now, that lets us
show the actual position, even when we
don't have it selected. When I select the
player, for example, or I select the camera,
the sphere is still showing in the
scene view, but it will not show in the game view. So what's next? We've got this position.
Well, its challenge time! It's challenge
time! It's now your job to turn this
position I've just created, and then
you'll just create, into a prefab.
and then use the prefab to create a
bunch of different positions within the
enemy formation. Now, be creative about
how they're laid out. These positions
are how your enemies are going to be
forming up as a squad of enemies to hound
the player, to attack the player. So take
some time now to kind of create, let's say,
a W pattern or something interesting from
how the enemies are going to form up. So pause the
video now, turn the position to a prefab,
and then use the position
prefab to add several positions into the
enemy formation.
Cool! Let's get our positions
turned into a prefab. So the first thing
I'm going do is I'm going to grab my
position from my hierarchy, drag it into
my assets, and turn it into a position
prefab. Now, I've got this enemy spawner,
position position prefab. All those
things really belong into the enemy
formation entity. So I'm going to create a
new folder within an entity, which is going
to be a... my Enemy Formation folder, and all the stuff about the enemy formation, I'm
going to drag and drop in there. So I'm
grabbing all my things, and you can use
command or control click, to select
multiple items, and I'm dropping them in
my Enemy Formation. So that's great! So I've got the enemy formation. I've got the position.
Let's have a look at it in the scene. Let
me add a couple more positions for my enemies.
This is where they're going to be. I'm going to create a pattern. You can also duplicate
an object, and don't forget to put them in the enemy position GameObject. You can also
duplicate an object, if you've got it
selected, by typing Control + D or Command + D
on a Mac. And you can see another
position has been created, and how about
something like that. I think that Is a
good formation, that will attack my player,
and it'll looked quite interesting. I can
always move him about a little bit. Here
we go. So that's my formation. I've got a formation of six enemies hounding the
player, in this manner. So now I've got my
positions. I want to spawn an enemy on
top of every position. That kind of makes
sense now, doesn't it?
So let's jump back into our code. Here we go.  So we've got our new spawner. Right now it's not doing
much, except spawning a single enemy.
What I want to do is spawn an enemy on top of
every position. So how am I going to do that? How do I get the child objects of the...
the formation... the enemy formation from my code?
Well, the way I'm going to do that is to use the transform objects. So every game object
you've got has a transform, so that's...
You can access that transform via this.
We've seen it before when we've moved...
For example, above here we set the
parent of the enemy to be our transform,
so that's the transform of the enemy
formation. But what we can also do with our
transform, so that's the transform of the enemy formation, is to go over it for every child,
and the way to do that is for each. And
our children are actually going to be
transforms too... transformed too. We're
considering them to be transforms. For
every transformed child in, myself, my
transform, I want to do something. So you
might not have met this, for each, looping
construct before, but that lets you go...
Well, it's calling at the docks right now for
us. So it's for every item in the
transform, for the expression. You're
going to be able to... Your going to have a loop of
every item in a collection, essentially.
So if we... if we want to spawn an enemy, we
already have the code to spawn enemies
just above us. We can grab that code and
move it into the loop instead. So we delete it, and put it in our loop, and tidy this up a
little bit. And now, I'm instantiating
an enemy, for every child transform
in myself. So those are going to be my
positions, and I want to re-parent my
enemy to the child itself.
So instead of putting the parent of the
enemy to be myself, I want
the parent of the enemy to be the
child. So the actual outcome you want, if
we take a look at our Unity editor, is for
enemy prefabs to be spawned underneath a given position, within a position. So you
can see that. We've got the position here, and we've got an enemy inside the position itself.
That's what we want. That's the
behavior we want. So let me take out my
enemy. And do I still have six positions? Yep! And why... So why did the the enemy come up?
Take a look at what happens when I bring
the enemy to that position. Look at the
enemy. It's not on top of the position,
and the reason for that is, it has a
non-zero X and Y transfer value. And now it's
on top of the position. So let's double check that our enemy... Yep! If we have a look at
our enemy prefab, for some reason I
reverted it back to something to be
non-zero. I want my enemy prefab to not
have a position by default.
Cool! So now, when I put an enemy prefab on top of a position, on any position here,
it should be on top of the position,
which is great. That's exactly what we
want. So that's the behavior we want. So let me remove the enemy I've got here, jump back into the
code, and do that in code this time. So I
want the parent of the enemy of the
spawn to be the child, instead of myself.
Remember this is being called from the
formation and not from the position. So
if I save that now and I jumped back into
my game, I should be able to just press
play and see what happens.
Hmmm.. Not quite what we were expecting. Why have we got an enemy here, but none in...
any other place? Well, if we take a look
at the... hierarchy, we
can actually see that enemies have been
spawned absolutely everywhere, and really,
they're just only being spawned, if we have
a look at the hierarchy again, on top of each
other. That's the problem. So if I select this one, it's still the same enemy.
They're all spawned at 000. So why is
that? What's going on here? Why are we getting
enemies spawned in the wrong place? Well, if we take a look at our code again. So let's
pause the game, and jump into our code. We can see that here, we are instituting an
enemy at 000, which is the absolute 00.
That's the game space's 000. So really we we want
to instantiate enemies on top of their
actual parent objects, because once we
re-parent the enemy, which is what we do in
line 11 just down here, when we re-parent the enemy.
That will change the relative position or
change compared to be relative to the
parent now. So really we want to change that. So instead of spawning at the origin
of the games space, essentially the entire game space, we're going to spawn them at
the child's position. So that's going to
be child.transform.position, and
now if we jump back into our game, they
should let me jump back into Unity. And
if we press play again, we can see that
all the enemies have been spawned at the right... at
their right position. So that's great!
We've got enemies spawning in the right
positions. We should be quite pleased
with that. We've got the beginnings of
the game. They look quite menacing,
attacking the player in this formation, and so we are finished with this video, so
far. So let's take a look at what we've
done. Let's do a little recap of what we've
just done. We have looped every child
object within a given game object,
and thats by looking at the full reach
transform of our transform, which is how
you... the hierarchy of objects in the
scene is represented in code, that's
through the transforms and their
children. We've grabbed the transform to
position our enemy, and then we spawned
an enemy on top of every position we had
within our formation. So great stuff! Just to give an overview of the
entire video, we've now got an enemy
formation, which we can see with our eyes
in the editor. You can't see with your ears , so that was a little bit redundant, but we see it in
the editor by using the gizmos. We've got
a position prefab, and we've got it so
that we can spawn multiple enemies in a formation. So well done for getting this
far! Well done for watching, and hopefully you can see how we'll be turning this little
formation into a lot more menacing
formation of enemies that start shooting
the player in another video. But that's
all for now. Thank you for watching! I'll see you later! Bye.
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1:Unity/Section6/05-Creating-Enemy-Positions.srt