So hi, and welcome back. In this video we're going to be getting the enemy
formation to start moving. Right now we
have a static enemy formation and it
doesn't look very threatening at all. So
let's change that. Lets make them attack
the player; hound them down. So the first
thing we need to do is we want to be
able to see the enemy formation, while we're editing, because right now we can't really see
what the formation is and where the edges
of the formation are. So what we can
do is we're going to add a gizmo to show
the formation, while we're editing. And
after that, we'll use the enemy's
formation update method, and then we'll
move it left or right
while we're in the update, leaving the player
no space to hide, so we can kind of
search in at the edges if the player
tries to hide. And finally we're going to
make sure that the formation does not leave the bounds of the play space. We don't want
the enemies to keep going past the play
space and miss the plane. So that's what
we're going to do. And, we're going to start with showing the formation in the editor,
using gizmos again and the width and
height of the formation. So let's get
started. Let's jump into Unity this is
what we have already. We have a formation,
which you can find here, but right now
it's just a transform with a script
and a bunch of positions underneath. So
let's change that. Lets go into the enemy
spawner script, and in the enemy spawner
script, we are going to first add
a width and a height to represent the formation itself, and those are going to be floats.
I'm going to set it... For now, I'm
going to make sure this is public, so we can
change it in the Inspector, and I'm going to
set it to something like 10 for now. I'm
not really worrying too much. I can
change those in the Inspector to make it
the right size, and I also need a height.
So public float height and that's going
to be 5. Here we go! Now, we have a
height and a width for our enemy...
spawner formation, and we're going
to jump into our OnDrawGizmo
function and add the formation gizmo there. So remember the public
void OnDrawGizmo? And here we want to create a new gizmo. So what gizmo are we going to
use?  Well we could use lines. Let's take a look at the gizmo namespace. All the
gizmos. We could draw a line, but
really we can also draw a cube, but a solid
cube will hide our formation. That's not what we want.  What we actually want is to draw a wire
cube. Drawing a wire cube will let us add an outline around our formation and show the
boundaries. So what's the center of our
formation gizmo? Well it's going to be
position of the formation itself,
right. So that's just going to be
transform.position. So that's the
center. And how about the width and
the height. So this vector 3 is going to
represent the width and the height. So it's
a new vector 3. We're just calling it in line.
Well what's the width? Well it's just width
isn't it?  We've already just defined it, up
here, in the class itself as a float. So
we can just do width and height. And we could also add
0 if you wanted to, but really we don't
care.
The constructor for vector 3 will add a 0 for us if we want it. And that is it. That is how
you add your draw gizmos. So, let's take a look at that in the game. Which I'm back into
Unity. It'll take a while to update, and
here we go. And now we have a box that
shows where the formation is, and if you select the enemy formation, we can see that the width and the
hight are here. And we can adjust those to be the right width and height. So something like that will now
cover all the positions
and that's how we're going to keep it
for now. So what's next? What's next? What's coming up next? What do we have to
do? Let's take a look at what's next, and
the next is your turn. It's in fact your
turn to move the formation side to side.
So we've got a formation script. Let's
remind ourselves what the formation
script is. We've just worked on it. We've
called it enemy spawner. We want to change the enemy spawner script, so that on
the update function, which is currently
empty,
you're going to move the formation side
to side.
And now this formation movement, you
want it to stop at the edges, so try and
figure out how using the same script, we
use the same kind of idea that we use for
the player, how to stop the formation from
moving past the edges and how to move it
from side to side. And whenever it hits one
of the edges, you want it to reverse
direction. So hopefully you can use the
player script for inspiration.
We've got a player controller here. So
the player controller has a bunch of
boundary detection already, so you can
inspire yourself from this and create
the enemy spawner. Make sure the enemy
formation moves from side to side. I will
see you very shortly, when you've done
that. See you soon.
So cool! Let's take a look at how to move
the enemy formation and make it
bounce off the edges. Let's jump back into
our Unity editor, grab the enemy
formation, and change the enemy spawner
script. So here we go, we've got the enemy
spawner script. That's probably not an
ideal name, but we might change that later.
For now, let's just change the update so that it
moves left and right. And the first thing
I need to do is select a way of
telling it, am I moving left or am I moving
right? So let's create a private boolean.
Boolean is true or false and we're going
to call it moving right. So this is the
boolean that's going to say moving
right, and I'm going to say our default
value is false. It doesn't matter what it
is;
could be true as well. It really doesn't
matter. What I want to do is, here in the
update function is to create an if
statement, so if moving right we want to
move the formation right. So how are we going to move the formation right. Well what we
could do to move the formation right is
do transform.position +=
So we're adding a little increment to the
position, in new
Vector3, which is going to be the speed times the time delta. So let's create a speed
variable. Let's create a float speed. That's the speed of of moving left to right, so that's a
public float speed. I'm going to call it
5 for now and make sure I've got a float symbol. I go
back down here, and lets do speed*Time.deltaTime. And that's in the
X direction, and that's going move right. So that's exactly what we're expecting. And what else
do we need to give once we've got that? The 0 in the Y direction, we don't want
the formation to move up or down. That's
not what we want, and that will now move
our formation right. Let's check it. Let's
make sure that's correct
by jumping into our Unity editor and
pressing the play button. That's right
that's exactly what we want, so cool! So let's jump back into our code. Now, if it's not
moving right, we want it to move left. So
else, we want to move left, and moving left
is going to be the exact same thing,
except we are going to be going the
opposite direction. So that is it. What
you could also do here is use
a trick of Vector3.left and Vector3.right
and that's the unit
vector going in one direction, and let me
show you that trick, right now, So this
will move left and right. We can also write
it like this. So that's Vector3.right
times speed times delta time. And that
reads much nicer actually, and this
Vector3.right object is really
a vector that
always points to the right. And similarly,
we have a Vector3.left object, which we
can use to move left.
So that's just an alternative, easier to read, way of changing your position. Let's check
the game to make sure it works, and yes
it does. So what's next? Well, what's next
is we want to stop the formation from
going past the edge. So what do we
need to do that? Well we've got the edge
of the screen, which is well defined, and
then, we have the edge of the formation
as well. So we'll need to be able to get
those two edges, compare their position, and then change the direction if they are
not... if the one goes past the other. So
let's jump into our code, and make sure we
have, in the start function, calculate the
edge of our screen. And we can do that
using a similar method that we used in the
player controller. That's by using
the Camera.main.ViewportToWorldPoint, and we use a new Vector3.
And we're on the left edge, so that's going to be 00. That's the bottom left-hand corner
remember, and we also want the last variable to be the distance... the distance to
the camera. And that should give us a 3 vector, which is the right edge...
Is that right? No, the left edge! That's the left edge! So let's call it Vector3, and then left edge.
Now, distance to camera hasn't been defined yet, so let's do that.
So that's float distanceToCamera = transform.position - Camera.main.transform.position.z
And we want the .z position in here as well.
So that's going to be the distance between the camera and the enemy spawner, the formation itself, which is going to
be what we use for our ViewportToWorldPoint
Now, some of you have rightly noted, in the
past, that you don't need to calculate
this because this is a 2D game using an
orthographic projection camera, not a
perspective camera. However, I want to
show you this way of creating this weird
strange vector, simply
so you don't get confused, when you come to doing this ViewportToWorldPoint
in a 3D space. So that's the method you
would use it in 3D space. In a 2D space,
like this with an orthographic camera, you
could have pretty much anything in there;
it wouldn't matter at all. However, I just
want to make sure that
the technique is correct. That way you
don't hit trouble when you try and
reproduce it for 3D space. So the left
edge and then, we want the right edge. And
naturally the right they just going to be
1 instead of 0. So now you've got this
left edge right edge. Let's create private
floats, which are the actual X values, and
I'm just rearranging my public and
private variables here, and then, you create a
private float xmax
and a private float xmin. So that's the
maximum and minimum value we are allowed
to go to, and we can calculate this by
going xmax = rightEdge.x and
xmim = leftEdge.x I think edge
might be a little confusing so let's
rename those guys to be left
boundary instead, and let's rename that
left boundary and right boundary. Here we
go.
Save it, and we can move on to the next
step, which is using those values of xmax
and xmin to decide whether or not
to reverse the direction So we've got this update
function. What we can do now is use xmax and xmin and compare those to our
current transform.position.x
and we can do it this way. So if the
our current position transform.position.x and then that's going to be
plus half the width. Let's remember that
the transform of the position is the
center of our formation, but actually you
want to get the right edge of our formation.
So let's actually break it down into some
variables. Float right so right edge
of formation is going to be transform of the
position.x plus, half the width.
Similarly, the left edge is going to be... so
rephrase this... the left edge of formation is going to
be transform.position.x minus half
the width,  and now what we're going to do is
if the left edge of the formation is
less than the minimum or if the right
edge of the formation is greater than the maximum
then, we want to flip the direction of
travel. Now, note here I've used the bar bar
symbol. That's the or. That means the logical or. That means either if this is
true... If the first condition is
true, or if the second condition is true
and those will be... If one is false and one is true, it will go into the if statement.
If they're both true it'll
go into the if statement. And then what do
you want to do? We want to reverse the
direction of travel, so now we're
controlling the direction of travel with this
moving right variable, which is boolean. So
what we want to do is turn a true into a false and a false into a true, and there's
a really shorthand way of doing that,
which is movingRight = not, and the
exclamation mark is a not symbol, it inverses the truth, truthfulness, of
whatever is afterwards. So I'm saying moving right is not moving right, and, basically
I'm assigning the inverse of moving
right to moving right again, so that will
flip the direction. So let's save that, jump
into our game, and press play and see
what happens. Compiler errors! Ooh, those are not good! Let's take a look!
Yep! That's right! 0.5f and
0.5f. Let's jump back and try and have a look. Here we go.
Brilliant! So now, we've got the formation
bouncing off the edges of the play space. Now,
notice my play space is actually quite narrow. I could have it being a bit wider. Let's
take a look. Let's go into my game. Change
the aspect ratio to something like
69 or even a free aspect and press
play, and then, we should see that they go all
the way to the edge. Now, you'll have to
fine tune, obviously, the edges and the
boundary condition and the speed and
things like that,
according to which aspect you're using
and what the size of your final game is.
This is going to be dependent on whether
you wanna ship to the web,
ship to the desktop, or maybe ship to
an iOS device. So you're really going to have
to worry about those things, when you
make the decision about which device to
go for.
What a nice trick. What you could do is actually
define the speed in terms of the width. So
you can get the width, because you can get
the edges of the play space, the
boundary conditions, and the width is
just 1 minus the other. That'll give you the width of the play space, and you can define your
speed based on those. So let's pause the game and take a recap of what
we've done so far. So we've done the move formation from side to side. That's great!
We've used transform.position and we've used Time.deltaTime to ensure the
movement is smooth. So using Time.deltaTime, if we jump back into our code to
have a look, is here in our code. When we
moved on the update.
We go speed times Time.deltaTime
The reason we use that is we want to make
the speed of our movement framerate
independent. We don't want to have the
speed depend on how often the update
function is called. We want the speed of
the movement to depend on a value we
give it, which is 5, and then
multiplying that by Time.deltaTime
will ensure that it'll always be the
right speed, no matter how quick or slow
the device we were running on is. So for example a player
running on a very fast computer isn't
playing against faster enemies than a
player running the game on a
slower computer. That wouldn't be very fair.
So that's why we use Time.deltaTime.  Now, we've moved the enemy formation
using the update. We've all done that.
We've created a gizmo to make sure the
formation is shown when we're editing. That's really helpful to see what exactly is
going on, and we've made sure the
formation doesn't leave the bounds of
the play space. So well done for getting
this far! I hope you've enjoyed it and I hope
you now know how to create a formation
that moves while bouncing off the edges
of the play space. I'll see you in the next
video! Bye for now