Hello and welcome back! In this video we're going to be looking at how to spawn
projectiles. We're going to be creating
projectiles from our player, so that
whenever the player, the the user, presses
space then there is a projectile
laser that's fired from our players ship.
And we're going to use instantiate to
create a new projectile every time, and
then give the projectile some velocity. So
your job is to create a laser prefab
from the bundled assets, and then use
that laser prefab, so that whenever
the player presses space you create a
new instance of the laser prefab. So you'll use instantiate as we've
done before, so that whenever the player
presses space,  you'll select space in
the update function and you'll
instantiated in new laser prefab. Ok so
let's get started. Right now we have a
player and we have a bunch of enemies,
but we don't care about the enemy's
right now. We just care about the player.
So the first thing I want to do is create a new instance a new
prefab for my laser. So how am I going to do that? Well I'm going to go to Import New Asset,
and then I'm going to go to my Laser
Defender asset bundle. So you
navigate to wherever is right for you.
I've got it in my Unity, Laser Defender.
There should be a bundle. Here we go.
SpaceShooterRedux. Open that up. I want the
PNG's. I want the lasers. And I'm going to go for laser blue 03. Now I've got a laser blue 03.
I've selected it and created it in my players
entities. I can dump it into my
scene. Bring it back into my editor, my
project pane rather, to create a prefab.
You can see that there's a black box
under prefab, that's just a sprite, and
you'll also see the actual item in the
hierarchy turns the color blue to show
you it's been turned into a prefab. I no
longer need an instance of it, so I can
delete that. Remove it from my place space. And now I've got my laser prefab, so awesome
that's great! We don't need anything else
for now. So now I need to be able to
spawn my laser prefab from my players
ship, and that's going to occur in my
player controller. So I've got the player, remember, prefab here, and I want to create in
my player controller a way of taking a
spacebar key press and turning
that into an instantiation. So the first
thing I'm going to do is... What do we instantiate?
I'm in my play controller. I'm going to need
some way of finding out what we
instantiate. I'm going to use a public
GameObject to do that. So I'm going to go
public GameObject beam or projectile. Let's make it much more generic. So I've
got a public projectile, and then I can
jump back into my game and drag the
prefab into the projectile slot created
into my player. Now, note here I'm adding it to
the player and it's gone bald, that's because I haven't applied the effect of the
prefab. So if I click on my player prefab you'll see that there's still in empty slot
where as my player itself has a
filled in slot. So I'm going to click Apply,
and now my player prefab also has the
blue laser set up. Now, I'm also gonna
rename this guy to call it player laser,
and hopefully this will not break
everything else. The projectile slot on
the player controller has actually been
renamed. Nothing's broken which is good.
So awesome! So now I've got my laser,
actually created as a prefab. We've got
the prefab linked to a projectile in the
player controller. The next step is to
launch it when you press space. So let's
create an if statement here to check for
space key presses. So I'm  going to go if,
and that's going to be same as before. (Input.GetKey(KeyCode.Space)) {}
Let me get that right. Here we go, KeyCode.Space. Then, we want to fire a projectile. So what do we
need to do to fire a projectile? Well we
need to call the instantiate method.
Instantiate takes in a game object to
start off with, so we're going to throw in
the projectile. And it also takes in a
position, and in which case we want to start
the projectile at the same position as
our ship. So that's going to be
transform.position, so that's the position of the ship.
Remember the player controller is
attached to the actual ship. So transform.position
That's a lowercase T not a capital
case T. And finally we want no rotational
whatsoever. We want it to be exactly the
same rotation we set in our sprite. I can
do Quaternion.identity, which
means I will not get any rotations. So
cool! So now we should be able to see
that whenever we press space we instantiate a
projectile. So you can see my
projectiles here, they're all over the
place. It's not very useful to see the
projectiles just standing there, but we're
going to change that very soon. What I want to do now actually is good to my camera and
change the background. I want a black
background, so that I can see my projectiles
much better. So let's take a look at that
now. If I press play, space rather, you can
see that my projectiles do come up, and
they are more visible against the dark
background. So cool! So now we've got
launching projectiles. What do we need to do next?
Well next we are going to want to have them go forward. Right? It's not sufficient to
just have projectiles spawned in empty air
and not move. So let's change that and
add the some velocity to our projectiles. So once we've created them we need to give them
some velocity. To give them some
velocity we'll need to actually get hold
of them, get a handle on our projectiles to
start off with. So we're going to want a
GameObject, and let's call it beam. The laser beam, is what we've just instantiated.
And I'll need put as GameObject
which is a bit ugly and a bit long, but
the reason for that is the instantiate
function returns an object. And we're
actually wanting a Game Object. So we're
saying we know what we're doing here. We
want whatever is returned by the
Instantiate function as a GameObject. So
that's the point.
So now we've got this beam. We want it to
move forward. So we can do beam.rigidbody2D
And then we'll need to
change the rigidbody2D to add a
velocity. So we don't want to add a force.
We want to change the velocity directly.
And we're going to do beam.rigidbody2D.velocity is a new
Vector3, not Vector4 but Vector3, and this Vector3 will be pointing up, so it will have 0 in the X direction,
and it will have the fire... the
projectile speed in the Y direction. So
projectileSpeed. Now note, I haven't
created projectile speed, so I'm going to
create another new public variable here.
That's going to be a float, so public float
projectileSpeed, and I'm going to set it to
nothing for now and we'll change that in
the Inspector. So I'm not initializing it;
I'm just going to be using it. And then here, back
in my update function, I can use the
projectile speed now. I don't want it to move
in the Z direction. We don't want it to
move into the screen. And that will
give some initial velocity to our beam. Now, of course we will need to change the player's
initial velocity. I'm just going to call it 5, and then we can press play and have a look at what that does.
So if I press space and we've got the
projectiles not moving, and the reason
for that is we have not attached a
rigidbody2D to the projectile. So let's
do that now. We grab the laser projectiles.
We'll add a component, and remember I'm
grabbing the prefab, and I want a rigidbody2D. Save everything. I'm going to say it is
not affected by gravity, so 0 for the gravity.
We don't want gravity messing around with
our movements. And save it and then try and play again. And now we can see that the projectile
actually goes forward. If I keep my spacebar pressed, you're getting a
lot of projectiles here! Thousands and thousands and thousands of projectiles
going out. So we want to change that. We
want to change it so it's only when we
press the spacebar. Not when it is
pressed, and to do that we use the
GetKeyDown instead. Now, there's a
difference between GetKey and GetKeyDown.
GetKey will fire if the key is pressed in. So if I press the key in it'll
start firing, and it will keep firing every update the key is pressed in. GetKeyDown will only
fire on the first update, when the key is
pressed down, and similarly GetKeyUp
will only fire when the key is released. So GetKeyDown is when it's pressed, GetKey
is when it is being pressed, and GetKeyUp is when it is released. So that's
the difference between the two. And if I jump back into my game, I can press play,
and now we should see that if I press
once then keep my finger on the
trigger it only fires one projectile. So I'm pressing the spacebar. I've got my spacebar pressed, but it's
only firing a single projectile. So and
that is it!  Now, we have a firing
spaceship that fires projectiles into
our enemy formation. Now, we want to do
more than that, because I don't like the
behavior of pressing once and only
getting one. I want to have a constant
rate the fire if I press the spacebar,
but I want it to be restricted. I want it to be limited.
I don't want to fire a new projectile every update, that's far too much. So let's change that
to a constant rate of fire whenever
the key is pressed. So let's jump back into our
code. And now we're going to first
create a fire method, which immediately
fires a projectile. So let's create a
void Fire(){} method, and this fire method is
really what we're going to use to fire our projectiles. Take all this out;
put it back in the Fire method. And now
of course, we could just replace what's happening,
on GetKeyDown, with the Fire method, but
however we're going to do something else.
Let's take a look at what we're going to be doing.
So We've done that. We're going to... We've done all this... What we're going to do is use the
InvokeRepeating() and CancelInvoke() to make sure that we are repeatedly firing the
projectile. Now, InvokeRepeating calls another method every interval, so we can
define an interval let's say every second and InvokeRepeating... will call that
method every second.
CancelInvoke() stops that process. So
we're going to use both of those
methods using GetKeyDown and GetKeyUp to whenever we press the spacebar we
start firing immediately and then keep
firing every X seconds, and then when we
released the spacebar it will cancel the
invocation it will stop repeatedly firing.
And there's a little trick I'll show you
to avoid a bug that often occurs when
you're delay is less than 0. So I'll
show you that straight away.
So, let's jump into our code. Now, we've got this (Input.GetKeyDown(KeyCode.Space)){} The thing
we want to do here is InvokeRepeating, and we want to invoke the Fire method. Now,
note this is a string, so I've got it in
quotes. It's a bit weird to call a string method,
but that's just how invoke repeating works. Now, the first time is
the time before the first invocation, and
we want it to be essentially 0. That's
our aim, however, because there's a slight
bug if you put 0 in this as an
argument what's going to happen is you
might get multiple invocations to start
with. We don't want that. So what we're
going to do is we're going to put a 0001,
a very small time increment,
making sure it's a float, and then that will avoid some of
the bugs that sometimes occur when you have a
0 time for invoke repeating. Then, we
have the repeat rate. Now, I don't have a
repeat rate, so I'm just going to imagine
that I have something called firingRate
and use that. And then I'm going to expose my firing rate as a public float in the Inspector.
That way we can tune the firing rate later
on when we need to. For now I'm just going to put 0.2
Cool! So now I've got the firingRate InvokeRepeating. Now, I do want to make sure
that if release the spacebar I stop the invocation of my fire method.
So I'm going to go if (Input.GetKeyUp(KeyCode.Space))
So if I release my spacebar
I want to cancel the invocation of fire, and we can do that by CancelInvoke("Fire") and now what I should see is...
If I jump into my game and press play. So if I jump into my game, press play, compiler errors...
Why is it a compile error? I've forgotten a f
somewhere, indeed, so I'm adding the little f.
Note I'm adding the little f here to my firing rate. Now, if I press play, what do I get? I've got the
spacebar pressed right now and I'm
getting a steady stream of beams of
lasers, but they are not going crazy, I'm not getting one every update. I'm only
getting one every X second, which I can
tune in the Inspector when I select my
player. So if I grab my player in the
Inspector, you'll see that I can tune the
firing rate here by increasing or
decreasing this number.
So cool! That is how you get a repeat
firing rate for your projectiles. That's
exactly the behavior wanted. That looks
good.
One final thing we want to do is, if we
take a look at our game now I'm gonna
press space and you can see the player
lasers are accumulating in our scene. There's
far too many of them, and they're not
dying off. They're not disappearing. So you want to
make sure that we don't get an infinite
supply of player lasers. There's far too
much. We don't need that. So what we're going to do is we're going to create a shredder
object. So we zoom out a little bit, and we
can move the scene slightly, create a new
empty GameObject, we rename it to
Shredder, and the purpose of the shredder
is to destroy everything that collides
with it, so it will need a trigger
collider. Let's find a Box Collider, so Box Collider 2D, and we will move that to a
trigger. So we've got a Box Collider 2D,
which is a trigger. We can select the
GameObject. We want to move it up.
Actually we want it to be well up above the
scene, or above the enemies at least. You can also change the scale to make it much
wider. You want it to cover the entire play space. I'm just going to select
a scale of 20. That should be sufficient
for now. My position... I'm just going to center my
position in the X direction... make it
quite big. So 10... 12 something like that,
and 2. I'm going to make it a little bit thicker for fast projectiles in the Y direction. So
remember position scale. I want it to be
maybe 3, maybe thick like this, to
make sure that the fast projectiles... make
sure they hit the trigger. Let's change the
name. I must have forgotten to press return. Here we go, now we've got the shredder up here. And the
final thing we need to add to our shredder is a script, and we're going to call it Shredder,
as well. That's not the cartoon character
from the Teenage Mutant Ninja Turtles,
thats just a mechanical machine. And then
in the Shredder, we're going to go void OnTriggerEnter2D
Now note the capitalization is
really important here, we need a capital
D and a capital O, or otherwise it's not
going to work.
And we are going to get a Collider2D,
and in this case what we're going to do
is destroy it. And how do we destroy
objects? Well, we use the destroy function. So I'm
destroying the object, but I don't want
to destroy the collider of what I'm colliding
with. I want to destroy the entire GameObject. So I'm going to grab the GameObject
from the collider itself, and here
we are, now we're grabbing the collider
from the game itself. We're grabbing the game object from the collider itself. Let's get this
the right way round.
Let's jump back into our game, and try it
out. So if I press play and I keep firing
bullets and let go of my spacebar, we should see them slowly disappear when
they hit the collider, or not, depending on
what we're doing. Why are they not disappearing?
Well, they don't have a collider
themselves do they? So let's take a look at our
projectile prefab, our player laser and add a collider to it. We're going to add a box
collider. Now, I want to double check my
box collider. So
let's instantiate in your prefab, and you can see that I was right to double check, because the
box collider is far too big. So once
we've got this player laser we want to
restrict the box collider to make sure
it's not too big for the laser. And we
can go down there and change the size.
Something like this seems pretty
reasonable. So I'm just tuning my collider to make sure it actually represents the
object and its not too big. And then I'm
going to make sure I apply these changes to my
prefab. And now we can see that the changes are no longer in
bold, because they've been applied to the
prefab. So if I
click on my prefab, we can see they scaled down in the prefab as well. So now I can delete my
player laser. I don't need that instance
anymore.
Start pressing play for the game, and now we should see that when I let go they get destroyed,
when they hit the shredder. And they do
indeed get destroyed when they hit the
shredder. And that is it for this video.
We've now destroyed the laser shots, when
they hit a collider, the shredder, and we
are done with spawning projectiles. We now can press space to spawn projectiles. We can in fact repeatedly
send projectiles by keeping the spacebar
pressed. And we've gone
on to use instantiate and given the
projectile some velocity and shredded
them, so that they don't clutter up our game space. And we're done! Thank you
very much for watching! Hope you found it
interesting and you can use this in your
own game,  and I will see you in another
video. Bye for now.