Hello and welcome back. In this video we're going to be looking at shooting our
enemies. Right now, let's remind ourselves slowly of what we have. Let's jump into our game and have a look.
We have a game where we can shoot lasers, but they are completely impotent to our
enemies. They don't actually cause any
damage. They don't strike the enemies.
Nothing occurs when they hit our
enemies. That's not what we want. So what
we're going to do in this video is turn that into lasers that cause damage to the enemies, and
to do that we're going to be adding a
Kinematic Rigidbody Trigger to our
enemy prefabs, and that will create an
event whenever it's collided with by the
projectile, by the laser beam itself, and
whenever that trigger is entered, the enemy will
take damage according to the projectile
component of our laser. So we'll add a
projectile script to our lasers. That projectile script will have a
public damage field, that's the amount of damage the projectile causes. So let's say if it's a big
massive laser that's the result of a power-up, it'll be a lot of damage. If it's the
normal laser it'll be a little damage, and
then we'll add this script as a component of
our lasers and we'll use that to cause damage to our enemies. And in fact, the first
thing I want you to do is to log a message,
when the projectile hits an enemy. I want
you to pause the video and make sure that
whenever you're using a kinematic rigid body
trigger, I want you to make sure that
whenever a projectile, whenever a laser,
hits one of the enemy's a message is
logged out to the console. So that's
whenever there's a collision a message is logged out to the console. There's a
bonus point if you can figure out how
to log messages, only when the projectile is
hit by a projectile object. And
there's a little hint here where you can
use the get competent projectile, and
it'll return either the projectile itself
or null if it doesn't exist. So pause the
video now, and try and get the enemies to
log out a message whenever a laser hits
them.
Ok! How did it go? Let's take a look at
how we would do that. So let's remind
ourselves we're trying to detect laser
collisions and log out a message
whenever we're hit by a projectile. So the
first thing I need to do is pause my
game, which is currently running. And I'm
going to grab my enemies themselves, so
let's take a look at our enemy. We've got an enemy prefab. Remember the folder
structure is so that the enemies are within the entities. Let's take a look at our enemy
prefab. Right now, we only have a sprite renderer. That's no good. We really want a
rigid body... Kinematic Rigidbody Trigger,
which means we're going to need a collider.
And let's take a look at what else.. We're going to need a rigid body on there. So let's find a
rigid body. And that's a 2D rigid body.
Remembered this is a 2D game. And we're going to
need a collider, too. So that's a 2D box
collider. And I'm using a box collider for simplicity's
sake. You could use a polygon collider to
make it a little bit more accurate, to
follow the outline of the wings, and
things like that, but frankly as far as
we're concerned a box collider will be
sufficient, because whenever the laser
hits it it'll be in the enemy, and we can
always change that later. So we now have
a Rigidbody 2D. Now, I don't want
my ships to have any angular drag. I don't want that, so I will set that to 0. And
they should not be affected by gravity, this is all in space. We have a fixed angle. This
is because we don't want them to rotate as a result of a collision, and
they are kinematic, which means we control how they move. Now, we have a Rigidbody
collider 2D, and it's got a size of 1 and 1, and I'm really not quite sure what that means. So
let's take a look. I'm going to create an
enemy in the game, and we can see here
the box collider has a green outline when you've got the enemy selected. And that looks
about right, and I'm happy with that,
so I'm going to delete my enemy from the game,
safe in the knowledge that my box collider in my prefab does what we want. So now we
have the box collider on the enemy. The
next step is
how do we detect the collision? So what
I'm gonna do now is, I'm going to go into
my enemy prefab, and I'm going to add a component. Now, that's going to be a script,
and it's gonna be a new script, and that's
going to be enemy behavior. So that enemy
behavior is going to... Whenever we're hit by a
projectile, by anything in fact, I'm going to log out a message. So let's try that now.
Let's go into my enemy behavior script. And I don't need start. I don't
need update. I don't really mind those two functions. In fact, I'm just going to remove them. We
don't need them for now. What I do need is
a void OnTriggerEnter2D
And because it's a trigger let's... I forgot to do something quite vital
for this to work. I save the script. Let's jump back into our game. I have not set my
collider to be a trigger collider. So I'll set my collider to be a trigger
collider. Now, I'll jump back into my script. OnTriggerEnter2D Well what do I want
to do? And let's not forget that OnTriggerEnter2D takes in a collider. And that's a collider
2D, because we're working in 2D, And that's
the collider I'm colliding with, and
I now want to, whenever I hit a collider,
I'm going to log it out. So that's Debug.Log(Collider);
And I'm just going to log out the collider I've collided with. I think that will be
fine. So let's try this out in the game and
see what happens, when we run this. So we've
got the script attached to our prefabs, so
whenever they're generated they will do
something. Let's take a look at our console.
Let's clear on play. We don't want to
collapse, we want to see all the message. Let's press play, and right now there's nothing
happening. And here we go, whenever lasers hits our enemies, there's a log message
that comes out, which is great that's
exactly what we want. And we've got a
Box Collider2D result. Great! So now comes the little bonus point, which is I only
want this to occur whenever we've
got a projectile that actually hits our
enemy. If something else collides, we don't want to trigger the behavior. So what I'm going to
do is I'm gonna look at my players... the
player's laser, and on the player laser...
I want the player laser prefab, not the sprite.
And we don't have a script, so I'm going
to add a script. And I'm going to add a
projectile script, and this projectile
script is going to be a general script
for all projectiles and it's going to be
really simple. So let's open this up and
have a look. We don't want anything except
the public damage for the moment, so public
float damage, and I'm going to set it to 100 by default. There's no reason why it should
be anything else. I don't mind. Let's not forget it's a float. Right! So this is our entire
script! Very complex script right! But
really it's just to, for the moment, say
this is a projectile anything that has
this is considered as a projectile, and
we should trigger the projectile behavior whenever we collide with something that is a projectile.
So if we jump back into our enemy behavior script now, I want to check whether the
thing I'm colliding with is a projectile,
and to do that I do collider.GameObject.
And that will be the game object we're colliding with. So right now what we're getting is a collider,
so it'll be the... let's say the
rigid or the BoxCollider2D or
the PolygonCollider2D. Whichever one of
those, it's going to be a collider we get
back in the OnTriggerEnter2D. That's not really what we want. So we
need to get the GameObject out, and extract from the GameObject
another component. And the way to do
that is to use the GetComponent method,
and I want to get a projectile component,
so I'm calling it with the projectile
types. I'm saying,  I'm grabbing the colliders, I'm grabbing the game object of
the collider and from that GameObject I'm
grabbing another component. Basically, it's the
child of a GameObject, which is the projectile component, and
that's going to be a projectile missile.
Now, that's what we are looking
for, and if it doesn't exist this get
component method will return null. Now, I can check whether the missile
exists. If it doesn't that means the
collider I'm colliding with did not have
a projectile component. So let's say I'm colliding with another...
another ship... I'm colliding with a
player... I'm colliding with something else.
It doesn't matter, I'm just colliding
with something else. And the way to do that, I can just
check if(missile){}, which will mean if
missile exists, and is not null,
unknown, or false value then, I can do
something. And then I'm just going to log
out into my console, Debug.Log("Hit by a projectile") Let's make sure it's a string. Not
projectiles, projectile. So now I can save
this, and it won't really change the
behavior of what we saw in the game. Let's jump back into our game. Press play
again. We should still see, in the console,
the same messages, but now we know it's a
projectile, because it has... its checking
for the projectile component. If I remove
the projectile component from my prefab,
let's say for a moment I remove this
component. I'm doing this in the game in
the green mode, in the play mode... and
now I fired again. You'll see that there are no longer any debug objects.
I'm not getting the scrolling. The
console isn't scrolling, because it doesn't
have a component. I add the component again, so let's add a script, and let's call it...
What was it? It was projectile.
We add the projectile component again, and we start shooting again. And now you can see
the console is now scrolling again and
the number of messages goes up, which it
didn't when I didn't have the script. So
great that's fantastic, we can stop the
game, and we're happy with how this is
working out. Now, we've really done a lot
of the work we needed to. So let's recap!
Briefly how do you get
this behavior working? Well we've got the
OnTriggerEnter2D() to detect collisions. We
checked that something that's built into
our enemies is a projectile component, and
now comes the interesting bit. Now,  comes the bit where if we do... if
it is a projectile component, we're going to damage ourselves. So we're
introducing the concept of health. Our
enemies have health, and whenever we are hit by a projectile, we reduce our health by the
amount that the projectile has. And to finalize everything, we're going to call the
projectile and we're going to call the hit method of the projectile. Thats to tell a
missile... say we've been hit, we've taken the damage, it's time to end
the missile. Otherwise the
missile will continue on its way because
it's a trigger and wouldn't destroy
ourselves. And then the hit method is when
we will be, in the future, doing things
like animating the explosion of the
laser and things like that. So for the
moment let's jump back into our code.
Let's grab the projectile script. Right
now actually it's in a... it's in the wrong
place. It's in the Asset folder directly... because it's a general script that
applies a lot of things, I'm going to move
it to Scripts. The enemy behavior really
belongs to my Enemy folder. It's really about the enemy. So I'm just going to move it to
Entities Enemy. And my shredder script
is also a general script, it doesn't
really belong to anything. It's a very
general utility script. I'm just going to move it to Scripts.
So that's a little bit of a tidy up for
our assets. So let's
jump into our projectile script, which is
in the general scripts, and in the
projectile we're going to add... don't save.
Yes save. I'm not sure why he's asking that for, but
that's ok. In the projectile script we
can now add a new void method, which is
going to be hit and it will take nothing, and that's just to signal the
projectile that we've just hit an object. You know it's entering a trigger will
will say, hey, you've just hit an object,
now it's time to do your thing. So how do
we do...  What do we expect to do? Well
really we expect the projectile to...
We expect the projectile to destroy itself, so we'll do Destroy and destroy the GameObject.
So now we're destroying the GameObject. For some reason it's not... We've got a problem with Mono
behavior here, not recognizing something. Let's just save it and build it. Seems to be ok. It's
red for some reason, I'm not sure why.
And also we are going to create another
method. We're going to create a void GetDamage(){} function, and this get damage...
Let's capitalize it the way we wanted
to. This GetDamage function will, in fact,
return the damage we deal. So that's a
very simple return damage, and that's
just so to make our calling convention nicer. We don't really want to be messing
around with variable... and that's not void
actually, this will be float, if we're
returning the damage. So if we don't
really want to be twiddling the damage
property attribute from our... from the
code... from the enemy code itself. So let's
jump back out, and this time let's take a
look at...
Woo, it doesn't like... Something does not
like that. Let's take a look at what's
going on here.
I think I should not... so right. I think it has duplicated the projectile script, so
if you ever seen an error like this,
"the namespace global already contains a
definition for projectile" That means
it has duplicated a script. I'm just going to delete the old one, so
that we only have one in the Scripts folder.
So right now comes the turn to make the
enemy behavior handle the damage dealt
by the laser. So let's jump into enemy
behavior, we grab the enemy behavior
script, and if it's a missile then we can
say, if it's a projectile, we can say let's
pretend we have health.  health -= so I'm reducing the health
by missile.GetDamage(), and it'll be GetDamage. That's the right one? Yep, GetDamage
Oh, and let's make sure that get damage is
public. Let's make sure that both GetDamage
and Hit are public, otherwise, we'll never be able to call them from the outside.
That's why they're not coming up in the
autocomplete. So let's save
this one. Let's save our projectile script, jump back here GetDamage, and if the health is less
than equal to 0 that means we're dead. If
health less than or equal to 0 then we
want to destroy ourselves. Let's make
sure everything is spelled properly, and
let's do Destroy(gameObject) Here we go. Now health is
red. I haven't got the concept of health yet, so let's create.
a public health float. That's my hit points essentially, and that's
going to be equal to let's say 150, so you have to hit an enemy twice at least to destroy them. Now,
I'm doing it to 150. Do whatever you
want, this is really about play tuning
when you come to balancing the game, making sure the game is fun.
This is really where you want to be able to
twiddle those numbers. For the moment it
doesn't really matter, we're just building the
infrastructure, and we can do some of the
play tuning later. So I can remove the
Debug message, and we should see that now
if an enemy has been hit twice by a missile, then it will be
destroyed. And let's not forget we need
to tell the missile we've collided,
and I'm going to use the hit method. And
I'm going to do that,
not if the health is less than 0, but
always. So I'm just going to give the damage and
call the hit method. So that's missile.Hit()
And now, because we made it public
it comes up in the autocomplete. So
great let's jump back into our game, and
see what that all means, it's a bit abstract
right now. Let's see what that turns into. So
if I press play... here we go!
They get hit twice, and notice you'll need
two shots, and they get destroyed. And
that is essentially the end of this
video. We have, just to recap, we've got the
enemy responding to a projectile when it enters and hits them. We are
using a Kinematic Rigidbody Triggers for
the enemies. And we went over the missile
is entering the trigger, we're taking
damage, and notifying the missile to do its
animation. So that's it for now. That's it for this video.
Congratulations on getting this far! Hope
you've enjoyed it, and I will see you for
the next one! Bye for now.