Hello, and welcome back! In this video we're going to be looking at how to use layers to
control collisions. So we have some problems in our game. The first one we had
was, the player shoots itself when its
firing. The lasers from the player and
the enemies collide with each other, when
the projectiles from the enemies hit
other enemies and kill them, which it
makes the game, too, easy if the enemies are
shooting each other. So really we want to be able to control the collisions of those
projectiles. We want to be able to control
the collisions in our game in a
structured way, to say these things
collide with these things, and these
things do not collide with these things.
So let's, without further ado, take a look at
layers. So we've got a game here, and if I go back to my scene view and next
select my player, you will see this on
the top of the Inspector. You will see this layer
drop down, and right now, the layer has a
bunch of different ones and this is the
layer we're going to be using to change how collisions work. So let's without
getting started, we can see we've got
some layers here. Without moving
anywhere else... Without me doing anything, we're going to add a new layer. So we've got the
player selected. So let me create a new
layer, and you'll see you'll be taken straight to the
Tags and Layer View. That lets you
configure tags and layers, and you've
got different options. You've got tags, you've got
sorting layers, and we will go over those
in some other videos. For now, we're just
worrying about layers and they're useful
collision. So, right now, I've got a player.
I'm going to put my player in a new layer called Friendlies, and this
layer will be about all my friendly entities. And at this point, we've got a
Friendly Layer, and the player itself now
can be added to the Friendlies
Layer. You should see that, in the
Inspector, there is now a Friendlies
Layer coming up when you click on the
drop down. So let's do that. So what does
that mean, then? Well, the Friendlies Layer
lets us select how any
item, that has been attached to that layer, will react
with collisions. Let's take a look at how
we do that, now.
So if I go into my Edit Menu, I go into
my Project Settings, and I go Physics 2D.
Remember this is a 2D world,
there's the exact same options for 3D,
but in fact,  because we're in 2D we're using 2D components. We can see
we've got a Rigidbody2D; we've got a modified Physics2D. And here, at the bottom
of the Physics2D Inspector pane, you can see this little matrix of
check boxes, and what this matrix of
checkboxes does is it
lets you select what collides with what.
And at the moment, everything collides
with everything else, right? And you can
see that if, for example, I unchecked
Friendlies with Friendlies they would,
now, stop colliding with each other. So
the friendlies, anything that's attacked
friendlies, would stop colliding with
anything else that's also attached to the
Friendlies Layer. So that's how you
control
collisions in a game. So, now, really it's
up to you. Now, you're next job is going to be
to move the enemy... to create the Enemies and any projectiles and Friendly
Projectiles Layer and make sure that all the prefabs in the game are added to the
right layers. So, for the friendlies, I
want just the player ship. For the
enemies I want the enemies to be added
to that layer, and the enemy
projectiles should be the enemy lasers
and the friendly projectiles should be
the friendly lasers. So this is your job
now, to go around,  just the way I've shown
you. So feel free to rewind and play
again to see how I adjusted it
to put all the right GameObjects and prefabs in the appropriate
layers. So you'll have to create three
new layers thats
Enemies,  Enemy Projectiles, and Friendly
Projectiles, and you'll have to add all
the right things to them. So, I'll see you
very soon, when you've done all that. See you then.
Ok cool! So let's show you how I would do that. So let's jump back. I've already got one layer, and
you can always look at the layers by going to the Project Settings, just
like you do for Physics2D, but instead of Physics2D you go for the Tags and Layers
Menu. And you'll see that, now you have
the layers in the Inspector. I'm
just going to create all my layers here. So we've got enemies, we have enemy projectiles,
and we have friendly projectiles. So why
are we doing this? Why are we doing all this?
Friendly Projectiles. Well, we're doing this,
because we want to be able to control
collisions. We don't want things to collide, when we don't want them to.
The only thing we want to collide with
each other are the enemy projectiles
with the friendlies and the friendly
projectiles with the enemies', right. We
don't want friendly fire or anything
like that. So let's get going with adding
everything to the right layers. I'm just
going to  jump into my Entities, grab my
Enemy, so that's my Enemy Prefab, and change the layer in my prefab to Enemies. I'm going to
do the same with my enemy laser. I'm going to change the layer to Enemy
Projectiles. Now, I'm Jumping into my player. I'm going to grab my Player Laser Prefab. Remember it's
not the sprite, but the prefab. I'm going
to add that to the Friendly Projectiles;
similarly for my player. I've got a default, because I didn't apply my change to the player objects.
I'm just going to set that to Friendlies,
so now, I've got all four objects in the right
layers. So now, if I jump back... if I save
this game, now Command Save to save my
scene. If I press play the behavior
really hasn't changed at all, we really
haven't changed... although you'll see that this is happening, right here. We've got...
some projectiles are colliding with each
other, which is definitely not what we
want to happen. So now, how do we get the projectiles to not collide with each
other. That was a perfect example of projectiles colliding, because there's
projectiles moving downwards and projectiles moving upwards. They collide, they stop,
and then, they get stuck. So now, we're
going to go into our Project Settings, our
Physics 2D Settings, and we have
this matrix at the bottom. Now, remember I unchecked Friendlies with Friendlies.
That's exactly what we want, and we want to change the bottom of that matrix, with
the friendlies, the enemies, the enemy
projectiles, and the friendly projectiles.
Let me make that a little bit wider for you, so we can see what's going on. Here we go! And with that
matrix, I want to deselect everything and
keep only two collisions. So, the only two
collisions I'm going to be keeping, so I'm deselecting everything and then I can
reselect it by hand. The only collisions I
want is friendlies, with the enemy
projectiles, so that's this one here, and
then, the enemies with
the friendly projectiles, which is this
collision right here. So now, I've got my
two collisions going. That should have the behavior we want, and we can try that,
now. That should be all correct. Everything should be working as we
expect it to, but now it's difficult to
get the case to happen to occur. But
now the collisions between say my enemy
projectiles and my friendly projectiles,
simply won't occur, so we'll never get that case where two projectiles hit each other and
get stuck in the middle of the game. And
we can check this by, let's say, disabling
the friendly projectiles and... or rather, disabling the friendlies and
enemy projectiles, and you'll see that I
do not get hit by the enemies, rather they go
right through me. I don't whether you can notice that, but now, I've disabled the projectiles and their
lasers go straight through my player's
ship. So that was it! That was a nice short
video! Let's reenable that, make sure
I don't forget it.
Reenable, save my scene, and that was a nice short video to show you how to use
layers, to control collisions within your physics settings. And remember, this is the same
in 2D and 3D, so you can do exactly the
same in your 3D world, when you make a 3D game. So that was it.
Hope you enjoyed that,  hope you found it useful, and I will see you in another video!
Bye for now.