Hello, and welcome back!. In this video,
we're going to be looking at how to
detect the enemies have been destroyed.
So we need to know when all the enemies
are dead, so that we can add in the
other enemies to a new formation or to
add enemies to the formation that's now
empty. We're to going to use the
childCount property of a transform on
the positions. So basically, a childCount
shows you how many objects are inside a given object, and the transform has that
property. And an empty position, so we've created those position objects with an
enemy inside. When their position is empty, we have a dead enemy, and then,
when that happens when we have an empty array of positions, all the positions are empty,
we're going to respawn the enemies
when they are empty. So how are we going to do that?
Well, we're going to go for transform.childCount, and we will be looping over
every position. Then, we'll show you how to loop over every object inside another
object, in the hierarchy, and we'll kind of
encapsulate all that information in the
AllMembersAreDead()
method. So, let's get started! So if I jump
into my Unity editor, we can see what we
have already. If I press play, we see that
the enemies are currently here, they can be
shot down, I could shoot them down, and
they should be able to shoot me down as
well. If I take enough hits, I'm going to die.
I'm trying to get hit it's actually harder,
here we go, and then I die. So what I want to do is have the enemies respawn, recycle,
when I've killed them all, which they don't
currently do. So the first thing I'm
going to do, is I'm going to go to my enemy formation, and the enemy formation has an
enemy formation controller... a formation
controller script. So in this formation
controller script, in my update function, I'm going to check for all the enemies being
dead, and the way I'm going to do that is I'm going to call the AllMembersDead() method.
So if AllMembersDead,
then, I want to log something out to the console. Debug.Log ("Empty formation");
There we go. So now, I need to write this all members are dead
function. So AllMembersDead is going to
be a Boolean function, it'll return true or
false, that's bool and AllMembersDead. Here we go, and now, I need to look inside
the formation for every position, so
let's remind ourselves really what the
structure of the formation is. If we jump back into Unity, we have an enemy formation, and inside
the enemy formation we have a bunch of
positions. And when we press play, pause
the game, we can see that every position
has an enemy inside of it. So what we need
to do is, we need to loop over every
position in the formation and check
whether the position has a child... has an enemy. So let's jump back into our code, and we
can do that this way. So foreach(Transform child
PositionGameObject, which is what we're iterating over. Already, we're grabbing the transform
component with these... in transform{}. Now, that's going to seem a little weird, but what we have
here is my transform. The formation
controller is attached to the formation
GameObject. If we take another look at
our Unity, we can see that if we click on the
formation controller it's actually
attached... the formation controller
script is actually attached to the enemy
formation GameObject. So if we jump back
the transform of the formation... enemy
formations... the transform of the enemy
formation is going to be what we iterate
over, what we loop over, to get all the
position. So it's a bit weird that the
transforms are what keeps the child's
and the parent of, you know when you
structure your hierarchy, is done through
the transform, but that's just how it is. So that's what we're doing, we're going over
every child position in the transform of
the formation. So in there, now, we've got
the child formation childPositionGameObject...
childPositionGameObject... We can grab the childCount, and that's going to tell us how
many GameObjects that has. So, if I go for AllMembersAreDead; if I did, say
transform.childCount, at this level here.
transform.childCount. We're expecting
this to be, let's take a look at the game,
123456. We have six positions, we're
expecting this transform.childCount
to be six, right, and then, for the child
that's going to be one of the positions,
inside the position. We're expecting the childCount to be either 0,
which means a dead enemy, or 1, which
means a live enemy. So, what we want to say is,
if all members are dead what we are
actually expecting is if childCount.position...
So if the child count of my position, if there is an enemy, is
greater than 0, we return false, right,
because if there's any position with a
child in it, that means that we have at least
one live enemy, which means that not all
members are dead. And then, if we go
through every single object in our list,
so every position in our formation and
there are no children, or basically we'll get to the bottom of this loop so we'll
go through that for each. And then...
we'll reach the end and then at the
end we go return true; every member is dead, and that's how you check if all enemies are
dead or not. So let's see whether that
works in the game. So if I stop that, stop
playing, play again. Then, I'm going to have to kill my enemies. I really should make
that job easier for me, make them have
really low health, but yeah, especially
especially if they kill me first, right! [Laughs] So, there we go! Let's try and kill all the enemies, here we go. And then, we look at the console, and we
should be able to see an empty formation. So, that's exactly what we're expecting, and
note that counts... the empty formation count keeps going up because we're doing it
every update. That's ok for now. Later on, we'll trigger an action that stops the
formation from being empty, but for now, we're just checking that the formation is empty
and logging it out to the console on every update. Ok, so in fact, what we do next
is for you to respawn the enemies, when
the formation is empty. We already have
the enemy respawn code, that's all in the
start method of the formation
controller. So what I want you to do now
is grab that code, turn it into a
function, and then call that method
both in the start and in the...
whenever the enemy formation is empty. So go do that now.
So pause the video and try and create the respawn functionality when
all enemies are dead, and I will see you very soon.
So how did it go? Let's take a look at
how we would add the enemy spawning to
our code. So if I jump back into Unity, I can grab the formation controller code, and I've
got this AllMembersDead function. And what I want to do is extract the
functionality that spawns every enemy
into its own function, so let me create it
here. And I'm going to call it a void
function, because we return nothing, and
it's going to be SpawnEnemies(){}. Here we go.
So now, we've got spawn enemies. I can extract this for each loop, take it out, and put it in
spawn enemies, and then, call spawn
enemies from my formation controller start
function. Here we go. And I can also do the same when all my members are dead. So
empty formation and then spawn enemies, and now, the behavior should be that
whenever I kill all my enemies
they immediately respawn together. So let's take a look at the game and see whether our
expected outcome is really what happens. So I'm going to try very hard not to die. I'm
killing a bunch of enemies, and when I
kill this guy, we should see that they
all come back at once. And that's exactly what we see. So that's it!
That is how we spawn our enemies, once
they've all been destroyed. So, well done for
making it this far! This video was quite short. Hopefully you'll understand how it's quite
useful to use the Transform.childCount property, because that tells you how
many things are inside of it in the
hierarchy and how we're using it
currently to check that all the enemies
are dead. So that's it! I will see you in
the next video! Bye for now.