So, hi, and welcome back! In this video,
we're going to be animating the position
of incoming enemies. Really, we've got a
game, right now, and the enemies
kind of just pop into existence, which is really not what we want. So, instead of that,
we're going to be using the animation
for the first time and getting our
enemies to animate and to fly in
menacingly and attack the players.
So, how about we get started. Let's get
going!
Where would we start? We've never
seen animation before, so this is the
first time we've done animations. Where would we get started? Well, the first thing we
need to do, we're going to animate the
enemies, so we need an enemy. Right now,
we have no enemy in our scene. Remember,  they're being generated at runtime, so the
first thing we want to do, is grab an Enemy
Prefab and drop him in our scene. So, let's
zoom in and see this guy here, and right now, we can see in the Enemy Prefab, we've got
the script for the behavior, we've got a
Collider RigidBody, etc. What we don't
have is anything to do with animation. And
so, how am I going to create an animation
on my enemy? Well, I'm going to open up a
brand new pane, which was never seen
before, so I'm right clicking on my pane. Here we go, add a tab, and I'm adding the animation
tab. So, this is the tab we've not seen before. It looks a little bit complicated at first, but we
don't have to worry, too, much about that.
We select our enemy and you'll
see immediately the tab changes, and when we've got nothing selected, whereas when we
just selected our enemy the tab changes. Then, we go here, and we're going to create a new
clip. What does that mean? It pops up with a save window. Well, we're creating an
animation here; this is the Animation
Tool that lets you create and build
animations. So, right now, we're creating
a new animation for the enemy, and because we're
in the context of the enemy already,
because what we've done with the
folders, we're in the Enemy Folder already. And we're going to save this as Arrival Animation.
This is the animation where the enemy
swoops in, menacingly, against the player,
and so, that's what we've got. Now, what actually has happened here?
Let's take a little bit of a look
around, and see what's going on. So, we've
got this enemy selected. Let's take a
look at the Inspector. We can see at the
bottom of the Inspector, something new
has been added here. We've got an animator
being added, and we have a controller
being added here, the Enemy Controller.
So, if we take a look at the project, in the Enemy Folder, alongside the Arrival Animation,
which we just created, we also have an
Enemy Controller here. And if we select it, we
now have this animation, Animator Window, pop up. This is a brand new
window, we've not seen it before, so right now, we're not worried too much about that,
but a bunch of stuff has been going on
in the background, that Unity has put in
place for us to do animations. So, really we're only going to concentrate on
the one animation for now, and then, we'll try it. But really remember that Unity, when you've
created animation on an enemy, has
actually done a whole bunch of work in
the background for you, specifically to
create things like the Animator, the
Animator Controller, as well as the
animation itself. But we don't worry
about that just for now, we'll return to
it very soon. So, how about the animation?
Let's get our enemy selected and let's
take a look at the animation we've got.
So, we selected the Arrival Animation, which we've just created, and
here the animator has not been put on
the prefab. Remember, our enemies are all
built from prefab, and we haven't got
this applied. And how can I tell? I can
tell, because this is bold. Bold in the
Inspector, means it hasn't been applied
to the prefab. So, what am I going to do?
Well, firstly, I'm going to reset this position
to 000, right. Let me reset my position
to 000, so that I don't have to change my prefab. And then, I'm going to apply to my prefab, and
now, you can see this has stopped being bold. All the animator and the Animator
Controller and all the animation stuff has stopped being bold, because it's now applied to the prefab.
So, what do I do now? Well,  I'm going to grab my enemy unit, and I'm
going to add him to one of the positions of
the formation. That's because I want to
animate relative to the actual... I want to
animate relative to the final position,
not just an arbitrary position, so it's 000.
So, let's get started with the actual
animation. So, I click on my animation
pane, and what do I get? What does
this all mean? Well, this is a dope sheet,
and what this means is it's a timeline.
Let's actually see what this means in context. Right, what we can do is say, I want to
animate. Well, what do we want to animate? Let's think about this for a minute.
I want this guy to swoop in from outside
of the play space. What this means is,
I want him to change the position, so I'm going to click Add Curve, go to Transform, and select position.
Click the + button to add the position. So, now we've got some new things coming up
inside the Animation Pane, and you'll
notice if you're very careful, eagle-eyed,
that you have... this button has just gone
selected, this Record Button, as well as
the Play, Pause, and Step Button have actually turned red.
What this means is, we are now in
Animation Record Mode. Whatever we do to
the object in the scene now changes that
object's position or
rotational etc. the attributes of that object, for that particular animation
position in the time series, in the time
frame, right. This key frame here, a 0, is the
position of the enemy, and after 1
second, the enemy will be at this position
here. So, now we have two different positions at two different
points in time, and we'll change between
the two. So, what does that look like?
Well, if I press play absolutely nothing happens, because right now if I inspect this... Let me stop the
play. And you'll notice that the red bar
shows you at what point you're looking at
the variable for, so if I look at the positions,
it's all 000, right. And if I click on the
Start, it's all 0. If I click on the end, it's all 0. Ok fine, Brice, that's not very helpful!
How about I start at a different
position, I start at X is 2. You can see that has
just jumped in the frame itself, right. You can see that has just jumped in the scene. It has just jumped by
2, in the X direction. What happens if I press play, now?
Well, let's try it. You can see it. It's slowly
moving into position, and so all the work
of... and you'll notice also the
position itself has turned red in the
Inspector. That's to show us we're currently animating it, and it's being controlled by the
animation, not by us. So, let's pause that,
and we can see that in the middle...
Let's pick an arbitrary point. You'll see that the X position is not 2 and it's not 0.
That's because Unity has done all the
hard work for us. We've given it two
keyframes and we've said at time 0, the position is 2; at time 1, the position is 0,
sort the rest out for me. But we can do more stuff with it, and this is just
exactly what we're going to do. So, what
do I mean by swooping in? Well, let's zoom out
a little bit. Not quite like that. Let's zoom out a little bit. And I actually want to
start here, and instead of changing the
position in the Animation Pane itself, I'm actually going
to change it in the scene view by hand. And you'll notice that,  because I'm in Animation Record Mode,
when I change this, this will actually change the position in the animation. It will
not change the position of the object,
when I'm out of Animation Record. Let me
show you what I mean. I stop the
recording mode, my object immediately jumps back.
I press recording mode, my object jumps to the beginning of the animation, so what do I actually want
to show as an animation? Well, I want them to swoop in, from the top left-hand side,
into their position. So, right now, if I press play, what does it look like? Well, it's just
linearly coming in, that's not quite very
satisfying. So, I'm actually going to change the
position a little bit. I'm going to add a keyframe. So, I'm going to select a time, and I'm going to
select a time, about three quarters of the way there. Then, I'm going to move my ship, below its actual
accepted final destination position. So, what does the animation look like, now? Let's try it.
I kind of like that swooping effect. So, it comes in... in front of its intended position. Then, it
slows down and pops back, going backwards into its actual position in the formation.
I really like that effect, but it's
missing something. I don't quite like...
Let's zoom in, and we can see it in the game scene. I think... yeah here we go. It's missing something.
It doesn't feel quite alive, it feels like it's just moving
arbitrarily. What I actually want is to
add some rotation, so to do that, I'm
going to stop my animation from playing. I'm going to select the beginning keyframe.
The beginning keyframe is fine, I don't care, but this keyframe here, I'm going to rotate it
a little bit. So, I'm going to grab the rotation tool; I'm going to rotate it a little bit.
So now, it's actually coming forward. It'll have a rotation when it's coming down, and
it'll change its rotation back, so that when
you're towards the end, it should have a
rotation of 0. Let's take a look at that, now. At this point here, it has a
keyframe here and here. We're going to
change the rotation and put 0 here.
So, that's the final state. This is the intermediate state, about three-quarters of the way
through the animation, and this is the
beginning state, which is out of the
scene view right now, up here. So, what happens if I press play, now?
Let's take a look at it, in the game view.
So, it's coming in and it's rotating
nicely, and all the interpolation is done
by Unity itself. We don't have to do any
of the hard work. So now, it's your turn!
Now, it's your turn to mess around with the
the animation. I want you to create a little animation. It could be like mine, or you
could have it sweeping from the side or
coming from the top, up to you. Just animate
the enemy in a way that looks good, that feels like the enemy is coming in for the fight,
is getting prepared and ready to engage
your player. And remember, play around
with the Animation Tool. It's now your turn
to really play around with this. Right
now, I've only shown what you can
do by animating the transform, but
actually animations are a lot more
sophisticated than that. You can actually do
anything you can think of, really. Anything that can be changed in the Inspector,
can also be changed in the Animator. The
Animator can change any attribute within
the inspector, including things to do
with the Animator itself. So, what's
really interesting is that you can have
the animation animate values into your
script, which is always really useful. You
can do some really cool stuff with that,
by saying the size of an object given
its distance or anything else like that.
So, play around with this. This is now your
time to play around, and try out what you
can do with the animation. As a little
hint, as well as doing the rotation and
position, why don't you try and animate
the scale, so that it looks smaller when
it's further away. And then, animate in so that it's swooping into position,
coming closer to the player, so there's a really guttural feel. And don't forget,
when you're done with your animation to press pause, to stop recording. And
now, any changes you make will not
affect the animation, but will actually
affect the position of your object in
the game. So, go ahead! Give it a shot!
Play around with the animation! This is your time to go nuts and explore what the animation package can do.
So, how did it go? Did you manage to get your animation looking interesting? Did you manage to get something cool
going on? I'm going to go with the animation I originally had,
you know, and I've got this animation here.
And now, it's time to say when should we
play the animation? So, what happens if I
play the game, now? Something weird is going on here.
They're definitely animating in, and they're
animating in, relative to their position,
but they keep looping. Not only are they
keeping looping, but also only two of
them are coming down. So, why only two of them. That's a really interesting question.
So, let's first stop the looping, and then,
we figure out why two of them only, are
coming down. So, let's put a stop... And the
looping... If we go and select our... Oh, I forgot
to remove my enemy from the game,
actually. If you've got this enemy here, it lets
me remove him from the game. That's just
the enemy I used to build the
animation. I don't need him anymore, actually, I can remove him. So now, I said I want to select
my enemy prefab, and the enemy prefab should still have all the animator, because we applied
those to the prefab, remember? And if I click on the animator for the prefab, I
can see this arrival state. This is the arrival
animation. So Ok, the Arrival Animation is
going on. So, let me pull this guy out. Let me start the game. Let me pause it and
select one of the enemy objects. And you'll be able to see what the animation does,
in the Animator Pane, so let me keep playing that game, right. Can you see how it's simply looping over
the Arrival Animation? So, it's arriving once, and then, it keeps arriving and arriving and arriving and arriving. Not
very useful, that really. So, what we want
is to stop the game, come back into our
Animator, and what we want to do is create another state. We've got this in an arrival
state and we're going to create a second
state. This is just going to be an
empty state, and instead of calling him new state, I'm going to call him Idle. That
just means the enemy is, instead of being
animating in, the enemy is in the
formation doing its stuff, it's not doing anything else. So right now, nothing else will happen,
right, and you can tell Idle is different
from Arrival. You can see how Arrival
is orange and Idle is gray, that's because Arrival is a default animation.
Because we only had one, that was a
default animation, but you can change the
default animation. Let me do that now, to
change it to the Idle Animation and see
what happens. So, I can right click on Idle and go Set as Default, and
you can see that Idle now turns orange. If
I press the game, what happens? They just
pop in, and they're a bit dispersed. We'll
see about that in just a second.
But for now, let's go back to the Animator, and turn Arrival in as the default transition...
the default state. That's the right one. So, Arrival is when we arrive.
As soon as the enemy is created, it should
start in the Arrival and then arrive, and then, it should go into idle.
And to do that, to tell Unity to do that,
we're going to right click on Arrival, and
click Make Transition. And this gives
us an arrow, and we're going to attach this
arrow, by clicking on Idle. And now,
when you press play, they arrive, and then, they
go into formation. So now, we have two
new issues, right. We have the issues of,
were missing a lot of our enemies, and
secondly, we are also in the wrong
position. So, let's first fix the enemies
and then fix the position. So, we go for the
enemies. We'll have a look at the scene.
What's causing only two enemies to come
down? Well, if we think about what we're
doing here, it'll be pretty obvious
that when we play the game... And let me
pause it and go into the Scene View. I'm going to select the top Shredder, and I'm
going to carry on playing the game. Let's go
back to the scene, and I have the feeling
that they're being created just
underneath the Shredder and then,
shredded out of existence. So, I'm just
going to stop the game and move my shredder
upwards, because if they hit the shredder,
they'll immediately be destroyed, won't they.
So, let me click the shredder and move him
out of the way. So, I'm moving the shredder up a
little bit. Here we go, and if I press play,
again, they are indeed all coming at once.
So, why are they dispersed? We've solved the problems of them all disappearing. That
was just because they hit the Shredder and
got destroyed. Well, let's inspect the actual
enemies to see why they are dispersed.
Press pause, rather than
stop, and let's take a look at our
enemies. As you know, the enemy position is
-2, -1, and 0, when they are in
their Idle state. That's no good, that's
really not what we want. Why are they in that state? That's not really what we want. And the
reason for that is something is going
wrong with how the animation perceives
its position, and it's giving, if we have
a look,
0 0 is in the middle compared to the
formation. And really it's putting them
relative to the 0 0, and then, adding
that on top of their position from their
position object. So really, something is
off here in our animation, and really the
animation to blame isn't the Arrival
Animation. At the end of Arrival, they are
at the right place. So, which animation is to blame? Well, it's this. If we take a look at our Animator,
in the Idle Animation we can see there's no
animation whatsoever, there's no motion.
There's no animation being played in Idle, so by default it'll have a relative position,
rather it'll do the wrong thing with the relative positioning. So, what we
need to do is actually create... so we stop
the game. We drag in another enemy,
not into our Animator, but rather into our scene. And I'm going to create a new animation, to this guy.
So, I've got the Arrival, I'm going to create
a new animation clip, I'm going to call this
the Idle clip, and I'm going to add a curve for the transform position. And I'm going to
start at the 0 point, for 0 0, and I'm going to delete the second animation, the keyframe. Delete key, so
it's always 0 0, there's very little
animation to do, whatsoever. So, I've got this
saved. I can stop recording now, and if I
jump back into my Animator for my...
We've got the Idle 0 created automatically.
So, let me remove the old one, Delete, and
it'll prompt us for deletion.
Idle 0 and then, I can redo what I did before, which was to make a transition between my Arrival and
my Idle state. So, let's take a look, now. We've got the idle state with an Idle
position and see what goes on. Brilliant! Now, this little dude in the middle, [Laughs]
that's the dude that was there when I tried to do the animation, and I just forgot to
delete him. Stop the game, grab the enemy, and delete the dude. And then, we play the game again, and
all of the enemies now animate, as we want them to. They're quite a tough bunch.
I've got to say, they're not easy to kill, and they're shooting a lot and they're not easy to kill.
So, what I want to see is what happens
when I delete, or rather when I destroy,
all of them, and we should see that they are arriving one after the other. And
the effect is quite good.  I quite like
that effect of multiple enemies, coming in one after the other.
Now, it's your turn, when this video stops, to have a look at the animation,
and make it your own. Instead of having it coming in from the top left,
make it come from the top right. Make it come from the side. Make it come from the top, directly.
Have it, maybe twist around, play around
with the scaling factor, as I mentioned
earlier, and also see if you can try and
get it to animate and change the sprite.
Let's see some thruster on that sprite.
I'll definitely be going through a lot more
about animation in other videos, but for
now, we've got our first introduction.
Let's see where we can take it. I'll see
you later, in another video! Bye for now.
Have fun while you're at it!