Hello, and welcome back! In this video we're going to be looking at how to create a
starfield. Now, why are we going to do that?
Well, because right now, our game looks a little
barren. We've got a blank emptiness
behind the enemy ships. We've got
nothing in the background, to give it a
little bit more depth. So we're going to add a
starfield. Give it some sort of parallax effect, to give the impression
of depth, and we are going to be using
the Particle System from Unity, to do
this. So, what's a Particle System? Well, a Particle System is an object that Unity
provides you with, and it is very
versatile, to create all sorts of
interesting effects, from trails, from
smoke coming out of fires, from the fire
itself to things like...
blood splatters,  when an orc hits your
warrior with an axe. So, that's what we're
going to be using, and we're going to
position the particles so they are moving
like stars would, if we were moving forward, very fast. And we're going to start
tuning the Particle System, to make it
look great. So let's get on with that! Let's
get started, and let's try and put a
Particle System in. So, right now, the
game looks a little bit barren, as I
mentioned, just black. How do we add a
Particle System? Well, you go into the
Hierarchy, right click, and go Add a
Particle System. And we're going to change this name of the Particle System, to be Starfield,
and we're going to call it one, because we're actually going to have two starfields,
in the end. I've got my starfield, what am I going to do to it?
Well, let me select it, and you'll see
that when it's selected it's
simulated... It's simulating. So whenever
you've got it selected, the particle
system will actually be running, and you
can stop and pause and do all sorts of
things here, with the box dust created in the scene view, to change what the Particle
System is doing, what time you're simulating it for. What we want to do is actually
change it, so it looks like stars moving
down. So, the first thing we're going to do is,
we're going to change its shape. If we
zoom out, we can take a look, and we can see that the
Particle System is like a cone, really.
That's not quite what we want. We really
want a field of stars moving down, so
let's turn that into a box first, So, I
select my star field,
and then, I go into my shape. There's lots
and lots of options in the Inspector, but I'm going to
concentrate on the shape. I'm going to turn
that into a box. So, now it's a box system,
and if we... zoom back in, we can see there's a box here. And really, we've
got this Particle System, and it's really too small, right now. So, we're going to make it
much bigger, and the way we're going to do
that is, we're going to change the X
value of the box, to be something like
20. So, that way it's a much wider Particle
System, as you can see, and it'll cover
the entire play space. If it's not,
let's try it, now. Let's go back into our game,
and it's not quite covering everything
yet, or is it? Well, how about we check the main camera, and the particle system. Not quite
covering everything, and it's a little
bit off-center. So we'll put it in the center,
and we'll turn it into box width of 30, so it covers the entire width of the game.
So brilliant! Now, if I jump back into my game, the Particle System covers everything. So
let's go back into our scene and see what
we can do. Firstly, let's change the
the rotation of that Particle System,
it's really in the wrong angle. We want
the particles to move down, so just change
the X rotation by 180
degrees, so that the particles are moving
down. And now, we don't want it to be in the
middle of the scene, we want it to start at the top. So I'm going to move it up and
now, we have a scrolling starfield. Now,
let's take a look at what it looks like
in the game. If I press play, what do we have? And there we go, we've got snow coming
down. So, what's the first problem here? I
mean the stars look a bit weird, and all sorts of
things, so I can identify two problems,
besides just the look and feel of
the Particle System, itself. The first one
is, the Particle System is currently
above the enemies, which is not what we
want. We really want it to be
something in the background, we don't want it to be in front of the enemies, so we've got that
to fix, and the second issue is, it only
starts after a little while. It kind of
starts; It needs a little bit of time to warm up. That is not good enough, we don't want
that. We actually want the Particle
System to already be there, as soon as we
start the game. So let's get these two issues sorted, which is A,
it's the wrong layer it's above the enemies, and 2 we need it to be
ready and running already, when we start the game. So, let's fix the first one, we go
back into our scene, we've got the starfield. I'm just going to change the Z layer of my
starfield, to be something like five, and this will put it below. Let's have a look
at it in 3D. You can see it now, it's
actually behind the enemy...
positions. So let me switch back to 2D mode, so now if I press play
the particles will be below the enemies.
Let's check that that is actually... appear...
happening. Yep, that's exactly what's
happening. So cool! Now, the particles
are below the enemies. Let's fix the fact that it only takes a little time to get started, and
that is a single option in the Inspector
and that is the pre-warm option. If we
take the pre-warm option and then, press
play. We'll see that the Particle System
is ready to go, as soon as the game
starts, which is the behavior we want. So,
brilliant! So, now we are going to be
playing around, a little bit, with the tuning. Really, the
first thing I want to do is change the
star size. The stars are much too big, so
let's go 0.2 or something, and that looks a lot more like stars. If we
have a look at it in the game, that's
more like a starfield than the other one
was. So, that's already a good scrolling
starfield. I think there's not quite
enough there; I think there should be more,
so let's add a little more particles.
Let's go for the Max Particle and say
jump to 5,000. Cool! And we want to change
the Emission Rate, so we can have more particles. The rate is 10 by time.
Let's change that to say 30. Here we
go! Now, that's more like it! A lot more
particles here, and they are moving quite
quickly. I think we're going to keep it like that.
I think we're absolutely going to keep it
like this, that's a good scrolling
starfield. So now, it's your turn. It's
your turn to get started with exploring
Particle Systems. This is what I want you
to do, I want you to explore Particle
Systems. Spend some time, pause the video, and spend some time trying to
use Particle Systems to build different
stuff, right. Build different things, It
doesn't really matter what. I just want you to play around with the options of the
Particle System, get familiar with all
the different things.
Try stuff out, have a 3D scene maybe and
try stuff out in there, or try and
create a thruster effect, that you can
attach to one of the ships at the back
or something like that. So, try and play
with Particle Systems. So, I'll see you when
you've had a little play around, with
Particle Systems. So now, you've played
around with a particle system, we can move on to the second part, which is turning this
into a game that has a sense of depth,
right. If we play it right now, it still
feels flat, and it feels flat, because
really while we still have...
we have two layers, we have the enemy, and player, and the stars, it still doesn't
feel like there's a lot of depth to the
background. So, what we're going to do to add depth
is use something called parallax. So, parallax is the idea that as you move, things in the distance
seem to move less than things that are
close to you. Now, that completely makes sense, right.
Imagine yourself riding a bicycle, next
to a very tall fence, the chains of the
fence seem to scroll by you very very
quickly, but the building behind the
fence doesn't move very fast, in
comparison. So, it's a really good technique
to give an artificial sense of depth,
and the relative speed of the two is
going to be what gives you this
impression that things are moving, that
you've got a depth in your background, even though you don't really. So let's jump
back. So, what we're going to do now is, because remember even though we're in the... even though
we're in... we can use 3D positioning, our
camera mode, if we select the camera,
is not a perspective camera, so it won't show depth. It's orthographic, which means it's
just a projection, so it means we won't see depths of things, even if the camera
is rotated. So, the Z position is just
about layering things within our view. So,
the next thing we're going to do is build a
second Particle System, and I'm going to
clone the first, using Control D, and then,
rename it Particle 2
Starfield 2. And I'm going to move Starfield 2 a little bit further back, so it's...
the stars themselves, the sprites won't layer over each other, so let me call
it say 6. And also, I'm going to change the
speed, and that's the only thing I'm
going to do is change the speed of
these particles, right. So, the start speed is 5,
and I'm going to do 2.5 and see what that
gives us. We're hoping for a change of
space, which we can clearly see, but now, we have a problem. Let's press play. You can
see that the second layer of particles stops halfway through our scene, that's not
good. Let's fix that. So, we jump back; we've got a second particle system. We're going to
change the lifetime of the particles, so
the start lifetime, instead of being 5
it's going to be 10, and you can see now
it's all the way back. So, if we press play,
now, what do we get? Well, now it feels
like there's depth! I'm still not so sure about
that, because I think the background particles are too bright, so lets dim them a little bit,
right. Let's go back to our background system, the second starfield, and dim them
a little bit. So, what I want to do is change
the Alpha, so it's about half way around, and
then, try again. Here we go, now, the stars
in the background are darker dimmer to
show that they're further away, and now,
we've got a Particle System that looks
like we're scrolling through it. So now,
it's your turn! I want you to take a
little time and play around with your
Particle Systems, in the background, until
they are awesome. So, play tune until awesomeness! So, that means play
around with the shape, play around with the size, play around with the colors, until you've got a
background that you really like, that
feels like you're rushing through space,
shooting enemies down, rather than just
scrolling past a bunch of stars. So,
this is what I want you to do, now. Pause
the video and play tune, until your Particle
System feels awesome, and I will show you, when you get back, an example of what I did in that time.
So, welcome back! I hope you've got a cool
background! Here's what I turned up with, in the
meantime. So, this is what I did. If I
press... If I get the game playing again,
let me show you the effect. You can see
the stars rushing past me, and they're
kind of spreading as they get nearer, to
give us a really good sense of depth. We still have
a little bit of a problem with the stars
blinking off, at random time, but that's something
we can sort out later. In fact, let me figure out why that is. It's quite a big
Particle System, really, and just to show you what I mean, I've actually changed the type
of Particle Systems from normal to
boxes. So, from boxes rather to cones. So, instead of
being boxes, now, I've got a cone Particle Systems, and you can see the
different shape and size of the Particle
Systems here, the two starfields to, give
us this depth effect. So, I'm going to change my particle lifetime for the first one to
be much longer, in fact, and hopefully
that will stop our blinking out problem.
Here we go, now, we've got a particle system of stars that rush past us in a great
effect. So, play around with stuff! Play
around with it!
Have a look at what you can get. I'm
sure you can get a much nicer looking
Particle System than this, so I'm
looking forward to what you can come up
with and share on the forums. So, that's
it for the Particle System, the introduction
to Particle Systems. I hope you've
enjoyed it, and I will see you in another video!
Bye, for now.