Hello. and welcome back! In this video we're going to be adding sound effects to our
game. Now. we've got a little space
shooter game. right now. but it sounds a
little bit dull... Well. it
sounds a little bit dull without sound.
really. so let's take a look at what it's like. Let's take a look at the game.
when we play it. so we can definitely shoot stuff down and we can definitely get an
updating score and we can definitely
get shot ourselves. Let me get
deliberately killed. So we can do all
that. but really without sound...
it's just not as good. The sound adds a lot to the game. So our task.
now. is to add some sound to our game. That's basically it. and in fact. since you've
done this before. you're going to try and do that. You're going to be doing the
player firing. enemy firing. and enemy dying sounds. So I want you to grab the sounds from
the assets we bundled at the beginning
of this section and used as sounds.
or a sound you create or a sound you download yourself. to create some sort of
liveliness. whenever the player fires or
whenever the enemy fires or an enemy
dies. because it'll give a much better
feel to your game. And I'll see you in
a few minutes. and I'll show you how I would go about doing just that. So pause
the video. now. Try and add some sound for when the player fires. the enemy fires.
and the enemy dies. and I will see you
very shortly. to go through it. So. how did
you get on? Did you manage to get the
sounds added to your game. so that when
the player or enemy fires. they
make a sound. or when the enemy dies they
make a sound. And let's see how we would do that. So this is already a recap. and the
first thing I want to do is grab my sound assets and import them into Unity. So to
do that. I'm going to jump into my folder. that's part of the bundled assets from the
package we had at the beginning of the
section. So. I'm grabbing all my sound
assets. and that's in the SFX folder. the special effects folder. and I'm dragging them
into the sound folder within my assets tab.
So cool. so now I've got all the sounds in my game. Let's get started. I'm going to start
with my player. I'm going to open the player controller. and I'm going to add a public
audio clip. So. that's going to be the fire sound. right.  The public AudioClip
fireSound; that's going to be the sound of my guns and I'm going to drag and drop that
in the Inspector. and whenever we fire I
will also. as well as firing a beam or
projectile. I will also go AudioSource.PlayClipAtPoint. and I'm going to play my
fire sound at my current location.
my current location represented by the
position of my transform. So cool! For
now. I'm playing this sound. whenever
I fire. Let's jump back into our Unity
editor. and in this case. let's add the sound itself to the player prefab. So let's take
a look at the player prefab. There's now a slot open in the player controller script. for the fire
sound. Let's drag and drop our laser
sound into the prefab slot. Let's save our scene.
and let's press play. So now. you should be hearing that. whenever I press the
spacebar. whenever I shoot the laser. I get an isolated sound coming up. Brilliant! So what's
next? Well. next is my enemy. So. let's take a look at the enemy behavior script. and
this time we're  going to do exactly the same. We're going to create a public AudioClip.
for my fireSound. but we're also
going to do something else. We're going
to create a public AudioClip. for my
deathSound.
That sounds very morbid. isn't it.
Death sound and fire sound. so the fire sound is really exactly identical to what we did
with the player. We can do... so its AudioSource.PlayClipAtPoint fireSounds...
Not fire pause but fireSounds and my current position. And now. we've got the...
sound playing when we fire. We can also
do a little bit of clean up. while we're here. Because
we no longer collide with projectiles. we no longer need to add
this offset here. So we can just use
transform.position. instead of fire
pause. which saves us two lines and cleans this up a little bit. Here we ago! And so. whenever we
fire. we instantiate a new projectile. give it some velocity. and play a sound.
That's great! And next.
whenever we die. as well as notifying the
scorekeeper and destroying the object. we
will also do an Audio Source and do the
same thing but play the death sound. Dot PlayClipAtPoint.
and I want to play the death sound. at my
current position. dot position. Here we go.
So. now. I'm playing the sounds at the right position. I'm going to also extract this
stuff. We've got three lines here. I'm going extract that into a yet more morbid die
method. that's when the enemy dies. Grab
all the stuff and make it happen in a
function. make sure not to forget my
capital A. and then now. call the Die
function from the appropriate place in
my OnTriggerEnter2D function. Save all that. jump back
into my Unity. and this time I'm going to
add my appropriate sounds to my Enemy
prefab. Let's grab the sound. and for the
fire sound I'm going to use the SFX Laser 2.
Obviously. you can use whatever you
wanted that doesn't matter all that much.
and iSFX Lose for my death sound.
Awesome! Let's save that scene and press play and see what happens. So. you can hear
my sound. my fire. You can also hear the
enemy fire. Let's try and destroy a few
and see what happens then. Can you hear that enemy being killed?
Yep. sounds good to me! And that is us done! We have now added the sounds. very quickly.
to our little game. So. we now have not
only added some sounds for firing but for
dying as well. And obviously you can go
nuts. you can add sounds to many more
events in the game. not just the firing
and dying. but also things like let's say
once in awhile add a weird creepy sound
or anything you want. So. really go nuts
with sounds on the events. maybe add a
sound whenever the player dies or
something like that. or whenever. the
score goes up. instead of having a
player an enemy dying have a little clang or ching whenever the score goes up.
Anything like that. you can have a play around with. but that's the point. we've got the
sounds going in the game.
It sounds so much better. and when it
plays... when we play the game. it feels
much cooler with the sounds actually in
there. So that's great stuff! I hope you
enjoy the video and I will see you in
another one! Bye for now.