Are you ready for this! In this video we're
going to be talking about sprite
rendering order! Oh. my goodness. that sounds exciting! I am so excited. how about you?
Are you psyched about sprite rendering
order? Let's get started! What does that
mean? Well. let me show you the problem
first. and then. we'll talk about the
solution. So first. let's play our game.
And if you're very careful you'll
see that the lasers I'm shooting and the lasers the enemy is shooting are
first rendered above the enemy and
player sprites. That means the laser seems
to appear directly on top of the enemy
ship. which seems a bit weird really. and
we want to change that and we want to
change that in a nice effective way. So
how are we going to do that? Let's stop the game. How are we going to change the
renderings. so that the lasers get rendered below the enemy ships?
Well. what we're going to do is we're going to change the sprite rendering order. and
to do that. we're going to be using
sorting layers. And sorting layers are a
tool that we can use to tell the camera
which layer to render first. and the
camera will ignore the Z depth and will go
by sorting layer first. So. even if
an item that is in a given layer is closer to the camera in the Z dimension.
it'll still be rendered below. if the
layer is second after the one
we're rendering. So it's takes priority...
the sorting layers take priority
over the Z depth. and that's what we're
going to be using to make sure
everything is rendered at the right
layer. So note that the sorting layers
are different from the layers we use for
collisions. We already talked about
collision layers to stop. say the enemy
laser colliding with enemies.
These layers are a different type of layer. So now. we've explored two types
of layers. the sorting layers and the
physics layers. and they both have a very
different purpose. So. let's get started.
Let's get started. The first thing I'm going to
do is I'm going to jump into my game. I'm
going to go to my Edit Menu. go to my Project
Settings. and go to Tags and Layers.
and I'm going to close the Layers drop
down and I'm going to open the Sorting layers drop down.
And right now. we have no layers here. We
have no sorting layers. so I'm
going to add several sorting layers. and I'll
talk you through what each does and why
we're using it. So the first sorting layer I want. and I click on the + button to
create a new one. so that the first
sorting later I want is the lowest one.
That would be the enemy lasers. so Enemy Projectiles. That's my lower layer; the layer above
that will be my enemies themselves. and I might have those the wrong way around but that's ok.
because we can always. once you've created the layers. you can always drag and drop them
around with the mouse. So if we've got this the wrong way around. we can just swap them
around like that. And thirdly. I'm going to
have another layer. which is going to be my
Player Projectiles layer. and finally. lastly.
the top layer the top dog. the one that's
going to be rendered last. so it's going to be on top of everything is my player ship.
So I'm going to call that player. So now. we've got four for sorting layers. as well as a
default. So right now. it won't do much.
but if we check our enemy and we have
the enemy prefab here. we selected the enemy prefab. and you'll notice that the layer
is Enemies. That's our physics layer in the
inspector. the first one you see. however
you'll go to the Sprite Renderer. and the
Sprite Renderer will have a Sorting Layer
drop down. And now here. we can choose
to make our enemies appear in the
Enemies Layer. and then. if we do the same for the Enemy Laser. instead of having the
default layer. we'll make them be in Enemy Projectiles. So let's see whether that's
made any difference. whatsoever. to our
game whether we've got the projectiles the
right way around. Let's press play and see
whether they fire. And I don't know
whether you can notice it. but now the
projectiles are no longer being spawned
on top of... at least they don't appear to be
spawned on top of the enemy ships. but
they appear to be coming from underneath.
which is exactly the behavior we
wanted. So awesome! Basically. that is the
sorting layers.  Not much to it.  but a really useful trick to let you make sure that the
sprites are ordered. in the right way. and
that you have the right things on
top of each other. So your job is next
and that is to make sure that
the Player Laser is always drawn below
the ship. and in addition. make sure the
Player Laser is always drawn above the
enemies' prefabs. So that's your
job.
Make sure that the three layers work well for the different things. So good luck. and I
will see you very shortly. So how did it
go? Did you manage to get the sorting
layers doing the things that you wanted
them to. The last thing we really needed to
do was to go into our game and go grab our Player and make sure that the Player Sprite
Renderer is in the Player Layer and make
sure that the Player Laser Sprite Renderer
is in the Player Projectiles Layer. And then... we're going to add actually... we're going to
go back to our layers. and I'm going to add a final layer to all of them. So if I go back
to my Project Settings. go to my Tags and Layers. and then. go to my Sorting
Layers. in my Sorting Layers. I'm going to add a final layer. and that's going to be the
Explosions Layer. And the reason I'm doing the explosion is. anytime there's an
explosion. that should come on top of
everything. That's kind of like an
aftereffect. special effect. and that's
going to be my Explosion Layer. So awesome! We
now. have a bunch of layers. that we can
make sure that all the explosion... all
the effect... all the sprites are rendered
exactly the way we want them to. and we
can test that out in the game.
So if I... and look at where the shots are fired. They're firing it from underneath the enemy
ship. and they're fired from underneath the player's ship. Exactly what we wanted! Cool stuff! Now. that's just
another tool for your toolbox. Sorting
layers. letting you decide which order
sprites are rendered in. without resorting
to Z depth. So I hope you enjoyed it. Hope
you like this short video about sorting
layers.
that's what we talk about. when we talk
about them. See you in another video! Bye.
=======
Kind: captions
Language: en
Are you ready for this! In this video we're
going to be talking about sprite
rendering order! Oh, my goodness, that sounds exciting! I am so excited, how about you?
Are you psyched about sprite rendering
order? Let's get started! What does that
mean? Well, let me show you the problem
first, and then, we'll talk about the
solution. So first, let's play our game.
And if you're very careful you'll
see that the lasers I'm shooting and the lasers the enemy is shooting are
first rendered above the enemy and
player sprites. That means the laser seems
to appear directly on top of the enemy
ship, which seems a bit weird really, and
we want to change that and we want to
change that in a nice effective way. So
how are we going to do that? Let's stop the game. How are we going to change the
renderings, so that the lasers get rendered below the enemy ships?
Well, what we're going to do is we're going to change the sprite rendering order, and
to do that, we're going to be using
sorting layers. And sorting layers are a
tool that we can use to tell the camera
which layer to render first, and the
camera will ignore the Z depth and will go
by sorting layer first. So, even if
an item that is in a given layer is closer to the camera in the Z dimension,
it'll still be rendered below, if the
layer is second after the one
we're rendering. So it's takes priority...
the sorting layers take priority
over the Z depth, and that's what we're
going to be using to make sure
everything is rendered at the right
layer. So note that the sorting layers
are different from the layers we use for
collisions. We already talked about
collision layers to stop, say the enemy
laser colliding with enemies.
These layers are a different type of layer. So now, we've explored two types
of layers, the sorting layers and the
physics layers, and they both have a very
different purpose. So, let's get started.
Let's get started. The first thing I'm going to
do is I'm going to jump into my game, I'm
going to go to my Edit Menu, go to my Project
Settings, and go to Tags and Layers,
and I'm going to close the Layers drop
down and I'm going to open the Sorting layers drop down.
And right now, we have no layers here. We
have no sorting layers, so I'm
going to add several sorting layers, and I'll
talk you through what each does and why
we're using it. So the first sorting layer I want, and I click on the + button to
create a new one, so that the first
sorting later I want is the lowest one.
That would be the enemy lasers, so Enemy Projectiles. That's my lower layer; the layer above
that will be my enemies themselves, and I might have those the wrong way around but that's ok,
because we can always, once you've created the layers, you can always drag and drop them
around with the mouse. So if we've got this the wrong way around, we can just swap them
around like that. And thirdly, I'm going to
have another layer, which is going to be my
Player Projectiles layer, and finally, lastly,
the top layer the top dog, the one that's
going to be rendered last, so it's going to be on top of everything is my player ship.
So I'm going to call that player. So now, we've got four for sorting layers, as well as a
default. So right now, it won't do much,
but if we check our enemy and we have
the enemy prefab here, we selected the enemy prefab, and you'll notice that the layer
is Enemies. That's our physics layer in the
inspector, the first one you see, however
you'll go to the Sprite Renderer, and the
Sprite Renderer will have a Sorting Layer
drop down. And now here, we can choose
to make our enemies appear in the
Enemies Layer, and then, if we do the same for the Enemy Laser, instead of having the
default layer, we'll make them be in Enemy Projectiles. So let's see whether that's
made any difference, whatsoever, to our
game whether we've got the projectiles the
right way around. Let's press play and see
whether they fire. And I don't know
whether you can notice it, but now the
projectiles are no longer being spawned
on top of... at least they don't appear to be
spawned on top of the enemy ships, but
they appear to be coming from underneath,
which is exactly the behavior we
wanted. So awesome! Basically, that is the
sorting layers.  Not much to it,  but a really useful trick to let you make sure that the
sprites are ordered, in the right way, and
that you have the right things on
top of each other. So your job is next
and that is to make sure that
the Player Laser is always drawn below
the ship, and in addition, make sure the
Player Laser is always drawn above the
enemies' prefabs. So that's your
job.
Make sure that the three layers work well for the different things. So good luck, and I
will see you very shortly. So how did it
go? Did you manage to get the sorting
layers doing the things that you wanted
them to. The last thing we really needed to
do was to go into our game and go grab our Player and make sure that the Player Sprite
Renderer is in the Player Layer and make
sure that the Player Laser Sprite Renderer
is in the Player Projectiles Layer. And then... we're going to add actually... we're going to
go back to our layers, and I'm going to add a final layer to all of them. So if I go back
to my Project Settings, go to my Tags and Layers, and then, go to my Sorting
Layers, in my Sorting Layers, I'm going to add a final layer, and that's going to be the
Explosions Layer. And the reason I'm doing the explosion is, anytime there's an
explosion, that should come on top of
everything. That's kind of like an
aftereffect, special effect, and that's
going to be my Explosion Layer. So awesome! We
now, have a bunch of layers, that we can
make sure that all the explosion... all
the effect... all the sprites are rendered
exactly the way we want them to, and we
can test that out in the game.
So if I... and look at where the shots are fired. They're firing it from underneath the enemy
ship, and they're fired from underneath the player's ship. Exactly what we wanted! Cool stuff! Now, that's just
another tool for your toolbox. Sorting
layers, letting you decide which order
sprites are rendered in, without resorting
to Z depth. So I hope you enjoyed it. Hope
you like this short video about sorting
layers,
that's what we talk about, when we talk
about them. See you in another video! Bye.
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1:Unity/Section6/15-Sprite-Rendering-Order.srt