Hello, and welcome back! In this video,
we're going to be polishing our menu
system. So, right now, we've got our Laser
Defender 2D space shooter; the problem is
it's sandwiched between two menu systems... menu scenes. Both the Start
Menu and the End Menu are from a different games, so they've got completely
the wrong style, and in addition they
just feel wrong for that game. They've got the wrong
front, they've got the wrong color, and
even the text is wrong, it's referring to
a different game. And as well as that, we
are not currently passing the score
that we accumulate, in the game itself.
When we're beating the game,
we're not passing that score into our End Scene, so we can't tell the player, after he has died: Hey,
dude, you have now earned that many points. So, that's what we're
going to do. Those are the two things we're going to do. We're going to change the style, and we're
going to pass the score to the End
Scene. So, let's remind ourselves exactly
what we have, in our game. This is our
game screen our Game Scene. This is
our Start Menu, which we imported from
Block Breaker. This is our Win Screen,
which we imported from Block Breaker again. So, what we're going to do, now, and
in fact, what you're going to do now is, I
want you to change all the styles for
the two menus, for the Start Menu and the End Menu. So, that's your job, now! So, I want
you to pause the video, once I'm done
talking, and change all the menus, so that
they look like Laser Defender menus. So,
you know how to do all that and good
luck, and I will see you very shortly to
show you how I'm doing it. See you soon.
So, here we go, here is how I'm going to change the Menu System, so it looks like Laser
Defender. So, I'm going to jump back, and I'm going to start with my Start Menu. I'm going to, firstly,
change all the text. So, I've got the title, it's no longer Block Breaker, it's Laser
Defender. Not defeender but defender. And my "Smash all the blocks to win" my subtitle is going
to be "Defend the Earth from an Alien
Invasion". So, "Defend the Earth from an
Alien Invasion". And you'll notice that the text is, too, long for our text box. So, I'm
going to change the Vertical Overflow,
and I'm going to just change it to Overflow, so
everything shows up. And next, I'm going to
change all the fonts. I think the
fonts just aren't suitable for this game.
So, I'm going to pick a bunch of fonts that
I think look good, and in fact I'm picking  the front that I used for the
score inside the game scene itself. So,
I'm just changing all the fonts here,
nothing particularly fancy you've done all
this before.
Feel free to use a different font. Feel
free to use multiple different fonts. You
know now how to get new fonts and where
to get them from, so, don't hesitate to be
creative with your fonts. So, I've got this thing here, let me go and then, change
the subtitle. I want that to be a little bit
darker, because I think it's too bright.
It takes away from the title,
and the title, I think yellow is not
quite the color for this game,
so I'm going to change it. And I've got a
bunch of preset blues here; I'm going to
change it to a nice blue. And finally, the
buttons, when you move your mouse over
them, they get to their highlight color,
and right now, their highlight color is
green. I don't think that's great for
this game either, so I'm going to pick
a nice light blue. So, here we go! And what
does that menu look like, now?
If I press play, we can see the menu
looks a lot more like Laser Defender.
So, cool! We, also, have the music, and we'll worry about that in a little bit. So, now we've got the start menu
working. Does it take us to the right
scene? Yes, it does, everything is working as we want it to.
So, now, let's jump! Let's save our scene, Command S or Control S, and let's take care of
the Win Screen. Now, the Win Screen is going to be a little bit different.
Firstly, it's no longer a Start Menu, it's an End Menu. Here we go, and let
me capitalize that. Cool! So, I've got the End Menu here, and I've got the Title and the Play
Again Button. I actually want to show the score here, so I'm going to move myself...
I'm going to change my mode, my view mode, in the scene to be the UI Mode, UI Editing Mode,
and I'm going to move my buttons around, so I can leave some space, so that we can
then, add a couple of buttons in the
middle, to do things like well, not a button
rather, but some texts in the middle to
show the player's score. So, let's start by
changing all the fonts. I think that's where we should start! Let's select fronts that match the Start Menu.
That looks better. Let's change the color of the title, so that it's a more Laser Defender color. You
really can't tell in the scene view, so
I'm going to take a look at it in the game view
instead. That looks better. And now, I'm going to duplicate the title, and instead of
calling it title, I'm going to call it label.
That's going to be my label for my score, and the label for the score is
going to have a different text. It's
going to be a different color. So, I'm going to
change it to a much lighter blue, so it looks different, and I'm going to change this
position, as well. I'm going to make it
smaller, and I'm going to put it
a little bit to the left. I'm also going to change the text alignment,
so it's right align text, and then, I'm
going to duplicate it and put
a placeholder for my score. I haven't quite
duplicated it, so I'm dragging the original.
Let me duplicate it, and let me move this
one to the other side. Here we go, that looks about right.
And then, I'm going to left align that, and that's going to be the score itself and I'm just going to
put some place holder numbers in there. Here we go. So, cool! And then, this is no
longer the label, that is the actual
score. So cool! So, now, if I play
this scene, what does it look
like? Well, it looks alright.
You can do better. I know you can
do better. I know you can spend more time on it
and make it look even more awesome,
but really we still have this green
highlight, so let's change that. And once
we've changed the green highlight we're
really done with this menu system, for now anyway. So, I've changed the
green highlight. All good to go.
So, that's done for the styling changes. Right, we've done all the changes
for styling, so what's next?
Well, next up is passing the score to
the Final Scene. So, what are we going to
do to pass the score to the Final Scene? If you remember, we have a scorekeeper in the
Game Scene that keeps track of the
score, and we want to show it in the
Final Scene. And so, what we're going to
do to do that is, we're going to grab the...
change the score, so that the score is kept in a static variable. So,
the static variable means that it's kept
in the class and not the object, so we're
not going to keep it in the scorekeeper
we create, but instead we're going to keep it
in the template for scorekeeper objects. And then, we're going to use that score
to display, in the Final Scene with the
addition of a new script, and as
soon as we display it, we're going to reset it
to zero, so that the next game we play
we start from the score of 0 again. So, let's do that, now. We're going to start in our Game Scene, in
actually what is the player in the
Game Scene. So, let's jump into the Game
Scene, save the changes we made to the Final Scene, and in the Game Scene, we're going to
grab the player, and in the PlayerController script... [Sings do do do do do do do]
The first thing I want to do is, whenever we die we should jump to the End Scene.
So, let's jump back. And we have a Die
function and then, we have in the Die
function we just simply destroy the object,
but now, we want to do something else,
which is jump to the scene. How are we going to do that? Well, we're going to use our Level
Manager. We've got a Level Manager script that let's us load new levels easily. So, we're going
to jump back into our game,
grab one of the prefabs we created in a previous game, call the Level Manager, and
from the PlayerController we're going to
call our Level Manager. So, let's do that, now.
So, I'm dying. I want to find the Level
Manager, and I can do it using the Find
function. And once I've found the Level Manager object, I need to get the component from
inside the Level Manager Object, which is
the Level Manager component. So use
the GetComponent method, and I can use
the type to select exactly which component
I want, and here we are. So, now I've got the Level Manager Object. What I actually want to do is
load a new level. So, let me turn that into
a Level Manager Object, so LevelManager
man, is this thing here, and then I can just do man.LoadLevel(). And I'm going to pass
in a component, the level I want, which is
going to be the Win Screen. Cool! So,
brilliant! That's sorted. In fact, we're
not doing much in the Level Manager that we
wouldn't be able to do by just simply
going Application.LoadLevel, but for now it's
going to have that level of indirection. So, cool! We've reused that structure. We're loading the new
level, when we die. What's left? Well,
what's left? We're already updating the
score, so, we're already talking to the
scorekeeper, whenever one of the enemies
dies. Let's take a look at the enemies to remind ourselves. We've got a private ScoreKeeper,
and we do Find ("score").GetComponent&lt;ScoreKeeper&gt;(); and then, we add
scores to them. So, let's take a look at
the score keeper. What we want to do is
pass this score integer, from the Game
Scene, to the Win Screen.
And to do that, what I'm going to do is I'm
going to change that to be a public
static int score, and that's it.
In addition to that, I'm going to change
the Reset method to be public static, as
well. And now, because it's a static method, it can be called without having a myText
variable created, so I'm just going to remove that.
So, that's going to do two things. Let's take a look at what that does. Firstly, it keeps the
score in the ScoreKeeper, even when
there are no ScoreKeeper objects. Instead
of saving the score value against an
instance of something, we store it against
the template, so the template itself keeps
track of the score. That is the class that
keeps track of the score. And that let's us go back into our game, and from the,
not the Game Scene anymore, but from the Win Scene, if we jump into a scene... I do want to
save all the changes. Brilliant! Let's
take a look at the End Menu. Now, I'm going to
attach a script to my score here, let's
do that, now. Let me select the score.
Let's add a script to the score, and it's
a new script and I'm going to call it
ScoreDisplay. I've got the Score Display here, let's take a look at what we're going to do. So,
the Score Display... the only
responsibility of the Score Display is,
when it starts up, I want to, firstly, grab
hold of the score texts, which is going
to be from UnityEngine.UI. So, using UnityEngine.UI; that let's us
access now, and create the Text myText. And that's the text we're attached to, and we can
do that to grab hold of it, by using the GetComponent &lt;text&gt;();
And, now, we've got the text, what we can
do is grab the score from the
ScoreKeeper and do myText.text. So, that's the actual field... the actual
string that's going to be displayed is
ScoreKeeper, and notice I use the capital
S. That's ScoreKeeper.score and it'll come up in the auto complete, and then,
.ToString (); And ToString will turn the score, so, this thing here is the score, the
integer score. And then, I'm going to
change it into a string, before
displaying it as text. And finally, the
last thing I'm going to do is I'm going to go
ScoreKeeper, notice this is also capital, and I'm not going to destroy it or do anything like
that with it. What I am going to do is, I'm going to reset the score, and it comes up in
the autocomplete, because it is a static function, as well. So, one thing
that will break and then, you might
notice it is when we save this. This will be
fine, it'll set the score here to be
whatever score we've got saved and then,
delete it so that the next game we play, we start with a score
of 0. What we have not quite done yet is
that, in the Game Scene... Let's jump back into our
Game Scene. When we start playing, the score will be 99999. Obviously, as soon
as we kill an enemy, the score will change,
but we don't really want to
start with a score of 99999. So, let's change that, now, and that's really easy to change.
And we just grab the score; put a zero in there. That's a nice cheap and dirty way of getting that
going and very easy for us to sort out. So, what have we got left? We've got a
little bit of tidying up to do. I'm going to
move my Score Display Script to my
Scripts; the same with the Scorekeeper Script. Here we go,
done. So, now, I've got a nice clean folder structure. So, what does that give us?
Does that give us what we were after,
which is to pass the score to the Final
Scene? Well, let's try it out. We'll
start off in our Game Scene, and we'll
press play and we'll get a score. Let me get a modest
score, before I get killed. And, now, it's
the trick of deliberately getting shot. Come
on! Come on! Come on! There we go! And then, we jump into our Win Screen, and indeed, the score does
come up on the page, which is exactly what
we were wanting. So, brilliant! And then, we
can play again, and we press Start and the
score does start at 0, which is exactly what we want. So,
wow! Cool! That wasn't, too, bad! That wasn't, too, bad at all!
We, now, have replaced the menu style, so that it makes more sense for
Laser Defender, and we have, as well,
passed the score we managed to get, in the
game itself, to our Win Screen. So, that is it for this video. I hope you enjoyed it, and
I will see you in the next one! Bye for
now.