So hi and welcome back! In this video we're going to be polishing our menu
system a little bit further. So we've got a menu system for our
little Laser Defender game but we have several things that are missing, really, that
would make the game feel a lot better. So firstly is that we have no
music in the game that's really suitable. We have taken a cross weaver,
pulled across the music from a different game but it's not really suitable for
this one. And secondly, it would be much nicer if we add some
texture to the background of our menu systems, right?
When we start the game, right now we just have a black screen,
and it'll be nice to have something a little bit cooler in the background! So
let's go and talk a little bit more about the music!
So we're actually going to be using some music from opengameart.org,
by and artist called Clearside, and he's
licensed his music under Creative Commons, which means we are able to use it
and share it with you. And in fact, the four tracks
that he's shared are available for free in
the asset bundle, at the beginning of this section. And what we really want
isn't just to add music to our scene, we've already done that so it would be really simple to just replace
the music file with a different one. But actually,
we want to do something a little bit more, we want to change the music so that every scene has its own music,
its own soundtrack. So how are we going to do that? Well we're going to use a
function called OnLevelWasLoaded(), and this OnLevelWasLoaded() function
will let you get a message, whenever a level is loaded,
and then, you can start playing the appropriate track for that level.
So awesome! Let's get started with adding some music!
So where do I want to start? I've got the four tracks here, I've got my
game here. Well I'm going to start by thinking about what would it take for
my Music Player to play the right music. So we're going to start by
removing the existing Audio Clip in our audio source. That's the clip that's playing by
default. I'm going to say None, no clip will be playing by default.
And I'm going to jump into my Music Player and see how I can get the music files playing when I want them to.
Hi, it's Ben here, just doing a quick post edit before we carry on! Johnny
Riverez quite rightly pointed out that this code has suddenly appeared,
the stuff I've highlighted && instance is not != to this. We didn't write that
back in Block Breaker. So the purpose of that simple statement there is to make sure
that we don't destroy the last instance of the Music Manager.
So once we've claimed this as the instance, what we
obviously don't want to do is go and destroy it, the last one, so that's the purpose.
Right now, the MusicPlayer script only makes sure that the MusicPlayer
exists throughout scenes, so that the music can continuously play. What
I'm going to want to do is say, I've got three audio clips. Those are my
three audio files and I can define them as public
AudioClips and I'm going to go startClip.
And then, I'm going to go for
gameClip and end
Clip. So those are my three files, my
three clip music clips, and I want to be able to play those, depending
on the level. So how am I going to decide? Firstly, how am I going to play
any clip whatsoever? Well the way to play clips is through an audio source,
so I'm also going to need access to my AudioSource. So let's create a
private AudioSource,
and I'm going to call it
music. So now I need to define where this music is.
Those public AudioClips, I'm going to drag and drop in the Inspector.
What about this music thing, this AudioSource? Well I'm going to
define it here, by grabbing the appropriate
component from the object I'm attached to. So I'm attached
to the MusicPlayer object, and this MusicPlayer object will have an Audio
Source, and I can simply grab it from
myself, basically my GameObject.
So here we go, now my music is an AudioSource, and
what I can do next is play some music! So
if I jump into now, this OnLevelWasLoaded() function,
and let's try it now, we go void
OnLevelWasLoaded()
and it'll take in an integer, which will be the level that has just been loaded.
So now, we've got this OnLevelWasLoaded() function, the first thing I'm going to do
is I'm going to Debug.Log. And the reason for
doing that is, if I've mistyped my function, if I've got a problem with
it, I want to make sure I want to not have to assume this thing is
being called, I want to be able to prove it's being called, and the way to do that is to have a custom
log message and go ("Music
Player:
loaded"... Let's spell that right, loaded
level " and then +level).
So now, every time I load the level my MusicPlayer will say, hey MusicPlayer, I've
received the message for loading levels! So what do I want to do whenever I load a level
in that general case? Well the first thing I want to do is stop the music, stop the existing music.
We're in a new level, so I'm going to stop the existing music. That's the
first thing I'm going to do! Then, I'm going to change the AudioClip, and the way to
change the AudioClip is to go music.clip
= new clip, and for the moment, I'm just going to go with start
Clip, whenever we change a level. And once I've done that, I
want to do... Most importantly don't forget that, start the music
playing again, alright. So now, that's the kind of logic, and then, depending
on which level we have, we're going to load a different AudioClip. So let's
put the logic in now! It's very simple, we can doif(level
is 0, then we load the startClip,
and that's easy enough to do. And
we can copy this logic for the different levels. Let's do
1 and level 2, which are all the levels we have in our game.
So level 1, what music
should I be playing? Well that's going to be the game music gameClip. What
about level 2? Well that's going to be the
endClip. So now, I've got the clips loading and playing.
One thing left to do is, I'm going to go music.loop
is true, and that just tells the AudioSource
that I want to loop this clip forever and ever, until I tell you otherwise.
So let's get started! Let's try this out! This
is missing only one thing now and that is the sound. We don't have the
sounds, we've got gaping gaps in our MusicPlayer
script, which is missing the sounds that we want to show off and show to the
player. So to do that, I'm going to need to import some sounds, and
I'm going to create a new special folder in my sounds, which is going to
be Music, which is going to be reserved to only music. And then, I'm
going to jump into my Finder,
grab all the music files, I've already got them selected here,
and those you'll find in the bundle, in the asset bundle at the beginning of this section.
Drag them in, drop them in, and it'll take a little bit of time for
Unity to load everything and process all the files, but it will
eventually get there. And done! So now, we've
got all the files loaded, one thing to do is to convert all of them
into 2D sounds. I don't want any 3D sounds, 3D sounds are great
when you've got objects in the game scene that make some sound
but this is all like, for example, the lasers and beams and explosions.
But that's not what I want, what I want here is just music,
it's just background music for the player to enjoy while he's playing the game,
to give it a little bit of atmosphere, so I don't want them to be 3D sounds
so I'm disabling all that. And done!
And obviously, disabling 3D will mean that
Unity has to reprocess the file, which can, once again, take a little bit of time.
Awesome! So now we've got a bunch of tracks!
We've got a music player missing some tracks, and obviously, you can choose
whichever track you want for whatever, the start, the game, the end,
and you can also choose your own clips, you don't have to use ours. In the same way you don't
have to use our sprites, you can use your own. We're going to be, I'm
going to be selecting Below the Shift for
my start music, that's the start menu music.
Assimilator for my Game Clip and
Coma for my End Clip.
So cool! Now what happens? Let's start on the start menu! What
happens if I press play? Hmm
nothing, I can't hear anything! Does it work when I press Start?
Yes it does! So what's going on here? Why is it working for Start,
then not working for the first scene? And then,
when we go back to the start, it starts sounding again. Well
that's because the first level loaded never calls OnLevel
WasLoaded(). So let's jump back into our code in our Music Player, and what we're going to
do is, we're going to set a default clip to play, whenever we get
started, and that's going to be music.clip is
going to be the startClip, and we're
going to set that to loop. And
to do loop you do loop = true, and
finally, we're going to get that playing.
Awesome! So now we have music
playing! We should have music playing when we press Start, and let's
try it now. And we do indeed! The first
moment you press play, you get some music sounding. So
cool! So we now have music throughout our game, and every scene, every
level in the game has a different soundtrack, which is exactly what we wanted.
So what's next? Well next it's your turn. Next, it's your
turn to make a texture, get some
texture to the start menu's background. So I
suggest we add a Starfield, I mean it's a game in space. Let's add
this Starfield, and it'll prime the player to
expect a Starfield in the game, as well, and it'll kind of tie all the different levels
together. So that's what I would suggest you do. So pause the video now, add some background
texture to your menus, either an image or a Starfield or something
else, and feel free to copy and paste the particle system that you've got in the game scene.
So how did it go?!
I'm going to be very very cheeky and go into my
scene. I'm not even going to modify my...
Let's make sure I save everything! I'm not even going to modify my Starfield. I'm going to go
grab them, copy them with Command C or
Control C, then jump back into my start menu, and paste
them in my Hierarchy. Great, and the same for the win screen. I'm
going to save my scene and paste them in the Hierarchy and then save my scene
again. So what happens now when I'm on the start menu and I press
play, well I have a Starfield in the background!
Brilliant stuff, right!
And one last thing we'd like to do is actually change the
text from "You Beat Block Breaker" to "You
Were Defeated". Make sure all of the text matches the game, right, we don't
want to talk about another game in this text. So "You Were Defeated!".
So that's great, we've got "You Were Defeated!" here!
And we are done, we've
got the menu systems good to go! That's it for this video,
I hope you enjoyed it, and I will see you in another one! So it's bye for now!