So hi. and welcome back! In this video
we're going to be polishing our menu
system a little bit further. So.
we've got a menu system for our little
Laser Defender game. but we have several things that are missing really. that
would make the game feel a lot better. So
firstly. is that we have no music in the
game that's really suitable. We have
taken a cross weaver.  pulled across the
music from a different game. but it's not
really suitable for this one. And
secondly. it would be much nicer if we add some texture to the background
of our many systems. right. When we go... When we start the game. right now we just have
a black screen and it'll be nice to have
something a little bit cooler in the
background. So. let's go and talk about a
little bit more about the music. So..
we're actually going to be using some
music from www.opengameart.org. by
an artist called clear side. and he's
licensed his music under Creative
Commons. which means we are able to use it and share it with you. and in fact
his four tracks that he's shared are available for free in the Acid Bundle at the
beginning of this section. And what we
really want isn't just to add music to
our scene. we've already done that. so it would be really simple to just replace the music
file by a different one. but actually we
want to do something a little bit more.
We want to change the music. so that every scene has its own music... it's own
soundtrack. So how are we going to do that? Well. we're going to use the function called
OnLevelWasLoaded(). and this OnLevelWasLoaded() function will let you get a
message. whenever a level is loaded and
then. you can start playing
the appropriate track for that level. So
awesome. let's get started with adding
some music. So. where do I want to start? I've got the four tracks here. I've got
my game here. While I'm going to start by
thinking about what would it take for my
music player to play the right music. So.
we're going to start by removing
the existing audio clip in our audio source. That's the clip that's playing by default.
I'm going to say none. no clip will be
playing by default. and I'm going to jump
into my music player and see  how I can get the music files playing. when I want them
to. Right now. the music player script
only makes sure that the music player
persists throughout scenes. so that the
music can continuously play. Well. what I'm going to want to do is say. I've got three
audio clips. Those are my three audio
files. and I can define them as public
AudioClip. And I'm going to go startClip.
and then. I'm going to go for gameClip
and endClip. So those are my three files. my three clip music clips. and I want to be able
to play those depending on the level. So.
how am I going to decide... firstly. how am I
going to play any clip whatsoever?
Well. the way to play clips is through an audio source. so I'm also going to need access
to my audio source. So. let's create a
private AudioSource. and I'm going to call
it music. So now. I need to define what
this music is. Those public audio clips
I'm going to drag and drop into the Inspector. but what about this music thing... this audio source?
What I'm going to... define it here. by grabbing the appropriate
component from the object I'm attached to. So I'm attached to
the music player object. and this music
player object will have an audio source
and I can simply grab it from my...
self. basically my game object. So. here we go.
now my music is an audio source. and
what I can do next is play some music. So
if I jump into now this OnLevelWasLoaded function. and lets
try it now. We go void OnLevelWasLoaded. and it will take in an integer. which
will be the level that has just been
loaded. So now. we've got this OnLevelWasLoaded function.
The first thing I'm actually going to do is I'm going to Debug.Log..
and the reason for doing that is if
I've miss typed my function. if I've
got a problem with... I want to make sure... I want to not have to assume this thing is
being called. I want to be able to prove
it's being called.
and the way to do that is to have a
custom log message and go ("MusicPlayer:
... spell that right.
loaded level " +level); So now.
every time I lower the level my music player will
say hey. music player. I've received the
message for loading levels. So what do I
want to do whenever I load a level in the general case? Well. the first thing I want to do
is stop the music... stop the existing music. We're in a new debt level. so I'm
going to stop the existing music. That's the first thing I'm going to do. Then. I'm going
to change the audio clip. and the way
to change the audio clip is to go
music.clip = startClip. For the moment.
I'm just going to go with start clip. whenever we
changed a level. and once I've done that
I want to do... Most importantly.
don't forget to stop the music from playing again. right. So now. that's the kind of logic
and then. depending on which level we
have. we're going to load a different audio clip. So
let's put the logic in now. it's very simple.
We can do if (level == 0) then. we load
the startClip. and that's easy enough to
do. And we can copy this logic for the
different levels. Let's do level 1 and
level 2. which are all the levels we have
in our game. So level 1. what... music should I be playing? Well. thats going to be
the game music game clip.
What about level 2?  Well. that's going to be the end clip. So now. I've got the clips
loading and playing. One thing left to do is I'm going to go music.loop is true. and
that just tells the audio source that I
want to loop this clip forever and ever.
until I tell you otherwise. So. let's get started! Let's try this out! This is missing only one thing
now and that is the sounds. We don't have the sounds. We've got gaping
gaps in our music player script. which is
missing the sounds that we want to show
off and show to the player. So. to do that.
I'm going to need to import some sounds.
and I'm going to create a new special
folder. in MySounds. which is going to be
music. which is going to be reserved to only music. And then. I'm going to jump into my
Finder. grab all the music files. I've already
got them selected here. and those you'll
find in the bundle... in the asset bundle at the beginning of this section...
Drag them in. drop them in. and it will take a little bit of time for Unity to load
everything and process all the files. but
it will eventually get there. And done! So now.
we've got all the files loaded. One thing
to do is to convert all of them into 2D
sounds. I don't want any 3D sounds. 3D sounds are great. when you've got objects in
the game scene that make some sound. but this is all like. for example. lasers
and beams and explosions. but that's not
what I want. What I want here is just
music... is just background music. for the
player to enjoy while he's playing the
game. to give a little bit of atmosphere.
so I don't want them to be 3D sounds. So.
I'm disabling all that and done. And
obviously. disabling 3D will mean that
Unity has to reprocess the file. which can
once again take a little bit of time. Awesome!
So now. we've got a bunch of tracks. we've got a music player missing some tracks. and
obviously. you can choose whichever track you want for whatever... the
start... the game... the end... And you can also choose your own clips. you don't have to
use ours. In the same way you don't have
to use our sprites. you can use your own.
I'm going to be selecting. below the shift. for my start music.
that's the Start Menu Music Simulator for my game clip and Coma for my end clip.
So cool! Now. what happens if I press... Let's start on the Start menu. What
happens if I press play? Nothing! I can't
hear anything. Does it work when I press
Start? Yes. it does! So. what's going on
here? Why is it working for start. but
then. not working for the first scene? And
then. when we go back to the start. it
starts sounding again.
Well. that's because the first level... never calls OnLevelWasLoaded.
So. let's jump back into our code in
our music player. and what we're going to do is.  we're
going to set a default clip to play.
whenever we get started. and that's going
to be music.clip... is going to be the
startClip. and we're going to set
that to loop. And to do loop. you do loop = true. and then. finally we're going to
get that playing. Awesome! So now. we have our music playing. We should have music
playing. when we press Start. And let's try it now. and we do indeed. The first
moment you press play. you get some music sounding. So. cool! So. we now have music
throughout our game. and every scene.
every level in the game. has a different
soundtrack. which is exactly what we
wanted. So. what's next? Well. next is your turn.
Next. is your turn to make...
some texture... give some texture to the
Start Menu's background. So... I
suggest we add a star field;
I mean. this is a game in space.
Let's add a star field. and it'll prime
the player to expect a star field in
the game. as well. and it'll kind of tie all
the different levels together. So.
that's what I would suggest you do. So. pause the video now. add some background
texture to your menus. either an image or
a star field or something else. and feel
free to copy and paste the particle
system that you've got in the game scene.
So. how did it go? I'm going to be very
very cheeky and go into my scene. I'm
not even going to modify my... I'll just make sure I save everything. I'm not even going to
modify my star fields. I'm going to go grab
them.
copy them is Command and C or control and C. then. jump back into my Start Menu.
and paste them in my hierarchy. Great and same for the Win Screen. I'm going to save my
scene. and paste them in the hierarchy
and save my scene again. So what happens now.
when I'm on the Start Menu and I press
play? Well. I have a star field in the background.
Brilliant stuff. right? And one less thing
we'd like to do is actually change
the text. from You Beat Block Breaker to be You Were Defeated. Make sure the text
matches the game. right. We don't want to talk about another game. in this text. So. You
Were Defeated! And so that's great. we've got. You Were Defeated here. and we are done.
We've got the menu systems good to go!
That's it for this video! I hope you
enjoyed it. and I will see you in another one!
So it's bye for now!