Hi there. it's Sam here again. and I am going to be showing you how to upgrade
Laser Defender to Unity 5. So. the first thing we need
to do is obviously fire up Unity 5. You'll notice I have a couple of version here.
I'm going to go for Unity 5 rather than Unity 4. for obvious reasons.
and then. we'll hit Open and locate our Laser
Defender project. And what we should be getting here
is. there we go. an automatic dialog which tells us
that Unity can't upgrade this project without
changing your script files. That's because the script files are
using some obsolete API's. which now it needs to go ahead and
update. and it's very cleaver. almost magical. that it does this all for you. And
we're going to be able to see what those exact changes are. So.
it does ask you to make a backup. so that's a
very good idea in a larger project where you may or may
not get the automatic tool to do a good job and you want to
make sure that you have a backup. and generally. using version control is a
good idea if you know how to do that. If not. don't worry just go ahead and make
a .zip of your folder and keep it somewhere. And I have
a backup. so I'm going to go ahead and hit that little blue button
and let Unity work its magic for me. Now. let's just open
it up on a different desktop but I'll bring it across.
and here we have our Unity screen. or as normal slightly
resized and weird. But we can go ahead and check out
that our game is working as intended. that we
can hit start and we can play and you
can hear all of the music and everything coming through my speakers. That's fine! And
everything seems to be working just fine. But what has changed
here? Let's just take a look at my version control.
I'll bring that over. as well. So. here this
shows us a list of files that have. in fact. changed. Among
all these asset files that we aren't interested in and we've
seen change in other projects. we also have these
.cs files. so C# scripts. that have changed. And as you'll
notice. it's exactly the same as before. We have rigid
body2D has been changed to a more explicit GetComponent
and so on. And we've seen this happen before
when you tried to upgrade Block Breaker. I'll just get it to ignore
the password for now. And so. that's nothing new.
and it works as it did before.
So. you may well have seen this challenge slide coming. I'd like you
to create a Web GL build. using this new upgraded project in
Unity 5. and then. share that with your friends. So. I'd
like you to check your game in Unity 5 first. Make sure everything is
working as it should do. and if not. go and post a question against this lecture
and figure out how to get it working. if you can;t figure it out by yourself of course.
And then. make your Web GL build. and once you've done
that. I'd like you to put it on Game Bucket and then share it with social media.
share it in the comments in the Q & A.
And then. when you've done that. with that you can move on
to the next video. If you're unsure about how to do any of this. check out some of the
previous upgrading to Unity 5 lectures. where the full instructions on
uploading to Game Bucket are there.