Hey. so congratulations! You have made it all the way through laser defender! No small
achievement. well done. I really hope you
made the game you're own. if you haven't
it's a great time to just stop right now and go back. change the art. change the sound.
change the animations. What else can they do. Brice. to really make this their own and make sure
they share it. Yeah there's lots of really cool improvements you can make to this game and
unique things you can do. So making
sure say the enemy's animate. when their
in formation is one thing you can do. one
concrete thing you can get done.
You can certainly obviously use your own
assets for everything. but a cool thing you
could do is actually to add an enemy type... another enemy type. Right now. we have
only one enemy. Adding a second enemy.
and then having different waves of
enemies coming in with different types...
that would be pretty cool! That would
give a lot of richness to the game. And
finally. we've got this health system
in place already in the game. So every
missile is actually causing damage
to the player or the enemies' health. but we're not really taking advantage of it. All the
health we have is less than the missile damage. so it's a one hit kill.
So you could really do something cool
by changing that and having missiles that do
different things from the enemies or
from the player. and also having multiple
lives for the player. so that you can
regenerate. Play around with the health
mechanics and make something cool. And look guys even if you don't change it at
all the most important thing is you
share it. Yeah. we want you to build it for the
web and share it using game bucket.io and then pasting as we show you how to do
into the discussion groups. so that other
people can see it. And if you want
feedback from outside of our student
community. go to the Facebook group. which is
facebook.com/unitycourse. And the
habit of actually sharing and putting
what you've created out is fantastic. Please don't make it precisely what
we taught you in the course. because that's a little bit lame. but even if you just change
something and share it that's great. You
can always re-share it as you customize it.
And we love to see your work actually. We've been really impressed with the
things you've already shared in the course. and we absolutely love to see what you do
with it. So please share it and
we'll definitely be commenting on it and
having a look and playing it. We've been playing all of the things you've shared.
Yeah. it's great. we don't have to actually do any work. we can just play your games that you made. all day! So that's cool! [Laughing]
=======
Kind: captions
Language: en
Hey, so congratulations! You have made it all the way through laser defender! No small
achievement, well done. I really hope you
made the game you're own, if you haven't
it's a great time to just stop right now and go back, change the art, change the sound,
change the animations. What else can they do, Brice, to really make this their own and make sure
they share it. Yeah there's lots of really cool improvements you can make to this game and
unique things you can do. So making
sure say the enemy's animate, when their
in formation is one thing you can do, one
concrete thing you can get done.
You can certainly obviously use your own
assets for everything, but a cool thing you
could do is actually to add an enemy type... another enemy type. Right now, we have
only one enemy. Adding a second enemy,
and then having different waves of
enemies coming in with different types...
that would be pretty cool! That would
give a lot of richness to the game. And
finally, we've got this health system
in place already in the game. So every
missile is actually causing damage
to the player or the enemies' health, but we're not really taking advantage of it. All the
health we have is less than the missile damage, so it's a one hit kill.
So you could really do something cool
by changing that and having missiles that do
different things from the enemies or
from the player, and also having multiple
lives for the player, so that you can
regenerate. Play around with the health
mechanics and make something cool. And look guys even if you don't change it at
all the most important thing is you
share it. Yeah, we want you to build it for the
web and share it using game bucket.io and then pasting as we show you how to do
into the discussion groups, so that other
people can see it. And if you want
feedback from outside of our student
community, go to the Facebook group, which is
facebook.com/unitycourse. And the
habit of actually sharing and putting
what you've created out is fantastic. Please don't make it precisely what
we taught you in the course, because that's a little bit lame, but even if you just change
something and share it that's great. You
can always re-share it as you customize it.
And we love to see your work actually. We've been really impressed with the
things you've already shared in the course, and we absolutely love to see what you do
with it. So please share it and
we'll definitely be commenting on it and
having a look and playing it. We've been playing all of the things you've shared.
Yeah, it's great, we don't have to actually do any work, we can just play your games that you made, all day! So that's cool! [Laughing]
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1:Unity/Section6/30-Recap-&-What's-Next.srt