OK. so here we are inside
Unity. for the first time. It's quite a complex interface. so
this first game is going to be specifically designed to only
use the Console. So. if you don't
see what I see. then go to the top right of Unity.
and then. click the drop-down. which is the Layout Drop-Down. and just go to
Default. so that it ends up looking like this. And then. I want you to
find the Console. Now. there are a few ways to find the Console. One way is you can go to
the Window drop down and then look for
Console. which is at the very bottom on a Mac. And it will
flip over to Console. or you just look for Console. which is in the bottom
section of the screen. next to project. Alright. let me talk
you through the Console just a little bit. So. what do we have here?
We have an ability to clear lines off the Console. The Console.
by the way. is just going to be full of lines of text. and our entire game
is going to be running in this Console. just for this project.
And the purpose is. we don't want your to be confused by all
this other complexity of Unity.
Of course. if you're already highly experienced with Unity. you can completely skip this
section and just move straight on to the next one. but for a beginner. I would really
strongly suggest you start here. because we're also covering programming basics.
a lot of really really important programming fundamentals in this
section. So. back to the Console! You can clear it. you
can collapse it. we'll talk about that later. So. all of these bits don't
worry about. The bits you do need to be a little bit aware of. especially before we move
the Console. is theres top right three buttons. This
one turns on and off logs to the Console. which we'll be making.
This one turns on and off errors or warnings. rather. the
middle one warning triangles. And then. the final one.
the stop sign is for errors. you turn on and off. They're turned on
when they're depressed in and slightly lighter. OK. so
a bit of a gotcha. in case you've actually clicked that off be careful.
Alright. that's that! So. what I want you to do is to move the
Console. We'll be looking at
moving windows around. in a more advance way later. but I want you to move
the Console over to the right hand side like this.
Alright. so just grab hold of it and drag it
to the right hand side. And what that's going to mean is. we can then
put MonoDevelop right over the rest of all of this stuff. so that we're
just dealing with the Console and MonoDevelop itself. You can
grab the divider between the scene or the game and the
Console on the right here. Just drag if you want and you can
adjust things. but you just need a bit of Console on the right hand side.
OK. now before we leave the Unity Editor.
I just want to delete the Main Camera in the Hierarchy. So. look for the Hierarchy
on the left. Main Camera. and I either go to Edit and Delete
or Right click and Delete. because we just don't need it for this
project. OK. next we're going to create an empty GameObject.
because in order for our script to run it needs to
be attached to a GameObject. So. we're going to go
to Game Object. Create Empty. from the Game Object
Menu. and I want to rename this GameObject Number Wizard. capital
N capital W and you can leave no space if you wish.
That's fine! This is called Pascal Case. it means all
the kind of components of the word have uppercase. so NumberWizard
like that! Alright So. that's
an empty GameObject. How are you going to add a script to it? A couple of different ways! You can
go to Inspector. Add Component. New Script.
Let's do it that way! And then.
type NumberWizard. The same component
name as the GameObject name in this case. which will
normally be the case. but you can add multiple scripts or components
to the same GameObject. So now. we have a NumberWizard Script!
It's sitting in the base of Assets. Let's be tidy. from the start. and put it
in a folder called Scripts. because that's how we're going to go on.
So. I've made a folder by right clicking down in Assets. going to Create.
and then. Folder. Call it Scripts and then drag
NumberWizard into it. Fantastic! Alright. this
other thing here. Main. it's the scene or the level used
interchangeably. It's also at the top of your screen up here. Main.
We need some sort of scene or a level. We need at least
one level for the game to run. so that needs to be there. That's just fine!
Alright. so we've created our NumberWizard Script. let's
go into it! Now. just quickly rearrange
your MonoDevelop. Move it to the left hand side of your screen. so
that you can see ideally both Mono... If any funny tool boxes come
up in Mono. just close them. So. you can see both Mono
and the Console. So. click on your Console in Unity.
Command or Alt Tab. back to MonoDevelop. and just
jiggle between them. until you can see as much Console as possible.
You might have a much bigger screen resolution than me. I'm actually on a really
big monitor here. but I've got the screen resolution
really low for you guys. so you can see the text really clearly.
So. this is the situation we want to end up with. just with the Console visible
on the right and the code visible on the left. Fantastic!
We're going to write our first bit of code right now! Let's do it!
So. we're going to go inside of the Start function. For now. we're only going to focus
on what's going inside the Start function.
We're using that because we know it's going to run. it runs at the very beginning
when the game first runs. Don't worry about any of the rest of the stuff out
here. we're going to keep our context where the cursor is for now.
Later on. we will zoom out and zoom out until you understand
absolutely everything that is on this screen. but for now. let's
focus here. Cool! So. we're going to use a statement called print.
Old as the houses! print ("Welcome
to Number Wizard"); and just do that!
And you can do same! print ("Welcome to Number Wizard"); Now. look
there's some syntax. there's some language. here. and the computer is super
fussy about how we type this. So.
this is a
string inside print. It's a string because it's in quotes.
OK. that'll come clear in a moment. And then.
the brackets indicate that print
requires some parameters. It requires some input. so print is a
function or a method. that requires something inside
its brackets. and what that requires is a string. And then.
on the end of every single line in C# we need a
semicolon. Without a semicolon.
it doesn't know the line has ended. It just ignores white space.
Alright. let's stop chatting and get on with seeing what this does!
Now. it's not saved yet! You know it's not saved for
two reasons. One. the circle up here.
Here's a circle. when I save watch what happens to the circle.
It turns to a cross. Now. you would be closing the tab. Previously it was telling
you. you could close me. but I'm not saved yet. Alright. the other
way you can tell is. if I make another change. you get a star on the
end of the file name there. Alright. there
being at the very top of the screen. next to where it says NumberWizard.cs.
Alright. great so make sure your script is saved. go back to Unity
and run it! Now. what you should be seeing over here is
Welcome to Number Wizard! and then a load of other bumf. Under every line. you're going to get
bumf. which is telling you where this log has come from.
It's come from UnityEngine.MonoBehavior. Again. if you can still
see it on your screen. make sure this little bubble is turned on. The bubble that enables
logs. If you don't. you won't see anything alright.
If you have a 1 but you can't see anything. it's because that is turned off.
OK. so that is that! We have
printed Welcome to Number Wizard. Fantastic! OK. so I've
got a challenge for you now which is. I want you to print another line.
without my help. And this is your first mini challenge!
During a mini challenge. I'm going to tell you what result I want. and then.
I want you to do it. Pause the video. so that you can make your own mistakes.
do your own learning. and then. unpause the video when it's time
to check your answer against what I've done.
So. here we go! I want you to just put another print statement
immediately underneath. that says Pick a number in your head. but don't
tell me". Alright. simple as that! Really easy challenge
for the first video. Go for it! Pause the video now.
OK. welcome back! So.
this is how I did it! I'm just going print ("Pick a number
in your head. but
don't tell me"); OK!
And then. close the bracket and add a semicolon on the end
of every line. Congratulations. a super simple video
but you're into scripting! Make sure it works by saving.
going to Unity. and running! Now. if
it was already running. you're going to need to stop it running and click
play again. There you go. now you get your two logs! "Welcome to Number Wizard".
Pick a number but don't tell me. Fantastic! Well done! See you in the next video!