Hi! In this video you're going to learn to create variables in
your scripts. assign values to variables. and then use
number variables inside strings or with strings.
OK. so let's dive into our NumberWizard.cs
Script. as an example here. So. we have our script on
the left and our Console on the right. We're building an entirely Console based
game. remember. just for the first project of this course.
So. we have a couple of things that
we know we're going to use more than once. i.e. the high
number and the low number. in the range. that you're allowed
to make your guess. It says. "Pick a number in your head. but don't tell me". The next thing
it's got to tell you is. between what and what. Say 1 and
1.000. So. we're going to use that high and low
very often. so I'm going to show you how to use something called a variable.
which is something that the computer can keep track of and
is allowed to change at runtime. So. here
we are. we're going to define int. which is the type of variable. It's an integer
and we use integers when it's something countable. So.
numbers. whole numbers are countable. We would use a different
type. if it wasn't countable. OK. so int and
we're going to call the variable max. So. the next thing that comes after the
type is the name. so int max. and we could call it what I like. what we
like. We could call it max or maximum or whatever. but I'm going to call it max.
Equals. = is an odd symbol. it doesn't
really equal it's actually an assignment. I would prefer that it was kind
of = forward slash or something like that. but it isn't. so we have to live with the
syntax we have. int max = 1000.
And what do I need here. apart from to type straight?
A semicolon! Absolutely. on the end of every line!
So. what we've done there is we've made a variable called max that
currently. at this moment. is going to be = to 1000.
and it's of type integer. which means that it's a whole number.
It can only be a whole number. Alright. micro
challenge for you! I want you to find another integer. immediately below.
called min. and I want you to make it = to 1. Pause
the video. go ahead. and do that now please! Please do it!
Please. you'll learn so much more!
OK welcome back! Here it is! int
min = 1; Not rocket science. but could
form the basis of some rocket science. if we were to go on and expand
on it enough. Alright. so next thing we need to do
is actually tell the user what range they can pick their numbers in.
So. I'm going to do something like this!
print ("The highest
number you
can pick is ". Space
because I want a space after my is. Close the string.
because we're no longer in the string. by closing the
quotes. Then. a plus! Now. it doesn't actually matter how many spaces
I put before my +. so I'm going to put an ugly number for a moment.
And then. max. which is that variable. Now. notice
it's also helping us. because it knows about max.
Close the brackets. close the
semicolon. Let's save our script and see the effect in
Unity. It's going to be a pretty predictable effect. Here it is!
Ooh. and there it is! "The highest number you can pick is
1000". Alright. it's pretty
hopefully turned this max
number into a string for us. The + operator
has done something clever here. it's called overloading and we don't need to worry about it now.
But just be aware. you are mixing types here. You are mixing a
string. in these quotes. with an integer.
but this statement handles it. This + operator handles
it. it's all cool! I'm going to get rid of my number of ugly spaces. I was just trying to
demonstrate that the spaces you use outside of the string don't matter.
The spaces you use inside the string do matter!
If I didn't have a space at the end of is. well go ahead and try it! Get rid
of your space between is and the quotes and see
what happens in the Console. I will leave that to you. Alright.
another thing I'm going to leave to you is the next challenge. Fairly simple.
I want you to print another line that says The lowest number you can pick is".
with your space. and then. use the min variable.
OK. pause the video. go ahead.
and make it say. "The lowest number you can pick is 1". using
the variable. Alright. here's a
solution! Print. really
basic stuff for the moment. but if we get you into the basics of programming
properly. you're going to be setup for life!
...pick is. space.
close. There we go. like that! It's
very hard to talk and type at the same time. especially when you're typing and saying
different things. but anyway I seem to manage it! Save that. test it.
and I think we are done! There you go!
"The highest number you can pick is 1000". "The lowest number you can pick is 1".
We are all good. Congratulations! You are slowly
becoming a scripting. programming coding ninja!
See you soon!
=======
Hi! In this video you're going to learn to create variables in
your scripts, assign values to variables, and then use
number variables inside strings or with strings.
OK, so let's dive into our NumberWizard.cs
Script, as an example here. So, we have our script on
the left and our Console on the right. We're building an entirely Console based
game, remember, just for the first project of this course.
So, we have a couple of things that
we know we're going to use more than once, i.e. the high
number and the low number, in the range, that you're allowed
to make your guess. It says, "Pick a number in your head, but don't tell me". The next thing
it's got to tell you is, between what and what. Say 1 and
1,000. So, we're going to use that high and low
very often, so I'm going to show you how to use something called a variable,
which is something that the computer can keep track of and
is allowed to change at runtime. So, here
we are, we're going to define int, which is the type of variable. It's an integer
and we use integers when it's something countable. So,
numbers, whole numbers are countable. We would use a different
type, if it wasn't countable. OK, so int and
we're going to call the variable max. So, the next thing that comes after the
type is the name, so int max, and we could call it what I like, what we
like. We could call it max or maximum or whatever, but I'm going to call it max.
Equals, = is an odd symbol, it doesn't
really equal it's actually an assignment. I would prefer that it was kind
of = forward slash or something like that, but it isn't, so we have to live with the
syntax we have. int max = 1000.
And what do I need here, apart from to type straight?
A semicolon! Absolutely, on the end of every line!
So, what we've done there is we've made a variable called max that
currently, at this moment, is going to be = to 1000,
and it's of type integer, which means that it's a whole number.
It can only be a whole number. Alright, micro
challenge for you! I want you to find another integer, immediately below,
called min, and I want you to make it = to 1. Pause
the video, go ahead, and do that now please! Please do it!
Please, you'll learn so much more!
OK welcome back! Here it is! int
min = 1; Not rocket science, but could
form the basis of some rocket science, if we were to go on and expand
on it enough. Alright, so next thing we need to do
is actually tell the user what range they can pick their numbers in.
So, I'm going to do something like this!
print ("The highest
number you
can pick is ". Space
because I want a space after my is. Close the string,
because we're no longer in the string, by closing the
quotes. Then, a plus! Now, it doesn't actually matter how many spaces
I put before my +, so I'm going to put an ugly number for a moment.
And then, max, which is that variable. Now, notice
it's also helping us, because it knows about max.
Close the brackets, close the
semicolon. Let's save our script and see the effect in
Unity. It's going to be a pretty predictable effect. Here it is!
Ooh, and there it is! "The highest number you can pick is
1000". Alright, it's pretty
hopefully turned this max
number into a string for us. The + operator
has done something clever here, it's called overloading and we don't need to worry about it now.
But just be aware, you are mixing types here. You are mixing a
string, in these quotes, with an integer,
but this statement handles it. This + operator handles
it, it's all cool! I'm going to get rid of my number of ugly spaces. I was just trying to
demonstrate that the spaces you use outside of the string don't matter.
The spaces you use inside the string do matter!
If I didn't have a space at the end of is, well go ahead and try it! Get rid
of your space between is and the quotes and see
what happens in the Console. I will leave that to you. Alright,
another thing I'm going to leave to you is the next challenge. Fairly simple,
I want you to print another line that says The lowest number you can pick is",
with your space, and then, use the min variable.
OK, pause the video, go ahead,
and make it say, "The lowest number you can pick is 1", using
the variable. Alright, here's a
solution! Print, really
basic stuff for the moment, but if we get you into the basics of programming
properly, you're going to be setup for life!
...pick is, space,
close. There we go, like that! It's
very hard to talk and type at the same time, especially when you're typing and saying
different things, but anyway I seem to manage it! Save that, test it,
and I think we are done! There you go!
"The highest number you can pick is 1000". "The lowest number you can pick is 1".
We are all good. Congratulations! You are slowly
becoming a scripting, programming coding ninja!
See you soon!
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1:Unity/Section2/03-Variables-For-Things-That-Change.srt