Hey! In this video we're going to learn a
lot more about these wonderful if statement
things, so let's get on and do it by example.
Firstly, I want to explain a little bit about
indentation. So, this Start function, every
single statement within the Start function,
is indented by the same amount. It's four
spaces but actually don't use spaces please, use
a tab. So, there's a tab, it just happens
to be four characters in front of absolutely
everything, so that indicates that all these
things are inside the Start function. So,
let's look at that Update function. In the
Update function, all of these statements are
at that level of indentation as well. See
how easy it is for the eye to follow. Similarly
inside the if statement, all of its statements,
that it's going to run inside the code block
inside the curly brackets, will also be at
this level of indentation.
The beady-eyed among you may have noticed that it doesn't matter whether you put the curly brackets
here or not, but please DO continue to use to use them. The reason
is that if you don't and you accidentally add a 2nd statement in
this if statement perhaps under the word print("Up arrow pressed");
if you add another line of code there without the curly braces, that won't be executed
which is very confusing. So keep the curly braces in. They cause something called a
code block, and they keep all the statements inside your if statement together.
So, to give you
an example, I'm going to print and then ("Example");
OK, now because I want to be consistent I'm
going to take that space away, so let's just
save that. What's it going to give when I
push key down? Think about what it's going
to give, in the Console. OK, let's have a
look and see what happens. When I push key
down, what do we get? Down arrow pressed.
When I push key up, what do I get? Up arrow
pressed and Example. I hope that makes sense,
if you're in Collapse Mode you're going to
get something slightly different, when you
continue to press keys, because what it's
going to do is it's going to just layer the
same things on top of each other, so every
time it logs the same thing it just increments
the number, as previously explained. Alright
fantastic! So, that explains what indentation
does. Any other statements we put inside this
if statement, we would put at this level of
indentation. Cool! I'm going to get rid of
that example line now for you. Alright, so
here's a simple challenge for you then. We
want to add a third if statement, which responds
to the Enter key and logs the words I "Won!"
to the console. Third if statement, responding
to the Enter key and logs the words "I Won!"
Go ahead and do that now please. OK, so this
is how I'm doing it, I'm copying what's there.
I am going to guess that it's KeyCode.Enter.
I don't think it is, because it's come up
in red, so I'm going to try one other thing,
by hacking away until I go and look at the
docs. I'm going to try ("Enter") like that.
It's looking promising, let's try it, because
I haven't got anything gone red. OK, so I
just want it to say "I won". OK, now let's
save and try it, see if we've got the right
key code. Play...Input name key code. What's
it saying? Let's pause, click on the error,
and you can expand out the window if you want.
Key Enter is unknown. OK, it doesn't understand
Enter, so we've got to go and find out what
the Enter key code is. So, there are a few
ways of doing it. We may as well stay in the
safety of the Unity docs for a minute, so
I'm going to go Input.GetKeyDown. I'm going
to go Command and Apostrophe or Control and
Apostrophe on a PC. It's just the way of looking
up the docs for the currently selected word.
Go into Input.GetKeyDown and let's see if
we can find ourselves a list of all of the
key codes. Here we go, key code here. Now,
do we have Enter somewhere? I'm going to do
an in page search, in my browser, for keypad
Enter, that's possible we could use Keypad
Enter. I think I really mean Return, so you've
got to be careful about your keyboard, you've
got Enter and Return, and they're two different
keys. I really mean Return, so I'm going to
use Return, and here you go. And what is that?
It's KeyCode.Return. Alright, so that's a
typical thing you're going to go off and do,
is have a little nosy and find out what you
should be using, and I think what we should
be using is KeyCode.Return, like that. So,
let's just save and test. Now, if I push Enter
or Return, it says "I won!". Perfect! And
then, it keeps logging "I won!", every time
I hit it. Well, that's great! Alright, so
we can go up and down. Well, if I'm click
in the Game Window, remember. Up Arrow Pressed,
Down Arrow Pressed, "I Won!" if you hit Return.
Good, good, good, good! OK, so the only other
thing that's not fantastic here is that, if
I was to push two keys at the same time, like
up and down, look what it does. It logs both
Up and Down, at the same time or Down and
Return, and actually I want it to only log
one key. So, the way we're going to do that
is use something called an else if. So currently
we're doing this if, and then, it immediately
checks the next condition and if the Down
Key, the Up Arrow Key rather is still down
when I push the Down Arrow Key, then it's
going to do both of those things. I want it
to exclusively check to see which of the keys
is pressed, not all of them, and the way we
do this is we just say I put else here. And
then, I delete back, so that it says else
if like that. OK, that's the format. Let's
just do it again, else OK, and then, the same
for the Return Key. Now, it's only very subtly
different behavior. Let's save and look at
it, it should still operate in the same way,
Up and Down and Return, but if you do Up and
Down at the same time, it'll just pick which
ever one you pushed first, most of the time.
It depends how fast the frame rate is, actually.
It may actually... your key may be down for
two frames, in which case it is actually going
to still log both, but generally you'll get
one or the other. OK, so that's just an introduction
really, the main purpose of this is an introduction
to the else if statement. So, that's it now,
hopefully you understand a lot more about
if statements, not a huge amount more you
ever need to know about them, by the way.
So, congratulations! See you soon!