Congratulations on completing
the Console version of Number Wizard! What did they learn. Brice?
Lots actually. lots and lots of stuff! So. you wrote your first script
in Unity. You started learning about variables.
about if conditionals. how to make
choices. creating functions to do things.
and also keyboard input. You had a game. you can actually
play on the keyboard. And also. really importantly. and you're going to
use that all the time. it's learning about how to get information
out to the Console. to debug information out. because you're
going to be having a much more complex game and lots of things
are going to be happening at the same time. So. making sure the
information is available to you in the Console. to see exactly what's going on. that's really important!
So. you've already done that. so well done! Awesome! We've really given you
a useful foundation here. Printing to the Console is going to get you out of
trouble so many times later on. when you're not sure why something is not working.
So. it's fantastic that you've got this far! So.
well done! Well done! Some ideas for challenging yourself.
if you want to just extend this game a little bit before you go onto the
next section. You could try a different number
range. You could change the game so that it works with a number between.
I don't know. 1 and 10.000 or 1 and 1 million. whatever.
Or how about making the range choosable by the player. at the
beginning. So. you have a bunch of key inputs and you can choose which
range you want. Yeah yeah! It could be a little quirky
clunky if you do that. because you're going to have to...
The Console is not really going to give you key input in a particularly
nice way. but you could. when they push a key. log that key to the keyboard. Try it.
that'll be a really cool thing to try. responding to those key presses
and printing them out on the screen. So. player selectable number range
is what you're talking about? Yeah! And the final thing you can try is. actually. rather than
guessing the number half way. in the current range. try just making a
random guess. in the current range. so that first if it's
1 to 1.000 your first guess is completely random. You go. is it higher or lower than
15 or whatever? Just try it! You'll be surprised at how well it works! And it
feels a lot more natural when you do that. actually.
It feels like it's a real player. not just a computer that's randomly choosing.
so that's a lot more fun when you do that! Yeah!
It kind of hides the obvious trick. and it makes it
feel a bit more... It'll be more guesses and it'll take more effort to get to your answer
but it still works surprisingly well. and it feels. as you said. a bit more
alive. So. well done! We're going to take this code. we're going to
reuse it in the next section where we'e going to. for the first time. put a User
Interface on it. Good luck and see you then! See you!