OK, let's get this game finished up and cleaned off
or cleaned up and finished off or some combination
of those things. So, let's do it! Let's have a look at what's going on
then. Firstly, when the game finishes, it's not starting
again, so that's a problem. Very very easy to sort out!
When the computer has printed "I won!", why doesn't it just call
StartGame();? That would be easy wouldn't it? Let's try it!
I'm sure it will work! Let's just see it working?
Play, so I'm just going to say, oh you guessed me,
500, "I won!", and then, it gives me all the instructions again
and gives me the option to continue guessing, which
I can do. But it's really not clear, looking at
this Console, where the game started again. So, why don't we put a visual,
a simple visual break-in, so that
we can see that. And the way that I'm going to do that is just say print
and then a bunch of equals, until I get
about the same width or a little bit less wide than ("Welcome to Number
Wizard"), like that! Now, let's just see the effect of that.
It's pretty obvious but if I won the game straight away,
then I would have this, well nice... This is as good as you
can do in a Console, kind of, line of
equal signs that just says, OK you're in a new game! So, that's one thing
done! That's what we needed to do. Now, the other thing you
may notice is, the numbers don't reset. Let me go back to Unity
again. Excuse all the diving back and forth. And let's,
you know, do some movement. Let's get, OK, 763
but now look, it's back with the same numbers. Why? In fact,
why? What I mean is, it's for you to work out
why, for a second. So, if I give you a challenge where it's just a
work it out, what are you actually going to do? I suggest you write
down the answer, rather than just have it in your head, because it's
going to be very easy to tell yourself what you imagined is what you
actually see me tell you, and then, it's kind of deceiving yourself from
stuff. So, why not write down why you think
the number don't reset. Take a look at the code, pause the video,
do that, and come back when you're ready!
OK, so what did you write down? Well,
I think what's happening is that we are initializing these
numbers at the very very beginning, when the game
starts, and then, we're never changing them, which isn't
brilliant. So, what we need to do is just move
these simultaneous declarations
and initializations from the top here, to where?
Well, it would make sense to put them in StartGame () right?
OK, so there they are! And now,
they should work right within StartGame (), because every time
we restart the game we're going to reset these numbers. So,
that should work right? Well, let's see!
Oh, nasty compiler error! "The name guessed does not exist
in the current context". Where, please show me Mr. Console?
On NumberWizard line 32.
So, here's line 32.
It's the min, it's the first time I get to the min. Well, min can't see...
Well, sorry. the Update function
cannot see min or max or guess. It's a
scoping problem again. Why? Because they're declared in StartGame ()
and initialized in StartGame (), i.e. they're given
their value, but
they were not declared anywhere that is
accessible to both StarGame () and Update (). That's your problem!
So, that's what you're going to need to do is declare them,
at the top. So, lets do that declare but not initialize, which
means we take off the values. Does
that make sense? Just by declaring them, just by bringing them
into existence, before StartGame () or
guess or NextGuess () even start running. That will
fix that compiler error, and you should find now, that when we try and
run that you can just play the game and it works. Brilliant! And
that when you play the game, let's just do that again.
Let's, firstly, go to I don't know... Ooh,
now my ups and downs aren't working. So, we have another
challenge. Why why am I getting 0's coming out
of everywhere now, suddenly. So, what have I done wrong? int
max; int min; int guess; max =
1000; min = 1; guess = 500;
Hmmm, should be OK, shouldn't it?
So, let's just take a look at that! We need to do the first bit of
debugging. Click play. OK.
"Is the number higher or lower than 500?" It looks like it's guessing 500,
so let' me say =, and it goes "I won!". Fine, and then
we're back to where we were. Equals, I won, so it keeps going around in circles.
Good! Let's go down. "Higher or lower than 0?"
So why, when I push the Down Arrow Key, is it setting the guess to
0? Let's take a look at the code.
max = guess; min = guess;
hmm? OK, now
here's the lesson! The lesson is that, it's about
declarations and initializations. This
is a declarations, int it's the type and the
name of the variable, so I'm declaring them there. The problem is,
I'm redeclaring them here, inside StartGame ().
I don't want to be saying int max =,
I just want to say max =, min =, and
guess =. Then, these variables will refer
to the variables that were declared at the top. OK.
Easy mistake to make, because I just made it. Let's have a look!
Up and down, we get to 226,
hit Return, it starts a new game at 500.
let's just check the edge conditions, up to 1,000. Awesome!
Down to 1, up to 1,000.
Awesome, I think it's working! And the
beady eyed among you may have noticed that the
system prints 1001,
the first time it runs. So, let's just quickly run the game!
And it says here, the highest number you can pick is 1,001,
which is actually incorrect. It should be 1,000,
and the reason for that is that, we do our max = max + 1;
here on line 19, whereas we would be better moving that
down to the bottom of the function, somewhere underneath here.
So, I'm going to leave that to you, as an exercise to the reader, and Brice
will be fixing that in the next section. Basically we're there! You
have completed the Number Wizard Console game. You have hopefully
gained a lot of confidence in your programming skills, and we look
forward to building in some User Interface and some more interesting
stuff, in the rest of the course. See you soon!