Hello and welcome back! In this video. we're
going to go about looking at some approaches
to debug small programs. So. many of our students
come and have problems on the course. They
hit a bug. they hit the snag and we want to
help you out. so that when you hit those things
you have some things to try out so that you
don't get too stuck. So. the first thing I
want to go through is the compiler. The compiler
is our friend and our friend is the compiler.
So. the compiler is there basically to turn
your code into code that we can understand.
as humans. All the syntax we're going to be
using in MonoDevelop. all the stuff we're
going to be writing. all the code is basically
human readable. It's the human version of
what the computer actually needs. and the
compiler basically translates from the human
version. or human friendly version. to a computer
friendly version. If you were to look at a
file that's designed for the computer to read.
you'd find out it's actually completely illegible
to a human. The computer needs things in a
particular format. It's very very hard to
see what it's doing. from the eye. It's very
hard to read. and in fact. for every line
of our code in our language we use to talk
to the computer. the coding language. in our
case C#. we might generate thousands of computer
instructions that the actual processor inside
your computer is going to execute. So. basically
the compiler is the guy or the program that
takes the human readable to computer readable
source code. And basically. you might not
think that code is very human readable and
it isn't. It's not a great format for creating
and putting together instructions. but it's
currently the best we have. And if you have
a look at the code that the computer executes.
you'd find that it's a significant step up.
So. why is the compiler our friend?
Well. because the compiler has to understand
all the code that we write to be able to turn
it into code the computer will understand.
and it's a great way to find errors and warnings.
So. the first thing I would recommend is listen
to the errors and the warnings in the compiler.
that's really useful and important. Make sure
you have no errors and make sure you have
no warnings. when your game runs. and make
sure that every warning is investigated and
every error is investigated. So. when you
double click an error on compiler line or
if you're in Unity and you look at the Console
and there's an error there. you can always
double click it and it'll take you straight
to the line of code that caused the error.
That's really useful. And what you'll find
is that the error is always above or on the
line that's mentioned in the error. and what
you'll tend to find is that the error often.
if you have a simple syntax error. it'll be
on the line above. Let's say you've forgotten
the semicolon or you've forgotten to close
a curly braces. then it will tell you there's
an error on that line. But what you really
want to look at is. do I have a syntax error
on the line above? So. that's the first thing.
The second one is. you can run a build in
MonoDevelop before you test in Unity. and
you can use the shortcut Command D on OS X
or F8 on Windows. to run a build. And what
that will do is it will highlight the lines
of code that have warnings or errors attached.
even before you jump into Unity. so that you
can make sure your code can run correctly
or at least compile correctly. before you
get to your game. Now. understanding all the
errors. the error messages. can be quite intimidating.
and it's normal to not quite understand what's
going on when you begin to program and this
is something that will take time and practice.
to realize what an error means.So. if you
see an error have a look. dig through the
code. try the other steps we'll show you.
and then. eventually with time. you'll be
able to understand a lot of those compiler
error messages and see exactly what's going
on. And in fact. eventually it'll become a
super power. I've had situations where I've
sat next to somebody. and I've seen the compiler
say hey. this is what's happening with your
code. this is on the line above. this is what's
going on. The fact is. the compiler gives
you a lot of information. it just takes time
and practice to be able to realize what it
means. but don't worry too much. it's quite
helpful eventually. The second one. is The
Rubber Duck Sensei. Now. it's called a rubber
duck debugging. and as you can see our lovely
little yellow duck. right here. and The Rubber
Duck Sensei is basically every time you have
a problem with your code. every time you have
an issue or a bug. the first thing you want
to do is have a rubber duck next to you on
the table. and what you do is you turn to
the rubber duck and out loud. actually speaking.
you tell the rubber duck what the problem
is. Not only do you tell the rubber duck what
the problem is. but you also explain what
you think is going on with your code. So.
step the rubber duck through all the code.
line by line. explaining what's going on.
and eventually. you'll come to see the rubber
duck is the wisest friend you've ever had.
because the rubber duck will tell you when
you have a problem with your code. It won't
speak because it's far too wise to be using
such a simple method of communication. as
actually quacking. It'll actually simply look
at you and make you realize what the error
is. So. I highly recommend that any time you
have an error you step through the code. line
by line. speaking out loud explaining to the
rubber duck what you think is going on. it
is invaluable and you can look at more information
about Rubber Duck Debugging on that link right
there. I'm not joking. some programmers really
do have rubber ducks next to their computer.
I personally try and to write an e-mail to
a friend. that's always very useful. It's
like this is what is going on with my program.
it's got this bug I don't really understand
it. and the more I write the more I find out
the solution on my own. So. this is Rubber
Duck Debugging. that's another technique for
you to try. Next is assumptions. Right. when
you're debugging a program you should assume
nothing. Most bugs in computer code are actually
due to your incorrect assumption of the programmer.
so the programmer sitting in front of the
computer and is assuming something that isn't
so. Computers are really good at doing exactly
what we tell them to. and in fact. they're
too good at that right. So. if you tell them
to do something not quite right. they will
do it quite blindly. and that's the point.
The point is most of the time. we make assumptions
about the state of our program that cause
problems as the program progresses. So. the
first thing you want to do is list all the
assumptions. before and after a method is
called. for example. or any section of code.
So. list all the assumptions you're making.
Firstly. you're assuming simple things right.
the machine is on. I guarantee you I personally.
in my programming life. have had problems
where my assumption about the machine being
turned on or off was incorrect. and I spent
weeks debugging this problem. simply because
I did not make that assumption clear and didn't
check my assumption. So. prove your assumption
using prints or debug log messages. to make
sure that the assumptions you're making about
the state of your programs are correct. If
you can write the assumption down in your
code as comments. that's useful. but better
yet. you write them down in the code as tests
or assertions. So. you're making the assertions
that this is the state of your program. before
and after a particular section of code. this
is invaluable. Knowing what is an assumption
and what isn't is really useful. and whenever
you have an assumption don't think it's got
to be like that! No. prove your assumptions.There is nothing but.
It's only an assumption unless you've proven
it. So. until you can say this is so. because
I can prove it and I can prove it by writing
out the output on my console. you have proved
nothing. You have just got an assumption.
so turn assumptions into facts using proof
via printing or testing. And remember. this
is not just you that's going to make those
methods. it is hard. programming is hard.
and in fact the Mars Climate Orbiter was a
very expensive space probe that crashed in
the Martian atmosphere. because somebody made
an assumption about the units used in the
code. So. instead of using Newton per second.
they were using pounds per second or something
like that. and the difference between Metric
and Imperial unit meant the probe crashed. So.
this is hard. assumptions matter. and if you
are not careful they can lead to very very
expensive and embarrassing blunders. So. what's
next? The next one is the Minimum Viable Test
Case. When you've got a bug and you've got
a problem with your code. you want to be removing
as much code as possible. while still having
that bug. so you still have a bug in your
code. but you're removing every bit of code
that isn't relevant to that bug. So. step
by step. remove a line of code or remove a
section of code or remove a function. till
you've got only the code that causes the bug.
At some point. you'll be removing a line of
code that is where the bug is. and the bug
will disappear. the behavior will stop. That's
really useful. because you'll know exactly
where the bug is being created. where the
bug is being caused. It's also much easier
to reason about smaller code sizes smaller
code samples. and it's also. we'll jump a
little bit ahead of ourselves here. but once
you've got a Minimum Viable Test Case. it's
much easier to share with other people. If
you've got a 5.000 line program. or even just
a 500 or 50 line program. and the error is
just in 5 lines. it's much easier abouts for
somebody else to reason about those 5 lines.
than it is to reason about the 500 lines.
So. a minimum viable test case does not mean
you're removing code that works. You're making
the smallest thing that actually reproduces
the bug. not a line more. but the point is
it's still a fully working piece of code.
It still runs and executes. it's just that
it exhibits the behavior and nothing else.
That's the Minimum Viable Test Case. and we'll
meet it again when we do "How to Ask Good
Questions" . And finally. debugging is like
science. Use the Scientific Method for debugging.
So. roughly speaking. The Scientific Method
is. you make a hypothesis and you develop
a testable prediction. so if something goes
wrong with your program you make a hypothesis
about why that is. you develop a testable
prediction. given your hypothesis. and then.
you test it. So. let's say my hypothesis is
the variable isn't changed in those 5 lines
of code. Well. OK. let's make a test. Well.
I can test by printing the variable out before
the 5 lines of code. printing it out after
the 5 lines of code. and make sure that the
variable has the same value. And then. I test
the prediction by running this code in my
system and I repeat until my tests are in
agreement with my hypothesis. or I repeat
until I have to make a new hypothesis about
what the cause of my problem is. This is really
the key of debugging. The Scientific Method
is really what you're going to be using for
debugging your program. so don't forget this
scientist is the guy who can debug your code.
At least. it'll be what you look like. after
a crazy bug. I'm sure. [Laughs] So. that is
how to debug small programs. There are some
great resources as well. on this page. You
can see Eric Lippert. who is a programmer
who has written this great blog post about
how to debug small programs. and John Regehr's.
I apologize if I'm not saying his name correctly.
he also wrote something about the scientific
approach to debugging in that blog post. in
another blog post as well. As you progress
through the course. this will become more
and more relevant and should hopefully help
you sort out your problems with your code.
Alright. I'll see you in another video! Bye
for now!