Hi guys,
welcome to Box Modeling! We're going to be covering some awesome stuff in this next section,
really getting you into Blender and making your first model. And we're going to
start off with the real fundamentals of any 3D model. What are those,
Ben? So we're going to take you through, from the very beginning, because we think that it's
really important to understand what's going on, down at the detail level in
Blender. It's really going to serve you in the future, if you get that base layer of your understanding
sorted. So we're going to start by telling you what vertices are. Vertices are
basically points in space, that's all you need to think about them as. They're just something
in a 3 dimensional space, with an X, Y, and a Z coordinate.
Once we've got more than one vertex, let's say well two, we can draw a line between them.
And if we do that, what is that line we draw between two vertices? Well that's an edge and
edges will make up the majority of your geometry, and eventually,
when you have 3 or more edges closed together you
get a... You get a face! We'll be talking about faces a little bit more in the middle of the
section. But faces are what they sound like, it's a flat surface and it
[aw] does actually have a direction to it. A face can be facing outwards
or inwards, and that's quite important, so pay attention to that and we'll talk about that a little bit later
on. Basically, by the end of the section, what are they going to be able to do, Mikey? Well you
will be able to make any placeholder, any basic model that you like.
So think about childrens' toys and how they're representations of real life
objects. You're going to be able to create pretty much any of those that you can see.
Cool! And by a process of successive improvement, you 'll be able to go from your placeholder
objects to fully fledged models, if you want to do that, and here on the Blender course you probably
do. Some people might just want to be making placeholders, just to pop in maybe in their game,
and then, go away and carry on with development. Whatever you want to use these placeholders for, they're the
starting point for either you or somebody else to take that and make it into a fully fledged
model. You might just want to try it out in prototype and see is this the right type of shape and
size. Is this the thing I want to go for? So play around with it, have great fun!
And remember, share your creations as we go along! We as instructors
love to see what you guys come up with.  And first of all I want to show you one
the first things we'll be creating in this section.  It is a very simple
block work plane.  It's a great placeholder for any particular plane
you're going to use. Maybe not a jumbo jet! But, you get the idea.  This is just a
first iteration.  Once you have skilled up this will take you but
a few moments to make.  Of course from this you can build that out
and you end up with something more like this: Here we go!
This is literally just a little bit more time.  Well, I say a little a little bit more time it is
exponentially more time.  So, the first one I could
now do in about a minute- give or take.  This one with more
detail in it is probably going to take me about 5 times longer, maybe even 10
times longer if I start putting more detail in.  From this you can
now make out this looks kind of like an F-15 or something along those lines.
Maybe a Mig?  We just don't know at the moment 'cause the detail's not there, however from
this you can build upon it again.  That is the best way of building your
models: from the the ground up.  It is very tempting to go straight
for that high poly, ultra realistic, but really
if you get these low poly models nailed you will be able to
produce things much much quicker, and work out what you want to keep and what you
want to get rid of.  Now by the end of the section we'll be building
these Mayan pyramids.  There is lots to learn with insetting and
look at all these stairs!  I wonder how we can go about creating those in a way that
is not too painful to do.  This is a very simple Mayan
pyramid.  Obviously you can take all the skills you have learnt to add even more detail.
So, remember as you go please do share your work over on the forum.  I love
seeing what you guys come up with.  Especially as you are toying about and playing.
Sometimes you end up with happy accidents.  OK,
I will see you guys over on the next lecture!