So in this video we're going to explore some basic modeling
concepts! Let's hop over and draw something!
Hi guys, welcome back! Now, we're going to do a little
exercise with the board behind! Take a step back from Blender, just to grasp
a few concepts, and then, we're going to hop into Blender and start
working, using those concepts. So Blender
is great for modeling, as we all know, but it's
always worthwhile starting with some fundamentals. So we've already played
with some primitives. Now we're going to work on those primitives
and make them work for us, rather than the other way around. So
I'm going to use this red pen here, to represent what we call a
vertex or vertices. One vertex, many
vertices. So if you remember dot to dot, when you were little.
[Marker Board Squeaky Sounds] Isn't that great! I've just drawn what could be many things.
I'll draw the top bit there. So that would represent
our vertices. If I was then to join these
vertices together
with what are known as edges, we will end up
with something. Now, depending on
what you want to call that, most people I think would say a house.
Now I know of no houses that look like that, but it
represents the house itself. A similar argument can be
said for.. if I was to draw something like this
and then do that. Yes, some people may
say it's a mushroom cloud or some may say it's a tree. In fact, in this
case, I've drawn a tree, but it's not a reallistic tree,
it's a representation of a tree. And essentailly that's all
what low poly modeling is all about, it's enough polygons to
make sure what you're trying to show people, what it's representing,
is close enough. One final example, if we do
a couple of circles, put a line in,
and go around our model like that,
most people will see that as a car, and I don't know many cars that look
like that.
It's challenge time! Draw or model something simple.
Now this is a bit of an odd one, of course, we've taken a step away from Blender, and the whole
purpose of this is to get you thinking about how things
are constructed on a fundamental level. So I'd like you
to just grab a bit of paper and pen and draw somre representations
of common objects. Whether it's copying what I've done with the house,
perhaps add something to it, etc. Think about
animals, how are they constructed? For instance, a stick man and things
like that. It's important to grasp how things are constructed,
because that's going to help you massively, moving on when we start
modeling things within Blender. If you do have some Play
Dough or anything similar to that, maybe Plasticine, then try that too!
It's great fun, [Laughs] I certainly had fun doing it! And
it's very very satisfying creating something, so
pause the video now, go off and just sketch some representations,
and model if you've got your access to Play Dough,
Plasticine, etc.
Alright welcome back! Alright, let's see
what I got up to! Well I
grabbed my white board and I drew some representations. I
know what all of those items are, just by looking at them,
um, but I didn't look at
any reference material,
I just used what was in my mind, what do I think
these things look like. And we're got a ship, a rocket,
a tree, a house, some sort of bird,
and a train. Now, I'm not sure how closely those
resemble real world items, in fact, they're probably
far from them, but they're very similar to how kids toys are constructed.
I also got my hands on my
childrens' Plasticine and did a little tree and a little
house. Again they're not realistic, but if you showed them
to someone, they would grasp immediately what you were trying to show them.
Alright let's take the concepts we've learned now and head on
over into Blender!