Welcome to Insetting in Blender! In
this video, we're going to learn how to use a very powerful tool, the Inset
Tool, and also understanding how the Outset
option works. So let's hop over into Blender!
This is the default view, as always, and
let's just zoom in to our cube, hop
on over into Edit Mode, and we're going to select
a face. So the Inset Tool works best when you
select a face, and you can find it under Mesh,
Faces, and then, Inset
Faces. And you can see it's got the shortcut key I.
Now when you inset the face, it's effectively the same
as, and we've just locked it in there, it's effectively
the same as extruding that entire face by nothing,
by moving it nowhere, creating a duplicate face on top of it,
and then scaling it inwards. And we can demonstrate that on this face
here. If we extrude, as we've done before, but by
0 and then
scale that down, it produces a very
similar result but it allows us to do it in one operation.
We can then take that new face and do what we want with
it. Now this face here, we'll just play
with it a little more. If we go
inset and we just move it a little and left-click,
on the left-hand side we
see this area here, which allows us to alter
what we're doing. So we've got Inset Faces, let me see we've got the Boundary, Offset
Even, etc. etc. And now, down here, we have some finer
controls. So Thickness refers to how far this inset
has gone, and as we can see, if we adjust that, it moves up and
down. And, in this case, this number is
relative to the actual face
itself. So, in this case, 1 is insetting
all the way. Ah, so what I've done there is,
I've clicked away from this inset, so it's actually set it to those
distances, which is not what I wanted to do. So I'm going to
undo what we've just done, I'm going to go and inset again,
and left-click just the once.
So down here we've got our Thickness. If we set that to one, it will inset
it right to the middle. If we inset it 2.5,
then it will inset half way, that's how that is working
there. The Depth is slightly different. Now the Depth allows
you to push into your model or pull out
of your model. So you can do what we've just done to the top
in one movement from here and very precisely.
Now Outset is a bit different, Outset
keeps the new geometry in the
same place. Now it looks a bit weird, now that we've ticked the Outset button, so let's
go back and play with these numbers so we can see what happens.
Now you can see that this new face here, the depth
is the size of that face. So if we leave it set at 0,
it'll be the same size as it was before, but the Thickness is
pushing the rest of the geometry away from that face.
So this is what it looked like, and as we push, we're
pushing the rest of the geometry and it's squashing away and there will be certain
times when that will be of great benefit to us.
Just remember that Outset, you can toggle it
on and off here, and it will remember your previous ones. If you go to Inset
again, and Outset is actually turned on,
ticked on the left-hand side there in the Operator panel, then
you may find yourself [Laughs] having difficulties, thinking it's Insetting and
it's going to be outsetting. You can also use the O key, as well, to get
out of Outset move. So armed with that knowledge,
I have a challenge for you guys!
Create a Mayan
pyramid. So using the Inset Tool, I'd like you to create a
Mayan pyramid, make it at least 6 steps
high, and feel free to add extra detail,
if you want to. So, just for refernce, that's
the sort of pyramid I'm talking about, one that's basically a series of
steps up to the very top.
And just so you know exactly what we're looking for, at
this point in time, it's just the basic shape of a Mayan pyramid,
something that looks something like this. Now, of course, if you
feel confident enough to go ahead and produce something like this,
then please go ahead and, you know, really give it a go and see
what you're capable of, but this is the stage that I'll be taking
it through in this challenge solution. And then, we'll go and add on the
rest of the details in the following lectures. So pause the
video now and give that a go! OK,
welcome back! Let's go through the Mayan pyramid
challenge! So I'm going to hop back over into Blender,
and I'm going to get rid of what we've got on the screen,
because it's not going to be a good starting point. In this case, I'm just going to start a new file.
So I'm going to want to start with the base.
So I'm simply going to scale this cube,
whilst we're still in Object Mode, that's fine, and I only want it on the X, Y,
so I'm going to exclude the Z axis with Shift Z.
And I'm going to pull that out, and I'm going to lock it to a size of 10.
So that's 10 times bigger in the X, Y plane and nothing
in the Z.
OK, so now we can hop on over into Edit Mode,
and I'm going to go to Face Select.
Now another way, as you can see here, that you can do this is Control
and Tab. It gives you a pop-up, wherever you are
in the 3D Editor, to select what you want to do. So in this case, Face
and I'm going to select this top face. Now I'm going to inset
it by pressing the I key. Now remembering that
this is the number that it's going in by is
proportioned to the actual size of the face, so I want each step to
be 1, and I've gone out by 10, so I need 10%
or 0.1. So I'm just going to type in
0.1, and we can see along the bottom that the Thickness is set
to 0.1. And I'm just going to press Enter, at that point,
and there we go, we've inset. And now we can extrude that face
upwards, so I'm going to press the E key to extrude.
It already seems to be locked in the Z axis, and I can press 1
and press Enter. So there we go, there's our
first step. And we're going to have to repeat that, a couple of times, to get our steps in
place. So I'm going to do that now, so I'm going to go Inset
by 0.1, extrude, and we can see the blue
Z axis is highlighted, so I can just hit 1. I,
0.1, E, 1. So this
is quite a quick way of getting our pyramid
shape built up, by just using the keyboard. I'm not even
touching the mouse, at the moment. Of course, you could go through and...
Oh, I've gone out of sync there! You could go through
and use the normal commands with all the buttons on the
side, if you wanted to. I do like using keyboard shortcuts
where possible, because they tend to be very powerful,
and I have gone into automation mode now, so I have no idea
if I've done 7 or it has to be at least 7, I think I said. So
there we go! So we've got the final box on top, so there's a nice Mayan
pyramid there. And I'm actually
going to move this bottom face, also up by 1.
So I'm just going to grab it and move it up,
but I want it to be a bit more precise. So grab
by 1 and we can see it's traveling by 1 in the lower-
left, and press the Z key, to make sure it's going in the Z
axis and I want press Enter. So now I can see that the base of
this pyramid is actually on the X, Y plane,
so it is on what we call like the ground. So the final bit here
is this little bit of square stuff at the top.
I haven't a clue how wide that is, probably 3 or 4.
So if I extrude, and again the blue is already highlighted by
4, and just have a look. That just looks odd! It
looks too big, so I'm just going to bring it down
to there. So I'm just doing that by eye. So
there we go, we've got our basic pyramid! You, of course, could go in and
create some steps if you wanted to, and make this a much more fleshed out
pyramid, using the previous knowledge that we've got. Otherwise,
there we go, we've got our Mayan pyramid using the Inset Tool!
Take care! See you in the next lecture!