Welcome to Different Selection Methods! So in this video we're
going to learn some more ways to select your geometry using
two features, Border Select and
Circle Select. So let's hop over into Blender!
Now both of these features are located in the Select menu, on the 3D
Editor Header. So under Select we can see we've got
Circle Select and Border Select. Now you may hear me refer
to Box Select, which is exactly the same thing
as Border Select. You're essentially drawing a box or a border around
the things you wish to select. So you do need to be in Edit Mode, if you're not already,
and you do need to choose what you're going to
select, just like you would do if you were selecting things individually, whether they be edges,
faces, or vertices. So if we hit
the B key, let's see what happens! So we've got it on Edge Select and
we're going to draw a box around here. So we've selected every edge
that line came in contact with, and if we spin
around, we will see that it's not selected anything on the other side.
If you do want to select through an object, say
the whole top of this pyramid, I would suggest
you first move your view around, so you can select the box.
Orthographic View is best, so there's no perspective playing.
You'll want to deselect what you've already selected, and you can just press the A key, which
deselects as well as selecting all. Hit the B key
for Box Select, and
before you do that, you'll want to go
into Wireframe Mode.
So let's rotate it back around. In Wireframe mode, when you use a
selection tool, it selects through your object. So
if I'm cautious now about how I'm selecting, that should have selected
everything on top. You have to be careful, if
I had dragged the box around the actual..ah, too far, I
would have selected all the top of the pyramid as well. Now in this
view you'll notice, if I then go and box select that edge
it adds to the selection. And if you want to remove
from the selection, when you're doing the box selecting, you can middle-
click. So a middle-click and drag will deselect.
Just clicking
and selecting more will add to your selection, with no further input.
So let's try out Circle Select!
Well Circle Select produces a circle, and you can change the size
of that circle with your scroll wheel. So obviously if it's this big and we've
got it on Edge Select as we go over, I'm clicking now, you
can see I'm selecting loads of edges as we go, and as soon as...
And we see this one here, as soon as all four edges of a
face, or however many face...edges the face has, have
been selected, the face highlights as well. So if I
select that edge there it adds to it. And again, middle-clicking will
deselect as you go. So you can deselect and select using
both of these selection tools. Very powerful stuff, especially since
we can change the size of this circle. Finally, you can't
do anything until you've exited the circle, so you do need to right-
click at some point to exit, whereas the Box Select automatically
exits at the end of the selection. I
feel a challenge! OK guys,
I'd like you to remove some of the pyramid. Using either
Border or Circle Select, I'd like you to remove the parts of the pyramid,
covering the ramp that we've made ready for the stairs.
So go and pause the video now and give that a go!
Welcome back! Let's go and remove those parts
of the pyramid. So let's hop straight on over into Blender! Now,
we can see quite clearly... Oh, we can't actually,
because this pyramid's the same on both sides, and I've rotated
it around several times, so I can't see clearly! One of these has got a ramp under
it and one of them hasn't. How do we tell that, well we're going to hop over
into Wireframe Mode!
I'm going to move it back into Perspective Mode, and I'm just going to remove all the rest of the orange.
So we can see there that there's no ramp on this
side and there is on here. So now we know that, we can come out
of Wireframe Mode. Now the ramp itself, I'm being a bit forward
thinking here. The ramp itself stops on this edge, so we don't want
to delete that edge, otherwise the ramp itself will disappear.
So we need to delete that edge, all the way down to
that edge. We could hold down Shift and select them all, there's not a great number. In
this case I'm going to, because I'm at an angle I could make it perfectly square
and use Border Select, but because I'm at an angle, I'm going to hit C for
Circle Select. It doesn't have to be terribly big, so I'm just drawing straight
up here, all the way to there. Finally,
I can either go through Mesh, Delete, but I'm just going to hit the X key.
Ah, so with the circle selected, remember to right click out of it.
OK X! How are we going to delete the edges?
There's nothing else just the edges. And there we go, we can see our ramp
underneath. Brilliant! How did you guys get on?
Remember to save your pyramid, if you haven't done already.
And oh, I've just had a thought!
We or certainly I haven't named my
Cube... That's not a Cube! Oh dear! So let's change that
now, so it says Pyramid. Tut tut, if any
of you have already named your mesh Pyramid, congratulations you've beat the
teacher to doing it!
Make sure you do name your meshes, otherwise,
later on when you have something more complex it's going to be a pain to
find anything. See you guys in the next lecture!