Welcome to Using the Array Modifier! In this video we're
going to introduce you to your first modifier and that is the Array Modifier.
We're going to let you know that they are non-
destructive until you apply them, and finally how to
separate your geometry, so you can work on the array that you've
generated. Let's hop over into Blender!
So here we have our pyramid,
as always, because that's what we've been working on. I don't know whether you guys have been working on
anything in between, but this is our pyramid and we want to play with
the Array Modifier.
Now, over in the right-hand side,
if you've still got it open, we need the Properties window open. If you've shut it,
if you could bring open a frame and change it to the Properties type,
and you may want to drag these out a little more, so you can
see all of these different types of properties that we can mess
around with. And we want the one that looks like a spanner or a wrench,
and when we click on that, we've got this option here to Add a Modifier.
If we select Add Modifier and go to an Array,
we can see it immediately generates a copy
of our pyramid, but it doesn't exist yet, it doesn't
exist until we click Apply. So I'm going to generate three of
these, and I'm going to change the Offset here.
Now Relative Offset means it's relative to the
model itself, so they're exactly one of themselves apart
in the X axis. And if we have a look we can see that the
bottom of the stairs touches the rear of the pyramid each
time. So we can change that, we can set them a little further apart
if we want, and we can change the direction of which they're set apart.
Isn't that awesome! So we've got lots of control
over what we do there. However these are all
one object, at the moment, if I scale one they'll scale the others perfectly.
So if we want to make a difference here,
first of all we have to Apply. Ah, "Modifiers cannot be applied
in edit mode"! No secret, that's why I didn't want to switch over to Object Mode, so you
could see that. You do need to be in Object Mode to Apply this modifier.
So let's click on Apply and now
these three, they're not objects they're all one mesh. These
three parts of this mesh are now real.
We can start messing around with the
geometry of each one. So in order to do that, we really need
to separate them out, and there's a straight forward way of doing that. We do need
to go back into Edit Mode, and then, we have to select all of the geometry we
want to put into its own area. So I'm going to switch into
Wireframe Mode and then do a Border Select and highlight
all of that. Now I've selected the other model there, so I'm going to go
onto the top and I'm going to highlight all of our
model, after deselecting because Border Select adds
every time. There we go! Now I'm going to press the P key,
and we're going to Separate by Selection.
So now we've got Pyramid001, and I'm going to call that
excitedly, Pyramid 2. In fact,
in this case it's almost not worth
renaming them, but I am because I'm going to do a
big pyramid in the middle, once we've separated them all out.
So we've got that and we just need to separate this here. So we're going to hop into
Edit Mode on that object, and finally,
let's just go above everything and hit
Box Select and there we go! We've selected everything there, I'm going to go
P, by Selection and that's separated that out,
and I'm going to make that one Small...
Really, SmallPry great!
In all my rush, Pyramid. There we go! So
we've got Big Pyramid, Small Pyramid, and Pyramid 2, and when we select those we
can see they're now all separate objects that we can mess around with. So I can
literally grab this now and move it to my heart's content and to
where I want. So I can pop it over here, and for the purpose of this exercise I'm
going to constrain it to the X, Y axis. So I'm going to
exclude it, so it doesn't disappear into the ground. I'm going to pop over here and then finally
I'm going to scale it on the Z axis.
I can't really see what's going on unfortunately, so I'm going to
cancel that and rotate around. I'm going to scale it on the...
There we go! Scale it all the way up, so it's a super
pyramid but only on the Z axis. This is going to look a bit funny,
but that's OK for the purpose of this. This one I'm only going to scale on
the X, Y axis, so it's going to be lovely
and flat. As you can see, it's disappeared
into the distance there. And if we make it like that,
we've got our three different pyramids, brilliant, and they're all separate!
Now it's time for your challenge! Let's hop over
and see what it is!
Create your stairs! I bet you guys knew that was coming! So the steps
themselves should run from the bottom to the top all the way. I want
you to create your steps using the Array Modifier and finish with
one mesh object at the end. So there's a clue you're going to have to separate
something at some point. Pause the video now and go give that a
go! Welcome back!
Let's create some stairs for our pyramids! So let's hop straight on
over into Blender! So let's work on
our Pyramid 2, which is this one at the front. I'm going to leave the other ones in the background, just
for aesthetics, and I'm going to hop on over into Edit Mode. I'm going
to start at the bottom. You could start at the top if you want. And I'm
going to zoom in right to this front area here. I'm going to go to
Vertex Select, and you can do this a number of ways. And I'm going to turn
off Merging Vertices, for the moment, because I do want them
to be separate. I'm going to click that vertex there and
extrude. So I've just created an edge basically, another vertex freely
floating in space, but only on the Z axis
and I don't know how far to do it. Perhaps 0.2?
Yes, 0.2 sounds nice! 0.2.! And then, I'm
going to extrude it in the X axis again by
0.2. So that's going to be the outline
of our stair. I'm going to select it there
and here and extrude this way, and I'm going to
snap it over here. So in fact, in this case, I'm going to turn on the
snapping to Edge and move it across until its on this edge here.
It's going to cause us a few issues. I
only need to lock it in the Y axis. There we go! So now
that's our step, we just need to multiply it several times. However,
it's part of this pyramid, at the moment, so we're going to have to select
the geometry we want, and in this case, it's just these two faces that we've created.
And then, we want to separate it with the P key, by
Selection, and it's added it down here, so I'm just going to do that Pyramid 2
Stairs. OK,
so we've got Pyramid 2 and Pyramid 2 Stairs, and the
stairs are what I want to apply the modifier on. So we're going to go down to Add Modifier,
go to Array, and nothing's happened! Why has nothing
happened? Well it's probably disappeared inside the model. There we
go! If I turn on Wireframe you can see it's disappeared inside the model. So
it's actually going in the X axis in the right direction, it's going 1 step unit there. We also
want it to go 1 step unit up as well. So on Z we want that to go
to 1, and there we go, we've got our second step!
I haven't a clue how many steps we're going to need to fill up our pyramid,
so I'm just going to increase this number until it looks right.
Zoom around to the top, I think we need two more. Excellent! So in this case, with a
step height and depth of 0.2 I need
35 to get to the top of mine. Now finally,
because they don't exist yet, only the bottom one does, I'm going to Apply
my modifier. Now I can go in and, if I wanted to,
edit these ever so slightly, so I can make one higher,
one lower, etc. etc., if I wanted to. I don't but what
I do want to do is now merge these two objects back together. So
I'm going to hop over into Object Mode, select our Stairs,
and our Pyramid and press Control
and J for Join. They're now together and unfortunately
it's name is Pyramid 2 Stairs. I don't want that, it's just Pyramid
by itself at the moment. And there we go, we've got our Pyramid with
stairs. That's great! How did you guys get on?!
See you in the next lecture!