Welcome to Loop Cuts and Face Loops! In
this video you're going to build on your knowledge of loop cuttings and
how face loops are similar to edge loops.
Let's hop over into Blender! So we have
our Pyramid that we've been playing with. Let's go in
and add some more detail to this top section.
So let's hop on over into Edit Mode and let's
zoom in here. Now when you hold down Control and R you
enable your Loop Cutting Tool. Now, before we
click to actually apply that cut, we can
use the Scroll Wheel on our mouse, in order
to increase the number of cuts. And that can go up and up
and up and up and up, and we can see in the lower-left that that's 35 cuts
there. That's a bit too much for this exercise,
so we're going to lower that down to maybe 3
or 4. I like 5 actually,
in this case. I'm just thinking of what I'm going to do later on.
And then, you've got the slide function, once again.
Now there's plenty of stuff you can do this with, and I want to actually
push this up a little higher anyway. So I've got
a nice set of geometry. And this has created a series of edge loops around
our model and has cut up our top of this model into
several more faces, adding more geometry.
And the more geometry we have, the more control we have
over our model, the more detailed we can make it. So
at this point, I want to select all of these edges going around,
so I can bulge it out or move it in or do whatever I want with it.
So making sure that the Face Select is on,
again holding down Alt will enable you
to select an edge, sorry, a face loop, just like it does
with an edge loop. And if we click towards the
edge, the left or right edge, it will go around the...
Let's call it a cube for the moment, it's not quite. Go around the top this way.
If we click towards the top, then it will
follow...it'll follow our model around there.
So that's great, we can alter things very quickly. And similarly, if we want
to alter the height of one of these steps here, we can select
a edge loop towards the edge.
There we go, got it! And now we can do whatever we want, we can pull that
edge loop up and make it some sort of funky hidden thing. We need
to fill in some geometry, if we did do that. Ah but you can see how
powerful that would be. So I'm just going to undo that, so our pyramid's
not too crazy, so you guys can follow.
It's challenge time! I'd like you to create some temple
detail. So to create some extra geometry at the top of the
pyramid, that little square bit at the top, and modify that geometry to
make it a bit more exciting. I'm going to leave what you want to do
to what you want to do. All that I do ask is that you don't make it too
exciting around the top of the stairs, because shortly we'll
be creating a door into our temple, and if it's too exciting
around there, it's going to be more difficult to make the door. But go
wild with it, make it as crazy or as pointy or as large or small as you like.
Go for it! Pause the video now and give that a go!
OK guys, welcome back! Let's hop over
into Blender! Let's see what we can do to the top. So I've
already put lots of cuts in there, that's great. Um, I'm going to
Face Select and I'm going to hold down Alt and select this top ring here.
And I want to... I suppose it's scaling it out but
not up and down, so I
want to limit the Z. So we want to eliminate that by holding down
Shift and Z and pull that out. Now that seems to
be, that's not quite what I want because I still want that lip at the very top,
so I'm going to have to do something else first. So I'm going to
extrude into the same location. So I'm just going to hit
0 to make sure it stays in the same location, and that has generated an
edge. We won't see it at the moment, because they're on top of one another.
And now when we scale outwards, we've actually got
some extra geometry that prevents the top... I've zoomed in far
too far. Sorry guys! Let's scale that out again.
I've created an extra bit of geometry, which means that it's not going to bend
the rest of it as we scale out. So I'm happy with that! And let's do
just another one around here,
but this time I will bend it, so we'll do it slightly differently.
So let's scale this again... Oh uh oh, zoom out!
It's gone a bit crazy there isn't it?! So let's scale that
but this time I do want the bulge, but I don't want it over where I'm going to put the...
Ah no that's fine where the door is there. And I want to snap it, in this case,
so it's level with the roof line. So that's absolutely
fine. I'm going to have to pick a different snapping point, a Face snap.
So let's scale that out and draw along this face. No it's not
liking that! Let's try a Vertex Select and scale that
out, so it's on this edge there. So that was the best way of doing this,
so now they're the same width as one another but slightly different.
Excellent! Ah final thing to do on this top here,
I'm going to lift it up just a little more, so I'm going to extrude again,
and then, I'm going to scale inwards, so it's got a bit more of
a chamfered top. Excellent! That would to do for the moment, that's in
keeping with the rest of our model as well. How did you guys get on?!
I really want to see what you made from the top of your temple! Post it in the
discussions, and I will see you in the next lecture! Take care!