Hey guys, well done getting this far in the
course! We know you're doing great, because we see your creations in the discussions!
If you're not already posting in the discussions, then please go ahead and do
that and also ask questions in the discussions. So once you have
finished this section there's other things you could do! What are they, Mikey? Well go ahead and use
the skills you've got so far to make some more models. Go off. We've already made
a plane and some other things. Go off, perhaps find some kids toys and use
those as reference material and make those up in Blender as well.
Or just crack on with the next section and come back and practice your basic block modeling
later. Whatever you like, just keep making progress, keep having fun, keep sharing, and we'll
see you soon! Take care!