So I'm so excited to actually start coding with you now! C++
is a fantastic language. but it can be a little bit daunting
to the newcomer. so I've desgined this section called Bulls &amp; Cows
to make it a gentle introduction. We're going to ignore all the
complexities of the Unreal Engine. by focusing on developing pure
C++ code in your IDE. Integrated Development
Environment. whether that's Visual Studio on the PC or Xcode on the
Mac. We're going to need to use those tools when we move into Unreal in section
3. so let's spend some time getting the difficult stuff out of
the way and learning to be really comfortable with C++ and really comfortable
with our tools. The game we're going to buid is Bulls &amp;
Cows. and that is a word game. It's an adaption of the number game
Bulls &amp; Cows. The idea is. the computer picks a word. In fact. there's
just going to be one word in this version. And then. you hand the game over to a player.
who has to try and guess what that word is. and the computer will
tell them when they get a bull. Think of bullseye. as when they get a perfect hit.
which is where their letter is the right letter in the right place.
or when they get a cow. which is where they've got one of those that is right but it's in wrong
place. So. Bulls &amp; Cows. letters in the right place
and letters that are in the word but they're in the wrong place.
And it's a surprisingly good and strategic game. especially when you've got a limited
number of moves. You really get the sense that you're running out of time to
guess what this word is. What are we going to be learning in this section? Well.
types. routines. loops. and even
classes. all the fundamentals basically that you need
to be able to go off and start writing C++ programs. Everything we'll learn through the rest
of the course is going to be icing on the cake. It's going to be further detail and further
programming tools. but with these basic constructs like being
able to define types like strings and variables
and enumerations and being able to
loop. to be able to choose where you go in the program and to be able to go around in circles.
Conditionals. if statements. switch statements. With these basic tools.
you can do anything. and it's a great foundation for your programming.
So. we'll be following Unreal's coding style. We'll be doing a few
things to make sure that your code looks like the type of code that you're going to be making.
once we get inside Unreal in the next section. We're actually going to take our core
game class. that we build here. and we're going to move that into
the 3D game in the next section. so we're going to be reusing our code.
We'll be using Unreal's coding style. as I said. which is
by their documentation. which you can see by this link here. and
that is the Unreal coding standard. I'm going to adhere
to that as closely as I can. Attached to this lecture are notes
and resources. so you can download the
slide deck. You can even go to a URL. I'll just look it up for you.
It is bit.ly forward slash unreal
slides. and if you go there you;ll see a list of all the slides by section. And you can see
me create the slides live. actually. so that's a cool place to go! You can
download them as a .pdf. right here in the resources. Now remember. you can watch
the course offline on the iOS or Android App. And when
I announce new videos. I'll be posting it into the Facebook group and
onto the Unreal course Twitter account. So. let's dive in
and start making C++ work for us!
=======
So I'm so excited to actually start coding with you now! C++
is a fantastic language, but it can be a little bit daunting
to the newcomer, so I've desgined this section called Bulls &amp; Cows
to make it a gentle introduction. We're going to ignore all the
complexities of the Unreal Engine, by focusing on developing pure
C++ code in your IDE, Integrated Development
Environment, whether that's Visual Studio on the PC or Xcode on the
Mac. We're going to need to use those tools when we move into Unreal in section
3, so let's spend some time getting the difficult stuff out of
the way and learning to be really comfortable with C++ and really comfortable
with our tools. The game we're going to buid is Bulls &amp;
Cows, and that is a word game. It's an adaption of the number game
Bulls &amp; Cows. The idea is, the computer picks a word. In fact, there's
just going to be one word in this version. And then, you hand the game over to a player,
who has to try and guess what that word is, and the computer will
tell them when they get a bull. Think of bullseye, as when they get a perfect hit,
which is where their letter is the right letter in the right place,
or when they get a cow, which is where they've got one of those that is right but it's in wrong
place. So, Bulls &amp; Cows, letters in the right place
and letters that are in the word but they're in the wrong place.
And it's a surprisingly good and strategic game, especially when you've got a limited
number of moves. You really get the sense that you're running out of time to
guess what this word is. What are we going to be learning in this section? Well,
types, routines, loops, and even
classes, all the fundamentals basically that you need
to be able to go off and start writing C++ programs. Everything we'll learn through the rest
of the course is going to be icing on the cake. It's going to be further detail and further
programming tools, but with these basic constructs like being
able to define types like strings and variables
and enumerations and being able to
loop, to be able to choose where you go in the program and to be able to go around in circles.
Conditionals, if statements, switch statements. With these basic tools,
you can do anything, and it's a great foundation for your programming.
So, we'll be following Unreal's coding style. We'll be doing a few
things to make sure that your code looks like the type of code that you're going to be making,
once we get inside Unreal in the next section. We're actually going to take our core
game class, that we build here, and we're going to move that into
the 3D game in the next section, so we're going to be reusing our code.
We'll be using Unreal's coding style, as I said, which is
by their documentation, which you can see by this link here, and
that is the Unreal coding standard. I'm going to adhere
to that as closely as I can. Attached to this lecture are notes
and resources, so you can download the
slide deck. You can even go to a URL. I'll just look it up for you.
It is bit.ly forward slash unreal
slides, and if you go there you;ll see a list of all the slides by section. And you can see
me create the slides live, actually, so that's a cool place to go! You can
download them as a .pdf, right here in the resources. Now remember, you can watch
the course offline on the iOS or Android App. And when
I announce new videos, I'll be posting it into the Facebook group and
onto the Unreal course Twitter account. So, let's dive in
and start making C++ work for us!
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1