...
So just before I get into this lecture. I want to explain to the slightly more advanced people that this
section is purely a console game in VisualStudio. We don't even open
Unreal Engine in this section. So if you're a seasoned
C++ developer. please just do skip ahead to section 3. the Building Escape.
and we'll get straight into Unreal stuff. this really is just the basics.
An alternative is. you could go to the last lecture. have a look at our final bit of code. make
sure everything's clear to you. and carry on. but for everybody else. let's get on!
Hey guys and girls! So I want to talk to you a little bit about Game Design
Documents and start to introduce a process for planning your
games. Now it's going to be very brief. because we don't have a lot of experience at this stage. and there's a lot
of planning that we can't do. So in this video we're going to
talk about how much planning we should do. that's not very much for this first game.
I suggest you spend an hour or two on the planning.
Define the emotional problem the game solves. and I'll explain where I
got that idea from later. But basically. in all marketing
and all software we're always solving a problem. so we've got to think about the problem. for the
player. that we're solving. It's an interesting angle. Choose the concept. rules. and
requirements. that's another very basic skeleton for a
Game Design Document. and start to think about the architecture of the game. That's
the thing that you can't do yet. because with this current level of experience. I'm assuming you
don't know much about games or programming or game design. you can't really think about the software
architecture because you don't know enough about it. so we're going to kind of skip that. And then. we're going to copy
as much. as possible. of this into the code. We're actually going to do that in a future
lecture. But I just want to mention that we want this stuff to end up not just some dead
dry document. but we want our eyes on this stuff regularly. it's going to be a moving
plan. We also want to document now what may change later. So
future idea for the game. we need a not going to do now list. it's really important we
restrict the scope. If you don't take anything away from this slide apart from
this. the most important thing we do here in this design is we work out
what our initial requirements are for assets. for code. etc..
and we stick to them until we've got that working. We have a nice don't do
list. OK a good book for you is Code Complete by Steve McConnell.
Microsoft Press 2004. Chapter 3.3 talks about requirements
and the problem that the game solves. So let's dive straight in. talk about the problem.
and in a minute I'm going to challenge you to write down the requirements. So an example
of the problem this word game solves is. I want a mental challenge. That could be the problem it would solve.
I'm sitting down on the sofa and I think. ooh I want a mental challenge. Well maybe we reach for the
Bull Cow game. I want to feel smart or prove myself. perhaps you're just feeling a little
thick or something and you need to prove yourself. Maybe you just
miss word puzzles. maybe it's a nostalgia thing. Maybe you want to
prove yourself again. Maybe you want to challenge or
feel superior to. if we're honest. somebody else. and maybe you want to kind of
shove the game in front of somebody else's face. Anyway
there's lots of reasons but it's important to get clear on the problem that the game
solves. I know it's a strange thing to think about. but games still do scratch emotional
itches. So so what itch are they scratching?
So what's the concept and the rules of the game? So you need to just write that down. it's a "guess
the isogram" game. An isogram is a word with no repeating letters.
the user has a limited number of guesses. that's one of the things that
makes it fun. And after each guess the computer outputs a bull.
which is the right letter in the right place. so
we think of bullseye. if you want to remember it or cow.
which is the right letter in the wrong place. So bulls and cows. that's where it gets its name.
And you win by guessing the word within a maximum number of tries. Cool! So that is
the concept and the rules all in one actually. That's simple. look we've only got five bullet
points. OK. seven if you count the sub-bullets. But we've got the
concepts and the rules of the game written down. that's pretty powerful and that's the sort of thing
I want you to do with your game. OK so what I want you to do now is write up the
requirements. So knowing what the game needs to do. I want you to think about what the
inputs will be and in what format. Remember this is a console game. so let me give you a hint
here. The input is just text. just plain text on the console.
What will the outputs be? What tasks will
the user be asked to do? Do we have any performance
limitations to think about. in this simple game? And what assets are going to need to be created.
art. story. sound. etc.? So have a think and
pause the video for a moment. grab a sheet of paper or a document. and start writing
down some bullets. some really simple ideas and requirements. Try and get to
at least five requirements. OK so pause the video. I know you don't
necessarily know what you're doing here and this is a little fuzzy. But look. there's enough prompts on the screen
and I want you to get used to thinking about. what are the requirements. what is this game going
to need? Have a go!
Cool so welcome back! Hopefully you did pause the video there and you're doing the challenge. Here are some ideas
of requirements. Plain text instructions for all interactions. that's something we're going to need.
things like introducing the game and helping the user to make valid guesses and stuff.
Code to deal. I should say deal with. but
code to help the player make a valid guess. i.e. all lowercase.
You know. is it an isogram? Is the word that they're putting in the right
length? So we're going to need code to help them make a guess correctly. Code to check the
number of bulls and cows. in the guess. compared to the hidden word. That's kind of the core
of the game. And code to keep track of the number of
valid guesses. of course. and other things that we've forgotten. but I just wanted to give you an idea
of some of the things that you'd want to put into this. And of course. these will
actually translate into routines and lines of code. I'm quite sure.
So possible future ideas! Another way of looking at this is (The
No List). these are things we're not going to do OK. and it's important to have this list. It really
is important to have a list of things you've specifically chosen not to put in this version
of the game. OK. so we want to give feedback on every
key press. perhaps. in the future. We can't actually do that in a console. because a console submits an
entire string in one game. but in a 3D version of the game. we might want feedback on every key
press. So let me just revisit that. So what I mean is. if you start to type a
non isogram. say I start typing the word every then I might type
E V. and then when I hit the next E it might kind of go [Makes Funny Sound] or shake or do something
to say. no you can't put another E in because you've already had an E and if you did it would not be an isogram.
So key level checking. Have a large dictionary of hidden words. so the game we play
is with more than just one word. Have a user selectable word length. so the user chooses
a word length and then maybe a difficulty level as well. So if you have a long word.
you get lots of tries. but if it's on hard you get less tries. you know that type of thing.
Checking the user's guess is a dictionary isogram. so every time they put a guess in maybe it goes into
a standard dictionary and says: Well is this a word in the dictionary and is it an isogram?
Maybe we provide a time limit for the guesses. put the pressure on a little. Maybe we have a hint
system. Maybe you could spend one of your turns in return for a hint. I don't know but these
are possible future ideas. and importantly these are things we're not going to do in this version
of the game. So that's it. we've covered an overview of
how you would do a design. Hopefully you've at least written down the requirements. which is the bits
that we need to move on to the next stage. We're going to skip over the software architecture this time around.
because we're going to build this code from the inside out. starting with the coding
and then wrapping things up into what we call routings and then kind of building
outwards like that. So in future sections. in future games. we'll get a
little bit more detailed on our planning. but this is enough for now. let's crack on in the next video
and get our environment setup!