...
Welcome to how solutions and projects relate! So. in this video we'll be talking about
how a solution is a group of projects. One analogy I've
heard is. if a solution is like a house then a project is like a room in the house.
We'll be setting up a new command line project. We'll give you an overview
of the structure of our solution for this section. and in the case of Visual Studio.
you're going to need to add a main.cpp source code file to our project.
By the end of it. it'll look something like this. You'll have a second section right next
to Section_01 nice and organized. and in there amongst other clutter.
you'll have a bull cow game project folder and in that project folder you will
have your main.cpp source code file.
OK. so let''s dive in and get this section setup. and at the same time. let's
understand how folders for solutions in projects relate!
So. I'm going to go into Visual Studio. and I'm going to create myself a new project.
It's very similar in Xcode. Now. in Visual Studio. I'm looking for Visual C++
Win32 Console Application. That's where I should be in Visual Studio
If you're in Xcode then you're looking for this. OSX Application.
Application Command Line Tool. OK. that's on the slides! Great!
So. here in Xcode. when I give my project a name... I'm just going to call it Project
for now. You're welcome to follow along or you can wait until the challenge to do all of this. Then. it's
actually going to name the solution the same thing as the project. but I'm going to rename the solution
so that it's clear. So. my new project Name is Project and my Solution name is Solution.
This is my folder. I'm going to not create a Git repository
and click OK. Now. in Visual
Studio. you're going to be asked a few more questions. I'm going to select empty project and turn off
SDL. Now. remember this for your challenge. When it comes to your challenge. this is how you're
going to want to setup your application. You leave the top radio button by default. but we
select an empty project and we un-tick SDL. We basically make it as simple as we
can. Then. click finish. Right now. in the case of
Xcode. it will have actually setup a little more than it does in Visual Studio. In some ways.
it will have created a main.cpp file. but we'll talk about that in a moment. Let's
just click and see what it's made. It's made a folder called Solution. which is our Solution Folder.
Inside that. we have a folder called Project. which
is our project folder. and then. we have a Project.vxproj. And
in Xcode you'll have a very very similar setup but there'll be less files. and
under Project you'll have Project dot xcodeproj.
OK fantastic! So. that's how it works! What I want you to do now is setup
the section proper. So. I'm going to go back and delete
the Solution Folder. because we just don't need and that was just a test.
And I'm going to give you your challenge slide! So. your challenge is as follows. Setting up
your project. I want you to end up with this. Unreal
Course or whatever you've called your folder that holds all your sections. Section
02. that's your section or solution sub-folder. In Visual Studio
it's called a solution and you'll have one solution per section. In Xcode
well they really don't have the idea of solutions. so it's just a folder.
Inside that Section_02 Folder we want a BullCowGame sub-folder. That's the
Project Folder. and it should be automatically created by your IDE.
And then. within that sub-folder you'll find BullCowGame.vcxproj or
.xcodeproj. if you're in Xcode. Alright. so that's what I want
you to end up with. And inside BullCowGame. as an extra
challenge. on Visual Studio you're going to need to create yourself a main.cpp.
You're going to need to just add a file to the solution. see if you can work out how to do it yourself.
of type C++ and just call it main. It doesn't need any code in it for now
but that's it. In Xcode. over on the Mac.
you'll find that it's already done this for you. but in Visual Studio you're going to need to do the work. So.
go ahead. pause the video! See if you can get all of that setup right now. It doesn't matter if you struggle. It doesn't matter if
it takes a little while. This is good. because this is teaching you how to folder structure works.
...
Hey welcome back! So. the first part of this challenge is relatively straight forward. It's what I
showed you before. We open our IDE.
By the way. if you're an Xcode user. skip to about 7 minutes and 20 seconds. and I'll
be giving you different instructions there.
We make a new project. We're going to go Win32
Console Application or similarly in Xcode. as I showed you before.
I'm going to call it BullCowGame. because that's the name of the project and the
application that we are going to be making. But I'm going to rename
the Solution of Section_02 for organization. I'm
going to leave both of these... Well. you certainly want to create a directory for the solution. that's the whole
point of naming the directory here. but I'm going to create a Git repository. If
you don't know what that means. just leave it unchecked for now. it'll save some disk space. It's to do with Version
Management and we're not doing that at this stage in the course. OK cool!
So then. the settings I asked you to set was a Console Application. because that's what we're aiming at.
And then. I want an empty project with no SDL. Now. it doesn't matter what any of these things
actually mean. The motivation here is. we want the simplest possible project. so it's empty
and it has no clutter in the project. so we finish off.
Great! So. that part of the project is fairly straight forward. Let's see. we have a directory called Section_02.
we have a sub-directory called BullCowGame. and inside it. we have a BullCowGame.vcxproj
or xcodeproj. Fantastic. so that's
good! Now. we need this main.cpp file. If you're on Xcode.
by the way. you can stop watching now and skip to the next video. because you'll already have it already done.
But in Visual Studio there are some subtleties here. So. how do you get this
main.cpp file added? Well. there are two ways. Really there's lots of ways but
the easiest way is to click into
the Project. So. this is the Solution here. which contains one project. That project
is BullCowGame. You right-click on the project. and you can say Add. New Item.
Alright. now the easiest way is to do that. so let's do that!
Add. New Item. It's a C++ file and we're simply going to call it
main.cpp.
Oops. I'll get there in
the end! There we go. main.cpp. Add. Now. this does lots for us. If we
look on the File System. there it is as planned! It's also attached as
a source file. a source code. to the
Project OK. That's cool and we're done! That's the challenge
finished! Now. there's another way you may have attempted this. and it will cause you a little problem.
If you'd have gone New File. that's OK. And you may have said Visual C++
and C++ File. very nice. And then.
you may have put something in it. because otherwise you'll realize you can't save it until you've actually done something
like maybe made and deleted a space. And then. there's a star. which means it's an unsaved
file. Now. if you go File and Save or Save All.
it'll come up and say well. what do you want to call this guy and where do you want to put it? Well. now you've got to go work out where to put
it. which is in Section_02 BullCowGame. next to the main.cpp.
as a test. And you save it and you're still not
done. because look. it's not actually a part of the project. You see project force
files don't include it! That's a pain right! So. there are several ways you can get
it there. but one is that you could go Add. Existing Item. go and find
it. and finally it's connected in part of your solution. So. I'm actually
going to delete test. we don't need it. Remove. by right-clicking
and then Delete. and it's going to delete it off the Disk. But you see that by
far. the easiest way is to right-click the project. Add.
New Item. That does it all for us. That's it! So congratulations
you are setup! I think you understand that a solution is a container for one or more projects.
Our project is called BullCowGame. Our Solution Folder is called
Section_02 here. and we are good to start coding!
So. the rest of this video is just for Xcode users. If you're on Visual Studio.
we're finished. just skip to the next video. So. here in Xcode on a Mac. you want to
create a new Xcode project. You want to choose the
OS X section and then Application and Command Line Tool and
click Next. So. the project name is going to be BullCowGame.
And we don't have
a concept of solutions here. we're just going to use a folder for solutions
in Xcode. Just put a name in for your Organization
Name and an Identifier as a single word. It doesn't really matter what you put here. but it does
matter that you choose C++ as the language. Click Next!
So. this is my UnrealCourse Folder. empty here. In there.
I'm going to create what I'm calling a Solution Folder over in Visual Studio. but as far as Xcode is concerned.
it's just a folder to organize things. and this is section 02.
And then. once I have Section_02 selected here.
I click Create. Then. my main.cpp file
ends up in Downloads. In my case. UnrealCourse. Section_02. BullCowGame.
BullCowGame again. main.cpp. That's the folder
that we end up in. And here is your main.cpp file! We don't even need
to create one in Xcode. it's as simple as that! So. that's it!
We just want to quit Xcode. If you want to re-open that. you go to
Downloads. Unreal Course. Section_02. BullCowGame. and just go
and open the dot Xcode proj file. And that will take you back to where we
just were. Great! Congratulations and I'll see you soon!
=======
...
Welcome to how solutions and projects relate! So, in this video we'll be talking about
how a solution is a group of projects. One analogy I've
heard is, if a solution is like a house then a project is like a room in the house.
We'll be setting up a new command line project. We'll give you an overview
of the structure of our solution for this section, and in the case of Visual Studio,
you're going to need to add a main.cpp source code file to our project.
By the end of it, it'll look something like this. You'll have a second section right next
to Section_01 nice and organized, and in there amongst other clutter,
you'll have a bull cow game project folder and in that project folder you will
have your main.cpp source code file.
OK, so let''s dive in and get this section setup, and at the same time, let's
understand how folders for solutions in projects relate!
So, I'm going to go into Visual Studio, and I'm going to create myself a new project.
It's very similar in Xcode. Now, in Visual Studio, I'm looking for Visual C++
Win32 Console Application. That's where I should be in Visual Studio
If you're in Xcode then you're looking for this, OSX Application,
Application Command Line Tool. OK, that's on the slides! Great!
So, here in Xcode, when I give my project a name... I'm just going to call it Project
for now. You're welcome to follow along or you can wait until the challenge to do all of this. Then, it's
actually going to name the solution the same thing as the project, but I'm going to rename the solution
so that it's clear. So, my new project Name is Project and my Solution name is Solution.
This is my folder. I'm going to not create a Git repository
and click OK. Now, in Visual
Studio, you're going to be asked a few more questions. I'm going to select empty project and turn off
SDL. Now, remember this for your challenge. When it comes to your challenge, this is how you're
going to want to setup your application. You leave the top radio button by default, but we
select an empty project and we un-tick SDL. We basically make it as simple as we
can. Then, click finish. Right now, in the case of
Xcode, it will have actually setup a little more than it does in Visual Studio. In some ways,
it will have created a main.cpp file, but we'll talk about that in a moment. Let's
just click and see what it's made. It's made a folder called Solution, which is our Solution Folder.
Inside that, we have a folder called Project, which
is our project folder, and then, we have a Project.vxproj. And
in Xcode you'll have a very very similar setup but there'll be less files, and
under Project you'll have Project dot xcodeproj.
OK fantastic! So, that's how it works! What I want you to do now is setup
the section proper. So, I'm going to go back and delete
the Solution Folder, because we just don't need and that was just a test.
And I'm going to give you your challenge slide! So, your challenge is as follows. Setting up
your project. I want you to end up with this. Unreal
Course or whatever you've called your folder that holds all your sections. Section
02, that's your section or solution sub-folder. In Visual Studio
it's called a solution and you'll have one solution per section. In Xcode
well they really don't have the idea of solutions, so it's just a folder.
Inside that Section_02 Folder we want a BullCowGame sub-folder. That's the
Project Folder, and it should be automatically created by your IDE.
And then, within that sub-folder you'll find BullCowGame.vcxproj or
.xcodeproj, if you're in Xcode. Alright, so that's what I want
you to end up with. And inside BullCowGame, as an extra
challenge, on Visual Studio you're going to need to create yourself a main.cpp.
You're going to need to just add a file to the solution, see if you can work out how to do it yourself,
of type C++ and just call it main. It doesn't need any code in it for now
but that's it. In Xcode, over on the Mac,
you'll find that it's already done this for you, but in Visual Studio you're going to need to do the work. So,
go ahead, pause the video! See if you can get all of that setup right now. It doesn't matter if you struggle. It doesn't matter if
it takes a little while. This is good, because this is teaching you how to folder structure works.
...
Hey welcome back! So, the first part of this challenge is relatively straight forward. It's what I
showed you before. We open our IDE.
By the way, if you're an Xcode user, skip to about 7 minutes and 20 seconds, and I'll
be giving you different instructions there.
We make a new project. We're going to go Win32
Console Application or similarly in Xcode, as I showed you before.
I'm going to call it BullCowGame, because that's the name of the project and the
application that we are going to be making. But I'm going to rename
the Solution of Section_02 for organization. I'm
going to leave both of these... Well, you certainly want to create a directory for the solution, that's the whole
point of naming the directory here, but I'm going to create a Git repository. If
you don't know what that means, just leave it unchecked for now, it'll save some disk space. It's to do with Version
Management and we're not doing that at this stage in the course. OK cool!
So then, the settings I asked you to set was a Console Application, because that's what we're aiming at.
And then, I want an empty project with no SDL. Now, it doesn't matter what any of these things
actually mean. The motivation here is, we want the simplest possible project, so it's empty
and it has no clutter in the project, so we finish off.
Great! So, that part of the project is fairly straight forward. Let's see, we have a directory called Section_02,
we have a sub-directory called BullCowGame, and inside it, we have a BullCowGame.vcxproj
or xcodeproj. Fantastic, so that's
good! Now, we need this main.cpp file. If you're on Xcode,
by the way, you can stop watching now and skip to the next video, because you'll already have it already done.
But in Visual Studio there are some subtleties here. So, how do you get this
main.cpp file added? Well, there are two ways. Really there's lots of ways but
the easiest way is to click into
the Project. So, this is the Solution here, which contains one project. That project
is BullCowGame. You right-click on the project, and you can say Add, New Item.
Alright, now the easiest way is to do that, so let's do that!
Add, New Item. It's a C++ file and we're simply going to call it
main.cpp.
Oops, I'll get there in
the end! There we go, main.cpp. Add. Now, this does lots for us. If we
look on the File System, there it is as planned! It's also attached as
a source file, a source code, to the
Project OK. That's cool and we're done! That's the challenge
finished! Now, there's another way you may have attempted this, and it will cause you a little problem.
If you'd have gone New File, that's OK. And you may have said Visual C++
and C++ File, very nice. And then,
you may have put something in it, because otherwise you'll realize you can't save it until you've actually done something
like maybe made and deleted a space. And then, there's a star, which means it's an unsaved
file. Now, if you go File and Save or Save All,
it'll come up and say well, what do you want to call this guy and where do you want to put it? Well, now you've got to go work out where to put
it, which is in Section_02 BullCowGame, next to the main.cpp,
as a test. And you save it and you're still not
done, because look, it's not actually a part of the project. You see project force
files don't include it! That's a pain right! So, there are several ways you can get
it there, but one is that you could go Add, Existing Item, go and find
it, and finally it's connected in part of your solution. So, I'm actually
going to delete test, we don't need it. Remove, by right-clicking
and then Delete, and it's going to delete it off the Disk. But you see that by
far, the easiest way is to right-click the project, Add,
New Item. That does it all for us. That's it! So congratulations
you are setup! I think you understand that a solution is a container for one or more projects.
Our project is called BullCowGame. Our Solution Folder is called
Section_02 here, and we are good to start coding!
So, the rest of this video is just for Xcode users. If you're on Visual Studio,
we're finished, just skip to the next video. So, here in Xcode on a Mac, you want to
create a new Xcode project. You want to choose the
OS X section and then Application and Command Line Tool and
click Next. So, the project name is going to be BullCowGame.
And we don't have
a concept of solutions here, we're just going to use a folder for solutions
in Xcode. Just put a name in for your Organization
Name and an Identifier as a single word. It doesn't really matter what you put here, but it does
matter that you choose C++ as the language. Click Next!
So, this is my UnrealCourse Folder, empty here. In there,
I'm going to create what I'm calling a Solution Folder over in Visual Studio, but as far as Xcode is concerned,
it's just a folder to organize things, and this is section 02.
And then, once I have Section_02 selected here,
I click Create. Then, my main.cpp file
ends up in Downloads. In my case, UnrealCourse, Section_02, BullCowGame,
BullCowGame again, main.cpp. That's the folder
that we end up in. And here is your main.cpp file! We don't even need
to create one in Xcode, it's as simple as that! So, that's it!
We just want to quit Xcode. If you want to re-open that, you go to
Downloads, Unreal Course, Section_02, BullCowGame, and just go
and open the dot Xcode proj file. And that will take you back to where we
just were. Great! Congratulations and I'll see you soon!
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1