...
Welcome to C++ Function Syntax! In this video, we're going to talk about briefly the difference
between an Engine and a Library and how this relates to our Console application.
We will be looking at how the Console
knows where to find our code. That's an important point.
And then, we will look at what is called the syntax of a function in C++, how it's laid out.
We'll write the minimum C++ program to remove an error
and end up running our code, so that it just says this. Just nothing,
but the Console has no errors and says "Press any key to continue..."
It's a very very simple few lines, but it's important that you understand why we're
writing those lines. In the first section, we just wrote them. Don't look back there and cheat, by the way! But in the first
section, we just wrote these lines. Now, that you understand the anatomy
of a function, once you understand that, you'll be able to actually
write it yourself and have a much better ownership of what's going on. So, let's dive in and get this done!
...
OK, so here we are in our project. What we need to understand is that
to even write any code, we need to know where the system is looking for
our code. So, in the case of an engine like Unreal Engine it's an engine, which means that
it calls our code. In a library, you may have heard people talk about using libraries.
The difference there is that we write code that calls out to the library, but we're
in an environment, both here in the Console and in Unreal, where in an engine
effectively, and that means that something is calling into our code, at least
to get started. And right now, this will not run. Anything we write
will not run, because the system does not know where
to find our code, it's missing something. Now, if you're on Xcode, by the way, before we
do anything it has already solved this problem for you. So, I suggest you watch this video
until I show you about the anatomy of functions, and then, once I've
explained the anatomy of functions, you'll know what's already written on your screen and you'll be good to move on.
Alright, so let's just try running this! Debug, Start Without Debugging. Now, a couple of
things. Now, one of a couple of things may happen. You may get these horrible errors down here,
and if you're lucky you'll get, would you like to run the last successful build? Or
maybe you'll just come straight to this but regardless it's not working right. Why? Because we
have errors. Whenever we've got errors down here in our error list that's bad!
And this is running but it's immediately giving us an error!
It's saying, This is not recognized as an internal or external command,
operable program or batch file." right, so it doesn't like our code!
That's what we need to set out to solve, and you could get a very similar problem inside
Unreal, where it just doesn't know where to find your code. Alright,
so I'm going to tell you firstly how a function is
setup, inside C++, and then, I'm going to tell
you the anatomy of the function that we need to write. And then, I'm going to challenge
you to write it.
So, the syntax of a function in C++! What's syntax,
firstly? Syntax is the structure of the statements that we write, so it's telling us
how to write in such a way that the Compiler understands what we're saying.
What's a function? A function is something that does something. Here's a very trivial and simple function,
called DoubleMe. You send in a number, as an
integer, which is a whole number that you can count on your fingers, and it returns
another integer and we call it DoubleMe,
just to prevent any confusion with reserved words like double, which are also another
type of number. So, what's the syntax? Firstly, we have
the return type. That's the first thing we need to put in. It could be an integer? It could be
a void, which means nothing comes back? It could be a character or
string, all sorts of things, but in our case, it's an integer coming back. Then, we must have a space here
that's indicated by this underscore. It must have a space, then it's the name.
Now, our coding standard says that we're going to use upper case, and I'm actually going to use
separate uppercase letters, in the middle of my word, just to distinguish where the
second word starts at DoubleMe. Then, there may or there may not be a space here. I
have used an inconsistency on purpose, just to show you that you need to be able to see what the
compiler sees, which it ignores this type of white space. Generally
we won't put a space, but there may be a space. Then, int
or whatever the type of the thing coming in is, and then, you give
the thing coming in a name, and we're going to give it the name number in this
case. And this is something called a variable, or actually it's being used as a
parameter in a method. It's another way of describing what this number is and it
only exists inside DoubleMe. Once we get outside this curly brace, this
number no longer exists. And generally, it's bad
practice to actually modify this thing, but we'll talk about that later.
So, number comes in and it gets doubled, multiplied by 2, and then,
returned out of the function as integer type.
OK, so that's what comes in! An integer comes in, gets doubled, goes out, and
that's the general pattern. And the reason I'm telling you all this is because,
in a moment, I'm going to challenge you to write your own method, that's going to allow
our code to actually run properly.
So, here's your challenge! Write the minimal C++ program! The return type is int,
short for integer. The function name we want is main, lower case like that.
It takes no parameters and for extra credit make it return
0. Test this by running and seeing if the error goes away, when you
try and go Control, F 5, for Debug,
and run without debugging.
OK, go ahead, pause the video, and do this challenge now!
Welcome back! So, take a look at what we need to do!
Int is the return type. It's come up in blue, that's good! It's in a list, that's
good! That means that the intelli-sense or the system knows what we're typing.
Now by the way, as I said if you're in Xcode you can stop watching now,
because it's already solved this problem for you. You can move on to the next video. There's nothing
more to learn, we're just go?ing to type out the method that's already on your screen. So, main is the name.
Now, I'm going to not have a space. I'm going to use lowercase, because that's what the system is
expecting here OK, and then, I'm going to put in some curly
braces. Now, you can put them on this line, like this, but a good idea with any
braces is to open them and close them, open them and close them. Now, actually the system is doing
it for me. Visual Studio is closing them for me, which is good. So, I can just come straight in there
and put a return like that. Now, you'll sometimes see the brace there. It doesn't make any difference actually,
none of this white space makes a difference. What does make a difference to me
is that we have an indentation. So I'm going to come down, but I do want a tab,
not four spaces. Its the same as four spaces, but I want a tab before I do anything else,
and for the extra credit I want to return. It's a good sign that it's filling this in.
By the way, as soon as you see it's got the right thing, you can hit Tab.
OK, it's gone blue, it's recognized the statement. 0 and then remember
I said that all statements need a semicolon on the end. Ah cool!
Alright, now before by the way, I would put my semicolon on the end. Look, there's a little red dot here.
Start to get used to this. This is the Integrated Development Environment saying that it doesn't understand
what's going on at this close bracket, and that's saying, I expect a semicolon. So, put a
semicolon. OK cool! Let's go Debug,
Start Without Debugging, or Control, F 5. Ah
this is it! We have the Console coming up and just saying, "Press any key to continue..."
It is running and it's not complaining. The return 0 just means that when the
Console App finishes, it returns a status of 0 and is exited normally.
That's it! You have done it! I want you to save everything now, and
congratulate yourself! It's even more minimum what we did in the setup section, right,
but I hope that you understand a little bit more about what's going on. The system is
looking for one of the files in my project,
and it's looking through the files and saying, do any of these contain a method called main?
Ah here's the one called main! Now, in that method let's go
ahead and do what it says. Well, it says do nothing actually! It just says return, I leave
with a status code of 0, but at least you know
pretty much why we got here. What we're going to do next, by the way, is come above this
return and start actually writing our game at last. So, if you have been
fiddling, you'll notice a star. The star means the file has changed. Again you can
Save All and we're good to go! See you in the next video!