Welcome to #include and
Namespaces! That all sounds very technical doesn't it? So, what are we going to be doing in
this video? We're going to look at various aspects of code, that by the end of it will allow us to do
things like #include  and using namespace
standard. And we'll understand what that means and how that lets us
use character output like this, to write out to the Console,
and when we run our program we all get simply "Welcome to Bulls and Cows"
but we'll have learned a lot about what all of this stuff means. So, let's dive right in and
get that working!
OK, so we've got this far! The operating system is calling our code.
Now we want our code to do something, so unfortunately without
including some more code, we can't really
do anything, we can't print. If we type the word print the word Autocomplete
isn't suggesting anything. You may have seen cout before, that's not here.
You'll notice, from the first section, we did something like this std:
nothing still nothing nothing nothing. OK, so what you need to do is understand
how we're going to get the code that our code needs in,
and we're going to use something called a pre-processor directive and that is #.
Anything that starts # is, as I say, is a pre-proccesor
directive. There are a few, #include is down in this list somewhere
here. #define various others OK.
The one we're going to use for now is #include.
Now, that literally cuts and pastes from another file,
at the time that you say build. So,
when yo go Build or Debug, Start Without Debugging, it does a build,
and it'll actually literally go into the file that we specify here, which in our case is going to be .
And it will cut and paste the contents above at the top. We don't see
it happen, but it's why it's called a pre-processor directive. It happens just before
the compilation happens. Just before, it then goes through all the text, the resulting
text, and turns it into a format that the computer can read.
So, #include is what we need. Now, when do you use these
curly brackets vs. when do we go #include?
They're not curly are they!? They're what do you call them? Chevrons! Let's call them chevrons or angular brackets!
You'll also see, if you do searches on the web, this stuff in quotes
#include. Now, this would be "MyCode dot
h or something like that, and we'll talk about that later. But the bottom line is that
you use these angular brackets or chevrons, when you're
importing standard stuff, that's going to be there because it came
with Visual Studio, basically. And when you write your own code, and you include your own
code, you're going to use the quotes. Alright, so #include . Now, having done
that, Visual Studio now knows about a whole load more stuff. Let's try
print now. We actually get a load of methods that include the word
print. All of this stuff! We suddenly get a bewildering amount of stuff, actually,
which is pretty cool! So, the idea of using
library code is that other people have written this code, it's been
tried and tested over the years, and we know that it's going to work for us. So, if we
start trying to do things with strings in a little bit, which are a sequence of characters,
for instance. We're not reinventing the wheel we are using somebody else's library code.
I talked about, in the previous lecture about, a library vs. an engine. So,
we're kind of acting like an engine, in that the system is calling
this main method and then all of our lines get executed, but then,
very quickly we're turing the tide and we're saying, actually we're going to start using libraries. We're going to call
out to libraries. Alright, so you get the idea. Angular brace
is for the standard stuff. Now, what we're going to need to do is to think
about how we're going to access our method that we're going to use to print out to
the Console, which is cout. If I type cout it doesn't come up. It's not even
in the list, cout is for character output but it's not there. Now, the reason
it's not there is it's wrapped up in something called a namespace. Now, a namespace
does pretty much what it says on the tin, it gives names of things a bit of space.
So, because when you start importing lots
of large libraries, it's quite possible that there's more than one thing called print or more
than one thing called cout or more than one thing called whatever. So,
it's protected behind something called a namespace, so to get to it we need to know that it's in the
standard namespace, std is short for standard. When we
type std, this little icon pops up. Now, notice that
it's a pair of curly braces, and that is an icon to indicate what type
of thing we're looking at in the list. There's various other icons, and they're actually listed in your slides.
Towards the end of this section, there's a summary of what all these icons mean.
But std is a namespace and in Xcode that's going to be n
for name space. And the way that you access members of the namespace, it's a general
way of accessing members here, is colon colon. Now, we get a list of everything
that is in the  library,
tagged if you like, with a standard std namespace. So, I go std::
colon colon cout. Ah hah! Thats what I need
to print stuff out! So, let's do the standard thing at this point.
Rather than doing hello world though, I'm going to go "Welcome to Bulls
and Cows" OK. And I'm just going to do that
and remember that all of our statements end with a semicolon, and remember
that you always need to match your brackets. Now, the system doing it for you. it's making sure
that you've got as many open brackets and close brackets, and the same thing happens
with quotes. We need as many close quotes as we have open quotes.
Alright, so that red is a good sign, it means that it's interpreting this thing here as
what we call a string, a string of characters all tied together.
And let's just try it! So, Debug, Start Without Debugging,
and we have an error!
So, what's the error? Now, it's an easy thing
to do this, is to try and use cout like this, but actually cout
is a slightly strange beast and it uses something called an overloaded operator. Now, we'll actually use
those and get into those much later in the course, but
what we need to do is to use a double back chevron like that. And that double
back chevron says, take the value that is here
and put it to the character output to the Console, OK.
So, it's cout, double back chevron, and then your string. Let's try again! I'm just going to go
Control, F 5, this time. Fantastic!
"Welcome to Bulls and CowsPress any key to continue..." That's ugly! It's ugly that it
says "Press any key to continue..." straight after "Bulls and Cows". So, the way that we deal with that is
at least two ways. One is that we go backslash n. Now, the backslash means
watch out, there's a special character coming, and the special character is a new line!
So, backslash n right in there like that will have the effect of putting
any other output onto a new line, and this "Press any key
to continue..." is coming from the system. OK that's cool! Another
way of doing this would be to come onto a separate line and type std
colon colon cout again, and then, put in our
backslash n for new line. That would be another way of doing it.
And if we run it, Control, F 5, we'll see that has the same effect!
So, another way to do this is to use end line. Now, if we type endl,
which you may find with a Google search for end line, it doesn't come up! Why doesn't it come up?!
Well, it's the same reason cout didn't come up. How do you think we're going to access it? it's hidden in
namespace. Let's try standard and l. OK
fantastic! So, that is again hidden in the standard namespace.
Let's run! Command, F 5, and it works! Alright, that's
cool! One more thing to tell you about cout is that you can string
these things together. So, instead of keep writing std::cout here, I can just
delete all this stuff and do that! So, I'm just
saying, take the result of this and
put it onto the end of this, and then, put all of that into
cout. OK, let's run it! And it works!
Great! OK, so now I've got a challenge for you! I want you to use
something to prevent us from having to keep writing
std:: every time. We're going to actually use a method called using,
and the terminology is using space namespace
space and then the name of the namespece, which is standard.
So, we're going to have using namespace standard OK, and that is going to go
up at the top here, where I've left space. Alright, now
doing that is great, and it means that we can avoid having
to write this all the time. There is a disadvantage and the disadvantage is that if
two different libraries contain
or even two namespaces within this library... Remember, a library like this can
have more than one namespace. If two namespaces both contain cout,
and we say using namespace standard,
if we start doing that a lot we run the risk of what we call a namspace clash, which is that this
method is defined in multiple places, and it's not completely obvious which
one we're using. So, that's the danger of doing it, and I want you to explain that danger to other people,
in a minute in the discussions the best you can. But
here's your challenge, it's pretty simple one! I want you to make appropriate use of the using
statement. I've told you the syntax. I've showed you the line you need to put it on.
I want you to test, by removing the std:: prefixes
from your cout and see if it still works. And you can remove the prefix from the end
line, and then, explain the risk of using a namespace like this,
in the discussions as best as you can. I know that you're brand new to this, and who are you to tell other programmers
how to use a namespace and what the risks are, but just have a pop at explaining. If you don't want to
do that don't worry, that's a bonus, explaining the risk. The main thing is that you type using namespace standard
and you get rid of those prefixes. Let's go!
Cool welcome back! So, let's do that then! Let's
watch what happens when we type using, using
namespace, and it's helping us there, std OK.
And then a semicolon on the end! This is a statement!
OK, now if we just run right now, you'll notice that it still runs! No problems
not even any warnings. But what we can do is remove the std
both here and from here. That's making our code a lot more
readable. In fact, if you're on a new line and you started typing cout, it's now available
here. OK, so
let's go ahead and run! That's it, "Welcome to Bulls and Cows" Press any key to
continue..." That's just great! So as a recap, we've talked about the fact that
hash itself represents a pre-processor directive. It tells the Compiler to
do something before it even starts compiling the code. We've used #include,
which copies and pastes other code into the top of our file, but we don't see it happen.
We talked about the idea of using library code. We've used  because it's full of useful
stuff for input and output streaming, funnily enough. We've
used chevrons or angular braces for standard libraries,
and you would use quotes for files you've created yourself. We've noticed the namespace
icon in the autocomplete with standard there, and we've done a few things with cout
as well actually, which I haven't put in this list. And then, we've imported the
library and we've used the std namespace.