...
Welcome to magic numbers and constants! So, we're going to talk about what a magic
number is, why it's a good idea to avoid them. We're going to use something called const
expr, constant expression, and I'll explain how that works,
briefly introduce you to coding standards, and then, if you want to link,
by the way, to the Unreal Engine coding standards it's in the slides but also just Google
for Unreal Engine coding standards. Then, we're actually going to use one of these
constant expressions for our word length. And at the end of it, what will happen is
you'll have a bit in our code like this that says WORLD_LENGTH =, and whatever we put
will be taken through to the code, so that we have a single place in our code,
where we constantly refer to this word length but we can change it in just one place.
OK cool, so let's dive in and make this happen!
OK, so I want to finish introducing this game! So, I'm going to say "Welcome
to Bulls and Cows, a fun word game."
Fantastic! Alright now, next line! You can put what you like here, but I'm
going to say something along the lines of, "Can you guess the
X letter isogram"... We'll come back to the X in a minute.
..."I'm thinking of
?" and then maybe a backslash n this time,
just to show that you can use either. OK,
so what does that give us? Well, let's run it and see! It's very simple!
It just says, "Can you guess the X letter isogram"? Now, X isn't very helpful. It's
tempting to come in here and just hard code, because this version of the game is going to have a single word in the dictionary.
Hard code five or six, but I want alarm bells to ring in your mind, whenever you write
a number that's higher than one. So, 0 and 1 can be OK in a program.
Anything higher than 1, like 2 and above, generally unless you're
using something literal like route
66 or you know A14, a road name
in the UK. Unless it's actually kind of literally, in the world, part of the name
of something, try and avoid magic numbers, just numbers that you've plucked
out of the air and popped into your program, because it can be very hard to change. What we want is a
mechanism to change the length of this word, anywhere in the
program, and that mechanism is going to be using something called a constant expression.
OK, const...
constexpr, that's a constant expression.
Now, there's something else called a constant right above it, and we'll talk about those later,
but we want to make heavy use in Unreal and C++ of things like constants and constant
expressions. Whenever something doesn't change, we're going to use one of these two. So, now we're
focused on constant expression, and constant expression means that this
thing can be evaluated, right now, at compile time. We know
the expression from the very beginning, so the syntax is like this. Const expression, then our
name. Now, I'm going to give it a name of WORLD_LENGTH for now,
WORLD_LENGTH. Underscore is a safe way to
separate things. Constant expression WORLD _LENGTH. Now, you need to immediately, and
it's a generally good habit, whenever you declare something like this, when you say
I've got a constant expression, it's called WORLD_LENGTH, let's give it a value,
and let's say 5. Ooops! OK, that's great!
Alright now, why have I done all of this in uppercase, and what is it
complaining about? Well firstly, it's complaining because I haven't given it a type. You need to
say what the type of this thing is. Constant expressions integer WORLD_
LENGTH = 5. A normal declaration would not have this
constant expression but we want constant expression here. So, what this is
saying is, I've got something. I'm calling WORLD_LENTHG, why all upper case, by the way? Well,
I've looked in Unreal's Engine coding standards, and they don't seem to say anything about
using constants, so I'm just going to go with all upper case, because it's a pretty common
practice. We may change that later, once we get in Unreal, but for now, this is representing.
This thing does not change. It's got a value of 5. It's an integer, which means you can count it on your fingers,
basically if you've got a lot of fingers. And it's a constant
expression. So, it's going to be determinable right now, as soon as I've written the
code, and the compiler will be able to know what it's value is, right at the start.
It cannot change once the program is running. Alright, that's what const expression
does, and we want to use it here. So, I've got a simple
challenge of you. I want you to include this constant expression into
your code. So, I want you to include the
WORLD_LENGTH in the intro text, and make sure it prints
with spaces properly. You're just going to have to try and work out how
that goes in there. It's using only syntax that
you've used before. You're going to have to pop the expression WORLD_LENGTH into
your code and maybe adjust things, so everything fits on one line. So, have a go at
that! Make a bit of a mess, play with it, see if you can get it printing out using WORLD_LENGTH, so if you
change that WORLD_LENGTH, the text changes.
So welcome back! Let's see how I'm going to do that! So, when I get
to the X in the X letter isogram, I'm going to close my quotes like that,
and then, I'm going to put another double chevron operator
and then I'm going to use WORLD_LENGTH. Notice how it populates for me. And I'm actually going to
end the line there, i.e. the statement, and
I'm going to go on to a new line, because I want to keep my code concise and then I'm going to start again.
Alright now, why does this work? It works
because... Let's see if it does work first, and then, I'll talk you through why it works. [Laughs]
Well, it doesn't, I've got my spaces wrong! Common error here! So, I missed a
space here. Now, what' going on? It prints out, "Can you guess the"
and then a space, and then these spaces don't matter because
the compiler ignores white space but it doesn't ignore it when it's inside
a quote. So, I could get rid of these spaces, I'll do that as an example.
Then, it puts on the WORLD_LENGTH, and luckily for us, it converts from this integer
thing here into a string. We're kind of taking that for granted
but it naturally does that for us. Then, the statement ends, but it comes right along here
and does another cout. And because we never ended the line
with a new line, we immediately start to print. We put a space,
which is the correction I just made, and then, we carry on and put another new line. So, let's just look
at that working! There you go! "Welcome to Bulls and Cows, can you
guess the 5 letter isogram?" Now, if I change this constant here to sasy 9,
you see it changes 9 fantastic!
A small thing but you'll see later why this really matters, because WORLD_LENGTH
is going to be used throughout our code, and there's going to be a load of stuff here,
eventually. And we're going to want to refer to WORLD_LENGTH right down here,
and there could be lots of references, so that we know if we only ever refer to
WORLD_LENGTH, like this, that if we change it we can always change it in one
place. You want to generally strive for having information in one place and one place
only. I'm going to put my spaces back in here, because they're ignored by the compiler.
Only spaces within strings like this actually make any sense.
Also, other places that spaces make a difference are like using space
namespace. We have to separate out these keywords. I can't just go usingnamespace, it doesn't
know where one word starts and the other finishes, right. But I can go using
namepsace standard, if I really want to make my code ugly. I could put all
sorts of weird spaces in here, and it would still compile
but it would just look really horrible. Generally, never hit the Spacebar more than once, is a good
rule of thumb. OK, so I'm going to tidy up my code and we are
done! We have learned a little bit about constant expressions. Now, the
strongest form of constant in C++, and you want to use it when
you can.