So in this video,
we're going to be talking about the difference between our \n and our endl that
we've been using, introducing something called pseudocode programming. We'll, tell you
why you need to import another library, and we'll be using
cin and a variable for input, and finally, we'll be discovering
some woes with our input buffer. So, what that means is that if
somebody tries to enter a single word guess then it all works out fine. They
can write enter then donkey then kong or good, but if
they try and enter a two word guess,
we get strange results here. Your guess
ignores you and goes straight on, so we'll see how to solve all that. Let's dive in and take a look!
Okie dokey! So, before we actually solve this,
I just want to tidy up an inconsistency and introduce you to pseudocode programming.
Firstly, the inconsistency is that I'm using endl sometimes and
/n others. They're almost identical, actually
backslash n is slightly different, in that it doesn't so called flush the
output buffer, but for our purposes, they're identical at the moment.
So, as it's simpler to type \n when you've already got some quotes open,
let's just do that, alright. So, that's going to be my convention. If I
haven't already got quotes open, then I might use endl.
Great! so let's talk about pseudocode programming. What that is, is it's
using English comments to write down what we want to do, before we
get buried in the details of how we actually do it in a particular language. It's really
freeing, it lets you think naturally and at a natural speed. It also raises
you to a higher level of abstraction with your thinking, so that you don't get
lost in the details. So firstly, let's comment what we already have. What we already have
here is introduce the game.
And then, what we're going to do in the future, and we're going to continue using pseudocode
programming from now, is we're going to get a
guess from the user or player. It's a player not a user.
And we're going to repeat the guess back to them.
So, that's going to be a way of checking it worked. Great, so that is as simple as that. You
just use comments to outline what you're plan to do.
So, if cout is what we use for character output, I wonder what we use
for character input. Well, people who create programming
languages, being as sensible as they are, it's called cin. Now, we
turn our chevrons around. The operator is just defined in the opposite direction
and then, we need to send it somewhere. So, where are we going to send it? Well, we need another
variable, because we don't know until the program runs what the user is going to enter.
So, we can't use one of these constant expression things. We're going to have to use something called a
variable. How do we define a variable? Well, let me show you! You put the type
of it first, and we're going to use something called a string. A string is quite a useful
feature in C++, and it is built into the
standard namespace, so we don't need the std:: because of this handy using statement
here. So, a string and I'm going to call it guess, and that's going to be with a
upper case G. We're going to name all our variables with upper case letters, just because
that complies with the Unreal coding standard. And immediately that we bring in into existence,
we give it a sensible value. In this case nothing, because there is no guess value at the moment.
Great! So, we've defined a place holder, like a parking space, for
whatever string the user decides to type, and we filled it with nothing,
to start with. That seems benign filling it with nothing, but it really is important
that you know what value is in your parking space,
if you like, all of the time. So, this is like assigning somebody a parking space.
You want to know what's in it. OK, so how do we do it? We go cin
forward slash forward slash, which isn't going to work. We'll talk about that in a minute.
Guess;... Now this would take whatever is on the input stream,
i.e. whatever the user has typed in the Console, and put it into Guess. Well, it would
if we didn't have this horrible error. Now, this error is because
we don't have a particular library imported, and that's the
string library. If we look up at the top, we have , and through
we're getting lots of useful stuff. If we were to turn it off by
turning it into a comment like this, you would see all sorts of things stop working, like
cout will stop working and string itself will stop working. But unfortunately,  doesn't
include all of the information we need to do all of the things we can do with strings. And one
of those is define something called an operator, i.e. this forward slash forward slash,
that tells the compiler what to do in this case when we have
a string on the right and an input stream on the left. It doesn't know what to do,
that's what that message is saying. And it'll find out what to do by using the string
library. So, we #include
oops, with a d. Now, how would you find that out,
if I didn't just tell you. Well, you could do a Google search for it
and you would probably find a good Stack Exchange article that will pretty quickly tell you that, that was
a suggestion. But as soon as I put #include , then this operator
error goes away and we're all good to go! So, that's how you
do it. I'm actually going to delete that and then put you into a challenge. I'm not going to delete the comment
though. We leave the comments in. So, here's your challenge! I want you to take
and repeat back the guess. Some of it's repeating what we just
did. I want you to ask the user for their guess. Use cin
to take the guess on the same line,
and on the next line, repeat back the guess. It's as simple as that! So, go ahead, pause the video.
Have a good play with that, play with the formatting. And I would like you to take a screenshot of the result,
by the way, on your Console, and paste it into the discussions so we can see how
you formatted your guess and how you've setup your game. OK go for it!
Cool and welcome back! So, this is how I'm going to do it!
I'm going to do exactly what I did before. I'm going to use this as an opportunity to reiterate string
Guess, and I'm going to initialize it as nothing,
which is good practice. Great! OK, so part of getting the guess from
the player is going to be asking them, actually. cout <<
"Enter your guess"
colon. I'm going to put a space and a semicolon. And then I'm not going
to put a new line, because I want to ask on the same line. Actually, I'm going to space this a little bit, so cout
endl. Here's an example where, because I didn't really have quotes open, endl is easier
to use. I'm struggling to find my keys. There you go! Poor me, I have to dart
between a Mac and a PC all the time, and I get confused about
the keyboards but we'll survive! Great! So, what has this done so far! Hopefully, so
far this has
hmm? Nothing? Let's try again! Control, F 5 is what I'm looking
for! Hah! Here we go! "Enter your guess:" and it hasn't asked me for the guess, so
that's because I haven't yet come along and done the cin operation.
cin >> Guess; and that's fine!
Let's check that! Hello great and we
just leave the program, because it doesn't tell us to do anything else. We might want to space before we leave,
by the way. So, I'm going to go cout end line, as well.
I'm going to bind it down, with the return statement, so that we get an extra space right at
the bottom here. This is all finesse but I find it quite important to make these things look right! Hello!
It didn't work, let's try again! That's because I hit F5
without the control. If you do that, you'll be going into debugging mode and that's
confusing and we don't need that right now. Cool, so that's all working! Now, what we need to do is repeat
the guess back! So, we can go cout and we can access the value of that variable of that guess,
right now. Remember to use your chevrons to the left. And that would
be fine, apart from let's be a little bit more polite and say what we're saying. Your guess
was colon and then your chevrons.
And we probably do want an end line here. An endline
because I haven't already got quotes open. That's how I'm going to do things, just to be consistent.
OK.
"Your guess was", apart from I missed the s in was.
That's pretty good! Let's try again! Now, there's a problem! Let's just check problem.
Great! "Your guess was: problem" It looks all good, but what happens if I put donkey space
kong, for example. Ah, your guess was donkey. It only took the first bit
off, right. And worse than that, look what happens here. Now, I
don't need you to follow this bit. I'm just going to duplicate all my code for a moment, underneath, so
I get the guess from the player and repeat it out twice.
I'm going to remove this line, because I don't want it to
declare string again, it already exists. String has been brought into
existence here, in string Guess. We don't need it again. In fact,
a good way of seeing where it's used is to click on it there, and it shows it's used here, here, here, here,
here, but we don't want to declare it again. That wouldn't make any sense. OK,
here you go! "Enter your guess: donkey" and that's fine!
Kong, so that's it going through twice and asking me and
repeating back, but what happens if I type donkey kong?
I get donkey and then immediately I get another your guess was
kong. And it didn't even ask me for my guess here, so what happened? The first cin
over here, this one here, that read
donkey and then stopped when it got to the space, by default,
and then, it printed out donkey here.
And then, it said "Enter your guess:', which happened. And then, cin found that
on the input stream there was still something left and that was kong or probably
space kong but it ignored the leading space. So, then it outputed
kong and the game was over. So, this isn't what we want because we want
the user to be able to put... It's part of our requirements actually that the user can put anything in.
And this is breaking our code, what the user is putting in is changing how the
code is operating, so we need to take control back of this game,
and that's going to be the subject of the next video. So, I'm going to leave the code like
this, actually, with two sets of "Enter your guess: ". You're welcome to bring your
code to this state now, so to be clear we have the intro at the top
there, and then we're getting the guess from the player, repeating it back, getting it from the player, repeating it
back. The only line that I haven't copied is this hole here, where I've removed
string. So, do this for yourself. You're welcome to try and run it with your string left in,
down here, and you'll find it'll fail. Get yourself to this state that
you see on the screen. Convince yourself that there's a problem, and in the next video,
I will talk about a solution to that!