Welcome to this here video on
using getline(). So. in this video we're going to recap the problem we're facing. Then. we'll talk
about why getline() is a useful method here. Then. we'll talk about
where to find documentation and where to lookup solutions to problems.
and then. we'll solve it!
OK. so here's a recap! The problem we've got is that if we put in a
multi-word guess. that it is
wrongly consuming the text. OK. So. what are we going to do about it?
Well. there's a method called getine().
So. a word on my getline() is useful here. It will read through any spaces by default.
which is useful for us. It will discard the input stream once it reaches
the new-line character. which is just what we want. When we hit Return. we want it
to consume all the way up to the Enter. the new-line. the Return. whatever you want to call
it. and then discard everything else. And you can read about it by searching for getline()
at www.cplusplus.com!
How firstly would you even find out about something like that
for yourself? Before I just present you with a solution. how would you do it?
Well. you'd do some Google searches right? It would be the best starting point. but this
actually is a none obvious solution. If you search for. well what would you
search for? It's always about asking the right question. So. I don't know? You
could try something like "cin
not working right c++". It might be
the type of query you might make. at this stage. and you see
a couple of things. That one there! Maybe open the second one! Stack Overflow
is a good resource in general. especially highly
rooted answers that are voted on by people with good reputations.
So. that's one good place to get it from. but sometimes it's just a slightly
non-obvious solution. and you need to just take a course like this or read a book. OK.
so that's a note on how you do it. getline(). what is this getline() thing?
Well. for simplicity I'm going to delete this duplicate code. because I just can't see the wood for the trees
like this. This by the way is why we don't repeat code. it's really confusing.
So. I'm going to get rid of the repeat. for the moment. We'll put it back to test. in a minute. And it's this
cin line that needs to change. I'm going to get rid of it. it doesn't work. getline()
is the method. As soon as I open the brackets. then I start to get some
basic information about how it might work. but this is really hard to read in here.
There's lot of different. what we call. signatures. Lots of different options for what
parameters we pass in. but it's not very easy to read this. So. there's
a better way of getting the documentation. and that better way is to type "getline c ++".
Ooh! There it is! And you go to www.cplusplus.com.
Make sure you're on C++ 11! This stuff here. you'll get your eye in
for this later. but for right now. your best bet is probably to look at the example code and see
if that makes sense. So. given this line of example code I've highlighted. you've
guessed it! Here's my challenge! I want you to fix the input problem. Replace both
cin lines. or in this case we're going to put one back in using
this new getline() method and then we're going to duplicate our code
again. And then. test that donkey kong is accepted as a guess. and then you can
put a second guess afterwards. So pass the video. see if you can work out how to use cin using
that piece of example code. and I will see you when you've had a good go at it!
OK welcome back! So. if you look at this example
it's saying. std::getline. but we don't need the std so we can
just go getline. and then it says cin effectively. if we ignore
the std bit because we're using name space std. Comma name and name is the
name of a string variable. so we just need to modify that a bit for our code!
So. this is how we do it! getline(cin.
is where we're getting it from. Guess) is where we're putting it to.
OK. so before we duplicate anything. let's just check that. that line works there.
So. I'm going to run the code and
just put in say "donkey kong". Now. we're not going to know right now. right. because we haven't
asked a second time. So now. let's go ahead and duplicate our code again!
Now. let me show you this error with
string. by the way. If you try and compile now. leaving your redeclaration of string here. let's
see what happens. It says. would you like to run the last
successful build? Well no. because I want to know what's wrong now. What's wrong?
Well look! If we look at the error stream. it's not particularly obvious
what's going on. "Illegal for class" access. At least here you get
" 'Guess': redifinition; multiple initialization". so it does tell you a useful error.
So. we remove that line. run our code donkey
kong. I'm missing an n aren't I?
Oh. your guess was donkey kong! Cool!
Works! Brilliant! So. we've achieved what we wanted to achieve
in this video! I'm going to leave two sets of input
in here like this. I think I'm just going to remove some spaces.
because visually this is horrible right now! "repeat the guess
back to the". No. You see. I'm trying the group the things by spacing. so let's do that!
Of course. we're going to sort all of this out with functions and stuff in a moment. OK.
that's how I'm going to leave my code. because it's somewhat clearer what's going on!
And fantastic. I'll see you in the next video!