...
So welcome to Simplifying with Functions! In this
video we are going to talk about the fact that programming
is all about managing complexity. We want to think about as few
things at a time as possible. We'll talk about the idea of abstraction
and encapsulation. We'll discuss how functions help us simplify
things. You'll write and call your own functions.
We'll have a warning about the side effects of functions, as they're called
and why we always use return at the end of your functions. I'm going to
let you make a mistake in the first challenge. Oh no, now I've told you, I've given the game away, and you
may not make the mistake! [Laughs] OK let's dive in and take a look at this!
So looking at my code right now, I'm not
entirely happy, because I'm starting to what I call lose the wood for the trees. There's just too much
stuff on the screen to look at, so we want to start
managing this complexity, so a word on that firstly
Abstraction and encapsulation, big words and you'll see them on
smart answers on Stack Overflow. So let me just give you my take on this!
Firstly, I would say that a major goal in writing software is to manage complexity.
Right a big piece of software is very complex, and we can only keep a
certain number of things in our brains at once, so we want to manage that complexity down.
We don't want to be too clever actually, we want to make sure that a future version of ourselves
or somebody else coming on and seeing our code can easily see what's going on, and that's
hard making things that clear and simple. So abstraction is
a technique for managing complexity, by considering things at a higher level.
For example, the lines of code that print the introduction,
as a whole, could be called print introduction. We've kind of
got it in the "// introduce the game" comment, but we actually want the comments to almost
disappear into the code, self documenting code, so we'll see how that works in a minute.
So then, encapsulation is a way of making sure your abstractions are adhered to.
So concretely, once we've decided that this is the way we introduce the game,
we can wrap that functionality off into a function and call that function
and it'll introduce the game for us, then there's only one way to introduce the game
and we get very consistent behavior. So just to help you get your eye in I'm gonna be using
curly braces in a couple of different ways in this video. You're gonna see different formats
out there on the web. In sample code, in boilerplate code in Unreal,
etc so I want you to be able to tell the difference. I want you to be read code like the
compiler reads code, which is it doesn't care whether I put my curly brace
at the end of the function definition, or on a new line after it so
it'll be a little bit interchangeable in this video, and then I will be regularly going through and
changing things to adhere to the standard that I'm aiming for
which is where they're on a separate line.
So enough talking, let's do it! We've
already got the right code highlighted. If I cut that code with Control X,
and then, I'm going to go and paste it into this new method that we talked about. Now
don't keep things in your copy buffer for too long, so I'd probably paste it straight
away. And then, wrap the code around it, because you could lose it couldn't you? You can always use
Control Z and stuff, you're not amateurs. Anyway, what are we going to call this method?
We're introducing the game, so Print
Intro() will do fine.
OK fantastic! PrintIntro(), so now curly braces!  Need
to put one curly brace at the bottom, and then, when you do so, it's helpfully indented. But if it
hasn't indented, for any reason, this is how you want to end up alright.
So that's a function that takes in no parameters and passes nothing back, but
even though we're passing nothing back, I still want you to be in the habit, at the bottom, of saying
return. We're not returning anything because it's void, which means
that we're returning nothing, but it's a very important habit, otherwise you can start to forget to return things.
So what's the point of this PrintIntro()? It's to introduce the game.
And it's got its WORD_LENGTH with it, if you click on that it shows you where the
other instances are. By the way, let's just have a quick check and make sure we haven't used WORD_LENGTH anywhere
else, because WORD_LENGTH is only going to be available now
inside PrintIntro(). That's actually a good thing, it means the scope,
the width of our code within which we can actually
use it, is limited to just what we're seeing there, in fact, right inside
here. So we create WORD_LENGTH there, we use it very very soon after,
and then, as soon as we leave this function it goes, what we call out of scope and it's
not available to anything else. In fact, if you come into main() here and start trying to type WORD_LENGTH
it doesn't come in the autocomplete. Alright, that's called scope and it's a good
thing. It's to do with encapsulation, it's making sure we can't get
hold of this where we don't need it. Now later, we will need to move it  to a different scope but for now
this is fine. So PrintIntro() and in the main() what we do is we
just go PrintIntro(). Great, let's make sure
that works! So we've tidied up the beginning by saying PrintIntro(), look how much tidier
main() is now. And it works, it prints the
intro! Now, there's something else I want to tell you before we move on! The second part of this is, I want to see
main(). In fact, what is main()? Let's comment to say what main is. This is "// the entry
point for our application"
or something. If you ever feel you need to describe something, do so.
I want PrintIntro() to be up underneath this, so let's cut it and put it
underneath, but we get a problem! Let's try compiling! Control F5,
it doesn't work, "identifier not found"
on line 11. So line 11 tries to use
PrintIntro(), it doesn't understand it. What we need to do here is take this part of
void PrintIntro() and put it at the top like that,
with a semicolon. Why a semicolon? Because if we try and put a pair of curly
braces, which by the way act as another way of completing
the statement. Look at main(), for example, it doesn't have a semicolon on the end and neither does Print
Intro(). Yeah, but if we try and just leave curly braces
or even curly braces and a semicolon or something, it's going to say no it
already has a body. So the curly braces are the implementation of
this, and we don't want to define the implementation in two places, really important.
So we say, void PrintIntro(), rather, with a semicolon on the end,
and if we click on it you can see that it also exists there and that the implementation is at the
bottom. OK we want to keep our main() function at the top, because when you first come into this you want to say:
what's it doing? Well this is the entry point for our application OK, and
what else is happening? And then, we print an intro. Well how does PrintIntro() work? You look down
here, it does this stuff. You see how it simplifies? OK let's check it runs!
It does, good good! OK,
now next thing! We want to put this stuff here into a method of its own, and
guess what? That's going to be a challenge for you! I want you to
write string GetGuess() as a function. Save your code so you can go
back, in case you mess things up. Write a function to get the guess,
return it as a string, at the bottom of the function, and restore your code to
its former working glory. Have a go, let yourself struggle with it a bit, but not too much.
If it takes you more than 15 minutes, 20 minutes, something like that, then watch my solution and
don't feel bad. Otherwise have a good go, have a look and see if you can do it by pattern matching
and just by sheer determination and by checking on the web if you need to.
Whatever you need, see if you can get it done. It's a useful problem to be able to solve, and it's using things you've
already learned. OK welcome back!
So I'm going to take all this code here, and I'm just going to
put it in a method called string GetGuess(),
and it takes in no parameters and that's the
code. Alright, so it's going to get a guess from the player. In fact, I'm going to move that comment
up above like that, because it describes what the whole function does. And I guess,
for consistency, I can do the same with PrintIntro().
OK so PrintIntro() very simply does
that, GetGuess() from player does that. Great! See how "Enter your guess: ", it
defines it just as late as it needs to and repeats the guess back to them. Now warning
sign, this doesn't just get the guess at the moment. This more than gets
the guess, it gets the guess and it prints the guess
back to them. I'm going to rename that "// print the guess back".
Hmm, not very good! This is what you call a side effect! If
you were up here now, let's see it in action, and I just put Get
Guess(), that's my function call. So we'd GetGuess().
I don't need this second load of code here. Look how simple
our main() method is now! We print an intro and get a guess. Let's make sure it works, then I'll talk about this
side effect. OK " 'GetGuess()':" " not found",
that's because I need to put a prototype of GetGuess() at the top.
Now this stuff at the top is starting to become the kind of contract,
an overview of what we're going to be doing, and later this will be in something called a header file.
But anyway, for now, we just need to make it available like that. Let's run it and see if it works!
OK " 'GetGuess': must return a value"!
I've made the mistake I told you not to make, return
Guess; so now we're returning a string. Enter you guess,
define yourself a variable called Guess,
use this getline() method, and then, let's have a space and say that we print
the guess back. OK let's check it works, and then, we will talk about side-effects.  Test,
your guess was test. Fantastic! Look at the win here is the
simplicity of main(), but reading main(), it prints the intro
and then it gets the guess. Hmm OK, and then you look at that and you
look at this, and you say, well there's a guess coming back as a string but I don't see anything.
The real problem, the side-effect, is that its printing. It shouldn't be printing
when it's just called GetGuess(). That's a bit nasty, so
we're going to own up to our mistake by renaming the method to say exactly what it does do.
Now you can do that by renaming it in all three places it exists or
clicking on it and going Control R once, and it's going to show,
waiting for a second chord, Control R again. You could say
GetGuessAndPrint
Back. In fact, that's what we'll do for now. And when you hit Return it'll say,
where do you want to replace this? You can pretty much trust it, if you had it selected right in the first place and it will
rename it there and where you call it and in the prototype at the top there.
Now this is what it does, this is a horrible method name, or method is another
word for function, is another word for routine, and they all have slight
subtleties as to what they actually are, but, for now, let's get used to all of the different ways of calling it.
GetGuessAndPrintBack() does a lot and that's a bad thing that
it does so much but at least we're honest about what it does, we have declared the side-
effect and we're going to leave it like this for this video. So all I want to do now is
do it twice. Now the structure of main() is it
Prints the Intro, GetGuessAndPrintBack(), GetGuessAndPrintBack(),
and then it leaves a space and exits. Let's have a look at this work!
Donkey... No "doinke" spoot! That'll do! And that
worked, and second guess "hello". Now we might want an extra space,
but look, let's leave the formatting, it works! And the big big win
is that main() is easy to understand and reads in
English now. So in the next video, we'll start looking at how we can do things
multiple times automatically, using loops, and we'll also look, in future videos, at
how we can make this method more single purposed. GetGuessAndPrintBack()
is not a nice method, because it's doing two things. OK fantastic! We'll see you soon!
...