...
So in this video. we're going to talk about why we need loops. when to use
for vs. while. We'll talk about the syntax of a for loop. and
then we will write a loop to repeat the game. so that at the end of it we
can have five separate plays of the game. with a little
bit nicer spacing. without having to write
our function call five times. So let's get on with it!
So. it's all very well writing something twice but three times is no
good. and we want to have at least a handful of guesses.
In fact. later on the number of guesses is going to depend upon the
size of the word. so we need to do something called looping. So. so
far everything we've done has been straight line code. effectively. It's just been
straight line code in statements. whether or not they've been inside
functions or not is just a way of organizing them. but it's just a straight sequence through.
So. we're introducing the second fundamental way of writing code now. which is
looping or called iteration. Between straight line code iteration and
branching or conditionals. we'll be able to do everything. and then
beyond that is just icing! Anyway. so this is the second one. is iteration!
Now. there are two types of loops. One is called for and one is called while. We're going to concern ourselves
with for. for the moment. How do we know
when to use each? Well. they can both do exactly the same thing. They can be
converted to one another. So. let's pick a standard to keep ourselves sane. I'm going to go with this.
When you know what you're in for. you know at compile time how many times it's going to
loop. and let's use for. And when you may be looping for a while.
i.e. your not sure how many times it will loop until the program actually runs. then we'll
use a while loop. So. we're going to start off with this user input. using a for. and we will
actually convert it to a while. later in the section. when we start to deal
with handling incorrect user input. because they don't want to be
consuming a turn or try if they put the wrong input. But for now. we're not
checking their input. we're not validating anything. we're just going to take five
guesses from them regardless. so we're going to use a for loop.
So. the syntax of a for loop is like this.
for. open brackets. some initialization. condition.
i.e. you create yourself a variable. In fact. let me put the whole lot on the
screen. it's going to be a lot easier. So. the actual hard implementation is there at the
bottom. and the top is the pattern for it. The pattern comes from www.cplusplus.com.
It's actually not a particularly precise definition of how a for loop works.
You'll get a better one there at the Microsoft link. But anyway. let's talk through this guy.
So. for some initialization. so i.e. I'm going to create
an integer counter and I'm going to start it with a value of 1. So. for
(int count = 1 for example. Semicolon. that's just how it works. Then.
the condition. So. the condition that you want to adhere to is that the count is less than
some limit. for example. which may be 5 in our case.
Then. how do you increase the counter? Well. count++. count++ is
a shorthand way of saying count = count +1. it just adds one to the counter.
And then. . Now. the other interesting thing about this is. they define it like
this statement. and I've put code blocks because generally we
repeat more than one thing. And actually. this whole thing between these curly braces is a
statement. Remember. we were saying before that another way of finishing off a statement
is to close the curly braces. you see. So. just start to get into
your mind that a single statement is basically logically
the same. as far as something like for is concerned. as a code block. i.e. a set of curly
braces. OK cool! So. given that you
know the syntax of the for loop. I think you're ready to wrap these
guys in a for loop. So. why don't you give that a crack!
Here we go! Make the game take five guesses. You know what you've learned so far. to make the game
take five guesses in a row. GetGuess() should appear as a function called only
once inside the for loop. so we don't just keep copying and pasting the code. And then.
as a bonus. remember what I said about magic numbers?
OK pause the video. have a go at making this print out. and ask for five guesses and I'll see you soon!
Oh. and be brave. Just before you come back and watch my solution. why not
take a screenshot and paste in the discussions the way you did it.
OK welcome back! So. let's take a look at how I'm going to do
this! I said we only need one of these. so for ().
Now. the syntax! Let's immediately get all the structure in place.
There we go! OK! Now.
we can change the way that Visual Basic does this. by the way. but I'm going to start
working towards this standard with my braces. OK so. for (int
count). It's very common. by the way. to use i and i
or j or k . they're OK. Excuse the pun! They're OK
until you start getting confused. and then. you use something more complex. But for now. I'm going to use
count. because it's more descriptive. for (int count) = 1;
count is < less than or = to now 5.
but that's a magic number! We'll replace that in a minute! OK.
count++) Let's check it works. and then we'll deal with this magic number.
Why is it a magic number? Well. because it's a number that's above 2 and it's in our code.
so it's a magic number. OK. let's have a look!
It should ask us for 5 guesses. 1. 2.
3. 4. 5. fantastic! Look I want to
space these guys out! I can't see what's going on! So. I'm going to GetGuess()
and PrintBack(). I'm also then going to cout and end line myself.
after every one of those. just to space it out. 1. 2.
3. 4. fantastic! 5. we actually have some code running!
Great! Now. don't like this magic number. naughty naughty! So. what are we going to do about
that! Well. what did we do about it before. is the question. Before. we defined a constant
expression of type integer. and we called it WORLD_LENGTH and made it 9. Well.
let's do a very similar thing here! What needs it? The for loop. so we might as well put it right above
the for loop. It's no longer called WORLD_LENGTH but it's... Hmmm. I don't know?
What do we call it? NUMBER_ OF_TURNS. something like that! Yeah!
It's long but you only have to type it once. remember. and it
saves you typing a comment. doesn't it. Number of turns equals 5.
and now. the reason I say you only have to write it once is because as soon as you start typing it again.
it autocompletes. Cool! So. we have a constant expression. because it's known at
compile time. It's an integer. number of turns five. There it is! So.
our main() thing prints the intro. Now. I need another comment. In fact. I'm a little naughty. I should have put a
...
comment before I even started writing anything but that's OK. Catch yourself and
just do it! So. "loop
for the number of turns
asking for guesses". Now. it's not
verified. It's not verifying any of these guesses or anything but that's fine! So. our main() method still
looks digestible. If it gets any more complicated than this. we'll continue to refactor it out.
like we could take this lot out. OK. let's just check it works.
or hit that key very loud. One. two. three.
four. [Laughs] I can't spell four. Five. OK great!
When we get an extra space here. we'll worry about all that type of stuff later.
Great! So. we're doing pretty well! Let me just look through my code. before we leave this
video and make things consistent. So. we come in. we print the intro. we loop around.
put an extra space in. which we actually don't even need
anymore. I think I can get rid of it. because it's reliably going to print a space here.
Then. the PrintIntro() is something that introduces the game.
I'm going to change to the syntax we're aiming for. with the braces like that.
OK. OK. our code is looking alright! It's looking
alright! Fantastic! So. I don't really like the
the way these comments work here. so I'm just going to put that comment back. It's fine to just
keep fiddling with your code. until you like the look of it. We don't really need to explain this silly
named method. especially if we're going to change it a bit later on.
PrintIntro() good! OK. so I'm looking at the code and making sure it's all indented sensibly.
and that it just reads well and makes sense. Do that regularly. keep y our code
tight and tidy. You want to be having plenty of mental bandwidth. for when things
go wrong. You don't want to struggle to understand your own code. OK. final check of
running it! Great! See you in
the next video!