So clarity,
it's worth fighting for, and that's what this video is all about. It's about making that
extra effort to reel this code in, as in reeling in a
fish on a fishing line, and bringing it back so that it looks almost too
simple, so we're ready to add more complexity in the next step.
I just want to explain something to you. Firstly, we're going to end up with a main() method that looks as simple as
this, and there'll be some improvements further down, which I won't spoil your challenges by showing you.
I also want to tell you that, if you want to do your own code thing and you're concerned that
you know, you do the challenge you do your own code, and then I come along and show you a solution.
If you feel like you have to change your code to match my solution, it's up to you whether you
do or don't. If you diverge from my solution and somehow your code stops working,
then you can always do the following. You can go to www.github.com/
UnrealCourse. OK, even if you're not logged in, in fact, I'm not
logged in here, and then, you can look for the section. This is section 2 BullCowGame,
and then, what you can do is you can make sure you're on the master branch. It should be
the only branch there. And look for this word here, 9 commits, and that means, at the
time of recording there are 9 lectures and there are the lectures in the commit list.
OK, so as a recap we're at github.com/UnrealCourse, then the section
name, commits, master. And then, if you go to a particular video, say this one
here, you can click, browse the repository at that point. Now, there's two things you can do. You're going to
either just kind of click in and look at the code at that stage, and you can even copy and paste it,
or when you're at this level here and you've found
the commit that you want, so let's go back another one to here.
Then, you can download .zip, if you want, and replace your whole project.
So, I just want to explain that, that's a possibility for you, if you want to do your own code, but if you're
concerned rather, you diverge and you can't keep track, well, you can always come in
and compare against my code or even just download it and pick up from where I left off.
...
So, at this stage if you're a beginner, we learned just enough to be dangerous! We've
just learned about enough things to create a real mess
and a mess we have. Here in the main() loop, this is what
I call a mess. Now, why is it a mess? It looks simple enough, but the problem with it is it's not a
consistant level or abstraction. PrintInfo() is higher
level than what's below. PrintInfo() is asking you to
do several things in one go, this stuff here which is simple and self contained
and well explained and has no nasty side effects. It does what it says and nothing else.
And we can sit here and look at PrintInfo(), and we can go yep, I'm happy with that. I don't need to look
at the details I know what it does. That's what we want! Then, you come down here and we've
got an implementation that's right down at the detail level. Look we've got
the things in here, ones and you know iterators, and stuff
right. And that's all fine and that needs to be somewhere, but we don't want it here, when
one minute we're thinking about printing a whole introduction section and then, we're talking about the details of the
loop. It's inconsistent abstraction. So, what I want to do, firstly,
is tidy this loop up so that it goes PrintIntro(),
play the game, and well that's it for the moment!
So, this bit here basically represents play game, doesn't it? It plays a single game.
So, how would we abstract this function. Well, we've done this before, but I want to show you Visual
Basic's tool, and then, I want to show you a nasty side effect and hence why
we won't use its tool for now and then later on we'll start using the tool again, because I think
that some of you are going to be experimenting and using the tool, so I may as well show you what happens when you to do that,
and we'll start learning about header files and we'll get our first view of them. OK, so highlight your
code, in here, the stuff that actually is responsible for playing the game. You can right click
or do Control and +, and you've got a quick action here.
Inside there you've got Extract Function,
so if for any reason you don't see that option go to Tools and Options, bringing up this
dialog box and down to Text Editor, C++,
Experimental, and then, you want to look under Refactoring for Enable
Extract Function. Set that to True and say OK.
It's quite powerful, it does various checks and things for you. it's done some checks, it thinks it's
possible to extract that, and now, let's give it a name: PlayGame,
and then just hit return. OK, now the main method has
got a lot simpler. Look, PrintIntro(); PlayGame();
return 0; so, i.e. "// exit the application". We can put that in!
OK, let's try!
[Sings] La di da di da di da! And then it exits. Great it works!
Now fantastic! It's done a lot for you! Where has it put PlayGame()? It's put
the details of PlayGame() down here. It's literally cut and pasted our code and written the method name
for us and indented it for us, done a lot of work for us. It's not used quite our
formatting, and eventually we'll go into Visual Studio's Tool
Options and change the way that it does hanging braces. But look what else
it's done! It has not put a prototype! How come PlayGame() is working,
when it doesn't have a prototype? I said you have to have prototypes. Remember, PrintInfo() didn't work unless
we declared it above hmm but PlayGame() does. How come?
Well, it's sneakily created us a main.h header file
over here, if you look in your Solution Explorer. If you don't see that, go to View, Solution Explorer,
and it's simply put in there void PlayGame();. Don't worry about #pragma once, it basically
says only include this header file once. But void PlayGame(); has been
put in there, and then, remember what I said #include does? It just does a copy and paste.
Well, it's put a #include in, as well, naughty thing. It's put a #include "main.h",
and it's made in the "main.h" and then it's put void PlayGame() in there. OK, that's
all fun and cool, and we will be doing that in general, including in this section, using header
files. It's an integral part of C++. Yes, it's a bit more work, but it does have some
benefits, which we'll see later. But for now, we don't want it to do that, so if you do
use it's extract method like that I'm just going to, for simplicity, remove the
reference to the header file. I'll show you now that it doesn't work. You see it says it says " 'PlayGame': identifier
not found". Let's move this function prototype
up here, into... I'm going to put it
here. I'm going to put the methods or the functions in the order that we use them. PrintIntro(), PlayGame(), Get
GuessAndPrintBack(). So, the logical structure here is, we include the libraries we want,
we tell it what namespaces to use, and then, we go ahead and write all our function
prototypes, although later these will all be in a header file. And then, we get into our main() method.
OK, so I'm actually going to delete main.h, so I don't care whether I save
changes to it, because I'm going to right-click over in the Solution Explorer, remove it, and
delete it. OK, we just don't need it. Take control of the program, get
it to do what you want it to do! And I'm going to remove some spaces here and put some
extra spaces between my method, so this is really clear now.
We find the entry point for the application, we print an intro, play the game, and leave.
OK, that is pretty cool! [Sing] La di da di da! OK
good! So, there's one more thing we need to do here which is, we've had this side effect
hanging over us for a while. In fact, we've had it hanging over us, too long! Alright, so
you should be a little bit uncomfortable now that I said that
GetGuessAndPrintBack() has a side effect, and the side effect is that it prints here.
We declared that it has a side effect, immediately that we realized, which is good,
but better than that let's remove the side effect! We don't want a method like this or function doing
two different things. So of course, that's going to be a challenge for you!
I want you to remove the side effect, rename the GetGuessAndPrintBack() method, move the
offending code, test it all still works, and ask yourself when you
look at your code, are you happy or very happy even with how your code reads?
And why not share it in the discussions, if you're pleased with a section of your code.
OK, see you soon!
Alright, so GetGuessAndPrintBack! What's the problem with it? It's that it prints back,
so let's do Control, R. Control, R, again! That's not letting me rename
it there, so I'll go to another instance of it here. Control, R,
Control, R. There you go! I don't know why it was being silly! I just did Control, R
several times, until it allowed me to do a rename. I'm going to change it back to
GetGuess(). Great! So, inside
PlayGame() we go and get the guess. GetGuess(), I would rather GetGuess() was right
next to where PlayGame() is, so I'm actually going to move PlayGame() down
as a method. Here come down to
here, so that when I'm in PlayGame() I can see GetGuess(). it's just easier
for me. Now, we don't want to print the guess back there, so we take it out of GetGuess(). Now, look
suddenly GetGuess() is good! It's clear, returns a string,
tells you what it does, enter your guess, and it
uses the GetLine method and returns it. Perfect! So, inside PlayGame() what does this do? Where it loops
for the number of turns, asking for guesses, there's the number of turns.
OK good! So we get the guess and then we need to print it back. Now, the only
problem here is, it's only going to print back if we have a variable. So, you could go
string Guess =
" " blank. string, remember always when you declare something
you always then initialize it like this, give it a value. And then, we could say that
Guess = GetGuess(). Now, what's that about? That is taking
the return value from GetGuess() and putting it into =.
OK, so we can do it this way, or we can simply short circuit this Guess = nothing " "
Guess = that, because if we're immediately setting it to the value of
GetGuess(), why not just cut to the chase and just do
that. string Guess = GetGuess();
OK, so we go get the guess and we print it back. I don't think we even need that
comment. It's pretty obvious what it's doing here.
So that's it! So, I want to make sure now that I'm very happy with the
code, top to bottom. I'm happy with the spacing, I'm happy with the main() method
particularly, because it's really clear what it's doing. I'm very happy with what the intro does.
I may put another space between functions here, make my
brackets style consistent all the way through the
program. So PlayGame(), it loops
around, it goes and gets the guess, it prints it out. OK, that's fine!
Now, is this a side effect? Not really, because part of playing the game is
asking for and giving feedback. Later, we won't just say what your guess was, of course, we'll be
counting bulls and cows, but I think that's OK. And I think that
all these methods now are clear. Let's just check it works! It's no good having
clear code if it doesn't work, by the way. So, one, two, three,
four, five. There you go!
Game works, code is good, and we are now good to move on
and think about the next level in our design. And it's now manageable again!
We've just got to keep reeling it in, every single time, bringing it back to manageable
and easy and simple. It should look almost too simple, that's what you
need, because in a minute we're going to come along and make it more complex again. OK, see you in a minute!