So, welcome to
this exciting video on Booleans and Comparisons! In this video, we're going to
explain what a boolean is and how to use it! I'll explain that you need to
use == for comparisons in C++, like many other languages.
&& for logical AND.
You need to use two of those vertical pipes for a logical OR, and if you want
to access part of a string, then you're going to use square brackets
and then the number of the character starting at 0. You'll see all this in context in a moment.
And finally, for characters you need to use single quotes, not double quotes.
It's characters and single quotes. Double quotes are for strings, so
you'll see all that come together, as we progress through the video.
So, let's take a look at our application!
What do we need to do next? Well, shortly we're going to want to make sure that
we can play the game multiple times. I know, it's not really a game yet,
but you know we're doing a kind of top-down design here. We're making sure
that the general flow is right, then going in and successively flushing out the details.
If we were to play another time, we would want to ask the player if they can play again
or if they want to play again. So, how would you do that? Well, you can put a comment in here, that's
fine, or we can even directly just say AskToPlayAgain.
So, you just put a method in there. That method doesn't exist, of course we get a warning.
So, what can we do? Well, we can come to the top and we can declare
the method. Of course, we're going to need to say what comes back. Now, let's think about what comes back, from our
AskToPlayAgain(). Should nothing come back or could we do something more useful with
this method? Could we ask them to play again and then return whether or not they
want to play again? That could be handy, because later on we're going to be
going around these introduction, game, play again, introduction, game,
AskToPlayAgain() many times. It would be very useful to be able to control that looping, as we call it,
dependent on what they respond here with. So, let's return
something called a bool, which is a boolean, it's true or false. Now, that is
represented as 0 for false and 1 for true
under the hood, but we really want to pretty much forget that actually. It's much better
to think of it in terms of true and false, logically true and false and not
to mess around with 1's and 0's trying to represent true and false. It'll just get us in trouble!
So, just remember that.
Now, a little more on the topic of naming. I know we seem to be spending
a lot of time thinking about naming, but actually, there's a famous quote that all
problems in computer science, well the hardest problems in computer science are naming
and cash validation or cash coherency, so
naming is really really important, alright. So, Unreal's coding
standards! They quite sensibly say that all functions that return a bool should
ask a true false question, such as is visible or should clear
buffer. We can do that here. We could
call it WantsToPlayAgain, but we would be hiding the side effect
of the method then. The more important thing right now is that this thing is actually
asking and it's asking something on the Console, and I don't want to hide that side
effect behind something like WantsToPlayAgain question mark, because it's
not clear that you're actually printing out to the Console. So, we're going to leave it like this! We're going to allow ourselves to
flex a bit. We don't have to totally adhere to their standard, because we're not writing
code that is going to be integrated into the Unreal Engine, or at least not yet.
And later one, when we introduce something called enumerations, we can actually solve this potential paradox, but one step at a time.
So, I've wishfully written it here. I've come up to the top and declared it.
Now, I can actually right-click, Quick Actions, and
Create Definition. It says Declaration / Definition
because it's a multipurpose line in there but you're creating the definition.
And it does this weird pop-in thing! It's actually just showing us what it's put at
the bottom of the code. Alright, so we can close that! So, looking at the
bottom, it's actually written the method for us, which is pretty cool!Now look, it has written it in a code format
that we're not going for. It hasn't put the brace on a new
line, so why don't we start getting it to do that! Let me show you where you control it! Tools,
Options. You could just type BRACE, for example, or you could
scroll down to Text Editor, C++, Formatting,
and then, New Lines. Here you go! And then, we're going to look for the
one for "Position of open braces for functions" there on a new line!
So, into the options, C++, Formatting,
New Lines, "Position of open braces for functions", New Lines. Let's just test that
works! I'm going to delete what it created, go back to the top,
and then, let it complain that AskToPlayAgain() doesn't exist.
Come on! If it doesn't, then you might need to just try recompiling. There you go!
So, there you go! Now, right-click, Quick Actions, "Create
definition of" it, and then, scroll to the bottom
and see that it has actually now started doing things in our code format. That's good, so
Again, take control of the tool, tell it what you want! That's under Tools and Options! Great, so we have
this AskToPlayAgain() method. Let's start writing it! cout
<< "Do you want to play again?" right,
question mark! Now, we're going to need something to store our input in,
so I'm going to say string Response = " " nothing.
Always initialize your variables. Now, let's go get this input.
Now, remember we used getline before, from the (cin) stream. We get
to put it into response. Great news OK!
And now, I want to be looking just at the first character
of this. So, how are we going to do that? Well, to get to the first character,
it's Response, open square brackets, 0, because computers start counting at
0. So, Response[0] is the first character of response! Let's
prove that to ourselves by just going cout << "First
character, char for short
and then like so. OK, let's have a go,
make sure all of this code so far is working. So, we put some guesses in. Do you want to play again?
DSDF, first character d. Great! OK,
so that's working! Now, what we want to do is think about
checking whether this first character is y
for yes. So, how do we do that? Well,
let's try is it y question mark.
And I'm going to put an end line here, by the way, just because it's really hard to
see without that space. Alright great! So, is it y? And what you can actually
output is the idea that Response == means equals.
It's the comparison operator y. Now, you need to use
single quotes for y, because y is a character,
and if you don't you're going to get an error. And you also need to put all of this in
brackets, so that this operator here
knows to read everything to the right, not just this response bit.
OK. So, we need to put all of this in brackets there. So, we're
saying the lump, the thing that we want to output, is this lot, so we
put it in brackets. Then, this operator knows what to operate on. We could also try
the problem of using double quotes. Let's see what happens here. You get another different type of error
about operand types being incompatible, char and const char star.
Don't worry about what that means. Just when you're comparing to characters, use
single quotes. And why is that a character? We turned it into a character by looking at just
one element of the Response string. So, is it yes? Let's take a look and
see what happens here. Just let you digest this code, for a second, before
I hit run, make sure you understand it. OK, let's take a look!
So, we put some guesses in, and then we type yes like that. And
is it yes? 1! Remember I said they represent true as 1. Now, we want to forget
that, but you do need to, for this instance, understand that cout is just instead
of saying true, which I prefer it did, it's saying 1. Alright, so that's
how you get a boolean out. The
actual result of this is a boolean, that thing in brackets there.
So, I've got a challenge for you, just to finish this method off. What I want you to do is
write the rest of AskToPlayAgain(). I want you to allow
for both "y" and big "Y" as the first letter. Remember I told you about the OR
operator at the beginning of the section here, this double pipe at the bottom of the screen.
See if you can work out how to use that, and then, I want you to ignore the rest of the letters in the word, as we started doing, and then return true for yes
and false for no. Now, there's a little star here, true
for yes and false for no is on the limit of what's obvious. So, true for yes and false for no is fine,
but true for red car false for green car, no no no never do that!
OK, pause the video, and I'll see you in a second!
Okie dokie! Let's crack
on and get this finished! So, what we're actually just doing here is, we're
returning, of course. Instead of returning false, which I've done by default here,
or when it wrote the method for us it nicely returned something by default.
I'm actually going to return this.
I'm going to say return
(Respons [0] == 'y'); OR
...
| | (Response [0], or we could make ourselves a temporary variable of
type character, called first character or something. Equals ==
'Y') ; so
we'll only return yes if the first character is y or Y. Let's go ahead and test it!
Y and it doesn't matter what we put
there. "Press any key to continue". Now of course, we don't know what we returned,
so you could come up here and get that value and print
it in the main loop. Where is it? Here! We could just cout
the result of the AskToPlayAgain() method,
so when AskToPlayAgain() finishes it leaves something sitting here, and you
could always out put that. Let's just try it!
Y e s. 1 you see!
So, it says yes. OK, let's just try putting something else
like, I don't know, starting with k. 0!
And we're pretty confident that it's going to work for the lower case y, because we did that before.
Alright, so that's it! What we've done is we've written a method called Ask
ToPlayAgain(), that is returning a
boolean. I'm going to get rid of this cout, because it's horrible! We don't have to use that
return value. In this instance, it's running and we're not using it, but it's there, ready, and waiting for us.
So, what we'll be able to do next, is to start to wrap all of this up into a loop,
so that we can go around doing this multiple times and stop doing this when
AskToPlayAgain() comes out as false. So, congratulations
on getting this far, you're doing great! And shortly, by the way, we're going to be taking a
step back. I'm going to be doing a talking head and we're going to talk about the design of the whole thing, and
it's going to start to get much more exciting, even more exciting than it already is!
I'll see you soon!