Hey, welcome
back! So, in this video we're going to introduce you to a useful structure called a do while loop,
and that's going to allow us to play the game one or more times, depending on what
the user responds, when you ask them do they want to play again.
...
So, here we are back at our code! The great thing about this video is it's pretty
much the last thing we need to do to complete the top level loop of our game,
and it'll stay pretty much like this, however much more we add later on to make the
rest of it run. So, let's get in and use a do while loop.
So, let's show you a slide, "The syntax of a do while loop". So,
how this thing works is like this. You say do and then you open some
curly braces and you put some code that you want to repeat and you
close the curly braces. Now, strictly speaking as we said, a pair of curly braces
is a statement. So, you could just say do and then a single simple statement, and then,
while but let's always use the curly braces. You know why? If another developer
comes along or you come along later on and try to add a second thing inside
the loop, then it won't work right unless you have these curly braces.
Just use the curly braces, they're free! They don't take a lot of time to
write! So do something, while (condition); that's just how it works.
This looks a bit odd, I think, but do loaded lines of code while some (condition)
holds. Now, the thing about a do while loop is that the code gets executed once,
before the check ever even happens. So, you use a do while loop
when you know that you want to do something at least once, so we know that we want to play the game at least once. It
doesn't make sense to ask the user, "Do you want to play again?", until they've played once. So, this is a perfect
structure for it. We do something, i.e. we print the intro and we play the game and then stuff like
that, and then, we check. Did they want to play again or not? OK so, that's the
logic of it. Where do you find out more about it? Well, that's www.cplusplus.com, I've been recommending. The other
good reliable source of information about C++ syntax, especially from a
Visual Studio perspective is Microsoft documentation. They don't make the prettiest URL,
so let me just show you how you would find it.
You'd do something like do while C++,
and what you'd get back is various things. And the ones I would
go to really and trust initially is I would probably go for the www.cplusplus.com link
I gave you, and also here, do-while loop MSDM reference.
So, if you get into that...
I'm not saying there's anything wrong with the other things, by the way, this is just these are the ones that you know are pretty reliable.
You may want to change your Visual Studio version but it's generally going to be 2015,
and then, it'll tell you about the do while loops. OK, so that's that! Let's
get in and make it happen! Oh, uh oh! I'm not going to be doing it though!
Guess who's got the job of making this work? It's going to be you. So, there's the syntax! You've got that on
the slide. You've got your links to your references. Here's your challenge. Make the game play multiple times. Put a do while
loop in main(). Refer to the example on the previous slide for the syntax, and
test you can play as many times as you like. OK, pause the video and
wrap that stuff up in a do while loop!
Cool welcome back! So, let's just do it! It's pretty simple,
it's going to be a nice short, concise video this one, I think. We do
some stuff, oops, open curly
brace. Then, we're going to put the bottom curly brace where?
Here, because we don't want to exit the application
each time we play. So why is return complaining? Because we haven't got our while statement. While
what? Now, I wonder how you used your initiative here? You could just say
while (true), which means that we would be able to do
this forever. This would be playing forever; while (true) is a way of making an infinite
loop. You need, by the way, a semicolon on the end.
So, let's just try this! while (true) should simply keep playing
the game again and again and again. So we play once. We say we want to play again.
Even if we say no, because we're not even testing it, then it just plays again. So, it's an inescapable
game, that doesn't even work. Oh what a nightmare! So we don't want that, but it
just proves that while (true) is going to happen. So, how are we going to
actually respond to this? Well, we're going to need a boolean,
and this is the format I want us to use for boolean, because it's in C++
coding standards. We're going to go bool wants to play again, so bool b.
We're going to prefix booleans with a small b. Weird hey!
But why not? That's what C++ coding
standards says. That's what we're going to see in a lot of C++ boiler play code. Why not use it?
OK, so we're going to initialize it to false, right. We're going to assume they don't want to play again,
to start with, unless we know any different. Then, I'm going to grab the value coming back to
AskToPlayAgain(). Remember it's a boolean. Now, we shouldn't need to look down at it. By the way, if you
feel you need to look down at a method, then it's not clear enough what it does. So, it's pretty
clear. AskToPlayAgain() and what comes out is true, if they want to
play again. See what I mean? It's just on the limit of what you can assume.
If it was any more obscure than this, then you'd have to look down
to AskToPlayAgain(), and if you have to look to AskToPlayAgain(), see how that matters? We're
working at different levels of abstraction and hence we're breaking
encapsulation and hence we're not making programming simple, OK. But anyway, in this case I
think it's pretty clear. So, b wants to play again. bw
= the result of calling that function
OK. Now, this is just OK, but because
we say Ask here, and there's a verb, and there should always be a verb in your method
names. We can see pretty much at a glance that AskToPlayAgain() is
actually going to print to the Console, OK.
I think that actually pushing it all the way out to the right here
though, may obscure the fact that we're printing to the Console, so we could potentially
help that by just making bWantsToPlayAgain a shorter method name.
It could just be bPlayAgain.
OK, I think that's a little bit better! But whatever we do,
we have to be aware that this thing almost has a side effect. It
does something that's not 100% clear, when you read this really quickly, but we have to live
with that. I can't think of another simple structure that's going to make this
as readable as it is, so let's go with that! So, you grab
that boolean, and then, you look at bPlayAgain here. So, the
job of working out what why and no and all that means is all inside AskToPlayAgain(). We don't need to
look at it. We can just go OK, print the intro, play the game, ask
if they want to play again, and then, loop depending on whether they want to play again. Let's try it!
Play again...
No. "Press any key to continue". Good! Now, before we move on there's a problem.
AskToPlayAgain(), it should tell us what we can put in right? y/n
so let's try again!
Play again, yes! Ah
cool! Yes! So, we can loop or we can
not loop. Perfect, I love it! We've done it! We've used do
while loops! Pat yourself on the back and we'll see you in a moment!