Hey. so time for a quick mid-section recap and
congratulations! Firstly congratulations. you've almost learned enough C++ to write
pretty much any program. But if you were just to use the structures that we've
showed you so far. plus a little sprinkling of if or switch.
which we'll meed soon. then your code would be almost impossible
to read. for a complex project. And even this simple
Bull Cows Game is getting sufficiently complex. So we need to introduce another tool in our
armory and that tool is something called the class. Now. a class is called
a class because mathematicians came up with the idea. These days. we'd probably call it
a type. You've already used a class actually. you've used
string and string is beyond the basic primitive
types that we started with. We started with int. which is a primitive type. We've also seen
bool. which is another primitive type. meaning you don't even need to import a library to use it.
And then quite quickly. we wanted access to string. and that came somewhere
because we introduced  as a library. and somewhere in there it had a standard
namespace and somewhere in there was a string. A string is a user
defined type. which is another way of saying a class. What a class does is it
packages together functions and variables into
a package that allows you to talk in a very consistent way to it. as if it's a black
box. A class is a form of abstraction. it should represent something
real or something conceptual. so in the case of bull cow game. of course.
bull cow game is really a concept.... So. we're going to be building ourselves a class.
that makes a black box that allows us to do things like say. OK. Bull Cow Game.
make a new game. OK. Bull Cow Game. go and pick a seven letter word. and don't tell me
what it is. OK. Bull Cow Game. here's my guess; tell me how many bulls and cows
it's got in it. OK. Bull Cow Game. tell me if the game is won! OK. Bull Cow Game.
tell me how many turns I've got left. That sort of stuff! Put all that logic over
in a separate class called Bull Cow Game. We're actually going to prefix it with f. because
that's the way that Unreal does things. f Bull Cow Game. And we're going to
only talk to this using methods. We're not going to directly access
any of its data. any of its variables. any of its own integers and
bulls and stuff. that's all it's business. We just need to create a really clear
and simple interface to it. so that in this Console game we can call
it and it gives us what we need and does what we need it to do. And in the future. we can take the same
class and not modify it very much. in the next section. when we actually build this
into a 3D game in the Unreal Engine. So that's the idea!
That's what we're striving for! We're making a black box. it's another tool to allow ourselves to
work at a higher level of abstraction and hints to keep a limited number of things
in our mind a one point. As the problem gets more big and more complex.
the way to make sure it doesn't occupy more than five to ten
slots in our mind is that you just make the slots
represent bigger things. and therefore. we need higher level tools such as classes.
Apart from anything. if you don't understand classes you've got no change when we hit the Unreal Engine. So
let's dive in. learn about classes. learn about a whole lot of other exciting programming tools.
and I'll see you at the end of the section.
=======
Hey, so time for a quick mid-section recap and
congratulations! Firstly congratulations, you've almost learned enough C++ to write
pretty much any program. But if you were just to use the structures that we've
showed you so far, plus a little sprinkling of if or switch,
which we'll meed soon, then your code would be almost impossible
to read, for a complex project. And even this simple
Bull Cows Game is getting sufficiently complex. So we need to introduce another tool in our
armory and that tool is something called the class. Now, a class is called
a class because mathematicians came up with the idea. These days, we'd probably call it
a type. You've already used a class actually, you've used
string and string is beyond the basic primitive
types that we started with. We started with int, which is a primitive type. We've also seen
bool, which is another primitive type, meaning you don't even need to import a library to use it.
And then quite quickly, we wanted access to string, and that came somewhere
because we introduced  as a library, and somewhere in there it had a standard
namespace and somewhere in there was a string. A string is a user
defined type, which is another way of saying a class. What a class does is it
packages together functions and variables into
a package that allows you to talk in a very consistent way to it, as if it's a black
box. A class is a form of abstraction, it should represent something
real or something conceptual, so in the case of bull cow game, of course,
bull cow game is really a concept.... So, we're going to be building ourselves a class,
that makes a black box that allows us to do things like say, OK, Bull Cow Game,
make a new game. OK, Bull Cow Game, go and pick a seven letter word, and don't tell me
what it is. OK, Bull Cow Game, here's my guess; tell me how many bulls and cows
it's got in it. OK, Bull Cow Game, tell me if the game is won! OK, Bull Cow Game,
tell me how many turns I've got left. That sort of stuff! Put all that logic over
in a separate class called Bull Cow Game. We're actually going to prefix it with f, because
that's the way that Unreal does things, f Bull Cow Game. And we're going to
only talk to this using methods. We're not going to directly access
any of its data, any of its variables, any of its own integers and
bulls and stuff, that's all it's business. We just need to create a really clear
and simple interface to it, so that in this Console game we can call
it and it gives us what we need and does what we need it to do. And in the future, we can take the same
class and not modify it very much, in the next section, when we actually build this
into a 3D game in the Unreal Engine. So that's the idea!
That's what we're striving for! We're making a black box, it's another tool to allow ourselves to
work at a higher level of abstraction and hints to keep a limited number of things
in our mind a one point. As the problem gets more big and more complex,
the way to make sure it doesn't occupy more than five to ten
slots in our mind is that you just make the slots
represent bigger things, and therefore, we need higher level tools such as classes.
Apart from anything, if you don't understand classes you've got no change when we hit the Unreal Engine. So
let's dive in, learn about classes, learn about a whole lot of other exciting programming tools,
and I'll see you at the end of the section.
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1