...
So welcome to Using Header Files as Contracts! We're going to focus
purely on the interface to our new class. And by the end of the video.
we will have a whole new file called FBullCowGame.h.
and in the case of you Xcode people. it will have created you a full .cpp file. too.
And we'll have written class FBullCowGame like this and public.
and we will have written some methods that are blurred out here. because I don't want to ruin
the challenge. And there's no right or wrong answer anyway. but these are going to define the
interface to the class. what we're allowed to do. It's a black box we're building right now.
There will also be a private section. which will be things that it will use in order to do its
work. but we shouldn't concern ourselves too much with that right now. we want to focus on
what work it's going to be doing. not how it's going to be doing the work. So
let's dive in and explore the exciting world of clases!
So let's make our own
class for the very first time! The way to do that. the way to add a new file. is to click on the project
name here. So we have the solution and inside the solution we have a single project. Right-click.
Add. and then New Item. OK so that's what we're doing on the screen.
And then. in the case of VisualStudio here. I'm just going to add a header file
to start with. We're just going to start with a header file here in VisualStudio. we'll add a C++ file
later. so that we can focus on one thing at a time.
I'm going to call it FBullCowGame. Why am I prefixing with F?
Well if you look in the Unreal coding standard. I'll show you where to find that. We've seen it before.
Then. they suggest prefixing.
If you go to the naming conventions. you see "Most other classes are prefixed by F".
so I'm going to do that so that things start to feel familiar. So there we go. FBullCowGame.h.
Even though it's a bit weird. at least it will be familiar later.
Hi I'm Sam and I'm helping Ben out with some of the Mac content on this course.
So I just want to briefly show you how to create that class in Xcode
now. So you probably want to go and right-click on the BullCow folder.
that's this one under the project. So you've got the project here and then you've got this
folder or as Xcode likes to call it a group. Right-click on
this and then we want to go down to new file
and we want to go down to OS X.
Source. and select the .cpp file
here. Now don't worry. we don't want the header file we actually want the
.cpp. And hit Next. we can create our
FBullCowGame. as Ben said.
And we also want to create a header file. so we will
save that. And now that there's a distinction between folders and groups
in Xcode. so we're putting it in the BullCow group. which only
exists inside of Xcode. We could also arrange things in different folders.
We're not going to here. but just so you're aware. that is a distinction
in Xcode. So I'm going to create that and as you can see
it has created two files here. the .cpp and the
.hpp. which is slightly different to what you'll see
on VisualStudio. OK back to Ben! So there it is sitting under header
files. What is this thing? It is. as I said before. something that would
just be cut and paste onto the top of whatever we include it in.
OK and we're going to be including it in Main.cpp. it's one
of the things we're going to include it in. and the other thing we're going to include it in is our file. that we'll make
in a little while. called FBullCowGame.cpp. So it lets us
put the same text in multiple places. literally a cut and paste. So #pragma
once. what's that about? Well it's actually not completely standard. it's not in the standards for C++
but it's very very widely supported. and it's a way of making sure that
anything that is imported is only imported once. It's an optimization. we may as well leave it
there. So do we need to import any namespaces? No not at the moment. let's just
get on and write our class. The way you do that is you say class. you give it a name.
So what are we going to call the class? Well the same as the file in this case. it doesn't have to be. by the way.
One thing here in C++ is that you
can write as many classes in a single file as you want. but for simplicity. especially at the moment.
let's just have a file and one class per file.
One file per class. it's just going to be a lot easier. Then you put your chevrons.
So that's your structure class. alright! Now what we want to focus on.
here in this video. is the public interface to this class. What our class is going to consist
of is two things. public: and private:. By the way.
look at the way that it indents that. it indents it across here. That's a bit weird
in my opinion. because normally you'd expect everything that's inside braces
like this to be indented. But I allow the
default here. because it's pretty standard across the industry. and I just treat these things
slightly differently to normal keywords. These are just like bookmarks.
just to say which part of the class definition you're in. So let's live with that. Anyway.
what's this class thing about? Well look. it's going to have in general. the pattern we're going to go for is this.
we're going to have public methods. Let me write the first public method.
The first public method could be Reset. OK so let's just pretend it
exists. and we declare it here. Now. we need something to come back from Reset().
What would we have come back from Reset()? For now nothing
but. later on. we're going to want something richer to come back. so I might put
comment "// TODO make a more rich return
value." What I mean by that is something that tells us a bit of a
status about what actually came back OK. but. for now. we're going to go void
just to flesh out the idea. I'm going to write one more method. and then. your challenge is going to be to write
all the others. once I've given you the overview. So once you've reset the game.
another thing you might want to be doing is saying. well
let's get the hidden... Oh by the way. by the way before we move on. resetting the game
in future may take in. for instance. an integer as to
the size of the WordLength.
OK. But for this whole section. we're just going to have a
single word hard coded in. so we can leave that out. Alright. so
what else might we want to do to a Bull Cow game? Well. for example. once
we've reset the game. we might want to get the number of
tries. So we'd get an integer back. and we could call this something like
GetMaxTries() OK and it would return us an integer.
So GetMaxTries. it's quite obvious what it does. I'm going to leave you to fill out the rest of these public
methods. in a moment. after a bit more priming. Now private. what would be in private?
Basically we don't want to concern ourselves too much with this. we want
to concern ourselves with the public interface to this. But you are going to have
both private functions which are helper functions. which
allow these things to happen behind the scenes. but you are also going to have private variables.
called member variables. and these things would be things
like... I don't know. we may have an int MyCurrent
Try. would be an example. and we may have an int MyMax
Tries. Now I'll explain why I'm prefixing everything with My. later on.
Well what I'm trying to say is. that there's a certain amount of stuff... Let me suggest another method.
by the way. It could be something like bool Is
Isogram().
i.e. is a particular (string) an isogram? that would be
examples of private methods we could imagine we want. Now. of course.
(string) is not imported. so I'll take this away for clarity. So
the general pattern with Object Oriented Programming is that we
don't expose any variables publicly. we do all of the getting
and setting of variables. however simple it is. through methods.
The variables stay private like this. this is pure Object Oriented Programming like that and
there's a lot to be said for it. So certainly for now this is how we're going to do things. Let's learn the rules
before we break the rules. So I want you to kind of ignore the private members for now.
and. in fact. I'm even going to put a comment that says something like "// Please
try and
ignore this and focus on the
interface above". And spread it out.
you could even put some chevrons to say. look upwards don't get
concerned in the implementation details. So I'll leave a big space. Alright. let's focus right
here on what BullCowGame is going to do as an interface. What I want you to do now is have a
go at writing the rest of the interface. It's going to change but I just want you to think about
how would you talk to this BullCowGame thing. if you wanted to?
This is top down design now. we're thinking. we don't know how to make it work yet
and it doesn't do anything. but how would we talk to it if it we wanted to? So here's your challenge! Write all the methods you
can. I want you to write as many simple signatures as you can.
Don't worry about getting it right. there's no right way anyway. the point is to
think about it at this stage. and enjoy working at a higher level of thinking and abstraction.
Go and pause the video. just write in a couple more helper methods. things that you think you might need
in this game. OK welcome back! Before you watch
my solution. why not share what you've got? Just share your public interface. preferably
take a nice close in screenshot just of class
FBullCowGame and just this bit here. As a hint for you. by the way. for taking these screenshots. there's lots
and lots of tools but one free one is called Jing by TechSmith
and there's also I think there's lots of others. OK but there's just a tip. Jing. J i n g.
Cool! So let me just get you a couple of others that I think we may need. We may
need to get back. from this game system. the current try so
int GetCurrentTry. And we
may want to get from this. what else? We may want to know if the game is won. so
bool IsGameWon(). Yeah we don't let
our main code worry about this. Our view code. i.e. the stuff
that we've got over here in main .cpp. we let the game engine worry about that.
What else do we want? We may want to know
whether a guess is valid. For now we'll have bool coming back and
CheckGuessValidity
and incoming may be a (string). so we send
in a (string). Again. let's make a richer
return value for that later. What else?
We may want to actually submit a guess. Now what's going to come back from submitting a guess?
It's complicated because we need bulls and cows together and you can't put that in a
single thing like an integer. so we're going to have to create something called a struct. which we'll see shortly.
And that struct is beyond the scope of this video. it'll be in a very short future
video. So I think we've got enough methods. If you've got something vaguely looking
like this. you've done very well. So we've got a good few methods. you may have come up with some
others. It really doesn't matter what's in the private interface right now. that's just messy
implementation details. I'm not actually going to #include
string just yet. because I want to talk about a couple of consequences
here. What I certainly do not want you doing is using namespace
up at the top here. Using namespace is
considered. by some developers. a very naughty thing to do anywhere but you never ever do it in a
header file. and that's because you can just completely lose track of what's going
on. if you start including header files that use namespaces. So we do not
use using namespace. And I will. in the next video. start talking about
two things. one about how #includes and #including files that have
#include that others works. And also. we'll talk a little bit about using namespace and
how we don't use it here and do various other things to tidy this header file
up. But hopefully you get the idea that this is basically just a contract.
The most important bit of it is here and we are defining it at top level
what we want this thing to do. without worrying about how we're going to do it. Indeed somebody else could write the code potentially.
OK congratulations on this! I look forward to seeing your
suggested public interfaces to your class. I know some of this.
if you're a complete beginner. may all sound a little bit bamboozling but don't worry about it. just trust
in the process that it's OK to write these wishful methods that don't exist yet. and that
we can keep adding flesh to the bone as we go through it!
=======
...
So welcome to Using Header Files as Contracts! We're going to focus
purely on the interface to our new class. And by the end of the video,
we will have a whole new file called FBullCowGame.h,
and in the case of you Xcode people, it will have created you a full .cpp file, too.
And we'll have written class FBullCowGame like this and public,
and we will have written some methods that are blurred out here, because I don't want to ruin
the challenge. And there's no right or wrong answer anyway, but these are going to define the
interface to the class, what we're allowed to do. It's a black box we're building right now.
There will also be a private section, which will be things that it will use in order to do its
work, but we shouldn't concern ourselves too much with that right now, we want to focus on
what work it's going to be doing, not how it's going to be doing the work. So
let's dive in and explore the exciting world of clases!
So let's make our own
class for the very first time! The way to do that, the way to add a new file, is to click on the project
name here. So we have the solution and inside the solution we have a single project. Right-click,
Add, and then New Item. OK so that's what we're doing on the screen.
And then, in the case of VisualStudio here, I'm just going to add a header file
to start with. We're just going to start with a header file here in VisualStudio, we'll add a C++ file
later, so that we can focus on one thing at a time.
I'm going to call it FBullCowGame. Why am I prefixing with F?
Well if you look in the Unreal coding standard, I'll show you where to find that. We've seen it before.
Then, they suggest prefixing.
If you go to the naming conventions, you see "Most other classes are prefixed by F",
so I'm going to do that so that things start to feel familiar. So there we go, FBullCowGame.h.
Even though it's a bit weird, at least it will be familiar later.
Hi I'm Sam and I'm helping Ben out with some of the Mac content on this course.
So I just want to briefly show you how to create that class in Xcode
now. So you probably want to go and right-click on the BullCow folder,
that's this one under the project. So you've got the project here and then you've got this
folder or as Xcode likes to call it a group. Right-click on
this and then we want to go down to new file
and we want to go down to OS X,
Source, and select the .cpp file
here. Now don't worry, we don't want the header file we actually want the
.cpp. And hit Next, we can create our
FBullCowGame, as Ben said.
And we also want to create a header file, so we will
save that. And now that there's a distinction between folders and groups
in Xcode, so we're putting it in the BullCow group, which only
exists inside of Xcode. We could also arrange things in different folders.
We're not going to here, but just so you're aware, that is a distinction
in Xcode. So I'm going to create that and as you can see
it has created two files here, the .cpp and the
.hpp, which is slightly different to what you'll see
on VisualStudio. OK back to Ben! So there it is sitting under header
files. What is this thing? It is, as I said before, something that would
just be cut and paste onto the top of whatever we include it in.
OK and we're going to be including it in Main.cpp, it's one
of the things we're going to include it in, and the other thing we're going to include it in is our file, that we'll make
in a little while, called FBullCowGame.cpp. So it lets us
put the same text in multiple places, literally a cut and paste. So #pragma
once, what's that about? Well it's actually not completely standard, it's not in the standards for C++
but it's very very widely supported, and it's a way of making sure that
anything that is imported is only imported once. It's an optimization, we may as well leave it
there. So do we need to import any namespaces? No not at the moment, let's just
get on and write our class. The way you do that is you say class, you give it a name.
So what are we going to call the class? Well the same as the file in this case, it doesn't have to be, by the way.
One thing here in C++ is that you
can write as many classes in a single file as you want, but for simplicity, especially at the moment,
let's just have a file and one class per file.
One file per class, it's just going to be a lot easier. Then you put your chevrons.
So that's your structure class, alright! Now what we want to focus on,
here in this video, is the public interface to this class. What our class is going to consist
of is two things, public: and private:. By the way,
look at the way that it indents that, it indents it across here. That's a bit weird
in my opinion, because normally you'd expect everything that's inside braces
like this to be indented. But I allow the
default here, because it's pretty standard across the industry, and I just treat these things
slightly differently to normal keywords. These are just like bookmarks,
just to say which part of the class definition you're in. So let's live with that. Anyway,
what's this class thing about? Well look, it's going to have in general, the pattern we're going to go for is this,
we're going to have public methods. Let me write the first public method.
The first public method could be Reset. OK so let's just pretend it
exists, and we declare it here. Now, we need something to come back from Reset().
What would we have come back from Reset()? For now nothing
but, later on, we're going to want something richer to come back, so I might put
comment "// TODO make a more rich return
value." What I mean by that is something that tells us a bit of a
status about what actually came back OK, but, for now, we're going to go void
just to flesh out the idea. I'm going to write one more method, and then, your challenge is going to be to write
all the others, once I've given you the overview. So once you've reset the game,
another thing you might want to be doing is saying, well
let's get the hidden... Oh by the way, by the way before we move on, resetting the game
in future may take in, for instance, an integer as to
the size of the WordLength.
OK. But for this whole section, we're just going to have a
single word hard coded in, so we can leave that out. Alright, so
what else might we want to do to a Bull Cow game? Well, for example, once
we've reset the game, we might want to get the number of
tries. So we'd get an integer back, and we could call this something like
GetMaxTries() OK and it would return us an integer.
So GetMaxTries, it's quite obvious what it does. I'm going to leave you to fill out the rest of these public
methods, in a moment, after a bit more priming. Now private, what would be in private?
Basically we don't want to concern ourselves too much with this, we want
to concern ourselves with the public interface to this. But you are going to have
both private functions which are helper functions, which
allow these things to happen behind the scenes, but you are also going to have private variables,
called member variables, and these things would be things
like... I don't know, we may have an int MyCurrent
Try, would be an example, and we may have an int MyMax
Tries. Now I'll explain why I'm prefixing everything with My, later on.
Well what I'm trying to say is, that there's a certain amount of stuff... Let me suggest another method,
by the way. It could be something like bool Is
Isogram().
i.e. is a particular (string) an isogram? that would be
examples of private methods we could imagine we want. Now, of course,
(string) is not imported, so I'll take this away for clarity. So
the general pattern with Object Oriented Programming is that we
don't expose any variables publicly, we do all of the getting
and setting of variables, however simple it is, through methods.
The variables stay private like this, this is pure Object Oriented Programming like that and
there's a lot to be said for it. So certainly for now this is how we're going to do things. Let's learn the rules
before we break the rules. So I want you to kind of ignore the private members for now,
and, in fact, I'm even going to put a comment that says something like "// Please
try and
ignore this and focus on the
interface above". And spread it out,
you could even put some chevrons to say, look upwards don't get
concerned in the implementation details. So I'll leave a big space. Alright, let's focus right
here on what BullCowGame is going to do as an interface. What I want you to do now is have a
go at writing the rest of the interface. It's going to change but I just want you to think about
how would you talk to this BullCowGame thing, if you wanted to?
This is top down design now, we're thinking, we don't know how to make it work yet
and it doesn't do anything, but how would we talk to it if it we wanted to? So here's your challenge! Write all the methods you
can. I want you to write as many simple signatures as you can.
Don't worry about getting it right, there's no right way anyway, the point is to
think about it at this stage, and enjoy working at a higher level of thinking and abstraction.
Go and pause the video, just write in a couple more helper methods, things that you think you might need
in this game. OK welcome back! Before you watch
my solution, why not share what you've got? Just share your public interface, preferably
take a nice close in screenshot just of class
FBullCowGame and just this bit here. As a hint for you, by the way, for taking these screenshots, there's lots
and lots of tools but one free one is called Jing by TechSmith
and there's also I think there's lots of others. OK but there's just a tip, Jing, J i n g.
Cool! So let me just get you a couple of others that I think we may need. We may
need to get back, from this game system, the current try so
int GetCurrentTry. And we
may want to get from this, what else? We may want to know if the game is won, so
bool IsGameWon(). Yeah we don't let
our main code worry about this. Our view code, i.e. the stuff
that we've got over here in main .cpp, we let the game engine worry about that.
What else do we want? We may want to know
whether a guess is valid. For now we'll have bool coming back and
CheckGuessValidity
and incoming may be a (string), so we send
in a (string). Again, let's make a richer
return value for that later. What else?
We may want to actually submit a guess. Now what's going to come back from submitting a guess?
It's complicated because we need bulls and cows together and you can't put that in a
single thing like an integer, so we're going to have to create something called a struct, which we'll see shortly.
And that struct is beyond the scope of this video, it'll be in a very short future
video. So I think we've got enough methods. If you've got something vaguely looking
like this, you've done very well. So we've got a good few methods, you may have come up with some
others. It really doesn't matter what's in the private interface right now, that's just messy
implementation details. I'm not actually going to #include
string just yet, because I want to talk about a couple of consequences
here. What I certainly do not want you doing is using namespace
up at the top here. Using namespace is
considered, by some developers, a very naughty thing to do anywhere but you never ever do it in a
header file, and that's because you can just completely lose track of what's going
on, if you start including header files that use namespaces. So we do not
use using namespace. And I will, in the next video, start talking about
two things, one about how #includes and #including files that have
#include that others works. And also, we'll talk a little bit about using namespace and
how we don't use it here and do various other things to tidy this header file
up. But hopefully you get the idea that this is basically just a contract.
The most important bit of it is here and we are defining it at top level
what we want this thing to do, without worrying about how we're going to do it. Indeed somebody else could write the code potentially.
OK congratulations on this! I look forward to seeing your
suggested public interfaces to your class. I know some of this,
if you're a complete beginner, may all sound a little bit bamboozling but don't worry about it, just trust
in the process that it's OK to write these wishful methods that don't exist yet, and that
we can keep adding flesh to the bone as we go through it!
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1