...
So welcome to Including Our Own Header Files! In this video we'll be explaining
why you never use a namespace or use the keyword
using namespace in a dot header file. We'll actually stop using
it all together. So over here in main.cpp. where we used to
have using namespace standard. we're going to get rid of that and show you the alternative.
We are going to create our first .cpp file that actually is
associated with the header file. so we'll have a FBCowGame.h. we should have already got.
but we'll also have the .cpp file with empty methods. And
we'll talk about chains of includes. a little bit about #include. and how they work together.
So let's get on with it! So here we are
back at our merry code. and our first priority is to get rid of this error! The error
is caused because it doesn't understand (string). So what we need to do is
#include something. Do you know what we need to #include? Well
I'll forgive you if you say iostream. but in this case. we need to be more specific
and #include  itself. because that's
directly what we're trying to do. Now. how do I get (string) to work once I've done that?
I go (std::string) instead. and
all is right with the world again. Let's just compile our code now
and run it and make sure that it works. Good! So we're now in a state
where it runs. which is where we want to be most of the time. Now.
what you do not do is. using
namespace inside a header file. If you do that and you include that
header file somewhere else. you're going to completely lose track of what namespaces you have access
to. and you have open and that's a nightmare. In fact. it's such a nightmare
that a lot of people advocate not using namespace at all. and I'm
going to suggest we stop using it. I used it the first time around to make your syntax look simpler
and also to introduce you to it. because you're going to see it on the
web. you're going to see it in all sorts of places. when you do some searching. But we're going to get rid
of it. because it's too dangerous. You're going to end up putting it in a header file one
day. You're better off just being completely explicit like this. And also. by the way. this
is much easier to search for. this is a very specific searchable thing inside your code.
So what I want you to do is remove all references
to using namespace. which is only in your main.cpp
file. So go ahead and delete using namespace. When you do that your code
is going to break. Try and do Control F5 now. you're going to get all sorts of
errors. starting with this string at the top. So let me show you
how to start sorting it out. then I'm going to challenge you to go and finish sorting it out. What you want to do is
go to string. go to Edit. Find and Replace.
Quick Replace. That's one of the easiest ways. Control H remember that.
And then. what we're going to do is. where we see string we're going to replace it with std::
string. OK. I'm going to skip over that first one.
If you look through. you can use this button I'm clicking on here to
go through the searches right. and then.
when it gets to the top it says it's finished starting. I'm not going to show that in the future. so I can comfortably
click through the whole lot now. So you can see the one that's highlighted
in gray there. So I'm currently at this guy. and then. I'm going to use this button
here to replace. And it's saying it can't find anymore occurrences.
so you go next. You just have a quick preview of them all. and then. you say
Replace All. OK. now of course. it may have done this one here.
which just is the only one that doesn't make sense. High. it's Sam here again just helping
Ben out with a couple of the Mac bits of content. So I just wanted to
quickly show you how to do a find and replace in Xcode.
So the trick here. it's Command F. or if you want to actually find the
menu. you can go into Find and then Find...
very helpful. And we want to do Find and Replace. so actually
it's not Command F. it's Command Alt F like so. So we
want to search for "string". and we want to replace string with
standard string. so it's very straight forward. very much
like in VisualStudio. We can just click through to check that
everything is the one we want. and we can replace one by
one. like so.
And we won't replace the top one. so if I save and build that should all be OK.
Alright. so just checking that you haven't got double replacements.
because if you replace all that's basically how you do it. Let me do it slightly more competently
the second time. Let's look down our file. look for the red dots over here. see where
it first complains again. It complains at cout. I'm going to use Control and H for
quick replace. I'm going to replace cout with std::
cout like that. and I'm going to boldly hit Replace All. Boom!
8 occurrences replaced. I'm going to have a look through and see if it's caused
me any complete nightmares. It hasn't and
there you go! We're just going to finish that off. look for the other things that don't work.
replace them. Pause the video. do that now. There's no challenge slide up and
I'll come back to you in 2 seconds. Cool! Alright. so I'm just
going to finish this off with a few more Control H's. endl
endl. Replace All.
OK. so now it's found our endl's. What else has it got a concern about? It's done a
double replace there or I have. because I've been a fool. What else have
we got? OK. getline. let's do these ones manually. Standard getline also
cin itself. Alright. and here we go.
Standard getline. standard cin.
Great! Alright. let's recompile our code! Control F5.
It all works now! OK. it came up. I put it away a but quickly but it all works. That's great
news! Now a little bit later on. I'm actually going to make a type substitution of
this to something else that we're going to see inside
Unreal called fstring or ftext. so that we start to get even more used to
Unreal syntax. Actually the situation will get better again. but
for now. let's go from having our eye in to the simple clean stuff.
that without to actually be able to train ourselves to read this as well. I want you
to be as multitalented as possible. when it comes to reading C++. so that
when you need to go and dive online and say. how do I do this in C++. when you're making your own game.
you can read lots of different peoples' code. That's really important OK. it's not all sterile
code out there. This is actually much more strict. much more correct in many ways. It's just a
little bit more noisy. which is absolutely fine. Great! So what we need
to do next is. we need to actually make ourselves a .cpp file
and include this stuff. so that we can start implementing some of
these things that we have here. These greens are saying. it can't find a
definition for these things alright. So one simple way to
do that. by the way. would be to right click here and go to Quick Actions. I showed you before
how to enable that. from the Tools and Options menu if you need to.
Create definition of it. Look what happens!
It has already made you an FBullCowGame.cpp file. OK. it's
showing you a peak into that file. and then. you could open the file here by
double clicking in source. I like to have things ordered like this. main because
main is. well it's arguable where you put main. So
FBullCowGame.h first. for sure. because that thing gets pulled in here.
which main.cpp uses as well. Alright. so what we've
got now. what it's done for us. is this. It's #included "FBullCowGame.h"
but in quotes. You see because I said that if you're looking
for something on a standard library use chevrons. but if you're looking for something of your own you go
quotes. And it will help us autocomplete. And then it's
fleshed out. BullCowGame::Reset() method. and it has no
actual implementation right now. But if we go back to the header file.
close this little preview window. you can see over here
that Reset() is no longer complaining. So I simply want you to finish writing
blank definitions. Write blank definitions for all the methods and ensure there are no warnings
left in the .h file. Welcome
back. This is a simple job thanks to these tools. In fact. I'm going to use Control and dot for the Quick
Action. create a definition. and then. I'm just going to close it and trust it.
I'm going to come down here. Control and dot. create definition.
Close it and trust it. down here Control dot. create definition.
close it and trust it. Now we can go and look over here. Look it's done loads of work for us.
it's even returned the right things. The only thing it hasn't done is put a return at the end
of Reset(). and I want to return there. I said we should always think about
what we're going to be returning. even if it's nothing. Alright. so that's that! Now. one
question would be. where is... Oh. now GetMaxTries() is OK! Sorry! IsGameWon()
1. 2. 3. 4. 5. five methods! How many have we got
in here? 1. 2. 3. 4. so we're missing 1.
Is it the IsGameWon()? GetMaxTries(). Reset(). GetMaxTries().
GetCurrentTry()... It's GetCurrentTry()! I don't know. to be honest. why it isn't
complaining about Get... Yes I do. ha ha ha! Look! Get
CurrentTry. it's not complaining here because it's not a method! I should've added brackets after
it! OK. so that's the problem. and
this what I've done here is. I've defined a variable and you can't implement a variable.
So brackets. easy enough mistake to make! So right here.
create definition. and we're good to go! It doesn't matter if
the order is the same in here. that's not important. but it has actually put it in order.
So great! We've done a load of work there! We now have a file that has affectively.
once it's finished doing this #include. it's very much what we were doing in
main. We are defining these methods. just like we did here in main where we put
prototypes at the top here. The difference being here. we've wrapped it in something called a
class and said that these are public. Now. we'll understand a lot more about what that means later.
but well done in adding more skeleton to your code! And
we're doing really nicely here. so pat yourself on the back and I'll see you in the next video!