...
So. welcome to Instantiating Your Class! We're going to take the small but important
step of actually bringing an instance of the
class that you just created to life. so if the class is like a factory then instance is
like one of the cars rolling off the production line. So. let's go ahead explore that now!
So now that we have this fancy class thing we've created. or
user defined type called Bull Cow Game. how do we use it?
Well firstly. let's see how we've been using existing types that have been
defined. If we scroll down. in main.cpp. to GetGuess().
you can see this line here. This says there is a
type called string. OK. they've not used a capital and stuff.
but it's still a type and it's user defined and somebody else has defined it for us.
It happens to be wrapped up in a namespace. That's just like a folder. so it's in a folder called
Standard. if you like. but it's called string. And
this is the type. Guess is the name of the variable we're going to be creating. and we're
initializing it to a value of a blank string. You actually. strictly speaking. don't
need to do that. but it's a good habit given that we're not entirely sure
how this would create itself. So. how are we going to get
access to our own type. Well. we're going to do something like this. It's not going to
work right now. but I'm just going to show you what we're going to do. We're going to go something like FBullCowGame.
because that's the name of our class. just like string here was the name of the
class. This is the template. the mold if you like. that
this thing is going to come out of. and we're going to call the actual thing something like Bull Cow Game.
And that's just like our Guess. that's our variable. and that word.
once we've done the necessary steps. that would make a new variable called
BCGame. which is actually a game instance. It's a bigger thing. conceptually.
than just a string guess and that would be that. and then. we
can't just initialize it trivially like this. because it's not a string. it's not a
number. so we'll talk about initialization in a minute. too. i.e. how do we give it
an initial a starting value? What properties is it born with? But this is
what we're aiming for! So. why does this not work at the moment? Well.
the reason that doesn't work. at the moment. is because we haven't imported the
library. So. I'm just going to delete that line. I've made no changes to the code at this stage.
At the top of main.cpp what we need to be doing is. and I want you to do this.
#include. OK. so we do #include. Now. we use quotes
because it's not a system thing. this is something we've made  ourselves. and look it very happily says ooh.
in this project or solution there's something called "FCowBullGame.h".
Let's use that! Great! So now. we have included
our own header file. OK. And the compiler is cleaver enough. by the way.
to know that if we're including this header file. that because all this implementation
here refers back to the header file through this
and through these little prefixes. which we'll explore when we come to actually write methods.
it knows that by including the head file it knows where to go to find this code
we've written. Bear in mind. there's nothing scary about the header file. Remember. you
could copy and paste what's in this header file. cut it completely
if you wanted. stick it at the top up here. and it's the same as a #include.
#include literally means copy and paste. It's nothing
more cleaver than that really. There's a few other things the compiler might do. which we can
see later but that's it basically. Cool! So. once we've
#include "FBullCowGame.h". we can now actually start to get
access to it. so let's try this. Where are we first going to need the
BullCowGame? Well. when we play the game. one of the first things we're going to need to do before
we play the game is to actually have a game to play.
So now. I want you to create a BCGame instance. but don't panic. it's simpler
than it sounds. It's just like you've been making strings or integers or any other variable
declaration. This is just a user defined type. remember. It's just a big box full of
cleaver stuff. So. make it the first line of PlayGame(). for now.
Declare a new object called BCGame. make it of type "FBullCowGame".
don't worry about initializing it yet. and make sure your code
still runs when you're finished. That will be the proof that it's all worked. So. pause the video. have a go at that. and we'll show you how in a sec.
So. we're going to create the FBullCowGame BCGame;
and then. when I hit semicolon watch what happens!
You see it recognizes this is a class. and then. that
becomes our variable. This is actually an instance
of this game. So. this is the template and then out of that mold we
create a game. OK. So. that is our
first instantiation. So instantiate.
So. what does instantiate mean? It means create an instance of...
Yeah. instantiate a new game or make
an instance of a new game. And there it is. it's a game! It's a big lump! It's much more
complex than just a string or an integer. but it's exactly the same as this guy here. that
just says you know make me a guess. make me a string rather. called Guess
and then. it goes off and initializes it. Now. we do
need to talk about initializing. So we have made a game. right. That's fine!
Now. what properties does that game have?
It has some state. it's born with some
stuff. right. For example. later on we're going to be saying that each
game has a current try and a maximum tries.
What has this game been born with? We don't know. we haven't explicitly said.
We just don't know what these properties of the game. the current
try and maximum try if you even have them. we don't know what those values are and that's a
problem. This thing. at the moment is initialized. we don't know what state it's in.
Yeah. we know it's of game. but it's like making a car and saying well I don't know if it's
coming out of the factory with the headlights on or with the headlights off or with the blinkers going or with the wipers
going or with the engine on? You know. if you make cars and the factory is this
thing here and each of the cars is this. You know. see I might make another game right now.
I might say. BCGame there. and then. I might make another one. And
I might make it BCGame2 or Player2Game
you now. and this may be Player1Game. So. we've actually got
two games running at the same time. and it can keep track of them because they're completely separate.
They've got their own. well they will when we start fleshing this out. have their own
properties. You know the current turn that they're on. and
you know with the status of the game. whether the game is won or not. will be independent
for each of these two things. These are like two cars coming off of a production line. from the same mold.
but we need to be sure they all come off the production line in
the same state. You know. headlights off. wipers not working. etc.
So. that is the job of something called a constructor. When
we create a new game like this. what the code is going to do
is it's going to go over here and it's going to say we don't have a constructor.
So. the topic of the next video is going to be constructors. It's going to be to say.
how do we make sure that when our mold creates a new one of these things. whatever our
thing is in our case a game. that we set the state of
that thing to what we want it to be. that our cars come off the production line with all their wipers off
and all their lights off. OK. so look forward to seeing you there where we'll work on constructors!
=======
...
So, welcome to Instantiating Your Class! We're going to take the small but important
step of actually bringing an instance of the
class that you just created to life, so if the class is like a factory then instance is
like one of the cars rolling off the production line. So, let's go ahead explore that now!
So now that we have this fancy class thing we've created, or
user defined type called Bull Cow Game, how do we use it?
Well firstly, let's see how we've been using existing types that have been
defined. If we scroll down, in main.cpp, to GetGuess(),
you can see this line here. This says there is a
type called string. OK, they've not used a capital and stuff,
but it's still a type and it's user defined and somebody else has defined it for us.
It happens to be wrapped up in a namespace. That's just like a folder, so it's in a folder called
Standard, if you like, but it's called string. And
this is the type, Guess is the name of the variable we're going to be creating, and we're
initializing it to a value of a blank string. You actually, strictly speaking, don't
need to do that, but it's a good habit given that we're not entirely sure
how this would create itself. So, how are we going to get
access to our own type. Well, we're going to do something like this. It's not going to
work right now, but I'm just going to show you what we're going to do. We're going to go something like FBullCowGame,
because that's the name of our class, just like string here was the name of the
class. This is the template, the mold if you like, that
this thing is going to come out of, and we're going to call the actual thing something like Bull Cow Game.
And that's just like our Guess, that's our variable, and that word,
once we've done the necessary steps, that would make a new variable called
BCGame, which is actually a game instance. It's a bigger thing, conceptually,
than just a string guess and that would be that, and then, we
can't just initialize it trivially like this, because it's not a string, it's not a
number, so we'll talk about initialization in a minute, too, i.e. how do we give it
an initial a starting value? What properties is it born with? But this is
what we're aiming for! So, why does this not work at the moment? Well,
the reason that doesn't work, at the moment, is because we haven't imported the
library. So, I'm just going to delete that line, I've made no changes to the code at this stage.
At the top of main.cpp what we need to be doing is, and I want you to do this,
#include. OK, so we do #include. Now, we use quotes
because it's not a system thing, this is something we've made  ourselves, and look it very happily says ooh,
in this project or solution there's something called "FCowBullGame.h".
Let's use that! Great! So now, we have included
our own header file, OK. And the compiler is cleaver enough, by the way,
to know that if we're including this header file, that because all this implementation
here refers back to the header file through this
and through these little prefixes, which we'll explore when we come to actually write methods,
it knows that by including the head file it knows where to go to find this code
we've written. Bear in mind, there's nothing scary about the header file. Remember, you
could copy and paste what's in this header file, cut it completely
if you wanted, stick it at the top up here, and it's the same as a #include.
#include literally means copy and paste. It's nothing
more cleaver than that really. There's a few other things the compiler might do, which we can
see later but that's it basically. Cool! So, once we've
#include "FBullCowGame.h", we can now actually start to get
access to it, so let's try this. Where are we first going to need the
BullCowGame? Well, when we play the game, one of the first things we're going to need to do before
we play the game is to actually have a game to play.
So now, I want you to create a BCGame instance, but don't panic, it's simpler
than it sounds. It's just like you've been making strings or integers or any other variable
declaration. This is just a user defined type, remember. It's just a big box full of
cleaver stuff. So, make it the first line of PlayGame(), for now.
Declare a new object called BCGame, make it of type "FBullCowGame",
don't worry about initializing it yet, and make sure your code
still runs when you're finished. That will be the proof that it's all worked. So, pause the video, have a go at that, and we'll show you how in a sec.
So, we're going to create the FBullCowGame BCGame;
and then, when I hit semicolon watch what happens!
You see it recognizes this is a class, and then, that
becomes our variable. This is actually an instance
of this game. So, this is the template and then out of that mold we
create a game, OK. So, that is our
first instantiation. So instantiate.
So, what does instantiate mean? It means create an instance of...
Yeah, instantiate a new game or make
an instance of a new game. And there it is, it's a game! It's a big lump! It's much more
complex than just a string or an integer, but it's exactly the same as this guy here, that
just says you know make me a guess, make me a string rather, called Guess
and then, it goes off and initializes it. Now, we do
need to talk about initializing. So we have made a game, right. That's fine!
Now, what properties does that game have?
It has some state, it's born with some
stuff, right. For example, later on we're going to be saying that each
game has a current try and a maximum tries.
What has this game been born with? We don't know, we haven't explicitly said.
We just don't know what these properties of the game, the current
try and maximum try if you even have them, we don't know what those values are and that's a
problem. This thing, at the moment is initialized, we don't know what state it's in.
Yeah, we know it's of game, but it's like making a car and saying well I don't know if it's
coming out of the factory with the headlights on or with the headlights off or with the blinkers going or with the wipers
going or with the engine on? You know, if you make cars and the factory is this
thing here and each of the cars is this. You know, see I might make another game right now.
I might say, BCGame there, and then, I might make another one. And
I might make it BCGame2 or Player2Game
you now, and this may be Player1Game. So, we've actually got
two games running at the same time, and it can keep track of them because they're completely separate.
They've got their own, well they will when we start fleshing this out, have their own
properties. You know the current turn that they're on, and
you know with the status of the game, whether the game is won or not, will be independent
for each of these two things. These are like two cars coming off of a production line, from the same mold,
but we need to be sure they all come off the production line in
the same state. You know, headlights off, wipers not working, etc.
So, that is the job of something called a constructor. When
we create a new game like this, what the code is going to do
is it's going to go over here and it's going to say we don't have a constructor.
So, the topic of the next video is going to be constructors. It's going to be to say,
how do we make sure that when our mold creates a new one of these things, whatever our
thing is in our case a game, that we set the state of
that thing to what we want it to be, that our cars come off the production line with all their wipers off
and all their lights off. OK, so look forward to seeing you there where we'll work on constructors!
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1