Hey hey! So, in this video we'll be writing
and using getter methods. I'll tell you what a getter
method is. We'll explain why we never access these member variables that we
have over here, directly.
We will initialize these member variables with these numbers on the end, and then,
I will be showing you how to access things like the maximum
tries, using the GetMaxTries(). And we'll actually implement the GetMaxTries() getter,
so that we can, for a given game for example, get the tries, put it in an
integer, and then tell the user which try number they're on. "Try 1. Enter your
guess:", etc. OK, so that's what we're going to be doing! Let's dive in and make it happen!
So, we want to start moving some of the things that we've
got in the main.cpp, or at least this number of turns, into the
class, because look we've already got MyMaxTries! So any given instance
of the game, like this Player1Game... Actually,  I'm going to rename it! Let's rename
it just BCGame again. It's OK to change your mind about names, you must
feel comfortable with them. So, here's an instance of a game called BCGame, and that particular game
has a max tries. Look BCGame dot! And when we hit the
dot, look we get all the methods that we defined over here, and one
of those it GetMaxTries(). So let's do that, GetMaxTries().
And that of course is what we're trying to talk about here, in terms of number
of turns. So, is GetMaxTries() implemented
yet? Let's go have a look! Right-click it, you can Go To Definition. If you're confused about
definition and declaration, remember that definition is think about high definition
OK! It's more defined than something that is just declared, so it's the definition
we want to go to. The declaration would, of course, take us to the header file. The definition
takes us to the .cpp. So from here, the methods of
this class are allowed to access it's private
parts, but nothing else from the outside is. So, from here I can
go Return, MyMaxTries, which is fine.
So now, when I try doing this it should spit out the right
value! Let's try it! Let's just say int
MaxTries = BCGame.GetMaxTries(); Why am I doing
that? I'm just trying to make my life a bit simpler in here.
I'm going to put less than = to MaxTries and get rid of this constant.
So it is pretty clear what this does. It instantiates a new game,
goes and finds out how many tries the game has got, and then, goes around a loop
based on the number of tries. Now temporarily, let's output the number of tries, because
we may have an interesting effect here.
MaxTries end line.
So, we have written already something called a getter.
We're not using the standard namespace! Draght, why did I make that
decision? I think it's good to be able to work both ways. So, we're going to cout the MaxTries.
Let's have a look, see what happens! Oh,
minus 8 thousand! Oh wait, lots, billions or whatever it is!
Wow, that's a funny number! Now, why is it a funny number? Why is this MaxTries
so strange? The code is really simple, it's returning the MaxTries, because look we
never initialize the MaxTries here, when we declare it. Now, for
now let's initialize it in here! Let's initialize MaxTries to 5,
right where we declare it! Now this is appropriate, to initialize here
is fine, but of course, you can't change it or you can't
change the initialization of it at runtime. If in the future we want to make
another game or reset the game somehow, we may need to do this somewhere else in something called
the constructor, but for now let's just do it here. Let's re-run! Control, F, 5.
Ah, that hasn't worked or has it? Now, this is
where I want to suggest you don't completely trust
compilers. Visual Studio is playing up here. I have definitely initialized.
I have definitely saved my header file alright, there's no star on it,
and it is not behaving! So to make it behave,
it just hasn't noticed this change, it's just being silly. It turns out if I put
something up here, like a comment. Notice me I'm significant, like
that and then do Control, F, 5, again, then all is
right with the world, we're back to 5 OK. So, you can either
hack around till you solve it or you could do this. You could go to Build
and Rebuild BullCowGame, rebuilding the project. You could rebuild the
entire solution, which would be all of the projects. We've only got one project, but
if you get into a situation we think that this really should have work, then I'm afraid,
sorry, even if you're a beginner you cannot always completely trust compilers. So, in a situation
like that, trust your gut and say well rebuild the project to start with.
And that will now work! 5 is the number of tries, OK!
So, just before I throw you into a challenge, I want to set you up
to win! I'm going to, in a minute, ask you to do something very similar to this
but inside the GetGuess() method. And I'm going to ask you to
put in, before the guess, the try number that we're currently on so people
know how many more guesses they've got. So, that's all fine but
you're going to be doing something very similar to this, but what I don't want you doing is creating a new game
instance. So, I'm going to move this line in main.cpp
under PlayGame(). I'm going to take that and put it right at the top of the method around
there. It doesn't really matter where it is, but the point is it's gone leftwards
one tab, it's at a higher scope. OK, it's available now
to all of these methods, it's not inside any particular method. It's not in that block, it's
not in this block anymore. So now, it's become more global. Now, global
in general is a bad thing. Putting things in what we call a global scope is a bad
thing, but global access to this game instance
is absolutely fine. We have a main() loop here, and this is the game
manager, if you like. And of course, it needs access to a game! We're going to have a single instance
of a game. We're going to keep resetting the same thing, rather than making new games, which
is going to reset the game. So, we do want access to it everywhere, that's fine! So,
there it is, and then, you get access to it in PlayGame(). Now, you will be able to get access to it
inside GetGuess() as well, so you better do something very similar to this. Cool! Let's
dive into the challenge! So, I want you to implement GetCurrentTry().
Initialize the value to 1 in the header file, for now. Check it works by
printing the try from GetGuess(). For example, I want it to say "Try 1.
Enter your guess:". It doesn't need to update each guess, that's fine!
Where 1 is the value of MyCurrentTry. So go ahead,
pause the video, and give that a go now.
OK welcome back! So, here we are in
GetGuess(). We're going to need to do something with very similar. There's nothing wrong with cutting and pasting your code.
So, int CurrentTry...
Ooh.
= BCGame.GetCurrentTry();
OK, that's fine! So, we go off and get the CurrentTry()!
Now, straight away check that, that is implemented.
GetCurrentTry is not, so you're going to need to return MyCurrentTry().
Great! Another thing you're going to need to do is go off and initialize it.
So, that was working backwards, let's try working forwards. When the
game object was created, at the top of main.cpp here,
it gave itself two private member variables, MyCurrentTry and
MyMaxTries and initialized them to 1 and 5 respectively.
The implementation just says GetMaxTries() does that, GetCurrentTry() does that.
Really simple! By the way, you'll often see getters written like this. Let's do that! It's just often
takes a load of the fluff out, and remembering that compilers
ignore white space, apart from certain white space, obviously between keywords
and inside strings, but most white space is ignored. So, there's something to be
said for this. In fact, there's something to be said for putting your two getters right at the top
of the implementation. So, you've got your two getters and then you go into
all your methods. Alright, just a tidy up but that syntax is common, and I quite
like it. So we, down here, have
gone and got our current try. There we go!
Now, what I want to do is just modify this to just say try,
and then, we're going to need to close the quotes,
put in the current try,
and then do something like that, OK.
And a dot and a space. Try, grab the current try, and enter it. Let's try
and see what happens. Ah, "Try 1."
"Enter your guess:". "Try 1" "Try 1" "Try 1". Great! Do you want to play
again? No. Now, we're not yet updating the try, and that's
because that's a more advance thing we haven't even done yet. We haven't even got a SubmitGuess()
method, and it's the SubmitGuess() method that is going to be updating
that try for us. OK. We need to make sure we submit valid guesses. We're not going to
penalize people for putting rubbish in, when we finally check this input. So,
this is all I wanted you to do. Well done getting this far! We've written a couple of getters now,
for the first time, and there they are implemented. And in the next video,
we're going to talk about the keyword called const, which is going to protect us from
doing anything naughty inside these functions, that are supposed to just return values. We're going to make
sure that's enforced. See you soon!