So, Introducing the Const
Keyword. In this video we will be
talking about const's meaning and how it depends on context. Generally
it means I promise not to change this.
What this is, depends on exactly where it appears in a piece of
code. At the end of a member function,
for example int GetCurrentTry() const; It prevents the function from modifying
any member variables, and this is a good safety feature.
So let's dive in and take a look at it in action.
So, let's see how this useful protection mechanism actually works.
So, for example, here in this getter GetMaxTries(), you really hope that doesn't
change anything, it just returns a number right, but what I'm concerned about
is, at the moment, it can change things. You don't need to reformat you code like I'm doing, because I'm going to put
it back in a minute. I just want to show you we can go MyMaxTries, for example, in here
=, I don't know 12.
Not very nice, because that would be a horrible side effect, and the fact that it compiles
and lets us do that concerns me. So,
what we can do is use something called const, where we declare GetMaxTries(),
whenever you write a constructor in the future, I want you to write the word
const after it, and then, of course, in your definition you're going to have to write const for it
to match. And that const, in this position, it depends where you put
const as to what it does. It has a different meaning in different positions.
We're only talking about it on the end of a member function, right now. So, on the
end of a member function, look what it does when we try to compile. Look at the errors!
"Expression must be modifiable". MyMaxTries, we're
not allowed to change MyMaxTries. In fact, we're not allowed to change any of these
member variables. Let's try changing MyCurrentTry. it doesn't let us
change it, OK. = 23, it's going to complain!
Even if these things were public, MyCurrentTry, which they shouldn't be because we want
access to them through our nice methods, but if they were public we still couldn't
change it, which is absolutely good! OK, so this is
just protecting ourselves from ourselves and from other people.
So, let's go back to where we were. I've got const on the end there. I'm going to just get
rid of this nasty code and prove that const, in this position in
the declaration, has had the effect of making sure
that this function, a member function... It has to be a member
as part of a class and I'll explain that in a second, if I explain that now. Let's go to main.
And if we try to make, for example, PlayGame() const or
let's try something else actually, PrintIntro(). OK, so here's PrintIntro(). It turns
out... Don;'t do this, just watch for a second. It turns out, you need to put it above, so
there's PrintIntro(). If I go const here, look I'm going to get another error.
A type qualifier is
not allowed on a non-member function. This is a non-member function because it's not
inside a class declaration. OK, these methods are all
inside a class, this isn't. So, this only works on class functions, if you like,
or member functions is another way of calling it. You have to be careful
with these terms, because strictly speaking, in the C++ standards they just talk about
functions, but anyway... So over here,
we've said const and it prevents this method from changing
any properties or
variables of the object, which is really powerful. OK, it's pretty simple!
That's all I want to say in this is, the next level of strength down from const
expression, which means you have to know it at compile time. const says, well we don't necessarily
know what this thing is at compile time, but I want to make sure this method doesn't change anything at
runtime. So, I've got a challenge for you! So, your challenge it to
apply const to all your other getters. Make
all the getter methods constant, check it still runs, and I want you to answer this question
in the discussions. Are any of the other functions, that we've written so far, candidates
for the use of const. If so, suggest which if any in the discussions,
just because I want you to get used to putting your ideas out there and to thinking. Now, some of you may not
feel comfortable with that, but I'd encourage you to do things you're a little bit uncomfortable with. So,
think with any of the others, discuss with the other students, could we make
one of these other methods that we've got already declared here,
could one of these other be const, one of the three
that I've highlighted? OK, go ahead, pause the video,
and do that challenge now!
Cool! So welcome back! Obviously we're going to make GetCurrentTry()
const. Because it's a pure getter, it's called const,
and it's called get rather. It starts with get, we want to make it const. Now, there's another, of course,
which is the IsGameWon(). We haven't implemented this yet,
but from now on, I want you to start thinking about, if we're just asking a
question, is the game won even though there is no definition
of that yet, I want this to be constant, right; because
I know just contractually that looking at this I don't
want IsGameWon() to be changing anything. That would be bad, wouldn't it! I think
it would be bad. OK, so that's fine! I'm just going to more reset
down, because it's kind of a different class of method. This actually does stuff, so I'm going to move that down
one, leave all these guys there and the constant ones at the top.
I'm going to leave space here, because I want you to stop looking at the private parts
of the code. OK, focus
on the interface, which is getting clearer and clearer. OK, these things don't change
anything and now can't change anything, which is great and we can reset the game and check validity.
which we'll implement later. OK, let's compile, always compile, make sure things
work, and nice simple video. See you soon!
...