...
So. hi and welcome to Pseudocode Programming. In this video we'll be talking more about the Pseudocode
Programming Practice. sometimes known as PPP. We'll review our code
within its architecture. I'll talk about using to do as a comment prefix.
I'll introduce you briefly to Visual Studio's Task List. which is available
here in View and Task List and how that works.
and then. we'll just be generally planning our next wave of coding. So. let's dive in and see it work!
OK. so let's put the power or pseudocode in our hands and start
making even more progress on our game. So. I'm going to start at the top of main. In fact. I'm going to move
main to my left-hand most tab. because logically it kind of comes first.
If it'll move to my left-hand most tab. If it won't. I'll move something else in front of it. There you go!
So. I'm going main. then the header. then the main class definition.
So. let's go for it! Let's take a look down our code. We have.
in the main loop here. PlayIntro(). PlayGame(). and then. AskToPlayAgain().
What we know that we may want to do in the future is to add a
game summary. at the end. because it's not going to be a part of the actual
playing of the game. I don't think. Let's take a look down to the PlayGame() method
or function. It could go here! Arguably you could
say "// summarise game" here. or we could
have "// summaries game" here. I think it
goes with the PlayGame(). so I'm going to leave it down here with PlayGame().
So. I'm going to introduce you to a new prefix. which is TODO. and we've used
this before but a little bit more formally now. TODO is fairly. widely accepted
by integrated development environments. as a code for I need to
do something here. So. once you've written TODO in Visual
Studio. you can go to View. and then you can go to Task List here. View and Task List.
And your IDE. if you're using a different one. may have a similar feature.
And what it'll do is it'll show you where all of you TODO comments are. These are still
just comments. but this can help you to organize what you're doing.
There are some other settings on this to do with priorities. if you go to Options and then
Task View or Task List in here. You can find
some other things to do with setting priorities and adding other tokens. but for now.
all I want you to know is that TODO is a good way of saying. I plan to do this in the future. It must be done
but I can't do it right now. So. summarize the game.
after the game is finished. That's something we need to do. and I've decided to put it inside of
PlayGame(). because it makes more logical sense.
So. what else do we need to do? Let's look down! Printing the info is fine. apart from the
WORLD_LENGTH. [Laughs] Look at that. it should be WORD_LENGTH of course. so let's use the Refactor Tool
to fix it to WORD_LENGTH. That's good!
OK. inside PlayGame(). what are we doing? So. we're looping for the number of
turns. but notice that we are assuming that every time we get a
guess the guess is valid. Shortly. we're going to have to start doing input validation
and error checking. to make sure that only valid
guesses are entered. And at that point. we're actually not going to know how many times we need
to go around this PlayGame() loop. because if they enter an invalid
guess. then we're going to have to go around it again. So. what I want to do shortly
is TODO make check for valid
guesses. "Make loop checking
valid". basically something like that. So. GetGuess() is going to become GetValidGuess()
later or something. and that's going to keep persisting. until it gets a valid guess
out of the system. And then. what it's going to do is it's going to "Submit
valid guess
to the game".
OK. And then. when we submit the valid guess to the game. it's at
that point that it'll return the number of bulls and cows. So
after that. we're going to print number of bulls and
cows. So. use English here. when you're using pseudocode
programming. I'm going to try and be standard here and just use lower case.
So. what we're going to be doing in the future is using a while loop.
because there's going to be a couple of conditions on which we want to come out of the game.
One is that we have expired the number of MaxTries. but it's
not up to this for loop to count that. It's going to be up to the
game object to count that. and we will be reading from it. GetCurrentTry()
and making that control this loop. So. it goes from a known
for loop to a slightly less know while loop. We'll be doing that later.
so that's why I've said to change it from for to while loop. once we
are validating tries
or something like that. Now. when am I using TODO vs.
when am I using not TODO. I'm not putting TODO in.
when I'm adding new code or when the comment is going to stay.
So. t his comment will stay. even when I do this TODO. and these two comments
will stay. even once I've added the
code below them. But this stuff. that's actually changing existing code. then
I'll use that as a TODO. because the TODO itself will be deleted.
OK. so hopefully it's clear when you use TODO. and when you don't...
Like here as well. this is going to change. This GetGuess() is going to change. so I tend to use
the TODO for something that's going to change. Alright. so let's keep going
and thinking about the architecture. One of the things we're going to need to be able to do.
in the game itself. is to return the number of
bulls and cows. So. let's put something in here. We're going to have some new type. that we'll do in the
next video. and then. we're going to Submit
ValidGuess. and then. we're going to send in a
string but I'm not going to say what we send it in
detail. When you write comments. you want to try and avoid
actually coding in those comments. so this is
too like coding. So. I'm going to get rid of that comment
and write more in English. You have the luxury here
of working at a higher level of abstraction. so why would you try and get
bogged down in the details of code. at this point. What we're trying to say we do is.
we need to "// provide a
method for counting
bulls & cose and incrementing
or increasing turn number.
Ooh. that was my Start button. OK. so it's
this new method that we'll put in shortly. that will provide a way of counting bulls
and cows. It's going to return a singe entity. probably. that it contains both
bulls and cows. We're going to use something. which is just like a class for it. as you'll see.
and it will increase the turn number. If you've been wondering where the
turn number is going to be increased. it's going to be inside the method that's going to be called something like
SubmitValidGuess(). It'll spit back numbers of bulls and cows. possibly
in error code. and then. once a valid guess come in will increase
the turn number. Then. over in the game loop here. inside...
Where are we? Inside PlayGame(). Let me just zoom my font out a tiny bit.
Yeah. inside here inside PlayGame(). we won't be using this
count here to go in this loop. as I said it becomes a while loop. OK. So.
if we look at the interface to the Bull Cow Game. we're going to be doing things like. initially we get
the maximum tries. Then. we keep getting current tries. Checking
guess validity. submitting a guess using a new method we're going to write shortly.
which will increment the turn number. or should I say try number. because the try.
Let's try and be consistent between guess and try and turn. So. in fact.
when I say let's be consistent between guess and try and turn. as this is a clean
out video. let's do that. Let's do a find and see where we use Guess.
CheckGuessValidity(). so the guess is the actual string. Let's look
across the entire project. remember the Bull Cow Game Project. for the word guess.
Submit valid guess. I want to make sure the guess is always
referring to the string that the user sends in.
GetGuess(). ". Enter your guess: ";
Oh. I think I missed one. "Can you guess... I think that's OK! Good!
Alright. now let's try the word turn. because I've been using the word turn
as well. and it needs to be a whole word. So. to search for a whole word you can
use this thing here. match whole word. I don't use the word turn
anywhere in the project. Good! So then. I use the word try. which is the number
of times that the use has guessed. or the guess
number is the try and that's good! So. when you hear yourself saying. oh we really should be
consistent with that. do that sort of thing. Do a find and replace and get everything
tidied up and tightened up. We want to be doing this type of refactoring and tightening up
very frequently. So. my challenge to you now.
and there won't be a solution because I've basically done it for myself. is I want you to go through your code
and make sure it makes sense to you firstly. I want you to action any existing TODO's
that you can action. write any new TODO's for tasks that
must be done in the future. do not use code in your comments.
and give yourself the gift of working at this higher level of abstraction.
Start writing English statements about what you want it to do in the future. Then. we'll come behind
and we'll start coding from that. So. go ahead.
stop the video now because I'm not going to come back until the next video. And I'll see you in the next lecture.
when we'll talk about using structures. for returning these bulls and cows in one go!
...
=======
So, hi and welcome to Pseudocode Programming. In this video we'll be talking more about the Pseudocode
Programming Practice, sometimes known as PPP. We'll review our code
within its architecture. I'll talk about using to do as a comment prefix,
I'll introduce you briefly to Visual Studio's Task List, which is available
here in View and Task List and how that works,
and then, we'll just be generally planning our next wave of coding. So, let's dive in and see it work!
OK, so let's put the power or pseudocode in our hands and start
making even more progress on our game. So, I'm going to start at the top of main. In fact, I'm going to move
main to my left-hand most tab, because logically it kind of comes first.
If it'll move to my left-hand most tab. If it won't, I'll move something else in front of it. There you go!
So, I'm going main, then the header, then the main class definition.
So, let's go for it! Let's take a look down our code. We have,
in the main loop here, PlayIntro(), PlayGame(), and then, AskToPlayAgain().
What we know that we may want to do in the future is to add a
game summary, at the end, because it's not going to be a part of the actual
playing of the game, I don't think. Let's take a look down to the PlayGame() method
or function. It could go here! Arguably you could
say "// summarise game" here, or we could
have "// summaries game" here. I think it
goes with the PlayGame(), so I'm going to leave it down here with PlayGame().
So, I'm going to introduce you to a new prefix, which is TODO, and we've used
this before but a little bit more formally now. TODO is fairly, widely accepted
by integrated development environments, as a code for I need to
do something here. So, once you've written TODO in Visual
Studio, you can go to View, and then you can go to Task List here. View and Task List.
And your IDE, if you're using a different one, may have a similar feature.
And what it'll do is it'll show you where all of you TODO comments are. These are still
just comments, but this can help you to organize what you're doing.
There are some other settings on this to do with priorities, if you go to Options and then
Task View or Task List in here. You can find
some other things to do with setting priorities and adding other tokens, but for now,
all I want you to know is that TODO is a good way of saying, I plan to do this in the future. It must be done
but I can't do it right now. So, summarize the game,
after the game is finished. That's something we need to do, and I've decided to put it inside of
PlayGame(), because it makes more logical sense.
So, what else do we need to do? Let's look down! Printing the info is fine, apart from the
WORLD_LENGTH. [Laughs] Look at that, it should be WORD_LENGTH of course, so let's use the Refactor Tool
to fix it to WORD_LENGTH. That's good!
OK, inside PlayGame(), what are we doing? So, we're looping for the number of
turns, but notice that we are assuming that every time we get a
guess the guess is valid. Shortly, we're going to have to start doing input validation
and error checking, to make sure that only valid
guesses are entered. And at that point, we're actually not going to know how many times we need
to go around this PlayGame() loop, because if they enter an invalid
guess, then we're going to have to go around it again. So, what I want to do shortly
is TODO make check for valid
guesses. "Make loop checking
valid", basically something like that. So, GetGuess() is going to become GetValidGuess()
later or something, and that's going to keep persisting, until it gets a valid guess
out of the system. And then, what it's going to do is it's going to "Submit
valid guess
to the game".
OK. And then, when we submit the valid guess to the game, it's at
that point that it'll return the number of bulls and cows. So
after that, we're going to print number of bulls and
cows. So, use English here, when you're using pseudocode
programming. I'm going to try and be standard here and just use lower case.
So, what we're going to be doing in the future is using a while loop,
because there's going to be a couple of conditions on which we want to come out of the game.
One is that we have expired the number of MaxTries, but it's
not up to this for loop to count that. It's going to be up to the
game object to count that, and we will be reading from it, GetCurrentTry()
and making that control this loop. So, it goes from a known
for loop to a slightly less know while loop. We'll be doing that later,
so that's why I've said to change it from for to while loop, once we
are validating tries
or something like that. Now, when am I using TODO vs.
when am I using not TODO. I'm not putting TODO in,
when I'm adding new code or when the comment is going to stay.
So, t his comment will stay, even when I do this TODO, and these two comments
will stay, even once I've added the
code below them. But this stuff, that's actually changing existing code, then
I'll use that as a TODO, because the TODO itself will be deleted.
OK, so hopefully it's clear when you use TODO, and when you don't...
Like here as well, this is going to change. This GetGuess() is going to change, so I tend to use
the TODO for something that's going to change. Alright, so let's keep going
and thinking about the architecture. One of the things we're going to need to be able to do,
in the game itself, is to return the number of
bulls and cows. So, let's put something in here. We're going to have some new type, that we'll do in the
next video, and then, we're going to Submit
ValidGuess, and then, we're going to send in a
string but I'm not going to say what we send it in
detail. When you write comments, you want to try and avoid
actually coding in those comments, so this is
too like coding. So, I'm going to get rid of that comment
and write more in English. You have the luxury here
of working at a higher level of abstraction, so why would you try and get
bogged down in the details of code, at this point. What we're trying to say we do is,
we need to "// provide a
method for counting
bulls & cose and incrementing
or increasing turn number.
Ooh, that was my Start button. OK, so it's
this new method that we'll put in shortly, that will provide a way of counting bulls
and cows. It's going to return a singe entity, probably, that it contains both
bulls and cows. We're going to use something, which is just like a class for it, as you'll see,
and it will increase the turn number. If you've been wondering where the
turn number is going to be increased, it's going to be inside the method that's going to be called something like
SubmitValidGuess(). It'll spit back numbers of bulls and cows, possibly
in error code, and then, once a valid guess come in will increase
the turn number. Then, over in the game loop here, inside...
Where are we? Inside PlayGame(). Let me just zoom my font out a tiny bit.
Yeah, inside here inside PlayGame(), we won't be using this
count here to go in this loop, as I said it becomes a while loop. OK. So,
if we look at the interface to the Bull Cow Game, we're going to be doing things like, initially we get
the maximum tries. Then, we keep getting current tries. Checking
guess validity, submitting a guess using a new method we're going to write shortly,
which will increment the turn number, or should I say try number, because the try.
Let's try and be consistent between guess and try and turn. So, in fact,
when I say let's be consistent between guess and try and turn, as this is a clean
out video, let's do that. Let's do a find and see where we use Guess.
CheckGuessValidity(), so the guess is the actual string. Let's look
across the entire project, remember the Bull Cow Game Project, for the word guess.
Submit valid guess. I want to make sure the guess is always
referring to the string that the user sends in.
GetGuess(), ". Enter your guess: ";
Oh, I think I missed one. "Can you guess... I think that's OK! Good!
Alright, now let's try the word turn, because I've been using the word turn
as well, and it needs to be a whole word. So, to search for a whole word you can
use this thing here, match whole word. I don't use the word turn
anywhere in the project. Good! So then, I use the word try, which is the number
of times that the use has guessed, or the guess
number is the try and that's good! So, when you hear yourself saying, oh we really should be
consistent with that, do that sort of thing. Do a find and replace and get everything
tidied up and tightened up. We want to be doing this type of refactoring and tightening up
very frequently. So, my challenge to you now,
and there won't be a solution because I've basically done it for myself, is I want you to go through your code
and make sure it makes sense to you firstly. I want you to action any existing TODO's
that you can action, write any new TODO's for tasks that
must be done in the future, do not use code in your comments,
and give yourself the gift of working at this higher level of abstraction.
Start writing English statements about what you want it to do in the future. Then, we'll come behind
and we'll start coding from that. So, go ahead,
stop the video now because I'm not going to come back until the next video. And I'll see you in the next lecture,
when we'll talk about using structures, for returning these bulls and cows in one go!
...
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1