...
So, welcome to this video!
We'll be using struct to define simple types. Let me just show you, and then we'll
dive in and get it done. We're going to make a thing here called
struct BullCowCount and it's like a class but it's even simpler,
and it's a simple structure that can contain two integers in one go,
so that we can write a method like this BullCowCount SubmitGuess, taking
in a string and returning a pair of integers. So let's get it done!
...
OK guys, welcome back! So, we're going to do something fun
in this video. We're going to implement our actual BullCowCount, but before
we can do that, we need to define a new data type, because
where we have said here, in the header, that we want to provide a method for counting
bulls and cows and increasing the try number, we need bulls and cows to come back
together in one go. And how are we going to organize that? Well,
we're going to use something called a struct. Now, I must tell you that a struct
is exactly the same as a class, basically except for by default
its members are public, and that lends itself to being ideal for
simple data types like this. Let me show you! If we say struct
BullCowCount here... Now, I'm at the top of BullCowGame.h,
because this is a structure that we're not going to use in main.cpp but we are going
to use inside our game logic. OK. Now, I'm going to open up
some brackets, like that, and then, we're
going to give it some members. Now, in terms of this bracket style, you
can see that IDE sometimes puts them on the wrong line, so I'm going to go with
this. It just spaces things out a little and adheres to Unreal's standards.
So, it's actually very simple, we're going to have two integers in here! One called Bulls and we're
going to initialize it immediately to 0. Best with structs, keep it
simple and don't worry about constructors and things. So, it's
basically the same as saying class BullCowCount, but we don't need to say public because everything is public by
default. It's a bit convoluted to start making things private, why not use a class,
and we're not going to have any methods in here. Now, the only thing is I want to use
int32, so there's a new habit for you, since we made the substitution. So int32,
a 32 bit integer for bulls and a 32 bit integer for
cows, both initialized to 0. That's it,
BullCowCount, very simple it contains two integers. Once we've done that, we
can write the signature of our actual method here, so I won't
overdo the comment yet, I'm going to make sure I get the signature right. So, we're going to be
returning a BullCowCount. I'm going to call it
SubmitGuess for now, pending a better name if we find one,
and we're going to take in an (FString), starting to get used to our new types for Unreal.
So, I'm going to improve this comment, provide a
method for counting bulls and cows and increasing the try number. That's
fine! I'm just going to say "counts", just to make it shorter,
"bulls and cows & increases
try #". And I'm also going to say that this
method assumes or probably, in the implementation, I'm going to say
it assumes. Why not here, "assuming valid
guess". So, it assumes that a valid guess comes into this
method. Alright, so that's it, we have a SubmitGuess
signature there. Let's go ahead and define SubmitGuess.
So, you go Quick Actions and then Create Definition,
and then, go over to the game .cpp file. Fantastic!
Big news! OK, here we are! So, before we do anything let's
pseudo code this, before we even start. So, what are we going to do? Well, as soon as we
get in here, we've received a valid guess. Let's outline what
this does. So, "receives a VALID
guess,
increments turn,
and returns count. OK,
slightly doubling up on our work here, so if you want to get rid of this
in the header file you can, to keep the header file tight and clean like that,
and we can focus on the comment being just here
in the implementation. By the way, back at the header file, when this says to
make a more rich return value, this is the sort of thing I'm
talking about. This is a richer return value than just a single integer. We'll be doing a similar thing
here, but we'll actually be using an enumeration. OK, so we have a richer
return type. Let's see what this guy is going to do! It's going to increment the return number. Don't do it
yet! OK, just stay
at this level! What else are we going to do? Well, we're going to need to setup a return
structure. We're going to need to
setup a return variable, aren't we? We're going to need to declare ourselves an instance of this Bull
CowCount thing and stuff. Don't worry about how we do that yet. Then, we're going to "loop through
all letters in the guess",
and then, for each letter we're
going to do some comparisons. So, for each of those letters, I'm going
to indent to represent that. You can indent in pseudo code. I'm going to say "compare
letters against
all" or just against the hidden word.
OK, so we're going to increment the turn number, setup
something to return, loop through all letters in the guess, and then, compare
letters against the hidden word, one at a time, and then,
at the end we're going to return the BullCowCount(). So, that is the structure of our submit guess. Now
before I flesh it out, I want to make sure it still runs, that all the scaffolding
code I have written is valid. It is, which is fantastic! Alright,
so now we're going to start actually implementing it. I'm going to help you a little bit, and then, I'm
going to ask you to mainly complete this loop. So firstly,
how do we increment the turn number? Well, under the comment just go ahead and think
that it's MyCurrentTry, because it's the member variable, the data inside this class,
this current instance of the game ++. That's another way of saying
MyCurrentTry equals MyCurrentTry +
1, but I wan't bother writing that, ++ is a shortcut. So, we increment the turn number. Fantastic!
Now, we need to setup a return variable! How are we going to do that? We say, BullCowCount, because that's the type.
We give it a name, BullCowCount,
and that's it for now! OK, it's already going to have things initialized
to 0. If you want to be
good about this, you could say BullCowCount.Bulls
= 0. And you are, in this instance as we're using a struct, allowed to access
the members, but actually, there's no point, because if we look at how we've defined BullCowCount,
it automatically initializes to 0. OK.
If you wanted to know that, from where you were, you could put a comment here.
"two integers, initialized
to zero", or just say "all
values initialized to zero". If you make that comment ahead of
the struct, look what happens here when we say
BullCowCount, and you hover over it,
it says "all values initialized to zero", so we can just call it BullCowCount.
Now, in terms of Unreal's naming standard, I don't really like this. I don't
really like the fact that my line says BullCowCount BullCowCount,
If we were in a lower case standard, then we would say BullCowCount, lower case
bullCowCount but some people find that more confusing. You could also consider using
prefixes here, but we're just going to live with it. Again, I want you to read code
like the compiler does. The compiler is saying, the first thing I'm expecting here is a type, and then, I'm expecting,
after the type, the name of the variable. So, we're just going to say BullCowCount BullCowCount.
Now, at this stage, we're going to need the hidden word.
Let's go back to our header and think what we're doing about the hidden word. We already have
a piece of data for it. No we don't even! We don't even have a data for the hidden word! So, we need to make a piece of
data! Let's make it an FString, because it's inside here
and it's going to be something we may want to manipulate. FString
- MyHiddenWord;
So, now we have a place to store the hidden word!
Of course, I shouldn't have an equals, FString - MyHiddenWord; is just declaring it. Now,
we've added a new piece of data to this. Now, we need to decide where
are we going to initialize this hidden word? Well, in future versions of the game,
we could have lots of different hidden words on subsequent plays, but for this version of the game, we're going to have a
single hidden word. So, I'm going to initialize it, up in the reset method,
but just before I do I'm going to fix this error here, which is
saying call of an object of a class type without blah blah. So, what's the problem with return?
I'm trying to return a function, I should just be returning BullCow
Count, so the brackets give it away. Let's remove the brackets, and then, that error disappears.
So, here we are and, of course, this hidden word is very much a magic
word, in the same was as 8 was a magic number. So, we're going to use const.
Now, we're going to try const expression, because it is known at compile time, and let's see if this
works. FString HIDDEN
_WORD. Constants all in capitals
like that, and I'm going to use "planet" this time. So, this is where we're going to go to adjust our
HIDDEN_WORD. Now, it's complaining, what's the problem? It says
the const expression variable must have a literal type
or a reference type. So, we're not using reference types and
pointers and references and stuff at the moment, and it's not a literal
like an integer, so we can't use const expression, it's too strong here. So when that
happens, drop back to the next strongest which is just const. OK, that's great!
So, we've got that! Then, we're just going to say MyHiddenWord
equals HIDDEN_WORD. And hopefully, by now,
you get that we're doing this to get into the good habit of declaring
magic numbers and magic words and strings as constants, so that
when there's a big load of code in between here, we don't get in trouble and we can easily
access what we need to change in a single place. OK, enough on that!
We have our HIDDEN_WORD setup! Let's compile our code, see if it works!
So, what we're going to do in the next video is look at the length of the hidden word. Oh, I've
spelled hidden wrong! Let's just fix that!
Fantastic! See you soon!