So welcome to this
video! We'll be using Struct to define simple types! Let me just show you. and then.
we'll dive in and get it done. We're going to make a thing here called
struct BullCowCount. and it's like a class but it's even simpler
and it's a simple structure that can contain two integers in one go.
so that we can write a method like this. BullCowCount SubmitGuess. taking in
a string and returning a pair of integers. So let's get it done!
OK guys. welcome back! So we're going to
to do something fun in this video. we're going to implement our actual BullCowCount
But before we can do that. we need to define a new data type.
because where we have said here. in the header. that we want to provide a method
for counting bulls and cows and increasing the try number. we need bulls and cows
to come back together in one go. And how are we going to organize
that? Well we're going to use something called a struct. Now. I must tell
you that a struct is exactly the same as a class. basically. except
for. by default. it's members are public. and that lends itself to being
ideal for simple data types like this. Let me show you! If we say
struct BullCowCount here... Now. I'm at the top of Bull
CowGame.h. because this is a structure that we're not going to use in main.cpp
but we are going to use inside our game logic. OK. now I'm
going to open up some brackets. like that.
and then. we're going to give it some members. Now. in terms of this bracket style.
you can see that IDE sometimes puts them on the wrong line. so I'm
going to go with this. It just spaces things out a little and adheres to Unreal's
standards. So it's actually very simple. we're going to have two integers in here. one
called bulls and we're going to initialize it immediately to 0. Best with
structs. keep it simple and don't worry about contractors and things.
So it's basically the same as saying class BullCowCount but we don't need to say public. because everything's
public by default. It's a bit convoluted to start making things private. why not use a
class. and we're not going to have any methods in here. Now. the only thing is
I want to use int32. so there's a new habit for you since we made the substitution.
So int32. a 32 bit integer for bulls and a 32 bit
integer for Cows. both initialized to 0.
That's it. BullCowCount! Very simple. it contains two integers! Once we've
done that. we can write the signature of our actual method here.
So I wan't overdo the comment yet. I'm going to make sure I get the signature right. So
we're going to be returning a BullCowCount. I'm going to
call it SubmitGuess() for now. pending a better name if we
find one. and we're going to take in an (FString). starting to get used to our new types for Unreal.
So I'm going to improve this comment.
"// provide a method for counting bulls & cows and increasing the try
#". That's fine. I'm just going to say "counts". just
to make it shorter "bulls & cows. and increases
try #". And I'm also
going to say that this method assumes or probably in the implementation.
I'm going to say it assumes... Why not here? "assuming valid
guess". so it assumes that a valid guess comes
into this method. Alright. so that's it. we have a Submit
Guess signature there. Let's go ahead and define submit guess!
So you go Quick Actions and then Create
Definition. and then. go over to the game .cpp file.
Fantastic news! OK. here we are! So before we do anything.
let's pseudocode this before we even start. So what are we going to do?
Well as soon as we get in here. we received a valid guess. Let's
outline what this does. So "// receives a
VALID
guess. increments...
OK. so it turns out I can't spell increments. but this is a post edit
here and I'm afraid we're stuck with it till the end of the section now. So apologies
and I know it should be an e in the middle there. ..."turn. and
returns count". OK.
slightly doubling up on our work here. so if you want to get rid of this
in the header file you can. to keep the header file tight and clean like that.
and we can focus on the comment being just here
in the implementation. By the way. back at the header file. when this says to "make
a more rich return value.". this is the sort of thing I'm
talking about. This is a richer return value than just a single integer. We'll be doing a similar thing
here but we'll actually be using an enumeration. OK. so we have a richer
return type. Let's see what this guy is going to do! It's going to "increment the turn number"! Don't do it
yet! OK. just
stay at this level. What else are we going to do? Well we're going to need to setup a return
structure. We're going to need to
"// setup a return variable". aren't we? We're going to need to declare ourselves an instance of this Bull
CowCount thing and stuff. Don't worry about how we do that yet! Then. we're going to "// loop through
all letters in the guess".
and then. for each letter we're
going to do some comparisons. So for each of those letters. I'm going to
indent to represent that. You can indent in pseudocode. I'm going to say "// compare
letters against
all" or "just against the hidden word".
OK. so we're going to increment the turn number. setup
something to return. loop through all letters in the guess. and then. compare
letters against the hidden word. one at a time. and then.
at the end we're going to return the BullCowCount. So that is the structure of our SubmitGuess. Now.
before I flesh it out I want to make sure it still runs. that all the
scaffolding code I've written is valid. It is. which is fantastic! Alright.
so now we're going to start actually implementing it! I'm going to help you a little bit. and then. I'm
going to ask you to mainly complete this loop. So far. firstly.
how do we increment the turn number? Well under the comment just go ahead and think that
it's MyCurrentTry. because that's the member variable. the data inside this class
this current instance of the game ++. That's another way of saying
MyCurrentTry = MyCurrentTry + 1.
but I won't bother writing that. ++ is a shortcut. So we increment the turn number. Fantastic!
Now. we need to setup a return variable! How are we going to do that? We say BullCowCount. because that's the type.
We give it a name. BullCowCount.
and that's it for now! OK. it's already going to have things initialized
to 0. If you want to be
good about this. you could say BullCowCount.Bulls =
0. And you are in this instance. as we're using a struct. allowed to access
the members. But actually there's not point. because if we look at how we've defined BullCowCount
it automatically initializes to 0. OK.
If you wanted to know that from where you were. we could put a comment here.
"// two integers. initialized
to zero". Or just say. "// All
values initialized to zero". If you make that comment ahead of
the struct. look what happens here when we say
BullCowCount and you hover over it.
It says "all values initialized to zero". so we can just call it BullCowCount!
Now. in terms of Unreal's naming standard I don't really like this. I don't
really like the fact that my line says BullCowCount BullCowCount.
If we were a lowercase standard. then we would say BullCowCount lowercase
bullCowCount but some people find that more confusing. You could also consider using
prefixes here. but we're just going to live with it! Again. I want you to read code
like the compiler does! The compiler's saying. the first thing I'm expecting here is a type. and then. I'm expecting.
after the type. the name of the variable. So we're just going to say BullCowCount BullCowCount.
Now. at this stage. we're going to need the hidden word.
Let's go back to our header and think what we're doing about the hidden word! We already have
a piece of data for it... No we don't even! We don't even have a data for the hidden word! So we need to make a piece of
data! Let's make it an FString. because it's inside here
and it's going to be something we may want to manipulate. FString =
MyHiddenWord.
So now. we have a place to store the HiddenWord!
Of course. I shouldn't have an equals. FString MyHiddenWord is just declaring it. Now.
we've added a new piece of data to this. now we need to decide where
are we going to initialize this HiddenWord? Well in future versions of the game.
we can have lots of different HiddenWords on subsequent plays. but for this version of the game. we're going to have a
single HiddenWord. So I'm going to initialize it up in the Reset() method.
but just before I do. I'm going to fix this error here which is saying "call
of an object of a class type without" blah blah. So what's the problem with return? I'm trying to
return a function. I should just be returning BullCowCount.
So the brackets give it away. let's remove the brackets. and then. that
error disappears! So here we are. and. of course. this Hidden
Word is very much a magic word. in the same way as 8 was a magic number. So
we're going to use const! Now. we're going to try const expressions. because
it is known at compile time. And let's see if this works! FString
HIDDEN WORD.
Constants all in capitals. like that. and I'm going to use "planet" this time.
So this is where we're going to go to adjust our HiddenWord. Now. it's complaining! What's the
problem? It says the const expression
"variable must have a literal type or a reference
type". So we're not using reference types and pointers and references and stuff. at the moment.
and it's not a literal like a integer. So we can't use const
expressions. it's too strong here. So when that happens. drop back to the next strongest.
which is just const. OK. that's great! So we've got that. then
we're just going to say MyHiddenWord = HIDDEN_WORD.
And hopefully. by now. you get that we're doing this to get into the good
habit of declaring magic numbers and magic words and strings
as constants. so that when there's a big load of code in between here
we don't get in trouble and we can easily access what we need to change in a single place.
OK. enough on that. We have our HIDDEN_WORD setup! Let's compile our codes.
see if it works! So what we're going to do in the next video is look at the
length of the HIDDEN_WORD. Oh. I've spelled HIDEN wrong! Let's just fix that!
Fantastic! See you soon!
...
=======
So welcome to this
video! We'll be using Struct to define simple types! Let me just show you, and then,
we'll dive in and get it done. We're going to make a thing here called
struct BullCowCount, and it's like a class but it's even simpler
and it's a simple structure that can contain two integers in one go,
so that we can write a method like this, BullCowCount SubmitGuess, taking in
a string and returning a pair of integers. So let's get it done!
OK guys, welcome back! So we're going to
to do something fun in this video, we're going to implement our actual BullCowCount
But before we can do that, we need to define a new data type,
because where we have said here, in the header, that we want to provide a method
for counting bulls and cows and increasing the try number, we need bulls and cows
to come back together in one go. And how are we going to organize
that? Well we're going to use something called a struct. Now, I must tell
you that a struct is exactly the same as a class, basically, except
for, by default, it's members are public, and that lends itself to being
ideal for simple data types like this. Let me show you! If we say
struct BullCowCount here... Now, I'm at the top of Bull
CowGame.h, because this is a structure that we're not going to use in main.cpp
but we are going to use inside our game logic. OK, now I'm
going to open up some brackets, like that,
and then, we're going to give it some members. Now, in terms of this bracket style,
you can see that IDE sometimes puts them on the wrong line, so I'm
going to go with this. It just spaces things out a little and adheres to Unreal's
standards. So it's actually very simple, we're going to have two integers in here, one
called bulls and we're going to initialize it immediately to 0. Best with
structs, keep it simple and don't worry about contractors and things.
So it's basically the same as saying class BullCowCount but we don't need to say public, because everything's
public by default. It's a bit convoluted to start making things private, why not use a
class, and we're not going to have any methods in here. Now, the only thing is
I want to use int32, so there's a new habit for you since we made the substitution.
So int32, a 32 bit integer for bulls and a 32 bit
integer for Cows, both initialized to 0.
That's it, BullCowCount! Very simple, it contains two integers! Once we've
done that, we can write the signature of our actual method here.
So I wan't overdo the comment yet, I'm going to make sure I get the signature right. So
we're going to be returning a BullCowCount. I'm going to
call it SubmitGuess() for now, pending a better name if we
find one, and we're going to take in an (FString), starting to get used to our new types for Unreal.
So I'm going to improve this comment,
"// provide a method for counting bulls & cows and increasing the try
#". That's fine, I'm just going to say "counts", just
to make it shorter "bulls & cows, and increases
try #". And I'm also
going to say that this method assumes or probably in the implementation,
I'm going to say it assumes... Why not here? "assuming valid
guess", so it assumes that a valid guess comes
into this method. Alright, so that's it, we have a Submit
Guess signature there. Let's go ahead and define submit guess!
So you go Quick Actions and then Create
Definition, and then, go over to the game .cpp file.
Fantastic news! OK, here we are! So before we do anything,
let's pseudocode this before we even start. So what are we going to do?
Well as soon as we get in here, we received a valid guess. Let's
outline what this does. So "// receives a
VALID
guess, increments...
OK, so it turns out I can't spell increments, but this is a post edit
here and I'm afraid we're stuck with it till the end of the section now. So apologies
and I know it should be an e in the middle there. ..."turn, and
returns count". OK,
slightly doubling up on our work here, so if you want to get rid of this
in the header file you can, to keep the header file tight and clean like that,
and we can focus on the comment being just here
in the implementation. By the way, back at the header file, when this says to "make
a more rich return value.", this is the sort of thing I'm
talking about. This is a richer return value than just a single integer. We'll be doing a similar thing
here but we'll actually be using an enumeration. OK, so we have a richer
return type. Let's see what this guy is going to do! It's going to "increment the turn number"! Don't do it
yet! OK, just
stay at this level. What else are we going to do? Well we're going to need to setup a return
structure. We're going to need to
"// setup a return variable", aren't we? We're going to need to declare ourselves an instance of this Bull
CowCount thing and stuff. Don't worry about how we do that yet! Then, we're going to "// loop through
all letters in the guess",
and then, for each letter we're
going to do some comparisons. So for each of those letters, I'm going to
indent to represent that. You can indent in pseudocode. I'm going to say "// compare
letters against
all" or "just against the hidden word".
OK, so we're going to increment the turn number, setup
something to return, loop through all letters in the guess, and then, compare
letters against the hidden word, one at a time, and then,
at the end we're going to return the BullCowCount. So that is the structure of our SubmitGuess. Now,
before I flesh it out I want to make sure it still runs, that all the
scaffolding code I've written is valid. It is, which is fantastic! Alright,
so now we're going to start actually implementing it! I'm going to help you a little bit, and then, I'm
going to ask you to mainly complete this loop. So far, firstly,
how do we increment the turn number? Well under the comment just go ahead and think that
it's MyCurrentTry, because that's the member variable, the data inside this class
this current instance of the game ++. That's another way of saying
MyCurrentTry = MyCurrentTry + 1,
but I won't bother writing that, ++ is a shortcut. So we increment the turn number. Fantastic!
Now, we need to setup a return variable! How are we going to do that? We say BullCowCount, because that's the type.
We give it a name, BullCowCount,
and that's it for now! OK, it's already going to have things initialized
to 0. If you want to be
good about this, you could say BullCowCount.Bulls =
0. And you are in this instance, as we're using a struct, allowed to access
the members. But actually there's not point, because if we look at how we've defined BullCowCount
it automatically initializes to 0. OK.
If you wanted to know that from where you were, we could put a comment here.
"// two integers, initialized
to zero". Or just say, "// All
values initialized to zero". If you make that comment ahead of
the struct, look what happens here when we say
BullCowCount and you hover over it.
It says "all values initialized to zero", so we can just call it BullCowCount!
Now, in terms of Unreal's naming standard I don't really like this. I don't
really like the fact that my line says BullCowCount BullCowCount.
If we were a lowercase standard, then we would say BullCowCount lowercase
bullCowCount but some people find that more confusing. You could also consider using
prefixes here, but we're just going to live with it! Again, I want you to read code
like the compiler does! The compiler's saying, the first thing I'm expecting here is a type, and then, I'm expecting,
after the type, the name of the variable. So we're just going to say BullCowCount BullCowCount.
Now, at this stage, we're going to need the hidden word.
Let's go back to our header and think what we're doing about the hidden word! We already have
a piece of data for it... No we don't even! We don't even have a data for the hidden word! So we need to make a piece of
data! Let's make it an FString, because it's inside here
and it's going to be something we may want to manipulate. FString =
MyHiddenWord.
So now, we have a place to store the HiddenWord!
Of course, I shouldn't have an equals, FString MyHiddenWord is just declaring it. Now,
we've added a new piece of data to this, now we need to decide where
are we going to initialize this HiddenWord? Well in future versions of the game,
we can have lots of different HiddenWords on subsequent plays, but for this version of the game, we're going to have a
single HiddenWord. So I'm going to initialize it up in the Reset() method,
but just before I do, I'm going to fix this error here which is saying "call
of an object of a class type without" blah blah. So what's the problem with return? I'm trying to
return a function, I should just be returning BullCowCount.
So the brackets give it away, let's remove the brackets, and then, that
error disappears! So here we are, and, of course, this Hidden
Word is very much a magic word, in the same way as 8 was a magic number. So
we're going to use const! Now, we're going to try const expressions, because
it is known at compile time. And let's see if this works! FString
HIDDEN WORD.
Constants all in capitals, like that, and I'm going to use "planet" this time.
So this is where we're going to go to adjust our HiddenWord. Now, it's complaining! What's the
problem? It says the const expression
"variable must have a literal type or a reference
type". So we're not using reference types and pointers and references and stuff, at the moment,
and it's not a literal like a integer. So we can't use const
expressions, it's too strong here. So when that happens, drop back to the next strongest,
which is just const. OK, that's great! So we've got that, then
we're just going to say MyHiddenWord = HIDDEN_WORD.
And hopefully, by now, you get that we're doing this to get into the good
habit of declaring magic numbers and magic words and strings
as constants, so that when there's a big load of code in between here
we don't get in trouble and we can easily access what we need to change in a single place.
OK, enough on that. We have our HIDDEN_WORD setup! Let's compile our codes,
see if it works! So what we're going to do in the next video is look at the
length of the HIDDEN_WORD. Oh, I've spelled HIDEN wrong! Let's just fix that!
Fantastic! See you soon!
...
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1