So, Using if Statements in C++!
We'll talk about why we need conditionals for selection. We'll tell you when to use
if verses switch, basically use if when it reads better, and then, we'll show you
the syntax and we will write the bulls and cows calculating thing a ma
jig. So, let's dive in and make it work!
So, I'm pretty excited right now, because we're about to make our code actually do something useful.
Before we carry on, thank you to those people who pointed out that, according to the Unreal coding
standards I really should have called this BullCowCount struct FBullCow
Count, naming structs just like classes. So, I'm going to go ahead and fix that now,
by highlighting, clicking Control R for refactor twice,
and then, putting an F prefix in front. That also helps
us right here, when we see FBullCowCount
BullCowCount, it should be. So of course, the actual name of the variable shouldn't
change, so that was a slightly overzealous Find and Replace. OK, let
me recompile to prove that, that works, and
fantastic! Alright, so now we need to make this algorithm actually work, so before
we dive into the algorithm let's go a little bit further and introduce you to an if
statement. That's because you're going to need that in the algorithm, and then, we will write the algorithm in pseudocode
and then actually make it happen. So, this is an if statement. It basically says if
condition one, here in brackets, then execute a bunch of statements.
Optionally. Whoops, excuse me! Optionally we have an else if,
with another condition and some statements. And optionally, although I suggest you always put it
in, you have an else and some statements. If nothing else... Excuse the pun! [Laughs]
You should be putting else in, so that this condition here that you
think never should happen, well that's the point you want to alert the
developer that we should have never got here. Alright, so basically you're going to
be using if and else and sometimes else if. Now, I should say
that if you get to more than a handful of statements like this, then we want to be going to something called
a switch statement, which we'll see later. Basically, use if statements when the conditions
are slightly more complex than a switch statement, i.e. we may have different logic
in condition one and condition two, rather than just a value like,
you know, if it's one do this, if it's two do that, if it's three do the other. That seems like
a switch statement, but if statements, you know, if some logic then do something and if
some other logic do something else. That's setup for an if. So,
we're going to look through all letters in the guess, and then, we're going to compare against letters in the hidden word.
Then, if they match, then
we're going to say "increment
bulls if they're in the same place"
and "increment cows
if they're not".
OK, so let's make sure we're clear on that! We go through each letter of the word. So, let's
just write out the word ant, for example, and then, let's imagine that we've
guessed the word and. What do we do? We start with a here,
and we go through a. Ooh, they're the same, so that's a hit! And then, we compare that a
to an n, looking for cows and there's no match. No match! OK, then
we move on to the n and we compare it to the a. No match! Now, there's a
match and it's in the same place, so that's a bull! And then, the n to the d.
No match OK! And then, you do the same with a t. So, that the algorithm it's going through, pretty simple!
And now what we need to do is actually start writing the loops and the if statements!
Now, this is four levels of indentation. 1, 2, 3,
and then, the code that'll actually be inside here is the
fourth. You could actually say, if they're in the same place,
"increment bulls". And this would be pseudo code that's even closer to the actual code.
Can I spell increment? I think that's OK. And if not, or we could say
"else increment cows".
Now, be careful of writing code in comments, though,
OK. So, stay away from code. This is OK here,
just about, because it's still kind of English. So, make sure the algorithm works in
words like this, and then, we go through and start fleshing it out.
Now, let me do the first couple of bits of the... I'll do the outer loop for you,
and then, I'll ask you to do the rest, OK, because I want to give you a couple of tips.
For int32 is the name of the iterator. Now, you
may be tempted or you may have seen i. We're going to use i here,
and I'm going to change it later and I'm going to allow us to create a bug, so bear with me. You'll see
i and j a lot, so I want to use it so you're exposed to it. So, for i
starting at 0 let's go up to
but not including the length of the hidden word.
Now, we don't have the length of the hidden word, at the moment. So,
right here right above the loop, we need the things that we need to
support the loop, So, we have an int32 HiddenWord
Length equals
MyHiddenWord. Now, it's a string, so when you hit dot
and access its functions, you'll find that you have a length
option. It's a method, so you need to call it with braces. So, we're putting
the result of looking at the hidden word's length into this variable. OK.
So now, we can say we want to go up to the hidden word length, but not
including it. Now, that's because when we're going to use
this i, we're going to access the inside of a string and they start counting at
0, remember? So, this will go from 0 to one less than
the hidden word length, which is exactly what we want. We'll see that in a minute. Then, I'm going to put my ++,
which means increment i, and then, I'm going to put my braces, OK. Although I'm
going to put that second brace down at the bottom here, in the right place to
start with. I'm doing this very slowly for now, as it's our first time with an if statement.
It's only our second time with a for statement. So, there's our for loop, it's going to go around this!
It's looping through all letters in the guess. Now what we want to do is compare
that to the letters in the hidden word, so we're going to need another for statement.
And what's quite common is that people start doing stuff
like this. For j equals 0, because they use the next letter up.
J is less than hidden word length, because we're going to compare all the letters to all
the other letters, j++. Now, by the way, you might see ++
j and that works fine as well! There's a little bit of argument as to whether there's any performance difference.
Frankly, at this stage, we don't care whether we increment before or after, because we're not
returning the value, alright. So, we don't want to worry about that optimization
performance now at all. You'll also see sometimes rather than less than, you might say not
equal to, and you might see that, that is an optimization. But again, let's not
worry about optimization right now. Let's worry about getting the code running. If later, when
we do performance profiling, we find out there's a problem with the speed, we will fix it then.
You'll also notice I've used HiddenWordLength twice here. You might be asking why am I
using guess length or maybe just WORD_LENGTH to
illustrate the fact that the length of both the guess and the hidden word must be the same for
this whole algorithm to make sense? Well, we're going to create a bug, and we're going to be dealing with
it a little bit later on. You've got to learn debugging somehow!
OK, so before handing it over to you to complete this pseudo code, I want to check a couple of things.
Firstly, let's check our brackets match. I'm getting an error here, so the problem
is, if we click on this bracket you'll see that's its matching bracket. Therefore, this guy
here, if we scroll up, is matching the start of the definition of the function,
which is why it thinks the function is finished there, so let's just sort that bracket out there.
And then, we have some outdenting to do,
so that hopefully now it's clear that, that goes with that! When you click on this one it goes with that!
Alright, so that gets the flow of that. Right now also, we have to, in main.cpp,
actually output some of this stuff. So, I back in main.cpp
under PlayGame(),
we're going to submit a valid guess to the game alright, so we can actually do that.
Now, we can say BCGame.SubmitGuess
and we send the (Guess) in as a string.
Great! Now, we want to capture what comes back from that. So, what is it that comes back from that? Well, it's
an FBullCowCount. Remember we've changed the type to have a prefix F.
Just call it BullCowCount. Why not just call a thing a thing?
Alright, so then we get it back, that's fantastic! So, we "submit valid guess to the game",
"and receive counts".
And then, we print the number of bulls and cows. So, I'm going to
get rid of this, you're guess was, because it's quite useless, and we can actually say,
cout. And then, we're going to go, now
we need standard on the cout, of course.
Then, we're going to go Bulls equals
and then output BullCowCount. Now, the way we access
the member is, .Bulls. I'm going to go onto another line,
just to keep things simple to read in the code but without putting a new line on the end there.
Put a space and then cows equals,
and then, put the cows on. And then, I will
now put an end line. Remember, we need the standard.
Fantastic! There we go! Let's just run the code,
and make sure that it's going to run apart from... There you go, it's going to say bulls and cows equals
0, but your job is going to be to finish that! So, let's put you into the
challenge! This is the code I want you
to write, and what I want you to do is
finish SubmitGuess() and test, finish the function, test it works, and celebrate your coding ninja skills!
Go ahead! Have a go at that challenge, on your own now, and I'll see you in a minute!
...
So, welcome back! Let's get this working! So, what do we mean by if they match?
Well, we want to say something like... And I'm going to put all my braces in, and there are better ways
matching braces, by the way. Just for now, for the beginners, I want to get
into manually do it. There's plenty of ways of making blocks into braces simpler,
we're going to do that now! So, we're going to say, if the (Guess
at position [ i ]
...
equals, remember equals equals, the hidden word,
or in my case MyHiddenWord at position[ i ]).
Then, we're going to go and
start to do some more conditionals. So, why is guess
unidentified? Because when we wrote this declaration,
sorry this definition from the declaration, we never actually said what the variable name for
FGuess was going to be, so I'm going to call it Guess, very simply. Now, we have a handle to refer to
that thing. There it is! Now, there is a deliberate error on this line, but don't deliberate on it
too long. It may be fun if you write exactly what I've written, and then, we will use the debugger
in the next video to fix it, that's part of the point. OK, so if they're in the same place,
the way you say that is if (i -- j), if the indices are the same.
Then, we do something. What do we do? We just say
increment the bulls, so BullCowCount
dot Bulls
++; simple, worth incrementing.
And then, we're going to say... And I can put that comment on the end, by the way, leave the comments with
the code. And then, else... No point in deleting the comments, you see, you may as well leave them there. The proper
scaffolding that stays in there. They're like the stitches those dissolve. I can get rid of that.
I can get rid of that. Or don't dissolve, in this case, and just stay in place. [Laughs]
So then, what we're going to of if,
otherwise then the characters have matched... One second,
I've got an insert problem. The characters have
matched, and then, what we're doing is we're saying well they've matched and they're not in the same place,
therefore it must be a cow. OK,
I'll say that! So, if they're in the
same place, increment the bulls, we could even qualify here.
No this is the if they're in the same place. Let's take that, pop it on the end there,
and then, it reads quite well. Now, this is as complex as you're ever
going to get in any of your coding. That's a bold statement, but I don't want you ever indenting
more than four levels like this. This is as much as you're ever going to need to hold
in your mind. I'm showing this more as an exercise. Let's just try this.
Actually, let's start with a short word, I'm going to change my word from planet, to say ant.
And let's just try it!
I think I've gone back onto Overwrite? I have, look down on the bottom, Overwrite!
If you're having that problem remember to hit Insert. OK, let's try!
So, if I put and, what do I get? Two bulls, which is correct, the a and the d, and four
cows. That's wrong! If I put ant I get three bulls and six cows. Great! Perfect
setup, we have a bug. So, what we're going to do in the next video is find
and squash that bug, using the debugger. See you soon!