...
So, welcome to a place for everything! In this video, we are going to
implement this GetHiddenWordLength() method, so that when we actually
change our HIDDEN_WORD length, up here in the Reset(), then when we run the
game the WORD_LENGTH updates. It's a simple thing but it has a useful moral
in it about storing data! So let's crack on!
OK, so just before we start playing around with the HIDDEN_WORD length,
let's talk about a place for everything, one of my favorite expressions that I don't quite live up
to, which is that you should have a place for everything, everything
in its place. I wish my house was like that, but that's the theory. It's a good idea in
programming in general. So, basically I'm saying think carefully about
what data you store. This is a general issue of bandwidth
vs. storage or another example would be CPU vs. RAM.
Or typically on a machine, you're talking about access to
data, data locality, these types of things. So
for example, a concrete example is storing a birthday
vs. storing your age. You would want to
think carefully before, in a database or in a computer system, storing someone's age when it's so quick
and easy to calculate their current age from their birthday.
And even if you wanted to say, well I want another age at a particular date, well why not just store
that date, the date they signed up for the policy. The date they did this, you get the idea. That's
a very simple example. So basically, until proven otherwise, don't store
results. It tends to make your code harder to read, adding data. So,
for this WORD_LENGTH, this hidden WORD_LENGTH, we're not going to create a new member variable, a new
integer for the hidden WORD_LENGTH. We;re just going to calculate it as we go. You can read more around this in
a fantastic but slightly more advanced than we need book, "Game Programming
Patterns". Now, the whole book is available for free at www.gameprogrammingpatterns.com.
Data locality is one of the topics that touches on this. And
if you like the book, buy the physical copy and read it through, and then, maybe read it again
and again and again, until eventually we understand it all. So that's the idea, So, let's dive in
and make GetHiddenWordLength() available. Over in our main() method, we
currently have a hard coded  hidden WORD_LENGTH. Let's look at the game running! You see it says "9
letter isogram", but we don't want 9 letter isogram, do we? We want the number of
letters to depend on the currently set word.
So, we're going to get rid of this constant in here
and make a call to a new method, that we don't have yet, called
GetHiddenWordLength(), so let's write the signature for that! int32 using
the new Unreal syntax.
GetHiddenWordLength() is going to be constant, of course, because getting the hidden
word length, we wouldn't want to check anything. Oh, and by the way, while we're here thinking about
constants, CheckGuessValidity() is also pretty much
a getter isn't it? It's just going to get a status, some sort of status back later.
So, while we're here, we might as well think that should be constant, and if it should be
constant, I quite fancy moving it up along with all of the other constant getters.
It's not quite a getter, because it's going to return something a little richer but it's
close. We haven't, of course, implemented that method yet. Anyway, back to GetHidden
WordLength(). That's a constant method that just reads back the hidden word length.
So, let's go and implement it! But I'm not that kind, I'm not going to
implement it for you, I'm going to let you implement it. Just don't create a new private member, we don't need
it, of course. You can just calculate the hidden word length by using the dot length method.
So that's your challenge, basically!
It is to replace WORD_LENGTH completely, in that main() method,
in that main.cpp file. What we want to do is write Get
HiddenWordLength() getter. Just finish writing the declaration, define the declaration I've just written.
Make it read from the current WORD_LENGTH, don't create another member variable,
replcae WORD_LENGTH in the PrintIntro method, and test it with different
hidden word length. And make sure that is says, in the intro, the correct length
of the word. OK, go ahead! Pause the video and make this slightly different type of getter that,
rather than just reading from a member variable, it actually does a quick calculation
for you.
OK, welcome back! So, we've got GetHiddenWordLength() here. I
am going to put a space in, because these are all the guys that start with the word get.
That conceptually just says, look here are my getters right, and then, these are some other constant methods and
these are some methods that do stuff. Alright, let's go ahead and quick
actions, create a definition and look at our .cpp file.
So, what's it going to do? It's not going to return, you know, int32.
That doesn't even really make sense! What it's going to do is return
MyHiddenWord.Length(), which is a method.
OK. And because it's a getter and because
the logic of that getter is very short, it's on a single line, I'm going to go back to this
single line syntax! That's it! It's as simple as that! Now, we need to
call it OK. So, oh by the way,
just before we leave this, if you're concerned about resetting the game,
and saying well is this going to work, when we reset the game? Well, it will because it's always going to read from
the current HIDDEN_WORD. So, whenever we change the Hidden_WORD, this is the
last minute, when you call this method. It's going to look at the current HIDDEN_WORD and say, how
long it is. That's fine! That's late binding, that's answering the question,
as late as possible. I like it! One thing I'd like to do, just down here, is quickly rearrange
these constants. I'd like to get my constants together,
like so, and then, I'd like to do my actual resets like that. It's just being finickity. [Laughs]
OK, it's really not that important. OK, let's dive over
to the actual main.cpp, down in PlayGame(), and let's
ditch this WORD_LENGTH here altogether. And what we can actually do is
just, straight away, call the BCGame instance. Dot
GetHiddenWordLength(), which is a new method, and let's test it works!
No it doesn't.
What's wrong? Now, this is the type of error you may end up with! "Check
GuessValidity", "member function is not found". OK.
So, it's saying that it's not happy with CheckGuessValidity(). That's because I,
in my header file, while I was messing around decided to add const on the end, but I didn't
add const over here, in the declaration. So, that's absolutely fine!
You just have to add const there, so that the two headers match. Now, three letter isogram.
It works! Now, let's go back to our Reset() method, change it to
donkey, because I like the word donkey, and we should get five. We get six, d o
n k e y. Yep, that's fine! I can't count! Let's try one of the
extremes, which is a blank string, it should get 0. Can you guess the 0? That's an isogram I'm thinking
of! Well, is it nothing? I think it is. How about a long word, like pneumono-
ultramicrosopic...? p n e u m o
n o. No, let's not spell it all out. Well, anyway you get the idea! If you put a long word in,
then I'm hoping it will also get the string length back. I don't think we need to worry about
the limits of this string length, because there aren't any isograms that are so long
that they're going to break this. OK, so I'm going to reset this to say planet.
And we are pretty much there! That's good!
So, the moral of this one is, strive for a place for everything, and everything in its
place, and only store data when you really need to, when performance profiling
later tells you that that's necessary. So congratulations, and we'll see you
in the next video!