So, welcome
to Introducing enum erations! Enumerations,
that's it! So, I'm going to be explaining what an enumerated type
is, how we can use it to encode meaning, how
it makes our code more meaningful and readable, and also introduce
C++'s enum class thingy, which is pretty cool!
And at the end of it, we will be able to do something like this, instead of
CheckGuessValidity returning a boolean, which doesn't mean a lot, and having some
horrible TODO that we should be returning a richer value, it'll return thsi thing called OK
or whatever. Cool, so let's dive in and make it happen!
So, welcome welcome and welcome! If we look in our View and
Task List. It's here somewhere. There you go!
Then, have a look at some of these TODO's! One of these here says, CheckGuess
Validity, "TODO make a more rich return value."
And if we look here, the reset, we also want to make a more
rich return value. We don't know how to do that. And then, in our main loop there is,
we want to be validating tries. And also here, we want to be
checking that we got a valid guess. All sorts of stuff, we can't even really
summarize the game until we've got the game working. So, a lot of what we need to do right now,
a lot of our TODO's, a lot of what's wrong with the game if we play it is
based on the fact that if we say, put three letters in... Ahhhh,
the whole thing falls over! So, we need to start checking our input!
And once we start checking our input, we need a good way of getting back from
that check, some information about the check. So, here we've got a method
called CheckGuessValidity, and at the moment it says bool, which
presumably means if we return true then it's valid, and if we return false
it's not. And we don't know why it's not valid, and it's just trying to wrap up
too much information into a single bool, yes or no. It's making people
presume that false means it's not valid yada yada, and also it gives them
no information about what was wrong. So, we are going to make a more rich return value. I'm going to delete the
TODO boldly. And in order to do that, I'm going to introduce you to this enum
thing. So, we're going to define that somewhere at the top of our header file, because we want it
to be available, not in the main... Well, it will be available in the main, by the fact
that we have #included our BullCowGame class.
But we want it to be available in the class mainly.
This is a feature of the class, it belongs with the class, you'll see why in a second.
Let's just define it. So, we write something called an enum. Now, I'm going to just enum for the moment,
not enum class, and we're going to call it E, because Unreal's coding standard
suggests that you should start enums with E. And we're going to call it Words
Status, for example. OK, so we're defining an enum
called WordStatus. Now, let's give ourselves some squigglies. And I'm going to bring them
down a bit, just spread it out. Great! So, what's a status that comes back
from checking the guess. Well, OK is a meaningful status that could come back! Here's
another one, Not_Isogram.
That would tell us that the reason this is not good is because it's not an isogram. Now, I'm going to let you
finish this list, in a moment. But for now, I want to talk to you about the difference between an enum and a class,
but before we do that, let's just go and access this enum so we can
see it in context. So, I've printed this thing! What on earth is it? It's just a value
list. It's a way of preventing me from saying OK equals
1 and Not_Isogram equals 2, and making some horrible
coded thing there, where we've got to go and look up a table. No no no, don't do that!
Just use the words, and an enum allows you to use and access the words.
So, let's see how it allows us to access the words. Over in our implementation
of CheckGuessValidity, instead of returning a bool now, we're
going to be returning an E. We're going to remember that it was an enum, and then, it was going to
be... Was it WordStatus, I think we called it? Yeah, E
WordStatus! So, we'll be returning an enum called Word
Status. Now, it's not going to like that if we just do it in the .cpp
file, without also updating the header
to say that, that's what we're do?ing. So here, CheckGuessValidity returns an
EWordStatus. Now, there is a way to change the two of these, at the same time, but we'll use
those tools later. Great! So now, of course, we can't return false
right, because it's going to complain that the return type does not
match the function type. Well, that's good! it's saying
want a status back out of this, we're trying to return false. So, how do we get to that status? Well,
you start with the word of the enum. E makes you remember, oh it's an enum so we're going to start with E.
EWordStatus, there it is! And there's a little symbol that explains that it's an enum.
EWordStatus, now once you've done EWordStatus, we need to access it's members,
and the general way of accessing members is like this. FBullCow
Game's class, if we want to access the definition for CheckGuessValidity
we use colon colon. We do the same with the enum, colon colon and look, it gives us a
list. We're not going 1, 2, 3, some random coding looking it up! It's right here!
Let's just assume it's OK. So, later "TODO
make actual error". OK, so that's how you
access it! EWordStatus::OK; Now, before I put you in the challenge, let me just
give you a word of warning, about these enums. They're scope, i.e. where
they are visible to. We have a bit of a problem, just doing it like this,
this is older C++ syntax, because look what happens. If I come along, at some other
point, and decide that I want another enum. In fact, we do have an instance where we're going to
want another enum, that's going to be here when we reset, alright.
So, let's call it, imagine now, EReset
Status, alright, and I'm actually going to remove this
code and put it back in later, but I just want to show you something. If I later come and try and define
EResetStatus, and we could say, I don't
know No_Hidden_Word_Of_That_Length or something.
That could be an error. But we may then come along and say, we want
OK! Perfectly valid to say I want OK, but look, we're going to get a compiler problem here. It's going to say,
when we try and compile, " 'OK' : redefinition;". What do you mean I'm redefining it?
Here I'm calling an enum called EWordStatus. This is
for getting values back from checking my word, and this one, I want to get values back from my reset
method. I can't use OK, so OK is kind of what we call global
scope, at this point. It is available to both of these enums, and it won't let us even compile.
Wow, that's horrible! I want to be able to use OK! I don't want to have to prefix these things! Now,
let me just explain that. I don't want to have to prefix it with
like some other thing in front of here. I don't care what it is. Reset_OK, it's nasty!
OK is simple! So, what Unreal suggests, in their coding standards, let
me bring up their coding standards. "unreal coding
standards", and if we go down to enumarations,
they are suggesting we do... Where is it?
You're seeing it before me. I'm going to search for it, Enum. There you go, Strongly-
Typed Enums, and they're going to say, well you know,
because of this problem we're going to put enums in their own namespace. Well, that's a bit beyond the scope of
what we're doing, right now. And we also don't need to put them in their own namespace. With
C++ 11 to the rescue, we can do something called an enum
class. Watch what happens when I do that! This is now what we call a strongly
typed Enum. OK, forget the error, the
previous version. It may moan at you that you've just changed the definition, but look, if I just
put enum class and recompile anyway, obstinately, it's going to
compile and it doesn't mind, because this guy now, this enum, has
scope basically. And it's saying well, these values only mean anything
inside this enum. So, if I was over here, in my
code, and I was trying to access something else here like
EResetStatus::, I can still have OK
and No_Hidden_Word. I can repeat myself, and we have no conflict! OK,
so they're better because they're a smaller scope, and we don't create these global scope issues! Great!
So, what I want you to do now is, I'm going to delete this reset status, because I
just was using it for an example. I just want you to fill in a couple more error values down here.
Well, you think about what other things could go wrong or actually run the game,
and try some strange things like, think about what might happen with upper case or think what may happen if your
input is too short, etc. And put some meaningful value
labels in here, they're just labels for you to use. So, here's your challenge! Finish the Error Value List,
write at least two more error values, think about what could break the game,
or try using weird input and see what does break the game.
Go ahead, pause the video, and let's do that challenge now!
Okie dokie dokie! So, welcome back! Let's
just think another, too. Well, one here is wrong length, because if I put say two
or three letter in, I get this horrible error.
And normally I wouldn't dismiss such a serious error, so quickly and out of hand,
however, we know this is being caused by the fact that we have a
mismatch between our hidden word and our guess. And what we're going to be
doing in the next video is, creating error checking code to prevent that from ever happening.
...
So, what should we call an error that is wrong word length?
How about Wrong_Length. Why not word?
Because word is already in the status. So, EWordStatus::Wrong_Length
simple, simple. How about, it's not lower case. What shall we call
that? Well, let's be cryptic, not lower case! The whole point is to not
be cryptic. This is not error code 403, this is not lower case!
Alright, English is what we want! It's simple and clear! So, that
is our enum class, really nice there! What we're going to do in the next video is
start, of course, to flesh out this CheckGuessValidity() method, with a load of conditionals,
and then, that's going to check a bunch of things and return an appropriate error or OK
as necessary. And that means that over in our main, we'll be able to read
the error codes, and then, separately decide how we report those
error codes. In this game, we're talking to the user in the Console about the errors, but in
a future version of the game, we may use color or sound or lights or something else And we can just swap
that out on the interface level, on the view level, without worrying about
the class where it says we're getting meaningful error messages back. I hope that makes sense.
pretty cool stuff, and I shall see you on the other side!
The other side of what? I guess it's the other side of the gap between the videos! Any way, see you!