So.
we're going to be writing our first error checking code! I do warn you. by the way. in real code
quite a lot of it can end up being error checking code. Some estimates have been up to over
75%. so it's quite normal that there are quite a lot of lines
of code to do with error checking. We can't trust them. they're users to be putting sensible
input in. So. by the end of the video. we will have a situation
like this. where if we put in a word that's too short like "plan". when we're looking
for six letters. then our debugger is going to notice that our
status is coming back as wrong length. and it will catch that just
before the whole thing crashes. So. let's dive in and see how to catch this error!
Welcome back! Let's get this CheckGuessValidity() method actually
working! Because I'm focusing on it. I'm just going to give myself a little more space. so I can see it
there! Delete what's in there for now. Let's start pseudo-coding what its going to do.
So. we're going to say that "// if the guess
isn't an isogram. then
return an error". And we've got the error status
ready. "// if the guess isn't all
lowercase. return an error".
Now. you could start to just.
you know. use indentation here. That's slightly better than comma return
error. So. you can indent your pseudocode. that's
fine. and then. we could just say "if the
guess length is wrong"
then "// return an error". And then. we're just
going to say else. "// otherwise... Let's just use otherwise. just to get away from the
habit of kind of writing code in pseudocode. "// otherwise"
"// return OK". That's the structure! That is it!
It's as simple as that! So. let's start coding this up!
We're going to need a couple of supporting methods. by the way. which we don't have and we'll do in a
separate video. We don't have methods for isogram and lowercase.
but for now. to get this code working. let's just say if (false).
So. this condition will never happen. The fact that it isn't
a isogram isn't going to happen. for now. So. if false. then we can
come here and go squiggle. What do we do? Well. we return an error! How do we do
that? Well. we go BC...
We go return. rather sorry. return. It's an enumeration
and it's now called... What do we call it? EWordStatus.
I'm actually a bit uncomfortable with EWordStatus. I would rather it was GuessStatus. I'll change that
in a second. But if the guess isn't an isogram. return not isogram.
and that's the general pattern there. OK. now we don't
need "// return an error" as a comment. I don't think that's particularly useful. So.
EWordStatus. I just want to rename it! Highlight. Control. R. Control. R. and let's go
to EGuessStatus. I just feel more comfortable. So. if you think you're going to feel more comfortable with
a different name. try it on. OK. so now what do we do? Now we do.
for the first time. and else if! And the condition is. we're going to say the
condition is false. i.e. we're not going to detect the error now. til we have written the method.
But we're going to say. if the guess isn't all lowercase.
what are we going to do? And then. well. we're going
to return some enumeration.
It's called EGuessStatus. a bit easier to find now. and then. we're going to use
colon colon because we're accessing a member. like this is accessing a member here. And a
member. Not_Lowercase. alright. So. that's your else if! Now. don't
worry. I'm going to leave some of this to you. In fact. you're going to do the next else if condition.
The next else if condition is going to be false. for now. but
you're going to change it into actual logic in a second. For the if the guess
length is wrong. OK. Then. you'd return another error. and I'll
leave you to even return the error.
And that's going to go there!
And then. we're going to have one more thing. which is the else that catches the
final case. which is that we then go ahead and just
return EGuessStatus::OK;
I want you to be able to see the general pattern. We don't need any of these comments.
The whole thing fits on the screen.
If it's not an isogram then later we'll have the supporting methods in here and here.
So. we check isogram. lowercase. length. and then. we say OK. if we
can't find any of these things wrong with it. It doesn't mean its OK. it just means we can't find anything wrong with it. right.
I'm actually just going to pop in a return value here.
because I want this code to be
compilable. So. there's the return length error! Great! Alright!
So. now we have all of our conditions and all of our errors. These falses are going to need to be
replaced. Let's make sure that this actually gets called. at some point. Let's go to
main. and have a look inside PlayGame(). Now. ooof. I'm not really
liking the look of this PlayGame(). I'm going to just
do a bit of tidying up. I'm going to put the TODO on the end
here. to reduce the number of lines.
and I'm going to make loop checking
valid. GetGuess() is what we're saying
is. we want to change to GetValidGuess() or something later. So. I'm
going to put that down here and say.
make something like this. "// TODO
change
to GetValidGuess".
And that will loop asking for a guess. So.
that's a bit clearer! So it goes and gets a guess. submits a valid
guess to the game. and receives the count. prints the number of bulls and cows. and we don't need a
space before that end line. Alright. that's good! So. what I had there is a little panic. that I hit
PlayGame(). and it just looked too ugly to understand where I even need to put
my line. Great! So. we go get the guess! Now. let's just go check the
guess is valid. So. how are we going to do that? Well. I'm going to make myself an enum. which is
an EGuessStatus now. I'm going to call it Status =
and then I'm going to call BCGame
.CheckGuessValidity with the (Guess) that we
just got in the line above here. alright. And I don't think we really need to comment
that. it's quite clear. So. this is how we use the debugger to see the value of status. the value
that's coming back from this. We could put a watch on this. or you can
store it in a variable called status and pop yourself a break point. any time after that line.
Let's have a look! Let's run the Windows Debugger. put
anything in. like I don't know. Let's put in "planes". which is close to planet.
and then. the debugger comes back here. stops. and it says "Status OK". So. that
proves that OK has come out. and it will have done because we've gone through all of
these falses. until we've got down to the OK. Great! So.
now you have everything you need to be able to write the simple logic in here.
to finish this off. So. write the word length check.
No need to call any helper methods. at the moment. Use that syntax.
!= for not equals. Call GetHiddenWordLength(). as we've got it. rather
than interrogating HiddenWord.Length. and
test the value using the debugger. as I just showed you. Pause the video. have a go.
get this finished off. and actually try putting some guesses in that are the wrong length. and
the debugger should tell you that the error status is coming back.
Cool welcome back! So. this is hopefully pretty
simple. What we're doing is we're saying put your machine
into insert mode. Ben. We're saying (Guess
.length()). Now. we don't
have Guess. and that's because I never made a
handle for the incoming parameter. When we declare a method like this.
we don't have to give ourselves a variable name. alright. We don't have to get a handle to hold onto this.
but when we implement we do need a handle. so there's Guess! Now. (Guess.length())
will work. and if (Guess.length()) is not equal to
Get). now. we can call it directly. != GetHiddenWordLength())
because we're inside the class here. If it's not able to GetHiddenWordLength(). now
why not just compare it to the word length? You could but I prefer to
call the method if we've got a method. in case GetHiddenWordLength() does something different later.
then we know that this is the one place we call it. OK. even though we've
got access to the hidden word directly. why not use the method that we've
got that does it. It's just a bit safer for modified code. Alright. so
now we should get an error coming back about the wrong length. if we have the wrong length. We have
our breakpoint in place. let's try it! Firstly. let's see that we still get
OK. "planes". What do we get? Guess status
OK. Fantastic! So. I'm going to continue the debugger! Now. let's
try "plan". Return. Ah hah! Look at this!
We've got all sorts of problems. and we know that our code is about to crash.
but the most important thing is that we've caught it. because the status has come back
Wrong_Length. If we allowed it to continue running now. we'd get a horrible error. but
the cool thing is that we've got a load of red in our debugger
and we got an error status back before! Let's try that again!
Before it actually crashed. "plan". it's gone red. it's got some problems. but we've
got Wrong_Length and we can intercept it now. Awesome. so we have done our
first bit of proper error checking! So. congratulations on that and
I'll see you soon!
=======
So,
we're going to be writing our first error checking code! I do warn you, by the way, in real code
quite a lot of it can end up being error checking code. Some estimates have been up to over
75%, so it's quite normal that there are quite a lot of lines
of code to do with error checking. We can't trust them, they're users to be putting sensible
input in. So, by the end of the video, we will have a situation
like this, where if we put in a word that's too short like "plan", when we're looking
for six letters, then our debugger is going to notice that our
status is coming back as wrong length, and it will catch that just
before the whole thing crashes. So, let's dive in and see how to catch this error!
Welcome back! Let's get this CheckGuessValidity() method actually
working! Because I'm focusing on it, I'm just going to give myself a little more space, so I can see it
there! Delete what's in there for now. Let's start pseudo-coding what its going to do.
So, we're going to say that "// if the guess
isn't an isogram, then
return an error". And we've got the error status
ready. "// if the guess isn't all
lowercase, return an error".
Now, you could start to just,
you know, use indentation here. That's slightly better than comma return
error. So, you can indent your pseudocode, that's
fine, and then, we could just say "if the
guess length is wrong"
then "// return an error". And then, we're just
going to say else, "// otherwise... Let's just use otherwise, just to get away from the
habit of kind of writing code in pseudocode. "// otherwise"
"// return OK". That's the structure! That is it!
It's as simple as that! So, let's start coding this up!
We're going to need a couple of supporting methods, by the way, which we don't have and we'll do in a
separate video. We don't have methods for isogram and lowercase,
but for now, to get this code working, let's just say if (false).
So, this condition will never happen. The fact that it isn't
a isogram isn't going to happen, for now. So, if false, then we can
come here and go squiggle. What do we do? Well, we return an error! How do we do
that? Well, we go BC...
We go return, rather sorry, return. It's an enumeration
and it's now called... What do we call it? EWordStatus.
I'm actually a bit uncomfortable with EWordStatus, I would rather it was GuessStatus. I'll change that
in a second. But if the guess isn't an isogram, return not isogram,
and that's the general pattern there. OK, now we don't
need "// return an error" as a comment, I don't think that's particularly useful. So,
EWordStatus, I just want to rename it! Highlight, Control, R, Control, R, and let's go
to EGuessStatus. I just feel more comfortable. So, if you think you're going to feel more comfortable with
a different name, try it on. OK, so now what do we do? Now we do,
for the first time, and else if! And the condition is, we're going to say the
condition is false, i.e. we're not going to detect the error now, til we have written the method.
But we're going to say, if the guess isn't all lowercase,
what are we going to do? And then, well, we're going
to return some enumeration.
It's called EGuessStatus, a bit easier to find now, and then, we're going to use
colon colon because we're accessing a member, like this is accessing a member here. And a
member, Not_Lowercase, alright. So, that's your else if! Now, don't
worry, I'm going to leave some of this to you. In fact, you're going to do the next else if condition.
The next else if condition is going to be false, for now, but
you're going to change it into actual logic in a second. For the if the guess
length is wrong, OK. Then, you'd return another error, and I'll
leave you to even return the error.
And that's going to go there!
And then, we're going to have one more thing, which is the else that catches the
final case, which is that we then go ahead and just
return EGuessStatus::OK;
I want you to be able to see the general pattern. We don't need any of these comments.
The whole thing fits on the screen.
If it's not an isogram then later we'll have the supporting methods in here and here.
So, we check isogram, lowercase, length, and then, we say OK, if we
can't find any of these things wrong with it. It doesn't mean its OK, it just means we can't find anything wrong with it, right.
I'm actually just going to pop in a return value here,
because I want this code to be
compilable. So, there's the return length error! Great! Alright!
So, now we have all of our conditions and all of our errors. These falses are going to need to be
replaced. Let's make sure that this actually gets called, at some point. Let's go to
main, and have a look inside PlayGame(). Now, ooof, I'm not really
liking the look of this PlayGame(). I'm going to just
do a bit of tidying up. I'm going to put the TODO on the end
here, to reduce the number of lines,
and I'm going to make loop checking
valid. GetGuess() is what we're saying
is, we want to change to GetValidGuess() or something later. So, I'm
going to put that down here and say,
make something like this. "// TODO
change
to GetValidGuess".
And that will loop asking for a guess. So,
that's a bit clearer! So it goes and gets a guess, submits a valid
guess to the game, and receives the count, prints the number of bulls and cows, and we don't need a
space before that end line. Alright, that's good! So, what I had there is a little panic, that I hit
PlayGame(), and it just looked too ugly to understand where I even need to put
my line. Great! So, we go get the guess! Now, let's just go check the
guess is valid. So, how are we going to do that? Well, I'm going to make myself an enum, which is
an EGuessStatus now. I'm going to call it Status =
and then I'm going to call BCGame
.CheckGuessValidity with the (Guess) that we
just got in the line above here, alright. And I don't think we really need to comment
that, it's quite clear. So, this is how we use the debugger to see the value of status, the value
that's coming back from this. We could put a watch on this, or you can
store it in a variable called status and pop yourself a break point, any time after that line.
Let's have a look! Let's run the Windows Debugger, put
anything in, like I don't know. Let's put in "planes", which is close to planet,
and then, the debugger comes back here, stops, and it says "Status OK". So, that
proves that OK has come out, and it will have done because we've gone through all of
these falses, until we've got down to the OK. Great! So,
now you have everything you need to be able to write the simple logic in here,
to finish this off. So, write the word length check.
No need to call any helper methods, at the moment. Use that syntax,
!= for not equals. Call GetHiddenWordLength(), as we've got it, rather
than interrogating HiddenWord.Length, and
test the value using the debugger, as I just showed you. Pause the video, have a go,
get this finished off, and actually try putting some guesses in that are the wrong length, and
the debugger should tell you that the error status is coming back.
Cool welcome back! So, this is hopefully pretty
simple. What we're doing is we're saying put your machine
into insert mode, Ben. We're saying (Guess
.length()). Now, we don't
have Guess, and that's because I never made a
handle for the incoming parameter. When we declare a method like this,
we don't have to give ourselves a variable name, alright. We don't have to get a handle to hold onto this,
but when we implement we do need a handle, so there's Guess! Now, (Guess.length())
will work, and if (Guess.length()) is not equal to
Get), now, we can call it directly, != GetHiddenWordLength())
because we're inside the class here. If it's not able to GetHiddenWordLength(), now
why not just compare it to the word length? You could but I prefer to
call the method if we've got a method, in case GetHiddenWordLength() does something different later,
then we know that this is the one place we call it. OK, even though we've
got access to the hidden word directly, why not use the method that we've
got that does it. It's just a bit safer for modified code. Alright, so
now we should get an error coming back about the wrong length, if we have the wrong length. We have
our breakpoint in place, let's try it! Firstly, let's see that we still get
OK, "planes". What do we get? Guess status
OK. Fantastic! So, I'm going to continue the debugger! Now, let's
try "plan", Return. Ah hah! Look at this!
We've got all sorts of problems, and we know that our code is about to crash,
but the most important thing is that we've caught it, because the status has come back
Wrong_Length. If we allowed it to continue running now, we'd get a horrible error, but
the cool thing is that we've got a load of red in our debugger
and we got an error status back before! Let's try that again!
Before it actually crashed, "plan", it's gone red, it's got some problems, but we've
got Wrong_Length and we can intercept it now. Awesome, so we have done our
first bit of proper error checking! So, congratulations on that and
I'll see you soon!
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1