...
In this video.
we're going to use something called a switch statement. which is a bit like an if statement but different.
to work with our error checking code. And we can now finally.
if the user puts in the wrong length word. we're going to keep on
asking them for the right length word. until they finally put the right length
in. then we increment the turn number in the game. OK cool!
So. focusing our attention on the PlayGame() method. this is where we're going to
write the code for now. Firstly. there's too much of it. I want to reduce
it. so we don't need to have the comment "// print number of bulls and cows". It's very obvious from what it
says. Also. this lot here is a lot of text for
just outputting two new lines. ins't it. So. let's do it a different way. let's just go backslash
n backslash n. And that reduces the code. Less code is
generally better. less to reason about. Great! So. now we go
get a guess and we check the guess validity. and then we're not really doing anything
with the result of that check on the guess validity.
So. let's use a switch statement. It's going to go in here. this is the anatomy
of it. It goes like this. switch on some expression. that's what we're going to switch based on.
and then you put some curlies. and you go. in the case of some
constant. like I've received my error code wrong word length.
then write some statements like talk to you user and break. come out of the
switch statement. In another case. maybe it's not an isogram.
say something to the user and break out of the switch statement. And then. you always have a default
that says. well. if none of the cases above occur. what do we need to do?
Then. you end your curlies! OK. so let's just make a really simple
switch statement here! Let's say switch
based on (Status). and then. let's put our curlies
in. Alright. so now what are we going to
do? You go case and then we're going to say. for example. that if the enumerator
is coming back out of status. so this is what status equals.
If EGuessStatus:: is Wrong_
Length: it's just the syntax. Check over on the slide. it's
this colon on the end of the constant. Then. what do we do? Well. we say something.
So. we're going to go cout. and then. we're going to go... Well.
let's tell then exactly what we want. << "Please enter a " and then. we may as well go find
the length of the word. which is BCGame
.GetHiddenWordLength()
<< And then. we may as well say space "  letter
word and then a bit of a full stop and a backslash
n and end the line with a semicolon. So. that's it! We switched on status...
Oh. we need standard in front of the cout. of course. and if
the status is Wrong_Length. then we're going to output something. And then. at this
point. remember that we must have a break statement. so we come out of
the case. the switch. You'll see why this is important. when we have more cases.
It's to make sure that all the code under all the cases doesn't run. Let's see if this
works. What I'm hoping is. that when we put in a wrong length. that this case will
trigger and it will get some feedback. just before the game crashes.
"ksa". There you go. we get the
bug but we also see "Please enter a 6 letter word". just beforehand.
Great. so the user has had a little bit of feedback! So.
that's good news! Now. we're not going to flesh out the rest of this case
statement here. because we're in the wrong place. aren't we? This whole lot of
code here is all about getting valid guesses right? It's about going and getting
a guess. checking it's status. switching. and giving feedback to the user. And we ought to
tenaciously go around a loop doing this. until the user gives us a valid guess.
Then. we come back and start submitting the guess to the engine down here. So. all of this lot
should be to do with getting a valid guess. So. let's go ahead and do this refactor.
Remember when we named GetGuess(). we've got a TODO here saying. well. it's...
Actually. we're talking about getting a valid guess. so let's rename GetGuess() to GetValidGuess()
now. OK. and then. we don't need the comment anymore.
It's job is to continually loop. and we can comment more at a higher level.
"// loop continually until
the user gives a valid guess".
That's this thing's job. Now. we won't put the loop in just yet.
but we will move some of this code down so that it's clearer. So. we're going to
go and get a valid guess. All of this switchy stuff can come down
here now. So. you go and
get the guess. and then. we check the guess validity and check
that one condition. Now. what's better about this is. our PlayGame() method is now
shorter again. We get a valid guess looping until we
do. And if you hover over it. because we put that comment in. it now comes through here. "loop continually until the
user" gets "a valid guess". Ah hah! OK. then. submit the valid guess. then print
some feedback. And then. we look and GetValidGuess(). and we ask
them for the... I guess we could actually move this comment up. couldn't we. above
here and group all of this together. because it's all to do with just asking them for their
guess. Then. we CheckGuessValidity().
So. what we're going to do is. make the default case that we return the
guess. So. default: like
that. and then. we're going to put the return Guess; into the default:.
So. if none of the errors above happen. then we return the guess. Again. let's test the
code! If we go say "planes" it's fine. If we go "pla" we get the error.
So. focusing on this repeating unit. I want you
to write the rest of the case statements. which will be very much like this. in this gap here.
So. the challenge is write the rest of the errors! Write a message to the user.
for each error. tell them how to get it right next time. Remember. your break statements.
and test the Console output for the wrong
word length. for yourself as I just did for myself. OK.
pause the video. go ahead and write the error messages. and I'll see you in a moment!
OK. welcome back! So. let's
think about what these other cases could be. Well. we can pretty much just go through the enumerators.
There's another good thing about enumerators. if we just go colon colon. we've got Not_Isogram.
So. let's just deal with that one. the order doesn't really matter. Standard cout.
Please enter an isogram or "Please enter
a word without repeating
letters.  full stop. \n
OK. so then it will go ahead and ask them for their
guess. again. after that. but we'll sort the loop out in a minute. Let's just
get with all the error cases. Ah. break! Remember your break!
Cool! OK. so we have another case!
What's the other case? Well. the great thing about these enumerators is. we can just have a look inside it and see.
well what have we not dealt with? We've not dealt with all lowercase. Cool!
So. let's just give them a message. Again. make it a message that they can action.
they can deal with. << "Please
enter all lowercase letters
full stop \n". So. they're helpful! Alright. these are
helpful error messages. hopefully. Now. we can't preview any of these yet. because
none of these statuses are going to be triggering. but what I do want to do. before I leave this video.
is wrap all of this in a loop. What I want to do is
go around and around and around. until the user eventually gives us a correct
guess. So. the way to do that is literally to wrap the whole
lot in a do while loop. So. we go do and then open
chevrons. OK. Now. I'm going to delete the closed chevrons
and in this case. highlight everything. and then. down to here apart from the...
We don't want a last closing bracket. because that closes the whole method definition. the function definition.
Tab in to bring it all in one. and then.
close your brackets and then we can say while. Now. what is the while
condition here? So. we're going to do this all the time that status...
Now. that's not helping us! Status. it's not there! Why
is Status not here? The reason (Status) is an undeclared identifier.
at this point. and that's what it'll say. It says
if we try and compile identify status is undefined. Is because
we're now outside. By being here. at this curly brace. we're
outside of the do loop. and therefore. this status
here is what we call out of scope. It's not available right? It's just not available
to this while statement. because it's outside of this loop. so what we need
to do is declare this thing first. So. instead of saying
EGuessStatus Status. at the top here. I'm just going to take away
the word EGuessStatus. Before we enter the loop I'm going to say
EGuessStatus Status. Now. I want to give it a
default value. so we're going to go EGuessStatus::
Now. what would be a good one to give it? I think we ought to
have an Invalid_Status status
right. because it's invalid until we've actually set a value. So. let's go and
do that! Let's go into the header file. and let's make our first value
invalid. It's actually quite a good practice. for a variety of reasons I won't bore you with now.
But if we put Invalid_Status
as the first value. in here. it doesn't change anything else
that we've done. by the way.
And then. we come down here. we go ::Invalid_
Status; so we're initializing it to an invalid status.
By declaring it here. we now can access Status
inside. and that means that the while loop should be able to access
(Status). Now. it needs a boolean
type. because we haven't finished. We need to compare that to
EGuessStatus:: member
OK. And is it = or not =?
So. we keep looping. Let's put it in English. "// keep
looping until we get
valid input" or "no errors". This is slightly more accurate!
"// keep looping until we get no errors". You see what's going on? If we
zoom out... Let me actually literally turn the font size down a little bit. This is the whole of
GetValidGuess(). We get a guess from the player. we ask them
for their try. we check the status and get some feedback.
and we keep going until we get no errors OK. So. let's see if we can make
this work! Now. we're getting a warning: "not all
control paths return a value"! That's because the compiler doesn't like the fact
that we may never get out of this loop. Well. I'm going to
live with that now. We wouldn't generally ignore warnings. but we're doing this with volition. We do
want to keep looping until the user gives us a valid value. So. if I just put a few letters in.
Ah! "Please enter a 6 letter word." OK. well. there's six letters! Great!
I'll count them for you. And then. that's the only error it's going to detect. but you get the
idea! And look. the try number is not incrementing.. until I put in a
six letter word.
and then. our try number goes up and it counts. The only thing I want to do is put an extra line in. after
the instruction. So. where it say. please enter a blah
letter word. I just want to make sure we've got two backslash n's
on the end. Now. we could do that on all of these but that's a bit weird.
And also. I forgot my break statement. so let's put that break in!
So. rather than putting a new line on the end of all of these. what I want to do
is just do it at the end of the switch statement.
So. I'm just going to say here. cout end line.
Of course. standard cout
and standard end line. Because then. it's in a single
place. by making that format change in one place. Now. let's put in a
"planes". No problem. if I now put in too few letters... Ah. "Please enter a 6
letter word." This is looking much better! Fantastic! Great
job! Take a good look at that. make sure you understand how that method works.
and we will work on making it a little bit more compact. as we refactor moving
forward. OK. so this is what I would suggest is on the limit of how long a method wants to be.
because it becomes quite hard to reason about. Great! See you soon!
=======
...
In this video,
we're going to use something called a switch statement, which is a bit like an if statement but different,
to work with our error checking code. And we can now finally,
if the user puts in the wrong length word, we're going to keep on
asking them for the right length word, until they finally put the right length
in, then we increment the turn number in the game. OK cool!
So, focusing our attention on the PlayGame() method, this is where we're going to
write the code for now. Firstly, there's too much of it, I want to reduce
it, so we don't need to have the comment "// print number of bulls and cows". It's very obvious from what it
says. Also, this lot here is a lot of text for
just outputting two new lines, ins't it. So, let's do it a different way, let's just go backslash
n backslash n. And that reduces the code. Less code is
generally better, less to reason about. Great! So, now we go
get a guess and we check the guess validity, and then we're not really doing anything
with the result of that check on the guess validity.
So, let's use a switch statement. It's going to go in here, this is the anatomy
of it. It goes like this, switch on some expression, that's what we're going to switch based on,
and then you put some curlies, and you go, in the case of some
constant, like I've received my error code wrong word length,
then write some statements like talk to you user and break, come out of the
switch statement. In another case, maybe it's not an isogram,
say something to the user and break out of the switch statement. And then, you always have a default
that says, well, if none of the cases above occur, what do we need to do?
Then, you end your curlies! OK, so let's just make a really simple
switch statement here! Let's say switch
based on (Status), and then, let's put our curlies
in. Alright, so now what are we going to
do? You go case and then we're going to say, for example, that if the enumerator
is coming back out of status, so this is what status equals.
If EGuessStatus:: is Wrong_
Length: it's just the syntax. Check over on the slide, it's
this colon on the end of the constant. Then, what do we do? Well, we say something.
So, we're going to go cout, and then, we're going to go... Well,
let's tell then exactly what we want. << "Please enter a " and then, we may as well go find
the length of the word, which is BCGame
.GetHiddenWordLength()
<< And then, we may as well say space "  letter
word and then a bit of a full stop and a backslash
n and end the line with a semicolon. So, that's it! We switched on status...
Oh, we need standard in front of the cout, of course, and if
the status is Wrong_Length, then we're going to output something. And then, at this
point, remember that we must have a break statement, so we come out of
the case, the switch. You'll see why this is important, when we have more cases.
It's to make sure that all the code under all the cases doesn't run. Let's see if this
works. What I'm hoping is, that when we put in a wrong length, that this case will
trigger and it will get some feedback, just before the game crashes.
"ksa". There you go, we get the
bug but we also see "Please enter a 6 letter word", just beforehand.
Great, so the user has had a little bit of feedback! So,
that's good news! Now, we're not going to flesh out the rest of this case
statement here, because we're in the wrong place, aren't we? This whole lot of
code here is all about getting valid guesses right? It's about going and getting
a guess, checking it's status, switching, and giving feedback to the user. And we ought to
tenaciously go around a loop doing this, until the user gives us a valid guess.
Then, we come back and start submitting the guess to the engine down here. So, all of this lot
should be to do with getting a valid guess. So, let's go ahead and do this refactor.
Remember when we named GetGuess(), we've got a TODO here saying, well, it's...
Actually, we're talking about getting a valid guess, so let's rename GetGuess() to GetValidGuess()
now. OK, and then, we don't need the comment anymore.
It's job is to continually loop, and we can comment more at a higher level.
"// loop continually until
the user gives a valid guess".
That's this thing's job. Now, we won't put the loop in just yet,
but we will move some of this code down so that it's clearer. So, we're going to
go and get a valid guess. All of this switchy stuff can come down
here now. So, you go and
get the guess, and then, we check the guess validity and check
that one condition. Now, what's better about this is, our PlayGame() method is now
shorter again. We get a valid guess looping until we
do. And if you hover over it, because we put that comment in, it now comes through here, "loop continually until the
user" gets "a valid guess". Ah hah! OK, then, submit the valid guess, then print
some feedback. And then, we look and GetValidGuess(), and we ask
them for the... I guess we could actually move this comment up, couldn't we, above
here and group all of this together, because it's all to do with just asking them for their
guess. Then, we CheckGuessValidity().
So, what we're going to do is, make the default case that we return the
guess. So, default: like
that, and then, we're going to put the return Guess; into the default:.
So, if none of the errors above happen, then we return the guess. Again, let's test the
code! If we go say "planes" it's fine. If we go "pla" we get the error.
So, focusing on this repeating unit, I want you
to write the rest of the case statements, which will be very much like this, in this gap here.
So, the challenge is write the rest of the errors! Write a message to the user,
for each error, tell them how to get it right next time. Remember, your break statements,
and test the Console output for the wrong
word length, for yourself as I just did for myself. OK,
pause the video, go ahead and write the error messages, and I'll see you in a moment!
OK, welcome back! So, let's
think about what these other cases could be. Well, we can pretty much just go through the enumerators.
There's another good thing about enumerators, if we just go colon colon, we've got Not_Isogram.
So, let's just deal with that one, the order doesn't really matter. Standard cout,
Please enter an isogram or "Please enter
a word without repeating
letters.  full stop. \n
OK, so then it will go ahead and ask them for their
guess, again, after that, but we'll sort the loop out in a minute. Let's just
get with all the error cases. Ah, break! Remember your break!
Cool! OK, so we have another case!
What's the other case? Well, the great thing about these enumerators is, we can just have a look inside it and see,
well what have we not dealt with? We've not dealt with all lowercase. Cool!
So, let's just give them a message. Again, make it a message that they can action,
they can deal with. << "Please
enter all lowercase letters
full stop \n". So, they're helpful! Alright, these are
helpful error messages, hopefully. Now, we can't preview any of these yet, because
none of these statuses are going to be triggering, but what I do want to do, before I leave this video,
is wrap all of this in a loop. What I want to do is
go around and around and around, until the user eventually gives us a correct
guess. So, the way to do that is literally to wrap the whole
lot in a do while loop. So, we go do and then open
chevrons. OK. Now, I'm going to delete the closed chevrons
and in this case, highlight everything, and then, down to here apart from the...
We don't want a last closing bracket, because that closes the whole method definition, the function definition.
Tab in to bring it all in one, and then,
close your brackets and then we can say while. Now, what is the while
condition here? So, we're going to do this all the time that status...
Now, that's not helping us! Status, it's not there! Why
is Status not here? The reason (Status) is an undeclared identifier,
at this point, and that's what it'll say. It says
if we try and compile identify status is undefined. Is because
we're now outside. By being here, at this curly brace, we're
outside of the do loop, and therefore, this status
here is what we call out of scope. It's not available right? It's just not available
to this while statement, because it's outside of this loop, so what we need
to do is declare this thing first. So, instead of saying
EGuessStatus Status, at the top here, I'm just going to take away
the word EGuessStatus. Before we enter the loop I'm going to say
EGuessStatus Status. Now, I want to give it a
default value, so we're going to go EGuessStatus::
Now, what would be a good one to give it? I think we ought to
have an Invalid_Status status
right, because it's invalid until we've actually set a value. So, let's go and
do that! Let's go into the header file, and let's make our first value
invalid. It's actually quite a good practice, for a variety of reasons I won't bore you with now.
But if we put Invalid_Status
as the first value, in here, it doesn't change anything else
that we've done, by the way.
And then, we come down here, we go ::Invalid_
Status; so we're initializing it to an invalid status.
By declaring it here, we now can access Status
inside, and that means that the while loop should be able to access
(Status). Now, it needs a boolean
type, because we haven't finished. We need to compare that to
EGuessStatus:: member
OK. And is it = or not =?
So, we keep looping. Let's put it in English. "// keep
looping until we get
valid input" or "no errors". This is slightly more accurate!
"// keep looping until we get no errors". You see what's going on? If we
zoom out... Let me actually literally turn the font size down a little bit. This is the whole of
GetValidGuess(). We get a guess from the player, we ask them
for their try, we check the status and get some feedback,
and we keep going until we get no errors OK. So, let's see if we can make
this work! Now, we're getting a warning: "not all
control paths return a value"! That's because the compiler doesn't like the fact
that we may never get out of this loop. Well, I'm going to
live with that now. We wouldn't generally ignore warnings, but we're doing this with volition. We do
want to keep looping until the user gives us a valid value. So, if I just put a few letters in,
Ah! "Please enter a 6 letter word." OK, well, there's six letters! Great!
I'll count them for you. And then, that's the only error it's going to detect, but you get the
idea! And look, the try number is not incrementing,. until I put in a
six letter word,
and then, our try number goes up and it counts. The only thing I want to do is put an extra line in, after
the instruction. So, where it say, please enter a blah
letter word, I just want to make sure we've got two backslash n's
on the end. Now, we could do that on all of these but that's a bit weird.
And also, I forgot my break statement, so let's put that break in!
So, rather than putting a new line on the end of all of these, what I want to do
is just do it at the end of the switch statement.
So, I'm just going to say here, cout end line.
Of course, standard cout
and standard end line. Because then, it's in a single
place, by making that format change in one place. Now, let's put in a
"planes". No problem, if I now put in too few letters... Ah, "Please enter a 6
letter word." This is looking much better! Fantastic! Great
job! Take a good look at that, make sure you understand how that method works,
and we will work on making it a little bit more compact, as we refactor moving
forward. OK, so this is what I would suggest is on the limit of how long a method wants to be,
because it becomes quite hard to reason about. Great! See you soon!
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1