So, in this video we're
going to be handling the game win condition. By the end of it, you'll actually be able to put
a valid guess in, and it will say, do you want to play again?
And of course, eventually we'll also put in a well done, etc., but for now,
at least it's going to detect that you have won the game. Great news!
So guys, we need a way of winning the game as I said, so let's
find a way to make that happen. We already have a method called IsGameWon()
and it's const, which is great, but if we look at the implementation or
another way of saying that is the definition of that, it just returns false. Now, it's going to be your challenge
to make this do the right thing, but for now, let's write the surrounding code, so that you'll know when you've
got it right. So, we said in this TODO, that we want to change it to a
while loop, so let's do that! But before we do, let's write in English what we want this
loop to do. Loop for the number of turns, asking for guesses, until...
Or just say "loop asking for guesses"
or "while the game is NOT
won", "and
there are still tries
remaining".
OK, so "loop asking for guess while the game is NOT won and there are still tries remaining".
So, let's do it! Let's write out this while loop!
while, now we're going to write it like
this. Now, we need to reference
the (!BCGame), or course, because we're not inside the class. While (!BCGame
.IsGameWon()) but while not (!BCGame.Is
GameWon() && )
Then, the second condition is
we need to ask what the current guess is. Now, how do we do that?
BCGame.GetCurrentTry()
is less than or equal to the max tries
that we declared just above. Now, the one thing about this is it's really easy
to miss the exclamation mark, which says not IsGameWon().
You could say, IsGameWon() == false.
That would be OK,
like so. It's a bit redundant and I'm actually not going to do it this
way, because I want you again to recode like the compiler does.
You need to spot these little things, because in other peoples' code, in Unreal's Boiler Plate
Code, and even in your code, you're going to have exclamation marks. So, I
said not one, up here. In fact, you may even want to move the
NOT right down, so that it's near the exclamation mark there,
OK in the comment, but you need to just be aware of that.
You need to see these. You can space it out, if you like, possibly
even as much as this, but I think that you just need to get
used to that, I'm afraid. There's not really any way around it, OK. You need to see these
exclamation marks. They totally invert the meaning of things, so
I will settle on that format right there. So,
while the game isn't won, do all this stuff. So, let's just
check our code still works, And even if we
win the game, of course, we can still carry on
because the IsGameWon() method is always
returning false, at the moment. So, that is going to be your
challenge! I want you to finish implementing the IsGameWon(), so that we actually know
when the game is won. So, this is how you're going to do it. Finish it
by defining the appropriate getter method. So, we've already declared it IsGame
Won(). I want you to define it. Create a private variable, as necessary,
prefixed with b. Remember, booleans are prefixed with b.
Set the private variable in SubmitValidGuess(),
as a hint, when the number of bulls equals the word length, we've won.
Test you can now actually win the game. So, go ahead, pause the video,
and have a go at this challenge now!
OK, welcome back! So, let's start by thinking
about what private member we need here. We need a bull. Unreal's
coding standard suggests we start bulls with a small b, so we'll do that. And then, we're going to
say bGameIsWon, as a simple boolean. OK, it's OK to be a boolean,
It's sufficiently simple to be a boolean. So, we have this bool called bGameIsWon.
So, then what does IsGameWon() do for us now?
Well, it's quite simple! Let's go and have a look at the implementation. The easiest way,
of course, is to right click on it. Just say Go To Definition. There it is!
Now firstly, it's pretty much a getter, so I'm going to move it to the top here
along with all the other getters. And it's actually so simple
that I'm going to put it in line. What are we returning?
We're, of course, simply returning bIsGameWon,
and it's nice and simple, that prefix; b says well we're looking for a boolean, and there are all the booleans.
Cool! Thanks Unreal for a sensible coding standard. OK,
so let's just bring this into one line, simply because it'll fit there,
and I'm just going to make consistent spacing. There you go! Also, in the header
I think it should probably sit up, right next to all the
constants together. There all getters right, so there we go! Great!
So, we've done that! We've implemented our method there, as a
really simple one line implementation. Now, we need to set this IsGameWon and
we're going to copy it into the Copy Buffer, and then, I'm going to go and decide where we
set it. Well, we're going to set it at the bottom of SubmitValidGuess.
Just before we return bulls and cows, we're going to ask ourselves the question,
is the game won or is the game not won. So,
if (BullCowCount.Bulls
== WordLength)
then the game is won!
So, paste that in.
Equals, we want an equals here, equals true. Otherwise,
any other condition it equals false.
Just copy that
line, paste it in, false, sort out our spacing.
OK, so that's fine! Now have we initialized bIsGameWon
to false? It's all very well setting this value, but there's one more thing we need to do, which is in our
Reset() method, which is at the top of this function. We need to make
sure that it is actually set to false. So, MyCurrent
Try is 1, GameIsWon is false. So, I have a reset to false.
We submit our valid
guess, count our bulls and cows. At the bottom of this we say, OK, let's set
it to true, if the bull count is equal to the WordLength. If it's less than the WordLength or
it's not equal to the WordLength, then it's false. You could arguably say that it
would be better to say that the BullCowCount has to be less than or equal to
but equals is fine. It's the only condition, you should never have a bull count
longer than the word length, and it's only when it's equal to it that we have a valid win.
OK, so let's go! Let's have a look and see if this works! So, you put some rubbish
in, it asks you to put a sensible guess in, you put planes in, which isn't planet,
and it says "Try 2. Enter your guess". We're getting close to a working game here.
Planed, guess three! Planes,
planet, ahah! Bulls
6, would you like to play again, no, and we leave! Great! And let's make sure we
can play again. Planet, would you like to play again? Yes! We could
do with a space, before the introduction to the game, or probably put some ASCII art around this
later but it's working! That is good news! I'm actually going to put the space
in, before the welcome right now, because I'm otherwise what I call paying lip
service to the idea that we should do that. So, let's go and actually do that right
now. I'm going to put in, I think, two new lines before that, and just test
again. So OK, it starts off a bit down the screen. As I say, later we'll use ASCII art,
but for now, planet. Would I like to play again? Yes! And then, the new
game is relatively well spaced out.
That's great! So congratulations and I'll see you in the next video!