Let's imagine we're starting with the word planet! OK, I'm just
going to go through the first couple of letters, at the moment, so P and L. I'm going to end up drawing them
in a circle, if you're wondering why I'm drawing them like this. So, we have P and L, and we want to say
are those letters duplicated? Well, you just do one comparison between P and
L right? Pretty simple! So, let's now put some more letters in
A an N. I'll put them all in for now.
E and T. I'm putting them in a circle, you'll see why in a second, it just helps me draw a particular type of diagram.
So, if I now want to compare the letters in
P, L, and A, to see if any of them are repeating, then I can pair
P to L and then I could compare A to L and A to
P, doing now three comparisons! If I wanted a
P L A N, PLAN, then I could add to this three another
one, two, three, to get six comparisons. If I had
PLANE, then I could be adding to the six,
or I could be adding another one, two, three, four, so we're up
to ten. And then, if I had a T on the end, I could be adding another one,
two, three, four, five, for a
grand total of fifteen different comparisons here,
which we need to do. Another way of looking at that
is like this! What we're saying is, that as the size of the
word, so Word.Length
...
... goes up from say 0 to, I don't know, say
10 letters, the question is, how many comparisons do we need
to do, and how fast does this go up? This is
to do with the order, how fast is this? Well look, this is how I
reason about how fast it is. If we write the word Planet a couple of
times, like this: PLANET, and then, write it
again across a grid. The short answer,
by the way, is n squared, for those of you who are experienced, mathematical,
and/or impatient, but let me explain why it's rougly
n squared. It's not also exactly n squared. This little formula we're going to work out
is going to be quite helpful, because it helps you work out how many pairs there are between things.
By the way, this is not also the fastest way of doing this, just
rub some of that rubbish out. OK cool! So, let's quickly talk about the fact that we're not
interested in comparing letters to themselves like this, we're interested
in the two triangles. We have say a red triangle here,
and that red triangle is all of the instances in which
we say compare L to P, A to P, A to N, etc.
And that covers all of these lines, actually, and then, you've got the lines going the other way,
which are all of these elements up here. Let me make it a different color,
which is a say green triangle.
OK, so how many comparisons do we have to do
in general? Well, if we have two letters we do one comparison. If we have three letters we have
three, if we have four we do more, and at five letters, like this, it looks like we'd do
fifteen comparison. The way you work it out is you say, look if the number of letters...
This is the case n = 6 here, so we're here somewhere on the graph,
then the number of squares in the grid is 6 times 6.
So that's n squared: n squared,
number of squares. We need to take off n squares, for the diagonal,
and then, we need to divide the whole thing by two, because n squared
- n was the area of these two triangles. You then
say, well we only need one of these, it doesn't matter which way around we compare. So, n squared
- n over 2, and that's also the same as saying n into (n-1)
over 2 or a million other ways of writing it. The point about this
really, that I want to get across, is that the speed that this
goes up, the worst offender to the speed of which
the comparisons increases with the word length is the n squared bit. So,
what we say is, this thing is of order n squared. So,
we're saying it's like this: At a value of 10
comparisons, you'd have 10 squared which is 100 - 10, which is 90 over
2 is 45. So, you'd have 45 comparisons there.
At 6 you would have
15 comparisons, which we've just counted, because you'd have 6.
We'll just use this insistent color here. You'd have 6 times 6 is 36,
minus 6 is 30, and 30 over 2 is 15, so you get 15 there.
So, you can see that this algorithm, that you could easily come up with and write a nested
for loop for, goes up pretty fast. It goes up to what we call
order n squared, which means that if you double the number of
letters... I know there's only like the longest isogram in the
English language is like however many letters, we'll look it up in a minute, but the point
is to start thinking about this early. This does not scale well, as this problem
gets bigger. Now, in our case it doesn't matter, but it's an important point to consider
how fast it scales. So, is there a faster way?
Well, if you're smart you may realize that, actually what you could do
with a particular word is, you could say well why don't we just sort
the letters. So, we have the word planet,
and that is an isogram, but we could sort the letters. So, we go a
e... I don't know. l m n o p q r s t?
So, a e l n
p t. OK fine! So, that is an isogram, because we can
go through this... We can sort it, we'll talk about how fast sorting is in a minute, and then, we can go through
very quickly once and say OK there's no duplicates. How about if
I had, I don't know, boom?
That actually already is sorted, well it's nearly sorted. If you sorted
it you'd get bmoo, and you'd go through this and go
ah; as soon as you get to a duplicate letter, then it is not an isogram.
So, how fast is this way of doing it? Well, the first question is, how fast can
you sort? Well, let's take a look! Let's go something like "wiki sorting
algorithm". An algorithm is not an ex U.S.
vice president's dance style, rather a recipe for solving a problem.
Now, you'll get more than you need here, when you go to
Wikipedia, but what you'll see is a very common theme, is that the best you'll ever do
when sorting is something called n log n. In some cases, you can do what we call n,
which means that as the size of the word goes up the number
of operations you do goes up with it, in the case of in, but n log n is generally,
in the general case, the best you can do. So, what does n
log n look like? Well, it's worse than n. If we have
a chance, what we have... In fact, why don't I just use Wikipedia. Well, not Wikipedia! Oh, not Wikipedia,
WolframAlpha! Let's use WolframAlpha to show you how these two things compare! So, we go n
squared is, the thing that we talked about before and I gave you a little plot
of. I can't be bothered to plot n log n, so I'm going to go versus n log n for
n = 2 is the shortest word we care about, 2 say 17 is the longest
word we care about. Let's look at the performance of these two algorithms compared,
so there's the comparison! Our previous algorithm, where we did
all the pairings was n squared, but this sorting algorithm,
apparently, can be done in n log n, which is much quicker. Look how much quicker it is, especially for long
words, and if the problem got bigger, then it would get faster and faster.
So, this guy here, where we do firstly a sort,
then just
check for pairs... Oops, that's not very neat
is it! ... Is n log n
+, because afterwards you then just go through all of the pairs
1, 2, 3, which takes in operations. You basically go through all of
this in pairs there, there, there, which takes n.
So, it's n log n + n. We don't care about this, because it's much smaller than n
log n. If you don't believe me, let's add this to the plot, then we get our complete
plot. So, vs n and this shows us all the three
options for the challenge you're about to have, which is I want you to guess how fast it is
possible to detect an isogram. Here is n, it's as fast as we could possibly go!
By the way, I think it's reasonable to reason that you can't go any faster than n,
i. e., we need to look at every letter. The best you could possibly
do is of order, and it might be a little different to n, some little overhead either end.
But in general terms, you need to look at every letter to be sure there are no duplicates, right. I
think that that's a reasonable assumption, so I don't think we're making this guy go any faster than
n down here, which is scaling beautifully. It may be as slow as
n log n, where we do a sort, and then, we go through the sorted string
and check for duplicates. And we could use this kind of brute force method here, which seems
smart, when I first created it ah, but it's actually pretty slow because it's of order n
squared. So, this chart gives you the dramatic difference between the speed of those!
What I want you to do as a challenge now is as follows! I want
you to work out what order you think IsIsogram() can be written at
best. Vote for order n, order n log n, or oder n squared.
Share your vote in the discussions, and explain why you think that's as fast as it can possibly go.
And then, carry on watching the video, and I'll share what I think the fastest
algorithm is for this.
Welcome back! Now look, I just want to congratulate you for
doing what is basically very proper computer science at
this point. I'm really impressed, you've done a great job even
conceptualizing this stuff, so it's grown-up things. So, I think
we can do this in order n! How do we think we can do it in order n? I think we can do it in order
n, using something called a hash table and it's pretty simple. Let me save a copy
of this as n log n1. Yep, that's
fine, and then, just delete it all and
show you what I mean. It's actually very simple! What I think we could do
is, we could have a word. Let's just go Planet again, oops!
And what we could have over here is a table of all
the letters in the alphabet, A, B, C, D, E, so on
to Z. [Laughs] And I better have a P in here somewhere
and a T maybe. OK, you get the idea! And what I do is, as I go through
this word I just tally the number of these things
that I have. How many P's do I have? I go through it, I get to P, I say 1 here in this tally!
I get to L, I say there's an L, wherever that is! Here 1! I get to A,
and I say 1, I get to n and I say 1, and I keep going! And the
algorithm is that provided the moment I get a 2 we're done!
It's not an isogram! So, if I put the word Boom in again,
then we have a different tally but you get the idea. I go B
and then wherever O is, L, M, N, O, P, in here I go O!
And then, I go O again! Uh Oh! Now, suddenly because there are two
O's it's not a tally! I can stop, and the worst if I'd have to do is go through the entire
word. So, this guy is of order
n, which is hugely faster for big problems than
these other guys! So, that's the fastest we can do IsIsogram()!
It's too orders better than I initially thought! I thought I was being
smart with my funny diagram thingy I showed you in the beginning. I wasn't, somebody pointed out to me I
could easily do a sort, and then, we got humbled again when we thought about it and realized
you could just hash it! So, awesome introduction
to performance! See you soon!