So, welcome to Range Based
for Loops! In this video, we're going to be introducing containers and iterators
very briefly, using a range based for loop in Unreal,
gently introducing the auto keyword, and
finishing our IsIsogram() method. By the way, you can read more about range based
for loops, from the Unreal stand point, using that URL there.
So, just before we deal with our fancy ranged based for loop, a couple of
other things to do. We need to deal with this "treat 0 and 1 letter word
as isograms", but we also need to setup our map, which we'll do in a
moment. So, why do we treat 0 and 1 letter words as isograms? Well,
a word with only 0 or 1 letters cannot have repeating letters, so we
should declare it as an isogram. It is very meaningful, but it will also give us
the useful behavior, that when we run our game and put in a single character
like this, that it will go straight through the IsIsogram
test and go onto the next one, which in this case the word length is wrong,
which is useful guidance. So, let's simply say, if
(Word.length() ) remembering it's a method so it needs curly braces, is less than or equal
to 1, or you could say is less than 2 without the equals.
Then, I'm just going to end line, return true.
Very simple! So, treating 0 and 1 letter words as isograms! OK!
How do we setup our map? Well, we already declared a substitution up here using
#define. We said #define TMap as std::map,
because this is the Unreal syntax. So, let's use the word TMap
and come down to our implementation of IsIsogram
and think about how we're going to set it up. Let me show you the syntax! This is the standard
map syntax, the same obviously for TMap, because we've just made a
straight swap of this to this. It's literally textual replacement. So, we're saying we're making a
map of a character to a boolean. And we're going to call that map Letter
Seen, or you could call it SeenLetters or something else but we're going to declare it like that!
We're going to use the syntax, using LetterSeen{Letter]
a bit like accessing characters of a string, to access members of that map.
You can assign to a map element in the same way, but the same syntax.
For example, LetterSeen[Letter] = true; now, some people,
if you're more experienced, may say why don't you use an unordered set or an Unreal
T set. Absolutely perfectly valid alternative, I'm simply using a map here because it's more
versatile. We can reuse it later in the section, and it can be used for more things than
just this. But yes it's true to say that there is another data type called TSet,
that you can use when you're only setting elements to true or false, you just fill it with
letters in this case. But we're going to go with the mapping of the letter, to whether or
not we've seen it true or false. In fact, we're only go?ing to use true, so we're just going to have a table of
letter and true, letter and true, when we see them.
So, back in our code let's actually go ahead and set that map up
right now. So, TMap is the keyword we're going to be using. I'll substitute a keyword of
character and a boolean of true or false, and we're going to call it
LetterSeen. So, that is how we setup our map! Now,
the main subject of this lecture, of course, how do we do a range
based for loop? And what indeed even is a range based for loop? Well, if you do a Google search
for standard string in C++, you'll get to a page like this, which will explain that a
string provides an interface here, similar to that...
[Whispers] Highlight the right thing. [Laughs] "an interface similar to that of a standard container",
and a container is something that contains many elements. A string contains many
characters, and because we have an interface similar to a standard
container interface, the system basically knows how to step through the elements of
the string for you. That's very handy! It's called in iterator and it's really
useful! So, this is how we do it! We say for, and then we say
OK we need a type and we could say char. We'll deal with that in a second. And we could
call it Letter, so this is just the variable name that we're going to be able to access, inside the loop.
Four letter, now colon is the word for in, you just have to remember that for a
range based for. : Word) OK. So,
what this is doing, as a comment here, is it's saying "for all
letters of the word...
Ooh, can't type. OK, so "for all letters
of the word" is what we're doing there. Now, of course, we're going to have a
block of statements, so I'm going to put some curly braces. By the way, if you want to put your curly braces around
all these comments, rather than having to mess around, just highlight them and just open a curly brace.
And in Visual Studio, at least with my settings which are the default, if I change anything, by the way,
I will show you the changes of settings. So, I haven't changed anything without showing. It does this for me,
it indents for me, which is cool! Alright, so for (char Letter :
Word). Now, I want to introduce you to one more concept! We don't really care what the
elements of Word are; we can let go of that implementation detail and use the word
auto. I would never suggest using auto up
here, in the public declaration of a class, because we really want to know at this point
what's coming back, but when we get down at the bottom here and anything do to with the
implementation, we can start to think about maybe we could use auto. It means that the
compiler decides the type for us. In this case, if we hover over the
word auto here, we can see that it's work out "typedef char" and then some other
blurb. It's worked out that this is a character, so just trust me
for now. Let's start gently introducing auto. You may see it in other peoples' code, and I actually think it makes
a lot of sense. The compiler has to do a lot of good checking, to make sure that this type is
completely deducible and that's a good thing! So, just before I throw
you into a challenge, I want to help you out by doing this! I'm going to make a quick substitution, where I'm going to
change, actually, Letter for tolower
(Letter). Now, why am I making the letter lowercase? I'm changing
its value, and I'm doing this because I want to be able to
"handle mixed case". I
want to store and retrieve only lowercase letters, and that way,
the system will work case insensitively. OK, let's take a look
at a challenge! Finish IsIsogram()! I want you to finish the function, test it thoroughly,
try entering backslash 0, that null character, as a guess, and make sure it works for that!
Try a bland string and try mixed case. For example, Aa
like that. And share your implementation, in the discussions, before go?ing on.
Go on, be brave! OK,
welcome back! So, let's see how I'm going to implement it. So, we're going to loop through
all the letters in the word. We've already got that
comment, so I'm going to remove it. So, we're saying, if the letter is in the
map, how do we implement that? Well, it's simply a case of
saying, if (LetterSeen
[Letter]). So, that's the
list of letters that have been seen. And if this letter has been seen,
then what do we do? Well, I'm going to use a compact if notation
here, I'm going to go curly braces there, and then, I'm going to
force it to all be on one line, because I just want to keep things,
in this instance, compact, and I'm going to return false.
OK. And "we do NOT have
an isogram" at this stage. Alright,
so now I'm going to do a compact else, it's exactly the same. Remember, you need to read code like the
compiler does, so I do apologize to complete beginners that I'm being inconsistent with my spacing.
I'm doing it on purpose, because you must learn where spacing matters and
where it doesn't. Look the IDE has changed it to this. This is the same as this,
this is the same as this. That white space doesn't matter, you need your eye in for where
white space matters and where it doesn't. It matters between auto and letter. It wouldn't
understand autoLetter. It does not matter, for example, out here
in the e... [Laughs] It's like being out in space, you didn't know how much gap
you got between you. OK, so now what do we need to say? So,
I've already duplicated that, "we do NOT have an isogram" method. So, otherwise
what we need to do is add a letter to the map seen. The comment says it
there. We don't need otherwise, of course, because else is pretty obvious. So, I'm
going to write here, say LetterSeen
[Letter} = true. And this is the bit where
that simplification using a set would just be a little
simpler, but this is absolutely fine and very clear what it's doing! Let's
make sure that this works! Let's run with
backslash 0, for example. That works! And empty string works!
"Aa", complains about repeating letters. "aa", complains about repeating
letters. "planet", and I win! Play
again? No! Great news! We've done everything that we need to do
in this video, in terms of getting the isogram finished. We've used this very useful and
versatile Map Tool, and congratulations on getting this far!