So, welcome
to Design a Helper Function. The purpose of this video is to help you integrate the knowledge
that you've gained through the section and to do a slightly larger chunk of work
on your own, but the actual code you're going to have to write is quite simple.
We're also, in my solution, going to talk about something called implicit dependancies,
and at the end of it, your code will deal properly with things that are not all lower
case. So, here's that example of planet, and it's going to say no no enter all
lower case, steering the user toward entering input that's valid for the game.
So, in this video, we're going to integrate your previous knowledge,
by getting lowercase checking working, all on your own! Not doing anything new,
just reapplying knowledge that we've used before. So, declare and define
IsLowercase(), a helper method. We've made helper methods before.
Use a range-based for loop,
that we just learned about. use the auto keyword, that we also just started experimenting with.
Handle strings of zero length, backslash 0 and
spaces. Backslash 0 is the null character and it ends a string, and
a user entering that may mess things up, so let's test for that. Excuse me, by the way, if I've
confused backslash and forward slash 0 anywhere else. It is backslash 0
like that for the termination character, the null character of a string. Hint:
a method called islower(), spelled like that, may help. Share your
solution for discussion, in the discussions, would be great, and succeed or fail. Now, I
truly believe FAIL stands for: From Adversity I Learn. I want you to pat
yourself on the back! So, go ahead, pause the video, and have a go at that now!
Welcome back! So, how are we going to go about this? Helper method,
what does that mean? It means that if we look at the public
declaration of BullCowGame it's not there, it's down in the private. It's very much like
IsIsogram. It's going to be a bool IsLowercase
(Fstring)
because we're going to take in a string and it's going to be constant, because we don't want it to change anything.
Cool! Let's go, I need a capital S on the String. Lets go ahead and
implement that! Boom, here we go!
There it is! So, how are we going to do it? Well, let's use what we've learned, for.
Let's use a range based for loop. So, close the brackets,
(auto letter  :  in which has a colon,
Word) capital word, and of course, I need to
give my variable a handle. Now, by the way, on
whether or not you give your variables a name in the head file, it's kind of up to you.
It's kind of cleaner without. It doesn't really matter what you call this thing,
right, but if it's going to be descriptive to give it a name here, then go
ahead and give it a name here, it's kind of style at this stage.
It doesn't actually change anything, because you don't need, in the prototypes here, to be giving
your parameters actual names. So,
I tend to not give them a name in the header, just to keep this as clean and simple as possible,
and then, when I come over here, I tend to decide what the parameter name
is going to be, which is... It is a parameter here, by the way. There is
at the end of the slide deck for this section, I quite clearly show you
what the difference between a parameter and an argument is but I'll just tell you. You define a parameter,
so when you're defining or declaring a function, that is the parameter there.
OK, and then you call an argument. Just remember
you call people up for an argument. So, where you actually call the methods like
here, the guess here is an argument
when you're calling it, and it's a parameter when you're defining or declaring the method.
Alright, anyway, so for (auto letter  :  Word). Now, let's use the
spaced out notation, this time, because it's a relatively short function. OK, so
for each letter in the word. By the way, where's my pseudocode?
So, that's not very good.
We don't actually need to pseudocode, however, this bit, that's kind of obvious what it does
for the letters in the word, but I'm going to pseudocode here, before I write the details.
"// if not a lowercase
letter then
// return false"
otherwise return true.
Change this around, right, and I can return return false into an
actual piece of code there now. And now, I just have
to write the if statement, if not a lowercase letter. How do we say that? Well, if.
Now, we've got a not and then we've got (!Islower). We have a
method there, and it takes in the (Letter)).
So, if it's not a lowercase letter, then what do we want to do?
We want to return false. I'm going to use this spaced
out bracket syntax there, otherwise we return true.
So, that is a pretty simple method! Let's go ahead and
test to see if it works properly.
So, if I go planet now, with a capital P,
what happens? Nothing, it's not working! What have I done
wrong? Well, what I've possibly done wrong is never called IsLowercase().
Let's go and have a look! This would be a common mistake. Ah hah! We just
say if false. What we actually want to be doing if not (!Is
Lowercase(Guess)) OK.
Now, let's try it, and then, I'm going to talk about something called implicit dependancies,
before we leave this video. "Planet", "Please enter all lowercase".
"A", "Please enter all lowercase". "Aa". "Please enter a word without repeating letters."
OK now, I think this is actually guiding me quite nicely. If I enter nothing, it
says a six letter word. If I enter a, it says a six letter word. If I enter aa, it says
don't enter repeating letters. But the order in which it gives me these
errors is determined by the order of the if statements in the check guess
validity. OK. So, we actually
want to be able to change this order around. There's absolutely no reason that we have to
stick to this order. If this order is vital, for example, we can only pass isograms
into IsLower or something like that, so these have to be done in order.
Then, we have something called in implicit dependancy. What's an implicit dependency? Implicit
means suggested, though not directly expressed. A dependency means reliant on
something else. So, "an implicit dependency is when it's not completely clear that one thing
depends on another." "For example the order of the checks in CheckGuess
Validity()" and we don't want that. We've just arbitrarily, pretty much, come up
with this order, and it should only have one side effect.
It could have the side effect that your code works, and that would be a really bad
side effect. If your code doesn't work, with these things in any order, then these
methods are not sufficiently self contained. You know how we went to an effort to make sure that
IsIsrogram works for all types of strings? Well, it's the same thing for
IsLowercase. One way of testing IsLowercase would actually be to do
a block exclude here, with a forward-slash star,
and then here, we could go a star forward-slash and that would comment all
this stuff above.
Does it work with a blank string? Yes! Does it work with a backslash
0, the null character? Yes! Does it work with a mix of characters?
Yes! "Please enter a word without repeating letters". Does it work with just six
random letters? Yes!
Good! So, you see what I've done there! I've commented out the check of the isogram, to
make sure that IsLowercase works on it's own. And it's important that
all of these methods actually work on there. And I'm not going to go through in detail but I want to get
the point across, that none of these should depend on the other one having been executed
above, and we should always be able to change the order of if checks
like this. For example, when doing performance profiling, we might find the thing that happens
most often should be put at the top, to save the rest of the checks being done.
OK, so that's implicit dependencies, we want to avoid them. The second thing about
this, which is implicitly happening which is not
totally clear unless you think about it, but I'm comfortable with it, is that it's changing the feedback you
give to the user. It's changing the way in which we guide the user
towards putting the right thing in. What's wrong with that? Well, it has repeating letters but it's
also too short. If I wrote "aad", then it's
also repeating letter, but how about "And"? Too, short! Yeah,
a n d all lowercase. It's kind of a design decision, but I only want
to give them one piece of guiding information at a time. In this case, this is absolutely fine, it
very quickly guides them toward entering something that we want, so we're pretty much there
with this game. So, congratulations if you got this one done, and I'll see you soon!