Welcome to Difficulty
and Play Testing! In this video. we're going to create a facility
to map the length of the words to the maximum number of
tries. so that we can change our hidden word quickly and easily and have an appropriate number
of tries. And we're going to discover what that appropriate number of tries is
by doing some more play testing. and that is effectively what is called
play tuning. tuning the difficulty of our game. Now. why do we want to tune the difficulty
of our game? Well. if you do a Google image search for "flow channel". you'll get a bunch
of different results but most of them will be relevant. So. here's an example of the diagram! Let's
imagine we start off with a low challenge and a very low word length. If we just
increase the word length. without adjusting the number of tries.
then the game could get too difficult. If you had to say a three letter word with three tries
but then you went up to a ten letter word with only three tries. it would just create anxiety. it'd
be nearly impossible to play. Similarly. if we just increased the number of tries too
high. without increasing the word length. then we are going to just get a very
boring game. You don't need 100 tries to guess a 3 letter word.
So. the idea of the flow channel is you balance those two. So. as our word gets
longer the challenge goes up. Then. we need to also
increase the number of tries. so that as the player's skill goes up.
they can increase the word length. up at the challenge axis.
and still stay in flow. Otherwise. as their skills goes up
and they feel like increasing the word length. then the challenge won't actually
get any higher. or it'd get high too fast. if
the number of tries doesn't change. I hope that makes sense. It's relatively
simple. you just need to be careful about what's on each axis. The basic point is to
keep it fun. by keeping it challenging.
So. we are really on the home straight here. but there's one glaring omission
which is there is no difficulty tuning whatsoever. We
have a six letter isogram. in this case. and I've arbitrarily set my number of tries
to three. which is. of course. impossibly difficult. So. let's
implement a very simple system. so when we change the word we change the
number of tries. And I'm going to help you implement that now.
So. guess what we could use? We could use a map again. right!
So. how are we going to do that? Well. where would we code this?
Well. under GetMaxTries() would make sense. right. where we implement
GetMaxTries. which we declare here and then implement
right here. as a simple return. Why don't we make that a little
more complex and use another map. So. I'm going to move it down. just above the Reset() method.
just for simplicity. I'm going to remind myself that this thing at the top here
is the "default
constructor". because it's quite easy to say. why do we need that. let's get rid of it! No no. that is the
default constructor. it's called when the object is created. And here's the method.
So. rather than returning max tries. why don't we flesh this guy out a little bit.
How about we make another TMap. and how about it's of type
int32 to int32.
And we call it. something like. WordLength
ToMax
Tries; nice and descriptive. And we can actually use
something here called Braced Initializer Syntax. So. rather than
going through and doing inserts. there is a syntax in C++ which
uses braces to initialize. Now. you can actually use braces to
initialize this anywhere. You could. for example. instead of say int32 Max_Tries
= 3. you could say = braces 3. or you could
leave out the =. It's pretty redundant when it comes to single elements
like this. although it is considered by many to be good practice.
but when it comes to a collection of things like this. like a map
of the WordLength to the maximum tries.
this is going to be a really easy way to initialize this. Let me show you
how we do it! So. I'm going to start assuming that the
shortest word we have is say three. and I'm just going to give them all five
tries. because it's going to be your challenge to find a reasonable mapping. So. for a four
letter word we'll give them five tries and for a five letter word we'll give
them five tries and for a six letter word we'll give them five
tries. Very boring. of course. you wouldn't do this. but it's a starting
point. I'm trying to get the data structure in place. If you've got that in place.
that maps the WordLength to the MaxTries. WordLength Max
Tries. WordLength MaxTries. Then. you can. with a bit more consistent
spacing. very simply return this. of course.
We can just return now.
small r. WordLength
ToMaxTries. Remember. use square brackets to access the elements.
and then. we're going to call upon My
HiddenWord.length().
Can you see what we're doing there? We're passing in. we're accessing the element
by this first pair in the mapping.
by the WordLength. and it will return us this here. So now.
GetMaxTries does that. Fantastic! So. with a six letter word. well with
all of them we're expecting a return value of five tries.
which we get there. If I was to change this to 15 or something conspicuous.
as a test. then I get 15 tries!
And if I was to say go back down to a
five letter word. I like planet because it makes so many sub-words. plane and plan.
Here you go. 5! So. it does appear to be reading this properly. and it's a very simple method.
and. of course. what it means is we no longer need here to
have MyMaxTries. We just don't need that.
as data anymore. because the data is stored here right inside the method
that returns the number of tries. It's the only place we need it. so let's keep it
tight. right next to where we use it. and then. we never see it again and we never have access to it
again. So. similarly down here. we don't need a constant for MyMaxTries.
We don't even need that there. so we can just go
HIDDEN_WORD. HIDDEN_WORD. MyCurrentTry. that's the initialization.
All of the stuff about getting max tries is here. and we've
simplified our code. removing lines actually. whilst still
improving the functionality. So. pretty cool! What I want you to do now
is to. map your word length to your max tries. Populate your word length max tries
map. and write the code I just wrote. if you haven't done it already. Do more play
testing. to find the sweet spot for each word length. Ideally with a couple of different
people. What we want here is the word length
determines the difficulty of the game. and then. at a given word length. like five letters.
it's a fixed difficulty. In the next version of the game. in the next section.
we may add another dimension. so that at a given word length you can even choose the number of tries.
but for now. let's keep it simple. Do this for at least four to six letter words.
map at least four to six. I'm probably going to map three to seven letter words.
Optionally. but this is only a bonus option and only if you're really comfortable with what you're doing. let the
user select their word lengths. You could have a map of words. right?
You could say. if we have a four letter word it's this and a five letter word it's this and a six letter word it's the other.
But I'm not even going to show you the solution to that. so unless you're confident and you want to test it
yourself. by having it work then don't do it.
but if you want an extra challenge go ahead and do that and test it works yourself. It's using all existing
knowledge. So. see you in a moment!
Welcome back! So. through playing the game multiple times. all be it with my wife who's
quite good at these games. I came up with 4 tries is enough for a 3 letter word.
7 tries is enough for a 4 letter word. You need about 10
tries. I think. for a 5 letter word. Maybe 15
tries. when you get to a 6 letter word. and I think finally. we'll
just go for a 7 letter word. at which point I haven't spent a lot of time testing this one.
but I think 20 tries may be enough. So. here we have a map!
Great! And let's just check "plane". Well. let's just
work through "plan". PLA should come out at 3. I'm only going to test a couple of these.
4 rather. Yeah. 3 letter word gets 4 tries.
that's correct! And let's just go up a couple p l a n
e. that's 5. It should give me 10!
And it does. 10 tries! Let's also make sure that those 10 tries
work. so p l a n. I don't know. k or something. "plank"
"plank" "plank" "plank". I should have done this in the shorter one. I'm going to do
a shorter one. But frankly. is there any need? So. my
temptation there is to go and test that the game ends. but the game will end and I'm
going to stay confident in that. because we have only changed the
inside of GetMaxTries(). which still returns an int32 and all of the other logic hasn't
changed. So. I'm confident it'll work. and I'm not even going to test it. Is
that a good practice. isn't that? Is that a bad practice? Difficult to say right. because
we are very confident that we've only made a local change here.
In a commercial product. you may have automated tests in place. which would check this
for you. What is the correct kind of gut feel here?
The gut feel is. if you're in doubt check it. So. because that's what
I've said. I am going to go and check it now. but I'm going to go and check it with a three letter word and make sure
we only get four tries. p l a... No. p l d.
p l d. p l d. p l d. p l d.
and don't play again! Great! I'm going to leave this as
"plane" I think and that's enough! So. fantastic! We now have a difficulty
table or at least a way of selecting different word lengths. At least hard
coding different word lengths. As I said. it was a optional extra for you to ask the user for
word length. and you would have to create a couple more methods to map word lengths to
given words. So. well done. and I'll see you in a moment!
=======
Welcome to Difficulty
and Play Testing! In this video, we're going to create a facility
to map the length of the words to the maximum number of
tries, so that we can change our hidden word quickly and easily and have an appropriate number
of tries. And we're going to discover what that appropriate number of tries is
by doing some more play testing, and that is effectively what is called
play tuning, tuning the difficulty of our game. Now, why do we want to tune the difficulty
of our game? Well, if you do a Google image search for "flow channel", you'll get a bunch
of different results but most of them will be relevant. So, here's an example of the diagram! Let's
imagine we start off with a low challenge and a very low word length. If we just
increase the word length, without adjusting the number of tries,
then the game could get too difficult. If you had to say a three letter word with three tries
but then you went up to a ten letter word with only three tries, it would just create anxiety, it'd
be nearly impossible to play. Similarly, if we just increased the number of tries too
high, without increasing the word length, then we are going to just get a very
boring game. You don't need 100 tries to guess a 3 letter word.
So, the idea of the flow channel is you balance those two. So, as our word gets
longer the challenge goes up. Then, we need to also
increase the number of tries, so that as the player's skill goes up,
they can increase the word length, up at the challenge axis,
and still stay in flow. Otherwise, as their skills goes up
and they feel like increasing the word length, then the challenge won't actually
get any higher, or it'd get high too fast, if
the number of tries doesn't change. I hope that makes sense. It's relatively
simple, you just need to be careful about what's on each axis. The basic point is to
keep it fun, by keeping it challenging.
So, we are really on the home straight here, but there's one glaring omission
which is there is no difficulty tuning whatsoever. We
have a six letter isogram, in this case, and I've arbitrarily set my number of tries
to three, which is, of course, impossibly difficult. So, let's
implement a very simple system, so when we change the word we change the
number of tries. And I'm going to help you implement that now.
So, guess what we could use? We could use a map again, right!
So, how are we going to do that? Well, where would we code this?
Well, under GetMaxTries() would make sense, right, where we implement
GetMaxTries, which we declare here and then implement
right here, as a simple return. Why don't we make that a little
more complex and use another map. So, I'm going to move it down, just above the Reset() method,
just for simplicity. I'm going to remind myself that this thing at the top here
is the "default
constructor", because it's quite easy to say, why do we need that, let's get rid of it! No no, that is the
default constructor, it's called when the object is created. And here's the method.
So, rather than returning max tries, why don't we flesh this guy out a little bit.
How about we make another TMap, and how about it's of type
int32 to int32.
And we call it, something like, WordLength
ToMax
Tries; nice and descriptive. And we can actually use
something here called Braced Initializer Syntax. So, rather than
going through and doing inserts, there is a syntax in C++ which
uses braces to initialize. Now, you can actually use braces to
initialize this anywhere. You could, for example, instead of say int32 Max_Tries
= 3, you could say = braces 3, or you could
leave out the =. It's pretty redundant when it comes to single elements
like this, although it is considered by many to be good practice,
but when it comes to a collection of things like this, like a map
of the WordLength to the maximum tries,
this is going to be a really easy way to initialize this. Let me show you
how we do it! So, I'm going to start assuming that the
shortest word we have is say three, and I'm just going to give them all five
tries, because it's going to be your challenge to find a reasonable mapping. So, for a four
letter word we'll give them five tries and for a five letter word we'll give
them five tries and for a six letter word we'll give them five
tries. Very boring, of course, you wouldn't do this, but it's a starting
point, I'm trying to get the data structure in place. If you've got that in place,
that maps the WordLength to the MaxTries. WordLength Max
Tries, WordLength MaxTries. Then, you can, with a bit more consistent
spacing, very simply return this, of course.
We can just return now,
small r, WordLength
ToMaxTries. Remember, use square brackets to access the elements,
and then, we're going to call upon My
HiddenWord.length().
Can you see what we're doing there? We're passing in, we're accessing the element
by this first pair in the mapping,
by the WordLength, and it will return us this here. So now,
GetMaxTries does that. Fantastic! So, with a six letter word, well with
all of them we're expecting a return value of five tries,
which we get there. If I was to change this to 15 or something conspicuous,
as a test, then I get 15 tries!
And if I was to say go back down to a
five letter word. I like planet because it makes so many sub-words, plane and plan.
Here you go, 5! So, it does appear to be reading this properly, and it's a very simple method,
and, of course, what it means is we no longer need here to
have MyMaxTries. We just don't need that,
as data anymore, because the data is stored here right inside the method
that returns the number of tries. It's the only place we need it, so let's keep it
tight, right next to where we use it, and then, we never see it again and we never have access to it
again. So, similarly down here, we don't need a constant for MyMaxTries.
We don't even need that there, so we can just go
HIDDEN_WORD, HIDDEN_WORD, MyCurrentTry, that's the initialization.
All of the stuff about getting max tries is here, and we've
simplified our code, removing lines actually, whilst still
improving the functionality. So, pretty cool! What I want you to do now
is to, map your word length to your max tries. Populate your word length max tries
map, and write the code I just wrote, if you haven't done it already. Do more play
testing, to find the sweet spot for each word length, Ideally with a couple of different
people. What we want here is the word length
determines the difficulty of the game, and then, at a given word length, like five letters,
it's a fixed difficulty. In the next version of the game, in the next section,
we may add another dimension, so that at a given word length you can even choose the number of tries,
but for now, let's keep it simple. Do this for at least four to six letter words,
map at least four to six. I'm probably going to map three to seven letter words.
Optionally, but this is only a bonus option and only if you're really comfortable with what you're doing, let the
user select their word lengths. You could have a map of words, right?
You could say, if we have a four letter word it's this and a five letter word it's this and a six letter word it's the other.
But I'm not even going to show you the solution to that, so unless you're confident and you want to test it
yourself, by having it work then don't do it,
but if you want an extra challenge go ahead and do that and test it works yourself. It's using all existing
knowledge. So, see you in a moment!
Welcome back! So, through playing the game multiple times, all be it with my wife who's
quite good at these games, I came up with 4 tries is enough for a 3 letter word,
7 tries is enough for a 4 letter word. You need about 10
tries, I think, for a 5 letter word. Maybe 15
tries, when you get to a 6 letter word, and I think finally, we'll
just go for a 7 letter word, at which point I haven't spent a lot of time testing this one,
but I think 20 tries may be enough. So, here we have a map!
Great! And let's just check "plane". Well, let's just
work through "plan". PLA should come out at 3. I'm only going to test a couple of these,
4 rather. Yeah, 3 letter word gets 4 tries,
that's correct! And let's just go up a couple p l a n
e, that's 5. It should give me 10!
And it does, 10 tries! Let's also make sure that those 10 tries
work, so p l a n, I don't know, k or something, "plank"
"plank" "plank" "plank". I should have done this in the shorter one. I'm going to do
a shorter one. But frankly, is there any need? So, my
temptation there is to go and test that the game ends, but the game will end and I'm
going to stay confident in that, because we have only changed the
inside of GetMaxTries(), which still returns an int32 and all of the other logic hasn't
changed. So, I'm confident it'll work, and I'm not even going to test it. Is
that a good practice, isn't that? Is that a bad practice? Difficult to say right, because
we are very confident that we've only made a local change here.
In a commercial product, you may have automated tests in place, which would check this
for you. What is the correct kind of gut feel here?
The gut feel is, if you're in doubt check it. So, because that's what
I've said, I am going to go and check it now, but I'm going to go and check it with a three letter word and make sure
we only get four tries. p l a... No, p l d,
p l d, p l d, p l d, p l d,
and don't play again! Great! I'm going to leave this as
"plane" I think and that's enough! So, fantastic! We now have a difficulty
table or at least a way of selecting different word lengths. At least hard
coding different word lengths. As I said, it was a optional extra for you to ask the user for
word length, and you would have to create a couple more methods to map word lengths to
given words. So, well done, and I'll see you in a moment!
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1:Unreal/Section2/BC38 Difficulty & Play Tuning.srt