Hey. so huge congratulations on getting through
section 2. You've completed over 6 hours of content. you've done more than 30 challenges.
and we haven't even really explored Unreal at all yet!
This is just the tip of the iceberg! So. I hope now that you feel
prepared for when we go into Unreal. that when we open up our
scripts that Unreal is going to provide us with. you've got enough understanding of C++
that it's not going to scare you off for life. So. what I would
like you to do is. make sure you share your code with other students. That's really important!
Improve the game. It would be great if you could just spend a little bit of time. right now. just
making a few little tweaks to the game. maybe providing a list of words.
Maybe allowing the user to select the word length. Whatever you like.
just do something different to what I've taught you. because that initiative that
willingness to go that step further is going to make a lot of difference to you. And what we're going to do
next. in the next section. is take what we've built in terms of the Bull Cow
Game class and it's header file. and actually build around that
and modify that inside the engine and make a 3D
driven game inside Unreal. So. I'm looking forward to seeing you in the next section.
My suggestion is that you start the next section right away.
and that way. you're more likely to come back and carry on swiftly.
=======
Hey, so huge congratulations on getting through
section 2. You've completed over 6 hours of content, you've done more than 30 challenges,
and we haven't even really explored Unreal at all yet!
This is just the tip of the iceberg! So, I hope now that you feel
prepared for when we go into Unreal, that when we open up our
scripts that Unreal is going to provide us with, you've got enough understanding of C++
that it's not going to scare you off for life. So, what I would
like you to do is, make sure you share your code with other students. That's really important!
Improve the game. It would be great if you could just spend a little bit of time, right now, just
making a few little tweaks to the game, maybe providing a list of words.
Maybe allowing the user to select the word length. Whatever you like,
just do something different to what I've taught you, because that initiative that
willingness to go that step further is going to make a lot of difference to you. And what we're going to do
next, in the next section, is take what we've built in terms of the Bull Cow
Game class and it's header file, and actually build around that
and modify that inside the engine and make a 3D
driven game inside Unreal. So, I'm looking forward to seeing you in the next section.
My suggestion is that you start the next section right away,
and that way, you're more likely to come back and carry on swiftly.
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1:Unreal/Section2/BC40 Section Wrap-up.srt