So, Hi and welcome back!
In this section, we're going to be building a block breaking
game, in the style of Arkanoid and Breakout.
So, we're looking forward now to moving away from text based
stuff and moving into visual games, which is
what really this is all about. So, it's a very
simple breakout game, but it's actually really good fun and
very instructive, in how we use the Unity Editor.
So, what are we actually going to be learning then? Lots of things,
2D collisions and destroying objects, when things get
hit either once or many times, or you're going to be triggering
sound effects. Boing sounds and crack
sounds and that sort of thing. I encourage you to get your microphone out and make your own.
It's so much more fun if you do, actually, if you make
crazy sound effects yourself, from recording from your mic, it's so much more
fun. Or use your kids, child labor
is always good fun! I certainly use my daughter for my
prototype. Responding to mouse input, you'll be
actually responding to the mouse, for the first time.
We'll talk a little bit about automated play testing, so
we can check that the game is stable at high speeds.
Loads of stuff! That's actually really cool right, because
you're creating a little piece of
AI that sits in your game and plays, instead of the player, and kind
of irons out all the bugs to make sure that everything is working fine.
And it's always fun to see your game play itself. Yes exactly!
There's something quite fun about that! You're going to be a lot more confident
with the Editor, operating in 2D. We're going to be putting a lot of bricks
together, building walls, and things.
And again, you're going to have an opportunity to create something
that you can be very creative with. Go ahead! Make more levels,
add your own levels, again build them and
share them with the community on Udemy, and also on
www.completeunitydeveloper.com. Yeah, it's always fun to see
what levels people come up with! There's always so much cool stuff that people
create and we never expect. We
come and see these levels, that have been created by you
guys, and we're like, oh this is so cool! So, please do
create your own stuff and share it, because that's awesome! Awesome!
So, good luck, let's dive in, and get it done!