Hey guys! So. at this stage in the course
we're going to need some 2D assets. for Block
Breaker. so I've teamed up with here with
Michael my friend and 3D artist. [Michael
Says: Hey Guys!] And are making. over in another
Udemy course. the Complete Blender Creator
Course. and what we're going to be able to
do over there is make 3D models but it's not
just about making 3D models. Of course once
you've got a 3D model. you can make 2D sprites
from it. How would that happen Mikey? Well.
if you imagine a 3D model. let's grab this
here. so we've got a lovely phone here. now
you can angle it at a certain area and then
take a photo of it. and then. use that as
a sprite in your game. That's my daughter
on the screen of the phone. by the way. So.
you could get some really realistic looking
2D assets. by taking 3D assets and photographing
them effectively. from a particular direction.
Yes. exactly! So. this is one point in this
course. where you may want to consider diving
over to Blender and learning that in parallel.
Within 2 or 3 hours of the course. you will
be able to make very basic 2D assets. for
your game. So. if you're interested in that.
then it's udemy.com/blendertutorial. and of
course because you have got this far in the
course. I've put a special coupon for you.
so make good note of this. it is UnityStudentSpecial.
So. udemy.com/blendertutorial and then. put
in the coupon UnityStudentSpecial and you'll
get the best price that we're going to be
offering. on this course. so I hope you'll
decide to join us over there. Take care guys
and hopefully see you soon!