Hey! So. let's get stuck into Block Breaker! So. it's going to look
something like this. by the time we've finished. What are we going to do
this lecture? Well. let's take a look! We're going to
research the brick sizes. Plan our game space.
We're going to find an appropriate image. edit up
our sprites. and then. create a new Unity project and
import our three sprites. our Whole Brick.
And then. we're also going to have a Left Hand Brick
and a Right Hand Brick. If we look at a picture of a brick
wall. what do we get?
I'm going to go for Images.
I'm going to go for Search Tools.
Labeled for Reuse with Modification.
and then. look at one of these images. So. that is entirely
whole bricks. That's obviously an insulated double skinned wall.
but if you look at old fashioned walls. like this. then they have
whole bricks and half bricks. This one over here may be a
better example. Whole brick. half brick. whole brick. half
brick. and these half bricks are actually laying side on.
We're going to want both of these. because if you want to build
any sort of wall. actually. you need half bricks. because
otherwise how do you finish it? You don't want to stack whole
bricks on top of each other. it's not as strong. So. we're going
to need some half bricks. so our mission is to make whole bricks and
half bricks. Decide what size we want. and then how big
out game space is going to be.
So. let's take a look at some examples of like previous
Arkanoid games. How many blocks wide are they? 1. 2. 3. 4.
5. 6. 7. 8. So. I think that's going to be 16
or 15 blocks wide. In that example.
look at a different one. This one here will do.
1. 2. 3. 4. 5. 6. 7. 8.
I think that's going to be 15 blocks wide. So. 15
or 16 blocks wide is quite nice.
as far as I'm concerned. So.
finding the right image. Typical
Arkanoid had about 14. 15. 16 blocks.
There's a Wikipedia article on
brick images. if you care. you can look up brick sizes on
Wikipedia and find out what countries have
different brick sizes. I'm going to pull up
for about an aspect ratio of
128 by 40 pixels. So.
it gives me a 3.2 aspect ratio.
And it turns out that if you go 128 pixels
wide. then 16 blocks wide
is the same as an iPad Air screen. 2048.
There's a little star there. because actually I'm going to need
128 by 41 or it doesn't work properly. in the grid
system. when we get to Unity. So. your mission is
to go to Google.
type in Brick Wall. and then. look for an appropriate
brick wall image. Now. what's an appropriate image? Well. I said
that on the next slide. actually. I've used
Google Images. I filtered for "reuse with modification".
and I'm looking for a brick that has some texture.
that is even and that is taken from straight
on. And then. I'm going to crop that out to
128 by 41. so let's take a look! This
wall is even. It's taken from pretty much straight
on. although to my eye it's going down hill. It is going down hill.
to the left. so that's not ideal. But it's got no
texture. The bricks have no texture. so they're rubbish. These ones.
plenty of texture. plenty of character. but they're too uneven
to work in a gird system. This one here.
probably going to work. That type of thing would be fine. So.
if that one is going to work. let me show you how I would
doing it. View the image and save it.
somewhere. That's fine! Now. when you open
that image. I'm just using Preview on a Mac. it's going to come up like this.
And what I've done is I've just zoomed
in. found a brick that's
barely even and got some texture. and chopped it out like so.
taking about half the mortar on
either side. top and bottom. and then.
cropping the brick out like so. So. that's stage
1. The next stage is to Desaturate the brick. so
whatever tool you're using. turn the Saturation right down.
so that you can recolor the brick very easily. in the
program later. And now. it's just too dark. we want a
light brick. So. turn your Exposure up
with the appropriate Contrast. so there's not too much
detail. That's too much texture and that's too little
texture. So. you get some middle amount of texture.
And then. you might want to fiddle with the image a little bit. so
the mortar around the outside is a little more clear. Here we've got a
shadow. which looks funny. So. I've done this
already. and I've come up with this full brick pattern for me. which
seems to tesselate well with other bricks. The mortar isn't perfect
white and that's good. it makes it look more natural.
but it's got pretty clear mortar around the edges and it's precisely.
sizewise.
128 pixels wide
by 41 high. Excuse the weird 41.
Why 41 instead of 40? I actually don't know
why that works out. I was aiming for
128 divided by 40. which gives you a nice even 3.2
aspect ratio. You'll see why that matters
in Unity later. For some reason. we need an extra pixel. So. for the sharp
students. maybe when we get to that bit you can write
on the discussions and tell my why. I don't know why.
So. the next thing we need to do. once we've got an entire brick like this.
a whole brick is... Let's just look at the slides.
So. we desaturate
it so we can change its color later and we have.
The texture makes the bricks look better. You'll see that when we
get them into Unity. We want to create
new images for left and right bricks. so I showed you
left and right bricks. Let's now show you how we do new
images for those. So. what I've done is I've just cropped
at precisely 64 by 41 pixels.
There. half of it. copy that.
and make a new image from the clip board.
And what you get here is something that's nearly what we need.
That's nearly a right brick. The problem is. if you put this
right brick against another brick. it's going to look horrible because it's got no mortar
on the left. So. a very easy way to get mortar on the left
is to copy the mortar that's already there.
two pixels of it just two pixels.
copy and paste it back onto the image. and just put it on the left hand side.
And that actually works out really well! That is now
a pretty good right hand half brick. So. what I want you to do is
save yourself a right hand half brick. that's my one.
and a left hand half brick
and a full brick. So. the full brick is 128 by
41. Obviously the left brick is 64 by 41.
and the right brick will be the same dimensions.
So. save all three of those. which is a great
start. and ensure the mortar looks
half descent. You can always adjust these later OK.
so you don't have to get these looking right just now. How do you know
what looking right means. until you start placing
blocks next to each other. So. don't stress. just get your first version of you
images. and then. once they're in Unity
you can adjust them very easily and they will instantly update.
So next. we're going to create a new project and
import our bricks. So. we're going to go into
Unity. Here's a challenge for you! Just go into Unity. create a new project.
call it Block Breaker. and then. I want you to import all three
brick images into a folder called Sprites.
And then. save your scene as Level_01.
in Scenes. So. go ahead and do
what's on the screen now. Pause the video and come back when
you've done that. and I'll show you how I did it.
Alright. none of this is rocket science. Let's get over
to Unity. If you're anything like me. you'll still
have Number Wizard UI opened. You may not. it doesn't matter.
The point is we're going to create a new project. It's a
2D project.
We decide where we want it. In my case. in my
repositories. I'm going to create a new folder called Block
Breaker. This will then go at the same level as all of these. I'm
selected on Repos. I'm calling it Block Breaker.
and it'll go at this level. No packages.
2D. Create Project.
Unity will restart.
Fantastic! Now. I want to go and get my images. so where are they?
In my case. they're in my Finder. and
that's a good question.
You will find them. from the downloads. I have them in
my prototype here.
Sprites. And I want the right brick. the
left brick. and the full brick. and I want to bring those into
Unity. Fine! Then.
you're going to create yourself a folder and call it Sprites.
Pop them in. to be neat from the beginning.
Make a new folder.
I call mine underscore Scenes. because
_Scenes is a folder we're going to access very frequently.
and scenes. sprites. and scripts end up looking so
similar that this is a great way of keeping them separate.
The final thing to do is just save. because we have an untitled scene.
So. you save. File and Save. What are
we going to call it? Well. I'm going to call mine Level_01. the first level.
The very final thing is. you put Level_01
into the _Scenes Folder. and there we go. we have
_Scenes with Level_01 in it.
We have Sprites
with our three sprites in it. our whole
brick. our left brick. and our right brick.
and we're good to go! We can save the scene.
It's already done! Save the project if we like. and
we're in good shape! So congratulations. you have
done everything that we needed to do. and we are ready to start
building blocks!
=======
Hey! So, let's get stuck into Block Breaker! So, it's going to look
something like this, by the time we've finished. What are we going to do
this lecture? Well, let's take a look! We're going to
research the brick sizes. Plan our game space.
We're going to find an appropriate image, edit up
our sprites, and then, create a new Unity project and
import our three sprites, our Whole Brick.
And then, we're also going to have a Left Hand Brick
and a Right Hand Brick. If we look at a picture of a brick
wall, what do we get?
I'm going to go for Images.
I'm going to go for Search Tools,
Labeled for Reuse with Modification,
and then, look at one of these images. So, that is entirely
whole bricks. That's obviously an insulated double skinned wall,
but if you look at old fashioned walls, like this, then they have
whole bricks and half bricks. This one over here may be a
better example. Whole brick, half brick, whole brick, half
brick, and these half bricks are actually laying side on.
We're going to want both of these, because if you want to build
any sort of wall, actually, you need half bricks, because
otherwise how do you finish it? You don't want to stack whole
bricks on top of each other, it's not as strong. So, we're going
to need some half bricks, so our mission is to make whole bricks and
half bricks. Decide what size we want, and then how big
out game space is going to be.
So, let's take a look at some examples of like previous
Arkanoid games. How many blocks wide are they? 1, 2, 3, 4,
5, 6, 7, 8. So, I think that's going to be 16
or 15 blocks wide. In that example,
look at a different one. This one here will do.
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8.
I think that's going to be 15 blocks wide. So, 15
or 16 blocks wide is quite nice,
as far as I'm concerned. So,
finding the right image. Typical
Arkanoid had about 14, 15, 16 blocks.
There's a Wikipedia article on
brick images, if you care, you can look up brick sizes on
Wikipedia and find out what countries have
different brick sizes. I'm going to pull up
for about an aspect ratio of
128 by 40 pixels. So,
it gives me a 3.2 aspect ratio.
And it turns out that if you go 128 pixels
wide, then 16 blocks wide
is the same as an iPad Air screen, 2048.
There's a little star there, because actually I'm going to need
128 by 41 or it doesn't work properly, in the grid
system, when we get to Unity. So, your mission is
to go to Google,
type in Brick Wall, and then, look for an appropriate
brick wall image. Now, what's an appropriate image? Well, I said
that on the next slide, actually. I've used
Google Images, I filtered for "reuse with modification",
and I'm looking for a brick that has some texture,
that is even and that is taken from straight
on. And then, I'm going to crop that out to
128 by 41, so let's take a look! This
wall is even. It's taken from pretty much straight
on, although to my eye it's going down hill. It is going down hill,
to the left, so that's not ideal. But it's got no
texture. The bricks have no texture, so they're rubbish. These ones,
plenty of texture, plenty of character, but they're too uneven
to work in a gird system. This one here,
probably going to work. That type of thing would be fine. So,
if that one is going to work, let me show you how I would
doing it. View the image and save it,
somewhere. That's fine! Now, when you open
that image, I'm just using Preview on a Mac, it's going to come up like this.
And what I've done is I've just zoomed
in, found a brick that's
barely even and got some texture, and chopped it out like so,
taking about half the mortar on
either side, top and bottom, and then,
cropping the brick out like so. So, that's stage
1. The next stage is to Desaturate the brick, so
whatever tool you're using, turn the Saturation right down,
so that you can recolor the brick very easily, in the
program later. And now, it's just too dark, we want a
light brick. So, turn your Exposure up
with the appropriate Contrast, so there's not too much
detail. That's too much texture and that's too little
texture. So, you get some middle amount of texture.
And then, you might want to fiddle with the image a little bit, so
the mortar around the outside is a little more clear. Here we've got a
shadow, which looks funny. So, I've done this
already, and I've come up with this full brick pattern for me, which
seems to tesselate well with other bricks. The mortar isn't perfect
white and that's good, it makes it look more natural,
but it's got pretty clear mortar around the edges and it's precisely,
sizewise,
128 pixels wide
by 41 high. Excuse the weird 41.
Why 41 instead of 40? I actually don't know
why that works out. I was aiming for
128 divided by 40, which gives you a nice even 3.2
aspect ratio. You'll see why that matters
in Unity later. For some reason, we need an extra pixel. So, for the sharp
students, maybe when we get to that bit you can write
on the discussions and tell my why. I don't know why.
So, the next thing we need to do, once we've got an entire brick like this,
a whole brick is... Let's just look at the slides.
So, we desaturate
it so we can change its color later and we have.
The texture makes the bricks look better. You'll see that when we
get them into Unity. We want to create
new images for left and right bricks, so I showed you
left and right bricks. Let's now show you how we do new
images for those. So, what I've done is I've just cropped
at precisely 64 by 41 pixels.
There, half of it, copy that,
and make a new image from the clip board.
And what you get here is something that's nearly what we need.
That's nearly a right brick. The problem is, if you put this
right brick against another brick, it's going to look horrible because it's got no mortar
on the left. So, a very easy way to get mortar on the left
is to copy the mortar that's already there,
two pixels of it just two pixels,
copy and paste it back onto the image, and just put it on the left hand side.
And that actually works out really well! That is now
a pretty good right hand half brick. So, what I want you to do is
save yourself a right hand half brick, that's my one,
and a left hand half brick
and a full brick. So, the full brick is 128 by
41. Obviously the left brick is 64 by 41,
and the right brick will be the same dimensions.
So, save all three of those, which is a great
start, and ensure the mortar looks
half descent. You can always adjust these later OK,
so you don't have to get these looking right just now. How do you know
what looking right means, until you start placing
blocks next to each other. So, don't stress, just get your first version of you
images, and then, once they're in Unity
you can adjust them very easily and they will instantly update.
So next, we're going to create a new project and
import our bricks. So, we're going to go into
Unity. Here's a challenge for you! Just go into Unity, create a new project,
call it Block Breaker, and then, I want you to import all three
brick images into a folder called Sprites.
And then, save your scene as Level_01,
in Scenes. So, go ahead and do
what's on the screen now. Pause the video and come back when
you've done that, and I'll show you how I did it.
Alright, none of this is rocket science. Let's get over
to Unity. If you're anything like me, you'll still
have Number Wizard UI opened. You may not, it doesn't matter.
The point is we're going to create a new project. It's a
2D project.
We decide where we want it. In my case, in my
repositories. I'm going to create a new folder called Block
Breaker. This will then go at the same level as all of these. I'm
selected on Repos, I'm calling it Block Breaker,
and it'll go at this level. No packages,
2D, Create Project.
Unity will restart.
Fantastic! Now, I want to go and get my images, so where are they?
In my case, they're in my Finder, and
that's a good question.
You will find them, from the downloads, I have them in
my prototype here,
Sprites. And I want the right brick, the
left brick, and the full brick, and I want to bring those into
Unity. Fine! Then,
you're going to create yourself a folder and call it Sprites.
Pop them in, to be neat from the beginning.
Make a new folder.
I call mine underscore Scenes, because
_Scenes is a folder we're going to access very frequently,
and scenes, sprites, and scripts end up looking so
similar that this is a great way of keeping them separate.
The final thing to do is just save, because we have an untitled scene.
So, you save, File and Save. What are
we going to call it? Well, I'm going to call mine Level_01, the first level.
The very final thing is, you put Level_01
into the _Scenes Folder, and there we go, we have
_Scenes with Level_01 in it.
We have Sprites
with our three sprites in it, our whole
brick, our left brick, and our right brick,
and we're good to go! We can save the scene.
It's already done! Save the project if we like, and
we're in good shape! So congratulations, you have
done everything that we needed to do, and we are ready to start
building blocks!
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1:Unity/Section5/01-Creating-A-2D-Brick-Sprite.srt