So congratulations! You now have the .png
file you need. Hey guys! So, in this video
we're going to take a quick look at an image editing program, called
Gimp. I'm going to explain what it is and how we use it.
We're going to do some cropping and resizing, adjusting
color and exposure, a tiny bit with brushes,
and then, finally saving our .png. So, this
is going to help you with your Block Breaker project. So
firstly, what is Gimp? Well, let's take a look.
If you go to gimp.
org, gimp.org like this, you'll see a page something like
this. Now, it is important that you go to gimp.org,
not some other website, so if you Google for this
then be careful, because some people have had trouble by going
via sites like Source Forge, in particular.
But make sure you're getting it from the source, which is
gimp.org. And well, you may
as well go ahead and get the download going now, while I tell you about it.
So, I am going to find some
way to download it from now. This is not a
commercial piece of software and that's one of the benefits. It's completely
free, which is fantastic! One of the disadvantages
is it's not quite as comforting, when you try and download it,
as its main competitor, which would be Adobe Photoshop.
The problem with Adobe Photoshop, of course, is the price,
but look at Adobe's prices now. They're trying to
push you down a monthly rout, even if you say I just want
Photoshop, and I want to pay in advance, it's going to be
200 pounds or $300, just for one year.
So, in my mind that's a bit steep, and you can do
quite a lot, practically everything that you can do
in Photoshop you can do in Gimp. But you're going to
have to A work out how to download and install it, and B
just get used to it being a little bit less conventional and a bit
harder to get used to. That's what the purpose of this video is though.
Cool! So, let's try downloading. I'm going to download Gimp from
.org. Now, I'm trying to get a Torrent File here, so that's
not very helpful, so instead I'm going to go to this link,
and that's better, now I'm getting a .dmg file,
which is what I want on the Mac. Now, I can't see the Windows Down-
load page and on Windows it's going to look a little different, but I'm sure
you'll get around it. You'll find an alternative link and you'll put a download recent
version of Gimp; at the time of recording that's version
2.8. You can find out more about Gimp on
Wikipedia, "wiki gimp" for example, and
the first article that comes up will tell you about
Gimp and about its history. It's been going a long time, it's been out
for what, 19 years now.
Yeah, 19 years, so
it's quite a thing. It's open source community driven,
and I think it's well worth the effort. Personally, I really
hated it when I started using it, but I think it's well worth the effort getting
to use it. So, we're going to download Gimp. In my case, that's going
to take a few minutes, so I will cut to the end of that
download now, and I will see you in a moment. Now, if for any
reason you just want to get on and don't want to have to learn how to use Gimp,
then simply skip this video and use the
assets we provided, a couple of lectures ago, at the beginning of
this section. OK, so here I am,
my file has downloaded. So this is a Mac install,
but a PC install will be your standard PC
install. So, I get a file, put it in my Applications,
I Eject my Disk Image,
one it's finished copying I don't
think there will be anything different about the PC install from any other standard
PC package, by the way. So, obviously if you're on
Mac, this is helpful, but if you're on a PC just carry
on, install as usual.
OK, quick tip. If you are on the Mac, it may not open
for you, because of your security settings, so when you get to
Gimp you may get, depending on your security settings, a
complaint saying this is from an unknown publisher.
Here you go! "Are you sure you want to open it?" Well, you may
have this, it depends on your security settings. If you're really stuck,
go to System Preferences, and then, go to Security,
up here is Security and Privacy, and you should
have a message here saying Gimp,
at the requested opening or change your security setting
to "Apps can be downloaded from: Anywhere". Anyway, that's where you need
to go on a Mac. So, here we are, Gimp
has opened, but this is one of the first jarring things. Gimp is
open here, but what's going on? I've got
windows behind. So, one of the first things you're going to want to
do, when you're getting started, and here's the slide for getting started,
is: "Set Windows > Single Window
Mode." Set Windows, Single Window, so go to
Windows and then Single Window. And that's a little bit more
familiar. Now, we can maximize this window and we've got something approximating
to what we used to. Also, if you're ever unsure, we
can go to Edit and Undo, as in any normal program.
Alright, so we're on our way. Let's have a look at what's next!
So next,
we're going to look at selecting things in Gimp. Alright, so it's going to be
Tools, Selection Tools, Rectangular.  So firstly,
let's find ourselves an image.
So over here, this is something like the brick wall I was using in
the course. So, if we just save that image,
pop it in my Downloads for the moment,
and then, back into Gimp. File, Open,
you can just go Open, and then, look for
Ben, Downloads, the Brick_wall,
and open it. Great we've got that! So now, how are we
going to make a selection and chop out, so here
Rectangular Select Tool. It's either up there or if it's not there,
and sometimes tools are all over the place in Gimp, then you can just go to
Tools, Selection Tools, Rectangular Select,
which is the R Key, in my case. Great! So then, you can
drag a rough region like this, that's great.
If you then left drag, in the middle of the box, the region will move
and the corners will change the size. If you want to zoom in,
then it's View, Zoom In, and it'll
show you your keyboard shortcut as well. So, I'm going to use my keyboard
shortcut, Shift and +, and I'm just going to get
roughly around one of these bricks, really quickly. So, this
is how you select anyway, in Gimp. I'm going to do all this rather
rough and quite quickly, because I just want to give you the idea and the
tool, so that you can play with it and
do your own graphics in your own time. So, if you accidentally
add to the selection like that, as I said Control Z to undo,
it's not a problem. You can move around the image,
if you need to. Then, you can just use
the Cursor Keys, is one of the easiest ways to do that, just to scroll
around and then again, you get your Rectangular Select Tool,
highlight an area, and if you're this zoomed in, you can
do it pixel perfect. There you go! So, that is the selection
made for you. So then,
I've showed you how to Zoom. You can move the selection by
dragging in the middle, resize by dragging the corners. Cool! Also,
if you make a real mess with your selections, you can
undo them by just going to Select
None, Select None here. Alright cool!
So, that is how to select. Just
drag a rectangle and adjust a rectangle with a corner.
OK cool! So, what's next? Well, next
we're going to want to crop something out of this image, so
get the selection how you want it, and then, go to Image, Crop to Selection.
So, let's just do that. Image,
Crop to Selection. There you go!
Boom! So, now we have a cropped image. Aright, that's
much better. Then, what else might you want to do? Well,
you might want to resize this image. Then, you use Image Scale
to do that, and then, we may want to chop off
the longest bit. So, let's imagine we want to get this image to
precisely something like one hundred and twenty-
eight by 41 pixels. I think that's what we were aiming
for in the course. So,
let's aim for 128 by 41
pixels. OK so, Image,
Scale Image. Now, when you
do this, have a look. Try 128,
44, so we're busting in the Y direction. That's good!
OK so, that's fine! So, we're going to need to trim
3 pixels off, in the Y direction, that's great. So, 128
by 44, you click Scale, you may need to zoom out of this.
In my case, this is Shift and minus, to do
the Zoom Out. If for any reason it doesn't work,
then just go to your
Zoom Out here.
OK cool! So now, how do you know what size this
new rectangle is going to be. Well, look at the bottom of the screen,
128 by 43,
42, 41. There you go!
We can move it down 1 and that,
if I go crop again, Image,
Crop to Selection, is precisely
128 by 41 pixels.
Put my mouse at the bottom right. Perfect! OK, so that's
good news. Now, the next thing we're going to need to do
is to adjust color and exposure. So,
how do we do that? Well again, you can look back at the slides, which are attached to the front
of the section, but for colors you go to Colors, Hue Saturation.
You can desaturate by dragging the
Saturation down to 0. And then,
when that's done, you can go to Colors, Brightness, Contrast,
and then, you can adjust the Brightness,
which is the black level, B for Brightness, B for Black,
to get the black levels where you want them. And then, the Contrast,
which should really be called white level, and get that where you want it.
Something like that. Alright
cool! And then finally, you might want to grab a brush,
which is over on the left here. You're going to need to find
where your Brush Tool comes up. If you can't find it, go
to Windows,
Dockable Dialogs, and then, Tool Options
here. So, if you can't find your Brush Options,
just Windows, Dockable Dialogs, Tool Options, and you'll get
this thing here. Now, I'm finding that hard to see, so I'm making it bigger,
but if I make it a little bit bigger, you can see I can then
turn the size of this brush down to say 2 pixels. And
at this point, I can brush and change the properties and colors of my
brush, all I like. So, if you want to make some
edits, that's how you do it with a brush.
Cool! So, how do we save this thing and get it into Unity?
I would firstly just save it, just save
full stop. You save it as a .xcf
file, which is the Gimp default file.
This will save all the information. This
dialog is confusing. This thing at the bottom here is a filter
for what's on your screen, so that shows you what you can see,
whereas this select file type is an alternative way
of choosing the file type, and which we're
going by extension here, we could explicitly say .gif.
So, the simple answer is just go Save, and just hit Choose a
Folder, hit Save. And then, that's now saved the .gif
file, the Gimp file rather, that you can come back
to and make changes to later if you want. I would then, separately
export this as a .png, so Export
As. Now, how do you do a
.png? Well again, this All Exported Images, don't be
fooled by it, it's just telling you what you're seeing, so that is just a
filter, for the view. You could come down here, select File Type,
and then, find .png, if
you wanted to. There you go! And that would work!
Or you could leave it on the default, which is By Extension here,
and just type .png on the end and it will
take the file type from the .png.