Hey welcome back! So. before we dive in and start playing with blocks.
we're going to get our Menu System setup. Remember. we want
to get in the habit of having our Menu System setup from the very
beginning. so that we can navigate around the
Start Menu. the Game Screens. and then
onto the final Win Screen. So.
that we really set the president. we wet the standard.
and we've created the structure. So. we're going to go into the
Number Wizard UI and export the menus and
import them into this project. customize the words and fonts.
and then. you're going to wire up the buttons. So. let's
take a look! I'm sitting here in my Block Breaker. that's got almost nothing
in it. It's just got a game scene
and some sprites. I'm going to switch over to
Number Wizard UI. for a moment.
which is in my recent projects. when I go to open the File and Open
Project.
And here we are! So. what I'm going to do from here is. I'm
going to export a package. just like the packages you see in the Unity
Store. And I'm going to say to myself. well what do I need? Well.
I don't need the game. because the Number Wizard UI game is very
different to this game. and I don't need the Number Wizard
Script. because we're not going to be using any of Number Wizard's
behavior here. But I do want the LevelManager
and I do want the Start Screen and the Win Screen. because they're our starting
point for my next Menu System. so let's
do that. Make yourself a package somewhere.
It doesn't matter what you call it. Menus if you like.
OK. and you get menu.unitypackage
here. OK fantastic! So. what are
we going to do with that? Well. back over to
our Block Breaker project.
Once there. we go to
Assets and Import Package. and it's a Custom Package.
Don't we feel clever. we've made our own custom package already.
And we import menu.unitypackage.
the thing we just exported.
Well. we're going to import everything. because we just chose what we're going to export.
So. it's literally just copying and pasting between projects. at this stage.
Now. we need a little tidy up. In our previous
project. we called scenes. scenes with an S without an underscore.
Now. look how confusing that is. Scenes. Scripts. and Sprites. That's why
I prefer the underscore version . but immediately you seen an inconsistency
like that. sort it out. Take your Start and Win
Menus. put them in your _Scenes Folder. and Delete.
Oops... That's
better! Delete that one. Fantastic! So now. what
we have is we have three scenes. Start Menu.
Win Screen. and Level_01. and then. we have
the Scripts Folder with LevelManager in it and the same sprites we had
before. Let's get to work changing these scenes. one at a time.
Into your Start Menu! So. the first thing that's
inappropriate about this Start Menu is the fonts. We need to change
the font. in my opinion. so let's do that first!
I'm going to go to a website called
www.dafont.com a great place to get free fonts. and I'm just
going to search for block and see what we get.
Now. scroll down and find a font that
is readable and appropriate feeling.
It's entirely up to you what font you use. I'm
going to plump for the first one that looks good. I think I'm going to go for
BM Block here. So. download your font from
dafont. There it is. bm_block!
And then. just take the .ttf file from that.
and drop it into Unity
Assets. Now. I'm going to
make myself a tidy immediately. by
creating a folder called Fonts and putting the bm_block font in it.
Great! Now. you can select all of
your Text Elements under you Hierarchy. Start Menu.
and you can hold down Shift. click on Title. and keep
Shift held down. and click on the Quit button.
Then. you'll be able to select all of these elements or do them one at a time.
The way you change the fonts. one in the Inspector under the
Text Script component where it says Font.
click the little circle and choose your
bm_block. Great! Now. it's just a question of moving
things around to see your
taste and changing the Font Size again.
to taste. "Welcome to Number Wizard!"
If you get corruption like I've just got. play the game.
and then. un-play and you'll find that it should go away.
So. Start is clearly too big.
Quit I'm going to make a little smaller this time. so it's a bit more balanced.
OK. how does that
look? Let's hit the play button.
OK fantastic! Now. let's change the text.
Of course. you may be better changing
the text before you change the Font Size; then. you won't have to keep going in
circles. Tell them what they need to do.
"Smash all the blocks to win!" If you need to resize the Text Element.
of course. click on it. This is the Subtitle. Use the UI Element
Tool or the T Button on the keyboard. resize it.
and then. use it's snapping ability to decentralize.
OK. let's take a look at that!
Fantastic! Alright. let's give the same treatment
now to the other scene. which is the Win Scene. You'll
immediately see. oh that feels different and looks different.
OK. let's just change the font on both. so we're consistent.
Great! "I guessed right" is
no longer appropriate. so let's change that! "You
beat Block Breaker"
Get the font right .and then our
play button. again it's too big. "Play Again"
but that's looking about right.
We can move elements around. if we want to.
OK. let's play and see! "You beat Block Breaker"
OK fantastic! Now.
we have achieved most of our objectives! What I want you to do now
is to wire up these buttons. as a challenge. so that
they work. So. let's just dive into the presentation.
Here! Get the Start button to go to Level_01.
Add a temporary "Game Over"
button to Level_01. so that when we click it that
Game Over Button goes to the Win Screen.
Then. change the "Play Again" button to go back to
the Start Menu. So. you'll be able to navigate from the
Start Scene into a Game Screen. which will just be a blue background
with nothing in it. where you can click "Game Over".
And you'll go over to the Win Screen. and then. on the Win Screen you can click Play Again.
to restart the whole thing. and test that you can navigate fully. So.
pause the video and go ahead and get yourself confident
doing that now.
Awesome and welcome back! So. let's
take a look at how we're going to do this.
Hopefully you've already done it. Are you doing the challenges or are you just waiting for me to show you?
I hope you're doing the challenges. [Laughs] So. let's click on the Start Button.
What's wrong with it's script? Well. down at the bottom here.
under the button script on the OnClick event. we're going
to the Game Scene. There is no Game Scene in this game. and we have Level_01.
so that should fix the Start Button.
Let's try it! Start!
OK. Level_01 could not be loaded. because it's not been
added to the Build Settings. That's just fine and expected. Let's go to the
Build Settings. Let's get all of your scenes
visible and drag all of them into the Build Settings. and then.
set the order to be logical. i.e. Start Menu comes first.
You may have to click. it's a bit
awkward. There you go! Start Menu to Level_01 to Win Screen.
Fantastic! You don't need to build. You can just exit the Build
Settings. but now. when you come to run this you should
find that. when you click Start. it goes to the Level_01. which is
fantastic! And also. when you click Quite. nothing
will happen. but you will get a log down here on the bottom left saying "Quit
requested". Fantastic! So. the other scene you needed to modify was
your Win Scene. Saving as we go! Play again!
It should simply go to the Start Menu.
so actually by the looks of it you don't need to do anything.
It already works. Start! OK
fantastic! Now. the final thing you need to do is. on Level_01.
I said we needed a button that is going to allow us
to transition onto
the Win Screen. So. how are we going to do that? Well.
I'm going to create a UI Element.
and I'm going to make it a button.
What is this type of Canvas? Let's take a look! It's a Screen
Space Overlay. so it's going to cross the entire screen. That's OK!
And then. for now. we can just have a very ugly button somewhere. Where
shall I stick it? Bottom right. say for now. Let's just call it
Game Over.
So. once you've named the text on your button.
go back to the Button itself. under Hierarchy. Canvas. and
then Button. And we're going to need to
deal with the OnClick even. Now. the way
that the other scenes. let's take a look at say the Win Screen.
The way that they deal with that. let's look at this button. this Play Again
Button. What you have here is you
have a LevelManager passed in. you see. and then. it uses LevelManager
.LoadLevel. So. what we're missing is a LevelManager on
our Level_01 scene. So. let's put it on! Copy LevelManager
from here. that's one way of doing it. or you could recreate it.
Look. what is it at the end of the day? It's just a thing with a Level
Manager Script against it.
Paste into your Hierarchy
there. So. we now have a LevelManager in this scene.
Back to our Game Over Button. We can now
drag the Level Manager onto
the Game Over Button's OnClick event.
Now. we'll be able to choose LevelManager.LoadLevel
and we can call it Win Screen! Fantastic!
Just time to test! Let's click play! Game Over takes
us to there. "You beat Block Breaker". Great! Play Again!
We could Quit! We'll just expect to get a quit request
logged! You click Start. you go to a very basic and ugly
Game Screen. you click Game Over. Fantastic! Our Menu
System is functioning and customized to look like
Block Breaker. Congratulations! See you soon!
=======
Hey welcome back! So, before we dive in and start playing with blocks,
we're going to get our Menu System setup. Remember, we want
to get in the habit of having our Menu System setup from the very
beginning, so that we can navigate around the
Start Menu, the Game Screens, and then
onto the final Win Screen. So,
that we really set the president, we wet the standard,
and we've created the structure. So, we're going to go into the
Number Wizard UI and export the menus and
import them into this project, customize the words and fonts,
and then, you're going to wire up the buttons. So, let's
take a look! I'm sitting here in my Block Breaker, that's got almost nothing
in it. It's just got a game scene
and some sprites. I'm going to switch over to
Number Wizard UI, for a moment,
which is in my recent projects, when I go to open the File and Open
Project.
And here we are! So, what I'm going to do from here is, I'm
going to export a package, just like the packages you see in the Unity
Store. And I'm going to say to myself, well what do I need? Well,
I don't need the game, because the Number Wizard UI game is very
different to this game, and I don't need the Number Wizard
Script, because we're not going to be using any of Number Wizard's
behavior here. But I do want the LevelManager
and I do want the Start Screen and the Win Screen, because they're our starting
point for my next Menu System, so let's
do that. Make yourself a package somewhere.
It doesn't matter what you call it, Menus if you like.
OK, and you get menu.unitypackage
here. OK fantastic! So, what are
we going to do with that? Well, back over to
our Block Breaker project.
Once there, we go to
Assets and Import Package, and it's a Custom Package.
Don't we feel clever, we've made our own custom package already.
And we import menu.unitypackage,
the thing we just exported.
Well, we're going to import everything, because we just chose what we're going to export.
So, it's literally just copying and pasting between projects, at this stage.
Now, we need a little tidy up. In our previous
project, we called scenes, scenes with an S without an underscore.
Now, look how confusing that is, Scenes, Scripts, and Sprites. That's why
I prefer the underscore version , but immediately you seen an inconsistency
like that, sort it out. Take your Start and Win
Menus, put them in your _Scenes Folder, and Delete.
Oops... That's
better! Delete that one. Fantastic! So now, what
we have is we have three scenes, Start Menu,
Win Screen, and Level_01, and then, we have
the Scripts Folder with LevelManager in it and the same sprites we had
before. Let's get to work changing these scenes, one at a time.
Into your Start Menu! So, the first thing that's
inappropriate about this Start Menu is the fonts. We need to change
the font, in my opinion, so let's do that first!
I'm going to go to a website called
www.dafont.com a great place to get free fonts, and I'm just
going to search for block and see what we get.
Now, scroll down and find a font that
is readable and appropriate feeling.
It's entirely up to you what font you use. I'm
going to plump for the first one that looks good. I think I'm going to go for
BM Block here. So, download your font from
dafont. There it is, bm_block!
And then, just take the .ttf file from that,
and drop it into Unity
Assets. Now, I'm going to
make myself a tidy immediately, by
creating a folder called Fonts and putting the bm_block font in it.
Great! Now, you can select all of
your Text Elements under you Hierarchy, Start Menu,
and you can hold down Shift, click on Title, and keep
Shift held down, and click on the Quit button.
Then, you'll be able to select all of these elements or do them one at a time.
The way you change the fonts, one in the Inspector under the
Text Script component where it says Font,
click the little circle and choose your
bm_block. Great! Now, it's just a question of moving
things around to see your
taste and changing the Font Size again,
to taste. "Welcome to Number Wizard!"
If you get corruption like I've just got, play the game,
and then, un-play and you'll find that it should go away.
So, Start is clearly too big.
Quit I'm going to make a little smaller this time, so it's a bit more balanced.
OK, how does that
look? Let's hit the play button.
OK fantastic! Now, let's change the text.
Of course, you may be better changing
the text before you change the Font Size; then, you won't have to keep going in
circles. Tell them what they need to do.
"Smash all the blocks to win!" If you need to resize the Text Element,
of course, click on it. This is the Subtitle. Use the UI Element
Tool or the T Button on the keyboard, resize it,
and then, use it's snapping ability to decentralize.
OK, let's take a look at that!
Fantastic! Alright, let's give the same treatment
now to the other scene, which is the Win Scene. You'll
immediately see, oh that feels different and looks different.
OK, let's just change the font on both, so we're consistent.
Great! "I guessed right" is
no longer appropriate, so let's change that! "You
beat Block Breaker"
Get the font right ,and then our
play button, again it's too big. "Play Again"
but that's looking about right.
We can move elements around, if we want to.
OK, let's play and see! "You beat Block Breaker"
OK fantastic! Now,
we have achieved most of our objectives! What I want you to do now
is to wire up these buttons, as a challenge, so that
they work. So, let's just dive into the presentation.
Here! Get the Start button to go to Level_01.
Add a temporary "Game Over"
button to Level_01, so that when we click it that
Game Over Button goes to the Win Screen.
Then, change the "Play Again" button to go back to
the Start Menu. So, you'll be able to navigate from the
Start Scene into a Game Screen, which will just be a blue background
with nothing in it, where you can click "Game Over".
And you'll go over to the Win Screen, and then, on the Win Screen you can click Play Again,
to restart the whole thing, and test that you can navigate fully. So,
pause the video and go ahead and get yourself confident
doing that now.
Awesome and welcome back! So, let's
take a look at how we're going to do this.
Hopefully you've already done it. Are you doing the challenges or are you just waiting for me to show you?
I hope you're doing the challenges. [Laughs] So, let's click on the Start Button.
What's wrong with it's script? Well, down at the bottom here,
under the button script on the OnClick event, we're going
to the Game Scene. There is no Game Scene in this game, and we have Level_01,
so that should fix the Start Button.
Let's try it! Start!
OK, Level_01 could not be loaded, because it's not been
added to the Build Settings. That's just fine and expected. Let's go to the
Build Settings. Let's get all of your scenes
visible and drag all of them into the Build Settings, and then,
set the order to be logical, i.e. Start Menu comes first.
You may have to click, it's a bit
awkward. There you go! Start Menu to Level_01 to Win Screen.
Fantastic! You don't need to build. You can just exit the Build
Settings, but now, when you come to run this you should
find that, when you click Start, it goes to the Level_01, which is
fantastic! And also, when you click Quite, nothing
will happen, but you will get a log down here on the bottom left saying "Quit
requested". Fantastic! So, the other scene you needed to modify was
your Win Scene. Saving as we go! Play again!
It should simply go to the Start Menu,
so actually by the looks of it you don't need to do anything,
It already works. Start! OK
fantastic! Now, the final thing you need to do is, on Level_01,
I said we needed a button that is going to allow us
to transition onto
the Win Screen. So, how are we going to do that? Well,
I'm going to create a UI Element,
and I'm going to make it a button.
What is this type of Canvas? Let's take a look! It's a Screen
Space Overlay, so it's going to cross the entire screen. That's OK!
And then, for now, we can just have a very ugly button somewhere. Where
shall I stick it? Bottom right, say for now. Let's just call it
Game Over.
So, once you've named the text on your button,
go back to the Button itself, under Hierarchy, Canvas, and
then Button. And we're going to need to
deal with the OnClick even. Now, the way
that the other scenes, let's take a look at say the Win Screen.
The way that they deal with that, let's look at this button, this Play Again
Button. What you have here is you
have a LevelManager passed in, you see, and then, it uses LevelManager
.LoadLevel. So, what we're missing is a LevelManager on
our Level_01 scene. So, let's put it on! Copy LevelManager
from here, that's one way of doing it, or you could recreate it.
Look, what is it at the end of the day? It's just a thing with a Level
Manager Script against it.
Paste into your Hierarchy
there. So, we now have a LevelManager in this scene.
Back to our Game Over Button. We can now
drag the Level Manager onto
the Game Over Button's OnClick event.
Now, we'll be able to choose LevelManager.LoadLevel
and we can call it Win Screen! Fantastic!
Just time to test! Let's click play! Game Over takes
us to there. "You beat Block Breaker". Great! Play Again!
We could Quit! We'll just expect to get a quit request
logged! You click Start, you go to a very basic and ugly
Game Screen, you click Game Over. Fantastic! Our Menu
System is functioning and customized to look like
Block Breaker. Congratulations! See you soon!
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1:Unity/Section5/02-Add-Your-Menu-System.srt