So. hi and welcome to this video.
in which. we're going to talk to you about Statics and Singletons.
So. let's first talk about Statics. Statics
are proper variables that are properties of
classes and not instances. What does that mean? Well.
you've already met Static Variables.
In the course. we've got Mathf.PI. so.
Ben. talk a little bit more about Mathf.PI and how it's the
property of math instead of an instance
of math. Sure so this is your class. right. this is our template.
that makes instances. so if we're
going to make an instance of anything a ball. a music player.
a GameObject whatever. then that's this little guy comes out of the
mold and goes and lives it's life. as an instance coming out
of this mold. It may make a different instance. with a different property.
Math f is a class
that has methods on it. like .Clamp
and dot. all sorts of different things. and one of the things it has is
a property called .PI. And because PI is PI.
whoever asked the question. it doesn't make sense to store PI on
these little guys. onto these instances of our mass. We have a
static class. and Pi is just in one place. sitting here.
on the template itself. So basically.
Static Variables are variables that
are attached to the mold. to the class itself.
And if one of these guys wants to know about PI. these
instances. the children of this class. can
say PI. From outside.
if this guy was not created from this mold but is created over
here as a child. let's say of a different class. he needs to say
Mathf.PI. And you don't need an
instance. any of these Mathf type instances. anywhere in the
scene. This guy can still say Mathf.PI. and
you can access that anywhere. So. that's what a static is.
pretty handy. And we actually go and
use statics to create something that's called a
Singleton. Now. what is a Singleton. Well. a Singleton
is the idea that you have a single instance
of a particular object. So now. we've got
this mold. that can create any number of objects.
but we want it to create only one and that is
called a Singleton. when you only have one instance of an object. In our case.
we're going to be using the music player. Here it is! We've got a
MusicPlayer class and we have a static
variable. that's how we implement the Singleton pattern. We use
the static variable called Instance. and remember this is a
property of the class. And we're basically saying.
this is the one instance of MusicPlayer. we don't ever
want another one. So. when you create the first MusicPlayer.
here he is. so this red guy is the first MusicPlayer.
So. you put it in the mold. take it out of the mold. and you get a MusicPlayer.
And I've got the MusicPlayer here. and then. I'm going to set
that instance variable. that Instance.
the static variable named Instance.
to point to my red block. And now. when
I create the next one. it comes along and says.
what is the .Instance? It says. if Instance.
Now. if the Instance is null. then it must have been the
first one. and it would have claimed. just as Brice is showing you.
that the second time Instance is not null. And because
Instance isn't null. it must be something. it's pointing to that guy.
and that guy is responsible for the music management. so you don't
need to be. So. this music manager. that spawns in the scene. destroys
itself. Bye bye! And if in another scene or another
area. you've got another music manager that tries to create
itself. it goes. if Instance. Well. we do have an instance.
it's still the red one. so I destroy myself.
And that's how you use the Singleton pattern. using
static variables in Unity. Hope it's
clearer. Bye.
=======
So, hi and welcome to this video,
in which, we're going to talk to you about Statics and Singletons.
So, let's first talk about Statics. Statics
are proper variables that are properties of
classes and not instances. What does that mean? Well,
you've already met Static Variables.
In the course, we've got Mathf.PI, so,
Ben, talk a little bit more about Mathf.PI and how it's the
property of math instead of an instance
of math. Sure so this is your class, right, this is our template,
that makes instances, so if we're
going to make an instance of anything a ball, a music player,
a GameObject whatever, then that's this little guy comes out of the
mold and goes and lives it's life, as an instance coming out
of this mold. It may make a different instance, with a different property.
Math f is a class
that has methods on it, like .Clamp
and dot, all sorts of different things, and one of the things it has is
a property called .PI. And because PI is PI,
whoever asked the question, it doesn't make sense to store PI on
these little guys, onto these instances of our mass. We have a
static class, and Pi is just in one place, sitting here,
on the template itself. So basically,
Static Variables are variables that
are attached to the mold, to the class itself.
And if one of these guys wants to know about PI, these
instances, the children of this class, can
say PI. From outside,
if this guy was not created from this mold but is created over
here as a child, let's say of a different class, he needs to say
Mathf.PI. And you don't need an
instance, any of these Mathf type instances, anywhere in the
scene. This guy can still say Mathf.PI, and
you can access that anywhere. So, that's what a static is,
pretty handy. And we actually go and
use statics to create something that's called a
Singleton. Now, what is a Singleton. Well, a Singleton
is the idea that you have a single instance
of a particular object. So now, we've got
this mold, that can create any number of objects,
but we want it to create only one and that is
called a Singleton, when you only have one instance of an object. In our case,
we're going to be using the music player. Here it is! We've got a
MusicPlayer class and we have a static
variable, that's how we implement the Singleton pattern. We use
the static variable called Instance, and remember this is a
property of the class. And we're basically saying,
this is the one instance of MusicPlayer, we don't ever
want another one. So, when you create the first MusicPlayer,
here he is, so this red guy is the first MusicPlayer.
So, you put it in the mold, take it out of the mold, and you get a MusicPlayer.
And I've got the MusicPlayer here, and then, I'm going to set
that instance variable, that Instance,
the static variable named Instance,
to point to my red block. And now, when
I create the next one, it comes along and says,
what is the .Instance? It says, if Instance.
Now, if the Instance is null, then it must have been the
first one, and it would have claimed, just as Brice is showing you,
that the second time Instance is not null. And because
Instance isn't null, it must be something, it's pointing to that guy,
and that guy is responsible for the music management, so you don't
need to be. So, this music manager, that spawns in the scene, destroys
itself. Bye bye! And if in another scene or another
area, you've got another music manager that tries to create
itself, it goes, if Instance. Well, we do have an instance,
it's still the red one, so I destroy myself.
And that's how you use the Singleton pattern, using
static variables in Unity. Hope it's
clearer. Bye.
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1:Unity/Section5/03b-About-Statics-And-Singletons.srt