Hey. welcome back! So. the great news is
we've got music persisting through out scenes. The bad
news is. we accumulate music players every time we
arrive back at the Start scene. Take a look.
[Background Music Playing]
[Background Music Playing] Yeah. so you think the music sounds a bit funny.
It does. and that's because we've got two music players. and actually.
if we carried on going around the loop. we would continue
accumulating music players and making a real audio
mess. So. what are we going to do about that?
Well. this is where we need to introduce you to something called statics.
That's going to be the best way to solve it. so let's take a look. I'm
going to tell you how a static can help us here. Let me tell you. it's going to
prevent us from having duplicate music players. What I
think one of the best things you could do to start. is to click on this
link or just search for statics in Unity.
and look at their documentation. They have got some
pretty good docs. in general. They are not in context.
not project based most of them. but they do talk sense and they say
the right things. So. here you go. you've got a document and a video
here on statics. Why don't you stop the video now and
watch that Unity 3 to 4 minute video on statics.
[Temporary Silence]
Cool! So. hopefully you watched that. Hopefully you're still awake. If
you are and you're still alive and have the will to live. let's carry on!
Ahh! We're going to now prevent duplicate music players. using
basically what you've just learned from
Unity's videos. If you really want a challenge. go ahead
and do it yourself. If you're a confident coder. then why don't you
try and us the concept of statics. Modify
your MusicPlayer Script. and actually prevent
these duplicate music players from happening.
Why not just have a go! Let me give you a hint! Hint number 1 is you
only need to make changes to your MusicPlayer.cs
script. Hint number 2. you're going to be adding
no more than 10 lines of code. Hint number 3.
you're going to be using a static. So. why don't
you have a go at doing that yourself. If you're not confident
doing it. let's take a look at how we're going to do it. So. start on
your MusicPlayer.cs script.
Where is it? Here it is1
Let's go into it. So. the problem we have is that when
we get back to the Start Scene. we have the previous
MusicPlayer. that's persisting. and then
the Start Scene itself instantiates a second MusicPlayer.
Not very good. so what are we going to do? Well. we're going
to make a static. What is a static? It's a class variable.
it is something where you want to consider using a static
when you say to yourself. there's only going to ever be one of these things.
There's only ever going to be one MusicPlayer in the game. We only
want one MusicPlayer in the game. So. we're going to make something called a static.
Here we go. MusicPlayer is the type. so
it's defined in the same way. I'm going to call it instance.
Why am I going to call it instance? Well. you'll kind of see
in context why we're call it instance. I'm actually going to initialize
it to null. because at the start. on your Start
Scene. there will be no defined things
called instance. Let's see how this pans out
alright. So. here's some logic for you. We go.
if instance not =
to null. And that's saying if
a MusicPlayer instance exists.
any MusicPlayer instance exists. what do we do?
Well. we're going to destroy ourselves.
Destroy (gameObject); and let's log to
the Console that we've done that. ("Duplicate
music player self-destructing!");
which is kind of fun!
Alright. now let's stay with me
for a minute. Let's continue. so it should come clear in concept.
context even. Else. what do we do?
Well. if... Well. let's just show you what we do. We
are still going to do GameObject.DontDestroyOnLoad.
but there's one more thing we need to do. Sorry. I've pasted Unity's
docs in there for you. instead of the command. Here it comes.
Boing! There we go! Fantastic!
What we need to do is. else we claim the instance. so
instance = this; So. let's have a
think about this. Let's start. imagine we're playing from our Start
Scene. In fact. not imagine. let's to it. because at the same time we can
test it. We go to Scene Start Menu
and we play. Watch what happens.
Start. game over.
Play Again. log.
duplicate MusicPlayer self-destructing. How many music players in the
Start Scene? 1! Perfect! Let's go through the loop again.
Bopping our head to the music as we go!
Great! So. music player are not accumulating.
and if you check the Console. it has now
logged out twice. that it has self
destructed the MusicPlayer. So. now that we know that it
does work. let's talk about why it works.
Let's just go through in chronological order. We start.
the game starts up. this static thing
called instance of type MusicPlayer is set to null.
The Start method runs. and we're on the Start
Menu. at the beginning of the game. What happened?
Well. it says if instance not = to null. Well. hang on.
instance does equal null. at the moment. we've declared it that way and
defined it that way. So. we're in the else part of the statement.
It immediately claims the instance. it says
instance equals this. This
being this instance of the MusicPlayer is the
global instance. if you like. It is the class level
instance. So. that is now claimed. alright. And
then. it goes ahead and says OK. well don't destroy this instance.
persisted. Fine!
Now. we click Start and we
go into our Game Scene. The Game Scene loads and it goes if
instance not equal to null. Well.
instance now doesn't equal null. Actually. instance is
the MusicPlayer. So. it destroys
MusicPlayer. but actually.
this whole thing doesn't get called on the Game
Scene. because on the Game Scene we have not
got a MusicPlayer to defined in the Unity Editor. But if
we did drop a MusicPlayer into the Game Scene of the
Unity Editor. this code here. this top if
statement would protect us. Shall we do it to try? Let's have a go!
Go to Unity. pop into your
Level1. actually Start on your
Start Menu. grab your Music Player. pop
it into your Level 1.
Now. you've got a Music Player on Level 1. Let's see if our code is resilient.
Start on Start and let's play.
So. we click Start.
and look this is cool. Music Player has
self destructed and we only have one in the game
Scene. So. you see what's happening there. That's great! So.
that's what happened when we got to our Game Scene. Even if
we were to put a MusicPlayer in there obstinately. it would still sell destruct.
Alright. then we get to the Win Screen.
the same thing happens. If we'd dropped it in the Editor it self destructs.
If we haven't dropped it in the Editor. which we haven't
in this case. Let's take a look. There is no Music
Player dropped in the Editor. Then. this code never even
runs. because there is no MusicPlayer.cs Script
in the whole scene. so this code doesn't run. But when we get back
to the Start Menu again. this code does run. and
we get the self destruction happening. In fact. from now on. we're always
going to get the self destruction running. The
only time instance = this runs is the
first time that the script runs.
and it finds that initial Music Player that we
have on the Start Scene and it makes sure that it doesn't destroy
unload and that no others get created.
So. if you didn't fully understand how instances work.
from this video and how statics work. don't worry
too much about it. We're going to be revisiting the concept in the
future. We're going to be talking about Singletons. in the future. which are a
very similar concept. and it will all come clear. So. you're
quite at liberty to just copy my code and enjoy the fact it works.
Hopefully I've explained it clearly enough. and I'll be interested
in your feedback. Write us a note on the discussion. Let us
know. do you at this stage. feel you understand
how we're using statics here. but either way. just carry on and enjoy
the project. We're about to start doing fun stuff!
=======
Hey, welcome back! So, the great news is
we've got music persisting through out scenes. The bad
news is, we accumulate music players every time we
arrive back at the Start scene. Take a look.
[Background Music Playing]
[Background Music Playing] Yeah, so you think the music sounds a bit funny.
It does, and that's because we've got two music players, and actually,
if we carried on going around the loop, we would continue
accumulating music players and making a real audio
mess. So, what are we going to do about that?
Well, this is where we need to introduce you to something called statics.
That's going to be the best way to solve it, so let's take a look. I'm
going to tell you how a static can help us here. Let me tell you, it's going to
prevent us from having duplicate music players. What I
think one of the best things you could do to start, is to click on this
link or just search for statics in Unity,
and look at their documentation. They have got some
pretty good docs, in general. They are not in context,
not project based most of them, but they do talk sense and they say
the right things. So, here you go, you've got a document and a video
here on statics. Why don't you stop the video now and
watch that Unity 3 to 4 minute video on statics.
[Temporary Silence]
Cool! So, hopefully you watched that. Hopefully you're still awake. If
you are and you're still alive and have the will to live, let's carry on!
Ahh! We're going to now prevent duplicate music players, using
basically what you've just learned from
Unity's videos. If you really want a challenge, go ahead
and do it yourself. If you're a confident coder, then why don't you
try and us the concept of statics. Modify
your MusicPlayer Script, and actually prevent
these duplicate music players from happening.
Why not just have a go! Let me give you a hint! Hint number 1 is you
only need to make changes to your MusicPlayer.cs
script. Hint number 2, you're going to be adding
no more than 10 lines of code. Hint number 3,
you're going to be using a static. So, why don't
you have a go at doing that yourself. If you're not confident
doing it, let's take a look at how we're going to do it. So, start on
your MusicPlayer.cs script.
Where is it? Here it is1
Let's go into it. So, the problem we have is that when
we get back to the Start Scene, we have the previous
MusicPlayer, that's persisting, and then
the Start Scene itself instantiates a second MusicPlayer.
Not very good, so what are we going to do? Well, we're going
to make a static. What is a static? It's a class variable,
it is something where you want to consider using a static
when you say to yourself, there's only going to ever be one of these things.
There's only ever going to be one MusicPlayer in the game. We only
want one MusicPlayer in the game. So, we're going to make something called a static.
Here we go, MusicPlayer is the type, so
it's defined in the same way. I'm going to call it instance.
Why am I going to call it instance? Well, you'll kind of see
in context why we're call it instance. I'm actually going to initialize
it to null, because at the start, on your Start
Scene, there will be no defined things
called instance. Let's see how this pans out
alright. So, here's some logic for you. We go,
if instance not =
to null. And that's saying if
a MusicPlayer instance exists,
any MusicPlayer instance exists, what do we do?
Well, we're going to destroy ourselves,
Destroy (gameObject); and let's log to
the Console that we've done that. ("Duplicate
music player self-destructing!");
which is kind of fun!
Alright, now let's stay with me
for a minute. Let's continue, so it should come clear in concept,
context even. Else, what do we do?
Well, if... Well, let's just show you what we do. We
are still going to do GameObject.DontDestroyOnLoad,
but there's one more thing we need to do. Sorry, I've pasted Unity's
docs in there for you, instead of the command. Here it comes.
Boing! There we go! Fantastic!
What we need to do is, else we claim the instance, so
instance = this; So, let's have a
think about this. Let's start, imagine we're playing from our Start
Scene. In fact, not imagine, let's to it, because at the same time we can
test it. We go to Scene Start Menu
and we play. Watch what happens.
Start, game over,
Play Again, log.
duplicate MusicPlayer self-destructing. How many music players in the
Start Scene? 1! Perfect! Let's go through the loop again.
Bopping our head to the music as we go!
Great! So, music player are not accumulating,
and if you check the Console, it has now
logged out twice, that it has self
destructed the MusicPlayer. So, now that we know that it
does work, let's talk about why it works.
Let's just go through in chronological order. We start,
the game starts up, this static thing
called instance of type MusicPlayer is set to null.
The Start method runs, and we're on the Start
Menu, at the beginning of the game. What happened?
Well, it says if instance not = to null. Well, hang on,
instance does equal null, at the moment, we've declared it that way and
defined it that way. So, we're in the else part of the statement.
It immediately claims the instance, it says
instance equals this. This
being this instance of the MusicPlayer is the
global instance, if you like. It is the class level
instance. So, that is now claimed, alright. And
then, it goes ahead and says OK, well don't destroy this instance,
persisted. Fine!
Now, we click Start and we
go into our Game Scene. The Game Scene loads and it goes if
instance not equal to null. Well,
instance now doesn't equal null. Actually, instance is
the MusicPlayer. So, it destroys
MusicPlayer, but actually,
this whole thing doesn't get called on the Game
Scene, because on the Game Scene we have not
got a MusicPlayer to defined in the Unity Editor. But if
we did drop a MusicPlayer into the Game Scene of the
Unity Editor, this code here, this top if
statement would protect us. Shall we do it to try? Let's have a go!
Go to Unity, pop into your
Level1, actually Start on your
Start Menu, grab your Music Player, pop
it into your Level 1.
Now, you've got a Music Player on Level 1. Let's see if our code is resilient.
Start on Start and let's play.
So, we click Start,
and look this is cool, Music Player has
self destructed and we only have one in the game
Scene. So, you see what's happening there. That's great! So,
that's what happened when we got to our Game Scene. Even if
we were to put a MusicPlayer in there obstinately, it would still sell destruct.
Alright, then we get to the Win Screen,
the same thing happens. If we'd dropped it in the Editor it self destructs.
If we haven't dropped it in the Editor, which we haven't
in this case. Let's take a look. There is no Music
Player dropped in the Editor. Then, this code never even
runs, because there is no MusicPlayer.cs Script
in the whole scene, so this code doesn't run. But when we get back
to the Start Menu again, this code does run, and
we get the self destruction happening. In fact, from now on, we're always
going to get the self destruction running. The
only time instance = this runs is the
first time that the script runs,
and it finds that initial Music Player that we
have on the Start Scene and it makes sure that it doesn't destroy
unload and that no others get created.
So, if you didn't fully understand how instances work,
from this video and how statics work, don't worry
too much about it. We're going to be revisiting the concept in the
future. We're going to be talking about Singletons, in the future, which are a
very similar concept, and it will all come clear. So, you're
quite at liberty to just copy my code and enjoy the fact it works.
Hopefully I've explained it clearly enough, and I'll be interested
in your feedback. Write us a note on the discussion. Let us
know, do you at this stage, feel you understand
how we're using statics here, but either way, just carry on and enjoy
the project. We're about to start doing fun stuff!
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1:Unity/Section5/04-Using-Static-Variables.srt