In this video we're going to talk
about what Z depth means, we're going to
discuss the problem and the solution. The problem
we'll have if we don't understand Z depth is, sprites
becoming semi-transparent or invisible or generally
misbehaving, and the solution is to look at the Z
position of the sprites, relative to the background.
So, what is Z depth? Well, Unity is always
a 3D engine, even when switched to 2D.
The Z position of Sprites matters for rendering,
even when you're in a 2D mode, like
we are with this game. And sprites farther from the camera
get rendered first, and then, the
sprites nearer to the camera get rendered after that.
So, let's just quickly look at Unity and just look at where
I'm talking about with the Z depth, in a Canvas Element
or with a standard element, you have the
transform and you have a Z position here. Now, because we've been dealing with
X and Y in 2D, you haven't been paying a lot of attention
to the Z position, but if you were to click your 2D button off,
then, you would notice that actually everything is a 3D
world. And the same goes for, for instance, your camera, which sits
at -10 in Z. So, what
we need to start becoming aware of is, this Z depth.
A typical issue would be that my brick sprites
become semi-transparent, when the ball hits them, or my
paddle changes color when the ball hits it. Now, these are issues you
won't have come across yet in the course, but we've inserted this
video for you because, in our experience, these are things that
students farther down the course have trouble with and I want to
make sure you're prepared for it. So that you don't have
any of these issues, we want to think about the camera being
at -10, is its standard Z distance,
and the background is typically at Z = 0,
like that. Now, a badly placed
sprite would be on the background, at the background's
depth, so when you come to put your background in, in the future lectures,
and come to put a sprite in, you're going to want to bring your sprite
forward a little bit, like that, to maybe minus
5, in between the camera and the background. Now, it won't
appear any larger, because we're using an orthographic camera
and there's no perspective involved, but it does mean that
the sprite will definitely render after the background
and on top of the background.
Another way to do exactly the same thing would be to leave the sprite where it is,
and just to move your background back. And this is my preferred
method, because there's going to be a lot more sprites than there are
background images. There will be a single background image. So, just move your
background back, if you have these problems by adjusting its Z depth to a
more positive number. And that's really all I wanted to say
for this video. It's as simple as that, we just need
to become aware of Z depth, so if you have any of
these problems as we move forward or you miss where I change the Z depth,
or even if I don't change the Z depth, then go ahead and do it yourself.
Experiment and make sure you understand how it works. So, good
luck and I'll see you soon!