Hey. welcome back! So. the focus of this
video is setting up your Play Space.
So. one of the first things we need to decide is
what size is this Play Space? Well. if we go to Google.
and I mentioned before the iPad Air resolution
just is an example target resolution.
also will fit OK on the web. if we downscale.
So. let's look at that. 2048 x
1536. My first question is what's the
Aspect Ratio of that? Have a look. It's 1.333
33333. OK. what you'll notice is it's actually
the same as 800 x 600.
It's also 1.3 reoccurring.
So. 800 by 600 is compatible with that much higher
a resolution. And in fact. when you download your course
assets. you'll find that the Block Breaker Assets
Sprites Folder contains two background images.
This guy here. who's an angry looking robot
or something. which we're going to use for Level 1. and then.
I've just chosen arbitrarily another one. which is 800
x 600. This one is a train track. and it just doesn't matter really. you
choose your own images. But they're both 800 by 600.
So. first job is to get the background image into Unity.
so just simply drag into your
Sprites Folder and there it is.
Once it's in your Sprites Folder. it's just an image. it's simply that.
We have to think a little bit about our
Pixels per unit up here. because
we're going to have 16 blocks wide. as
a total overall game space. And
we have an image. that is 800
Pixels wide. so we want 800 Pixels
to map to 16 World Units.
because we're going to go for one World Unit per block. World
Units. for those of you who don't know. are the position in
Unity's game space. They're what you see in the
transform. over in the Inspector. in the X and
Y. They're held as a floating point value and they are
relative to some arbitrary origin. in the middle
of the Unity World Space. So. this is about
how a certain image in Pixels is
actually going to be scaled and displayed in the World Space.
So. the Pixels
per World Unit we need is 50. Let's try it and see what happens.
So. we go for 50 in here
and Apply. Now. drop your Level
1 background on.
like so.
[background Noise]
There it is! Once you've zoomed in. there is your Level 1 background. If you
double click on it in the Hierarchy. then you will see
it on the screen. Now. the question is. how big is that thing?
On here. let's reset its transform first. so click on the cob
and reset. So. now the Level 1 background is at
the very bottom left of the screen. Let's find
out how big it is. One way of doing this. for example. would be to
grab the Main Camera. and while you've got the Main Camera
open. I just want you to check that the Projection Mode
here on the right hand side is Orthographic
rather than Perspective. An Orthographic
Camera does not take account of how far away
an object is from it. at all.
Whereas a Perspective Camera does. So. it's important for this project
that we're set up with an Orthographic Camera.
Also. while you've got the camera open. I'd like you to check the
Z position of the background image. up at the top right
here. It needs to be in the negative Z. which is
away from you. otherwise it won't be visible to the
camera. So. it doesn't matter what distance it's at. because it's an
Orthographic perspective-less camera. but it does
need to be away from the camera. in the negative Z direction.
OK. so to measure the width
of this Play Space. we move the camera firstly to the left
and have a look at the X position.
and then. move the camera to the right hand side
and you see it's plus 8. Great! So. the image is
16 World Units wide. which is great. I'm going to
rename this. just Background.
and I'm going to stick it up right
below the Main Camera. just for neatness.
Fantastic! So. we have a background that is 16 World Units wide.
The next thing we want to do. I think. is alpha
that background down. which means make it a little bit transparent.
try and make it a little more subtle. So. click on your Color Picker.
and you can leave it at white. so that
it doesn't tint the background but you can drag the alpha down.
so that it just becomes more dim. I'm going to go for
something like that. Just pick something that you like.
That's great! So. we have a subtle background. Now. what's this
thing on here. this annoying thing? That's just its
transform. That is just
where its Anchor Point is. So if we click
on our Background image and go to the Sprite
Editor. it would be better if the Pivot Point of
this image was at the bottom left. So. you can either
drag to the bottom left. being sure it's snapped. or choose here
and Apply.
So. now when you click on your Background. you have
your Transform Tool down a the bottom left like that. which is much more...
Please if for any reason your transform
is showing in the middle of your image. like this.
then it's this button up at the top left here. You have
Center and Global. You may have clicked it across
the center. at some point. so you just click it back to
Pivot. on the left hand side. and you will then see the
transform. at the Pivot Point rather than in the center
of the object. So. the object is the Background.
this is showing the Center. this is now showing the Pivot.
So. that's just a little gotcha! Let's adjust
the camera. so it's roughly the right
size for the play space. Now. you'll notice. you cannot change the
Aspect Ratio of the camera. at the moment. Why not?
Because it's determined by the current size of this Game
Window. If I was to bring my Inspector
in and make the Game Window more square. look back on the scene.
you see it's more square. so that's actually a problem.
We don't want the Camera Aspect Ratio to change.
as we mess around in Unity. so let's lock the
Aspect Ratio of the Game Window now. Click on Game.
At the top left. you'll see a drop-down that says
Free Aspect. Well. we don't want Free Aspect.
we want an Aspect Ratio of 4:3.
which is the same a 1.33333 to 1.
There you go! Fantastic! So. now that is locked. so whatever happens
here. now when we start moving our things around and re-sizing
the Game Window. the aspect of it is locked. So. that's a very useful tool.
Alright. so next we need to get the camera to be exactly
the same size as the background. How are you going to do that? Well.
this is where you need to understand a little bit about what this camera size
means. It's currently. on my screen. set to 7.5.
What does that mean? Well. it's 7.5 World Units
from the center here to the top of the camera.
It's half the height of the Camera Viewport.
So. we need a bit of math again. If our
Play Space is 16 wide.
and we have an Aspect Ratio of 4:3.
then how high is it? Well. we have to do
16 divided by 4
times 3. which tells us the Play Space should be
12 World Units high. Which means
that the camera setting should be a size of 6. half of that.
There you go. perfect! Nearly perfect!
If you set the transform to 8. 6. rather than to 8. 6 point
1. now the camera is perfectly aligned. Look!
Background image. you can see
the image. it has not kind of gizmos around the outside of it.
The Main Camera sits perfectly
over the top of it. Great job! So.
that's it! Now. let's just click play and see what happens.
Well. we see the background. and it's perfectly sitting inside the
camera. and if we detach our Game Tab. then
that is all just working fine.
But the Game Over Button is being a bit weird. it only shows
in some circumstances. so let's
just fix that so we can always see it. And the reason is that. when we've
fixed the Aspect Ratio of the Game.
our button disappeared off. So. just stick it
back in the window. And this is a Screen Space
Overlay. remember. I've specifically left it like this with our
background. tiny in the bottom. to show you that a
Screen Space Overlay just
is relative to the screen. and it doesn't care how big
your actual background and other assets are. So. now
where we see this button. inside the Screen Space Overlay. is where
we will see it when we click the play. Yeah.
It just overlays over the top. We're going to ditch all that stuff soon
anyway. but for now look. you've done great! If we focus back
on our background. we have a background positioned
at the Origin. Just check that. We have its
Pivot Point. at the bottom left. which is sensible.
and we have a camera that is precisely
coincident with what we see there.
So. cool! See you soon!