Hey. welcome back! So. the next thing we need to
do is. add a ball to our scene. I think. and then. we can
pop a ball in the middle here. And we're going to arrange for a little bit of
gravity to pull it down. so that it falls out the bottom of the
play space. So. let's start with that.
So. you've got your assets. in the assets that we gave
you to download. or go and find your own ball image.
My Block Breaker assets are
here. So. a little
simple mini challenge for you. I want you to add this ball to the
play space. as follows.
Number 1. import the ball sprite into the Sprites Folder.
Play with the sensible Pixels Per Unit yourself.
to get the scale of that ball right. and then.
place the ball right in the middle. precisely in the middle of the play
space. So. go ahead. pause the video and do that now.
See you in a second.
Fantastic! So. this is how I'm doing it. I'm popping the ball
in the Sprites Folder. The ball. at the
moment. is just a sprite. Now. we don't know whether 100
is a suitable pixels per unit. so I'm going to drop the
ball where I want it. in the scene. roughly in the middle here and then have a
look. Now. that ball is firstly very not visible
and secondly. not very big. so I'm going to try going
upwards or downwards. with the pixels per world unit.
but if I go less pixels per
unit. that thing will get bigger. and actually let me show you a trick here.
If you hover your mouse over the word Pixels Per World Unit. you'll see that
you can drag left and right. It doesn't have much of an effect here.
because it doesn't update immediately. but that's a useful facility
in the Editor. I'm going to try 50
and apply. There you go. the ball has doubled in
size. I'm actually going to throttle back my background
image a little more. so it's darker.
Ah. there you go. the ball is clearer now.
Fantastic! So. that's stage 1. We
have a ball in the scene. I just want to make it precisely
in the middle. So. what is the middle? Well. explore the space 16
wide by 12 high. so it must
be 8. 6.
Perfect! Ball in the middle of the scene. as planned.
OK. now the next thing we want to do. if we play the game.
you'll notice
that the ball just sits there. We want it to fall
out the bottom of the screen. and actually we want that to trigger the Game Over.
at some point. So. let's start by. how do we make the ball
fall. Well. it needs some physics. it needs to have a component
on it. called a Rigidbody. The first thing I'm going to do is
just rename the ball. with a capital B. just to be tidy.
and then. I'm going to add a component. Physics
2D Rigidbody2D.
What's a Rigidbody? Well. the best way to find out is to look at it.
You can straightaway see that it has to do with its Mass
and its Drag and its Gravity Scale.
What's the mass unit? Well. it's unitless really. but if
you consider that one unit is a kilogram. then that's a
reasonable starting point.
Excuse me. We're not going to worry about drag or angular drag right
now. Gravity Scale of 1.
let's try it let's see what happens. click play.
There it goes! The ball falls
out the bottom of the scene. That's fantastic! So. that is a
great start! So. what we want to do now
is have some way of that ball
triggering the end of the level. rather than us having to
click the Game Over Button.
And while you're here. by the way. you'll notice we have
some work to do on this screen but that's fine.
Rather than clicking Game Over. we want the ball to do that work for us.
So. let's at least get the ball to log to the
Console. when it falls off the bottom of the screen. How are we going to do
that? Well. we need something called a collider. What's
a collider? We're going to cover that in different videos.
in detail. but I'm going to give an overview here. So
firstly. the ball will need a collider on it. It is a
physical body. now it has a Rigidbody. but it has no
collider. Go and find the collider. under Physic 2D.
Circle Collider 2D. if you zoom right in.
I'm rolling my mouse button to do that. you'll see that this is fitted Itself
quite well to the size of the
ball. You could change the radius using that technique perhaps.
I showed you before. you click in the Inspector
on the word Radius and hold the mouse button. Then. move left and right
slowly. and you'll see that the radius changes.
But about 0.2 isn't far off
at all. and that green circle
is the extent of this thing. called a collider.
That's fine. we want it just like that. it's not going to be a trigger actually.
because the ball is going to physically collide with things.
So. the difference with a trigger... Well. let's look at their docs. remember you can hit.
what I just did there was hit the Blue Book. So.
hit the Blue Book. to go to the docs. and it'll tell you.
What's a trigger? Does the collider behave as a trigger? Not particularly
helpful. So. let me tell you what a trigger is. A trigger is
something that is going to ignore the Physics Engine.
OK. the moment you click that. it would no longer collide and
actually appear to hit things. So in the case of the ball. we do want it
to actually hit things and exhibit physics.
So. that's one half of the puzzle. of making this
ball trigger a new level. It's still just going to fall out the bottom. when we click
play. because it's got nothing to
trigger with. Colliders work by hitting other
colliders. In fact. I've got a slide prepared for you.
that talks about colliders. Give me one moment to find that.
There you go! What is a collider? It's a component that
defines "the shape of an object. for the purposes of physical collisions."
"A collider. which is invisible. need not be the exact same shape as the object's."
And there's a link there to Unity's docs. on colliders.
The point is. you need two colliders. so
let's add a second one. Create yourself an
empty GameObject.
I'm going to call it.
LooseCollider. I think.
[Typing Sound]
[Screeching Record Sound] No! That's not how you spell
Lose! That's Loose you numpty. Oh.
well sorry. but it's going to stay like that until the end
of this section. where I will correct it. It's not possible to
change it in every single video. without re-recording the whole lot. which would be
crazy. And at the moment. this is nothing right. This
thing is just a transform. a GameObject.
But we're going to add
to it another component. which is that collider again. This time.
a Box Collider. and this will all come clear in a minute.
Look if we make the size in X 16.
because that's the width of our
play space. and then. if we move this thing
down to a position at the bottom of the screen.
you could put it at a Y of 0. It would probably do.
Preferably. just
below our play space actually. so maybe a Y of minus
a half or something. Maybe even minus
1. depending on the width. the vertical width
of your collider here. Well. actually it doesn't depend. because of where the
anchor is. you can have as big a collider as you like look.
And the anchor point of the collider stays there.
So. I'm going to have a collider that's 16 wide by 1 height
and that sits at a Transform Position of 8. -1 there.
OK. and this one is a trigger.
because we don't want the things staying on this.
Well. actually it kind of. in this case
it doesn't matter. Firstly. let's look at the behavior. what happens to this ball.
Well. in this view you can't see it.
so what we want to do is hit pause. then play.
Now. go back. Now.
once it's playing. make sure you're on the Scene View and un-pause.
You see the ball passes straight through
the bottom of the play space. That's
tricky to see. so what you might need to do is move your Game Tab next
to your Scene Tab. like that. Try this.
watch what happens. The ball passes
straight down through that collider. which is fine. If this
Lose Collider was not of type trigger.
try and see what happens now.
You see it lands on it and just stays
there. So. actually either of those behaviors would work
for this. because at the end of the day all we're trying to do
is trigger the loading of a new level. when this
happens. So. that's an overview
of how we're going to get the ball to trigger the new level. And we'll go
into detail about how we handle it from there. in script
shortly.