Hey. so in this video we're going to explore colliders in
Unity. and let's get rid of the confusion. before it even starts!
Just briefly. before I dive into the details of colliders. why do we even
care about these things? Look they are a super handy part
of Unity. These colliders allow us to
trigger events. like maybe you walk over a door threshold and
the automatic door opens for you. or we can
simulate collisions. like a pool game. or in the case of
Block Breaker the ball bouncing. It's really at the heart of all
physical objects interacting with each other. So. colliders are super cool.
they're super important. and I'm going to explain here
the different types and how they talk to each other. So. as an overview.
what we're going to talk about is if colliders overlap
during a frame. then messages may be passed by the
engine. And we're going to be talking about what message passing is
and go into a little bit of detail about how
all this works in Unity. So. what is message passing?
When two GameObjects with colliders meet.
the engine sends a message to those objects. we intercept those messages
in a script. and then. our script decides what to do next.
You can read more about message passing on Wikipedia. if you're
having trouble getting to sleep. So firstly. what do we mean about two
colliders meeting? Let's take a look at an example in Unity.
Here I have a ball that has a circular collider on it. 2D
circular collider. and here I have a Loose Collider
at the bottom of my play space. which has a Box Collider. And if those two colliders were to
overlap. so they're not touching now. but if the ball was a little
bit lower. like this maybe. then they would overlap. If they overlap during
a frame. and that is an important distinction. because if the ball
is moving really really fast and it jumps right through this thing in a frame. there
will be no collision message passed. But if
there's an overlap during a frame. then a message may get
passed. Why may get passed? Well. let's have a look at
this table here! In most
cases a message is passed. There are some white cells in my table. where
the messages are not passed. Let's look at the general pattern of this table.
Firstly. where did it come from? Well. Unity has this in their docs.
under their Colliders Overview document. Let's take a look at it!
Here it is. lots to read. again. if you're having trouble getting to
sleep. And at the bottom of the page. you've got two tables.
One about messages that are passed when a collision happens.
And another about messages are passed when a trigger happens.
But to me that's confusing. so what we've done is taken that table and
that table. and we've put them on top of each other
to give you that table. which I think is clearer.
So. what I'm saying is that in some situations
the engine will raise a message. and there's two different types of messages it can
pass. One is for a collision. which only happens
in the top-left of the table. where we have non-trigger
colliders interacting with non-trigger colliders.
None of these rows or columns. in the top-left. have the word trigger in them.
The moment you add a trigger to the equation. you're dealing with triggers
not collisions. You can take yourself down or to the right. or down
and right. So. all of these other columns are where one
or either of those objects have trigger set.
What does that mean? Well. let's look in here! Let's look at the Loose
Collider! If that checkbox is ticked. then we're in the territory
of triggers. and if it's un-ticked.
on there and un-ticked on the ball. then
we may be in the territory of collisions.
So. in this case. this is a collision. and the ball will actually.
if it's started off higher. it will fall
and stop when it hits that Loose Collider.
OK. and the message that will get passed
is one of these collision messages.
When the collisions are happening. then physics
is being calculated. Alright. so let's look at that
in action a little bit more. What do we have here? We have a ball
that has a Rigidbody on it. So.
what do these rows and column headers mean? I've got a slide
for you that's going to help disambiguate that!
Here are the types of colliders! It's Static
if it has a collider but no Rigidbody.
The moment you add a Rigidbody. it's a Rigidbody. and if
you make that Rigidbody Kinematic. i.e. it doesn't
move on its own basically. We have to move it. Then. it becomes a Kinematic
Rigidbody Collider. A rule of
thumb is. if it's going to move during the game. slap a Rigidbody on it. and avoid
moving Static Colliders.
because it's very inefficient. So. that's what the rows and
columns of this table mean. So. what do we have when our
ball.. as we're setting it up in our game. falls? Well.
the ball has a Rigidbody on it. and we want its physics to
occur. but what it's going to hit is one of
two things. depending on how we setup our Loose Collider. If our
Loose Collider is a trigger. then it's a Static Trigger Collider. and this
trigger message gets passed down here. And if we decide
that our Trigger Collider is going to be static but not
a trigger. then we get a collision up here.
OK. so let's go back to Unity. Go to your Loose Collider.
and we're going to need to add a component to it. Your ball. by the way.
will be sitting in the middle of the play space.
I just moved this for the sake of argument. So. there you go! You're looking like
that with your ball there and your collider there. Add a component. a new script.
and I'm just going to call it Loose Collider.
Very imaginatively! Now. in that script. I'm going to pop it into
the Scripts Folder. We're going to need to intercept
one of two messages. Now. don't be scared about these message things. Let me
show you a slide that explains how they work! They work very much like Start and
Update!
Here are the messages that are passed! If it's a collision. i.e. one of the blue
things at the top-left. where physics is involved. then the
message is void on CollisionEnter2D. and it is a
Collision2D that is passed in. And I'm going
to call that thing Collision. and it's an object. a green object comes in
collision. If it's a trigger. then you use OnTriggerEnter2D and it's
a collider. because there is no collision that gets passed in. And we don't
have to take any notice of the green objects that are
passed. but they're there for our information if we need them.
So. these are very much like Start and Update. As I said. they are just
methods that get called by the engine. They operate like
normal methods in all other respects. So.
let's take a look! Let's write both of these out. actually
and jus log to the Console. So. I'll write one and you can
write the other. void
On... Let's go for. I don't know. Trigger first.
...Enter2D. We're in 2D. you must have the 2D's. OnTriggerEnter
2D. well what do we have a collider or a collision? It's got to be a collider.
because there's no collision occurring
with a trigger. And I just want to print
("Trigger").
That'll do! Now. what I want you to do is pause the video and
write another method. directly under there. using the other signature which I shoed you
in the slide. which is the OnCollisionEnter2D at the top.
Go ahead and do that now.
Cool! Alright. so this is just void On
CollisionEnter2D. Now. you don't get any
autocompletion help. you have to spell these messages properly. Once you spelled them
right. you can intercept them. and you go
(Collision2D collision)
Now. you may have noticed my error in my function! I didn't
bother putting the variable. So. what does all this stuff mean?
void means that the method passes nothing
back. OnTriggerEnter means that. that's the
name of the method. Collider2D is the type of thing that
is going to be passed in to us. from the engine.
and then. we give that object a name. the instance a name.
and that we're calling trigger. OK. so exactly
the same pattern down here. We get a collision here.
I'm just going to print
("Collision"); OK cool. to the Console! Now. we can
explore the difference between those two. over in Unity. So. if our Loose
Collider has no trigger box on it. and our Ball
has no trigger box. it's a collision. let's see what happens!
So. you get a Collision logged out to the Console.
which is fine. And actually. if you watch carefully.
over in the Scene View the ball stops when it hits the collider. because
the physics is being calculated. Now. let's go to the
Loose Collider and make it a trigger. and watch what happens when
we play.
Two things are different there! Firstly. the ball passes straight through.
because the trigger makes it ignore the physics.
and secondly. we get a trigger logged out. So. hopefully
now you understand the difference between these
two messages that are passed. and you will be able to
refer to Unity's docs or our documentation when
it comes to this table here.
Alright. that's it! You know
how to do it. There are the different types of colliders. That's how you determine which row
and column you're in. And I look forward
to seeing you in the quiz. where I'm going to ask you to think about what
each of the things in the scene are. the ball. the loose collider. etc.
See how you can do in categorizing things yourself. OK.
take care!
=======
Hey, so in this video we're going to explore colliders in
Unity, and let's get rid of the confusion, before it even starts!
Just briefly, before I dive into the details of colliders, why do we even
care about these things? Look they are a super handy part
of Unity. These colliders allow us to
trigger events, like maybe you walk over a door threshold and
the automatic door opens for you, or we can
simulate collisions, like a pool game, or in the case of
Block Breaker the ball bouncing. It's really at the heart of all
physical objects interacting with each other. So, colliders are super cool,
they're super important, and I'm going to explain here
the different types and how they talk to each other. So, as an overview,
what we're going to talk about is if colliders overlap
during a frame, then messages may be passed by the
engine. And we're going to be talking about what message passing is
and go into a little bit of detail about how
all this works in Unity. So, what is message passing?
When two GameObjects with colliders meet,
the engine sends a message to those objects, we intercept those messages
in a script, and then, our script decides what to do next.
You can read more about message passing on Wikipedia, if you're
having trouble getting to sleep. So firstly, what do we mean about two
colliders meeting? Let's take a look at an example in Unity.
Here I have a ball that has a circular collider on it, 2D
circular collider, and here I have a Loose Collider
at the bottom of my play space, which has a Box Collider. And if those two colliders were to
overlap, so they're not touching now, but if the ball was a little
bit lower, like this maybe, then they would overlap. If they overlap during
a frame, and that is an important distinction, because if the ball
is moving really really fast and it jumps right through this thing in a frame, there
will be no collision message passed. But if
there's an overlap during a frame, then a message may get
passed. Why may get passed? Well, let's have a look at
this table here! In most
cases a message is passed. There are some white cells in my table, where
the messages are not passed. Let's look at the general pattern of this table.
Firstly, where did it come from? Well, Unity has this in their docs,
under their Colliders Overview document. Let's take a look at it!
Here it is, lots to read, again, if you're having trouble getting to
sleep. And at the bottom of the page, you've got two tables.
One about messages that are passed when a collision happens.
And another about messages are passed when a trigger happens.
But to me that's confusing, so what we've done is taken that table and
that table, and we've put them on top of each other
to give you that table, which I think is clearer.
So, what I'm saying is that in some situations
the engine will raise a message, and there's two different types of messages it can
pass. One is for a collision, which only happens
in the top-left of the table, where we have non-trigger
colliders interacting with non-trigger colliders.
None of these rows or columns, in the top-left, have the word trigger in them.
The moment you add a trigger to the equation, you're dealing with triggers
not collisions. You can take yourself down or to the right, or down
and right. So, all of these other columns are where one
or either of those objects have trigger set.
What does that mean? Well, let's look in here! Let's look at the Loose
Collider! If that checkbox is ticked, then we're in the territory
of triggers, and if it's un-ticked,
on there and un-ticked on the ball, then
we may be in the territory of collisions.
So, in this case, this is a collision, and the ball will actually,
if it's started off higher, it will fall
and stop when it hits that Loose Collider.
OK, and the message that will get passed
is one of these collision messages.
When the collisions are happening, then physics
is being calculated. Alright, so let's look at that
in action a little bit more. What do we have here? We have a ball
that has a Rigidbody on it. So,
what do these rows and column headers mean? I've got a slide
for you that's going to help disambiguate that!
Here are the types of colliders! It's Static
if it has a collider but no Rigidbody.
The moment you add a Rigidbody, it's a Rigidbody, and if
you make that Rigidbody Kinematic, i.e. it doesn't
move on its own basically. We have to move it. Then, it becomes a Kinematic
Rigidbody Collider. A rule of
thumb is, if it's going to move during the game, slap a Rigidbody on it, and avoid
moving Static Colliders,
because it's very inefficient. So, that's what the rows and
columns of this table mean. So, what do we have when our
ball., as we're setting it up in our game, falls? Well,
the ball has a Rigidbody on it, and we want its physics to
occur, but what it's going to hit is one of
two things, depending on how we setup our Loose Collider. If our
Loose Collider is a trigger, then it's a Static Trigger Collider, and this
trigger message gets passed down here. And if we decide
that our Trigger Collider is going to be static but not
a trigger, then we get a collision up here.
OK, so let's go back to Unity. Go to your Loose Collider,
and we're going to need to add a component to it. Your ball, by the way,
will be sitting in the middle of the play space.
I just moved this for the sake of argument. So, there you go! You're looking like
that with your ball there and your collider there. Add a component, a new script,
and I'm just going to call it Loose Collider.
Very imaginatively! Now, in that script, I'm going to pop it into
the Scripts Folder. We're going to need to intercept
one of two messages. Now, don't be scared about these message things. Let me
show you a slide that explains how they work! They work very much like Start and
Update!
Here are the messages that are passed! If it's a collision, i.e. one of the blue
things at the top-left, where physics is involved, then the
message is void on CollisionEnter2D, and it is a
Collision2D that is passed in. And I'm going
to call that thing Collision, and it's an object, a green object comes in
collision. If it's a trigger, then you use OnTriggerEnter2D and it's
a collider, because there is no collision that gets passed in. And we don't
have to take any notice of the green objects that are
passed, but they're there for our information if we need them.
So, these are very much like Start and Update. As I said, they are just
methods that get called by the engine. They operate like
normal methods in all other respects. So,
let's take a look! Let's write both of these out, actually
and jus log to the Console. So, I'll write one and you can
write the other. void
On... Let's go for, I don't know, Trigger first.
...Enter2D. We're in 2D, you must have the 2D's. OnTriggerEnter
2D, well what do we have a collider or a collision? It's got to be a collider,
because there's no collision occurring
with a trigger. And I just want to print
("Trigger").
That'll do! Now, what I want you to do is pause the video and
write another method, directly under there, using the other signature which I shoed you
in the slide, which is the OnCollisionEnter2D at the top.
Go ahead and do that now.
Cool! Alright, so this is just void On
CollisionEnter2D. Now, you don't get any
autocompletion help, you have to spell these messages properly. Once you spelled them
right, you can intercept them, and you go
(Collision2D collision)
Now, you may have noticed my error in my function! I didn't
bother putting the variable. So, what does all this stuff mean?
void means that the method passes nothing
back. OnTriggerEnter means that, that's the
name of the method. Collider2D is the type of thing that
is going to be passed in to us, from the engine,
and then, we give that object a name, the instance a name,
and that we're calling trigger. OK, so exactly
the same pattern down here. We get a collision here.
I'm just going to print
("Collision"); OK cool, to the Console! Now, we can
explore the difference between those two, over in Unity. So, if our Loose
Collider has no trigger box on it, and our Ball
has no trigger box, it's a collision, let's see what happens!
So, you get a Collision logged out to the Console,
which is fine. And actually, if you watch carefully,
over in the Scene View the ball stops when it hits the collider, because
the physics is being calculated. Now, let's go to the
Loose Collider and make it a trigger, and watch what happens when
we play.
Two things are different there! Firstly, the ball passes straight through,
because the trigger makes it ignore the physics,
and secondly, we get a trigger logged out. So, hopefully
now you understand the difference between these
two messages that are passed, and you will be able to
refer to Unity's docs or our documentation when
it comes to this table here.
Alright, that's it! You know
how to do it. There are the different types of colliders. That's how you determine which row
and column you're in. And I look forward
to seeing you in the quiz, where I'm going to ask you to think about what
each of the things in the scene are, the ball, the loose collider, etc.
See how you can do in categorizing things yourself. OK,
take care!
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1:Unity/Section5/07-Colliders-Triggers-Collisions-in-Unity.srt