Hmm? [He Makes Funny Music Sounds Drum Sounds]
[He Continues to Make Funny Drum Sounds]
Hey guys! So, we're going to tidy up a
little now, before we move on. We're going to delete the Music Player
that's unecessary. We're going to setup the game
window resolution, to our target resolution.
We're going to show you a couple of keyboard shortcuts,
and remove the whole canvas on the Game
Scene and make the Lose collider load the next level. Wow,
loads of thing! Cool! So, let's dive into Unity, take a look
at all of that then and see how it's going to work.
OK, so firstly
you'll notice that on the Start
Menu, we have a Music Player. Don't worry about this,
at the moment, the fact that the text is overspilling. We're going to sort that soon.
But we have a Music Player and when we play,
and move onto
the Game Scene, we end up with
the Music Player, if we look here, a duplicate Music Player
self destructing. We don't need a second Music
Player on this Game Scene. Now, you're Music Player is
designed to move from one scene to another, so this is a good time to just
tidy that up, so get rid of your Music Player.
OK, so whenever you see things that can
be tidied and simplified, do take the time like this to do it.
The second thing is we noticed, just now,
on the Start Menu that this text doesn't fit.
Why is that? Well, I'd like to show you in an
ability to change the actual resolution. We've locked
4:3 aspect ratio, but the text
is in a fixed number of pixels, and we don't know how many pixels
that is until we look at the context.
So, if you add a new resolution here,
so you go to Game, and then, you click on where
it says 4:3 and then you click on the + at the bottom
to get to this screen. And let's make our target resolution
800 by 600, which is still a 4:3
aspect ratio. And let's just get it a very clear...
Just give it a very clear name, 800 by 600.
What else is there to say?
Cool! Now, if we select that, then look
it looks the same, at the moment, but it gives us a warning that it's only
currently set to 416 by 312.
So, what I'm going to do for the rest of this section, probably, is
pull out the Game Window. It's quite tricky! You have to get it somewhere where it
detaches, like... Very tricky
sometimes. There you go! It's detached there, once you're dragging.
And then, I'm just going to make it quite large, but not the
entire screen, making sure that I've got at least 800 by 600. Here you go! Look at the
top left. The warning goes away when
the Vertical and Horizontal Resolutions both
exceed the Target Resolution. There you go, 800 by
600. Perfect! And actually now, the text fits fine!
I'm now going to use one new keyboard shortcut.
If you look in your Window Menu, you've got a
Command, or on a Windows machine Control
1 and 2, takes you between the scenes in the game. So look, let's just do that!
Command 2 is here, the game. Command 1 is the
scene. So, I'm going to switch between them like that now
and let's just test all this. Let's go to the Start
Menu, saving. Click play.
It defaults to the game. We could go back to the scene
to see what's going on, well behind the scenes! [Laughs] Excuse the pun!
Or we can go to the Game Window, and it's nice and big.
The ball falls off and then obviously
we'd need to, at the moment, click Game Over to go around the loop. Let's
just go back into the game and look at
the Console. Is there a duplicate Music Player
self destructing. There does still seem to be. So, when's that
happening, would be my question. Let's clear the Console,
start on the Start Menu,
and you can make
this smaller, if you need to be able to see the Console. So,
just play around with your windows, so that you can see your Game Scene and your
Console at the same time.
OK, that's good! And then, I'm using keyboard shortcuts to move between
them, so when I start it loads a level, and when I
go Game Over it loads the Win Screen. That's good!
OK, and now it's only when we go back to the
start that the Music Player self destructs. That is OK
because the Music Player is in the Start Scene, and when we loop
back to the Start Scene, we want the Music Player to
self destruct. That's some functionality we specifically put in
there. Cool! So, we've done that! The other handy
keyboard shortcut I wanted to show you was the ability to start and stop
Play. If you look in the Edit Menu, you have Play and Pause,
Command or Control P. So, I could be here and just go
Command P. It goes to the Game Window and I could go Command P
again to stop. OK,
and that's just another handy keyboard shortcut.
Cool! The other thing we've got hanging
over here is, we've got a Canvas
hanging around in Level 1, that has this "Game Over"
Button. We used that for testing the music, but we're about to
wire up the LoseCollider, so that it loads the levels.
So, let's just get rid of all of this User Interface stuff. So, click
on Canvas, and it will take away the Canvas
and the button, so just delete that
and the event system, because that's only related to the User Interface. That's
all gone and now maybe double click or click
on background and F to
frame it, i.e. to fill the screen with a background.
Cool! Now, you're game scene should still play, and the ball
will fall out. That's all normal, there's no music
because we started here. We'll only get music now
if we start on the Start Menu, because we deleted the
instance of the MusicManager. Let's try it!
Cool!
All working nicely! So, the final
thing to do is to make this Lose Collider Script actually
load the next level. So, how are we going to do that?
Well, let's do it! Firstly, let's check the LevelManager
Script, and make sure it has a method we can call.
LoadLevel(string name). Yes it does! Good!
That's good! And we have a LevelManager in the level,
so all we need to do is go into our LooseCollider.
And which trigger was it? ("Trigger")
or ("Collision")? Well, two ways of finding out, depends
what you left your LooseCollider as, in the
scene. Let's just click over to
the Game Scene. Let's take a look at the LoseCollider, mine
is a trigger. It probably makes sense. When we play
and look at the Console, we get
this log "Trigger". OK, so that tells us that
that's where we need to be in terms of the script. We need to be on
this OnTriggerEnter method OK.
So, I could leave the ("Collision") one there,
if necessary, but this is what I want to change.
So, let's leave the log, so that we know that it's happening.
And then, how are we going to do this? Well, we're going to need access
to a LevelManager to do this, so one of the first
things I need to do is expose the LevelManager like this.
public LevelManager, which is a type
that we've created.
levelManager; and then immediately save that script, go back
into Unity, and connect the LevelManager.
You see it's asking for it down here, in the Inspector now,
under the LooseCollider Script component. You
want to pop the LevelManager on there. Now, it's got access to the LevelManager!
That's great! So, back into the script,
and it's simply a question of levelManager, with a small
l. It's the instance of this LevelManager, dot LoadLevel
and then, we provide it a string name.
Now later, we're going to do this a slightly different way, but for now we just
load level ("Win Screen");
when we trigger this LooseCollider.
OK, let's try! Let's see what happens!
Perfect! OK, now let's just
test the whole loop. The music starts, perfect!
The ball falls out, level
loads, Play Again. Quit won't quit, but
It should be logging a quit request and it is.
Fantastic! So, as a recap this is what
we've managed to achieve here. We've deleted that ununecessary
Music Player instance, that was hanging around on Level 1.
We've set our Game Window
to an explicit resolution of 800 by 600, which
is going to be our target resolution, when we build this game for the web.
We've learned two handy keyboard shortcuts.
One is Command or Control 1 and 2,
which switches between the Scene and the Game
View respectively. Particularly useful, when we've detached our
Game Window, like that.
We then removed the whole User Interface, from the game level,
because we're allowing the code on the LooseCollider
to organize the loading of the
next level. We're not using a button anymore. That was just a testing button,
used for navigating ourself around and testing the music.
So that's it! Congratulations and I'll
see you soon!