Hey welcome back! So. in
this video we're going to get our ball bouncing. Let's
see where we're starting from. So. we have
a Start Menu with some music. that
persists into the game. The ball falls out of the play space.
and we may have beaten the game. but personally.
it doesn't satisfy me very much. Not much of a challenge right?
So. we need to have a paddle in
place. at the bottom. to block the ball.
So. go into your level. focus on your background
framing. as Unity calls it.
And let's go and grab our sprite.
that is our full brick. and let's pop it into the scene.
Now. by dragging the sprite into
the scene and letting go. let's see what happens.
A few things have happened. it's created a GameObject
here. called full brick. the same name as the sprite.
It's positioned it. wherever we left
it. and I'm actually going to position mine 8 units in
and 0.5 world units up.
So. we're precisely under the ball here.
It has also got a Transform.
as all GameObjects do by default. and a Sprite Renderer
on it. so we can see it in the scene. And let's just look at it
in the game. It's all very well!
The ball passes straight through it. which is interesting.
but we'll deal with that in a moment. So. I'm going to rename
my full brick to simply Paddle.
And I would like to organize... Oh. you see the naming. you have to be
careful that you definitely hit Return. if you're
going to rename in the Inspector. There you go!
It's definitely changed. Now. I'm going to move it below Ball but above
the LooseCollider. so we have a logical sequence of Ball. Paddle.
Lose Collider. The ordering here. in the Hierarchy.
doesn't make any different to how the game operates. it's just for your
own sanity. keeping check.
So. we need to add a collider to our
paddle. to stop the ball from passing straight through it. The question is.
what sort of collider? Hmm. good
question? So. let's start by reminding ourselves what the Ball
is. The Ball has a Rigidbody
on it. which is not Kinematic.
and it has a Collider on it. that is not a Trigger.
So. what type of collider does the ball have? What do we call
it? Do you remember this table that we produced?
Well. the Ball.
as I've shown here vertically. is a Ribidbody
Collider. because it's not static
because it has a Rigidbody on it. It's not a Kinematic
Rigid body. because the Rigidbody is not Kinematic.
Kinematic Rigidbodies. basically. you have to more yourself.
The Physics Engine doesn't move them.
And it's not a Trigger. The Collider is not set to
a Trigger. so the column. the verticle we're dealing with
is a Rigidbody Collider. on the Ball. Now comes the
question. what type of collider should we put on the paddle?
Well. we're going to be moving the paddle right?
So. Static Colliders. at the top on the left. are
out. because we're not supposed to move State Colliders. They're
for things like walls. The walls of the game will be Static Colliders.
So. what's the next thing it could be? Could it be a
Rigid body Collider or a Kinematic Rigidbody Collider?
Well. you're going to experiment with that in a minute. It's definately
either a Kinematic Rigidbody or just a plain
Rigidbody. because we want a collision to come out of
this result. not just a Trigger. We actually want the Physics Engine to
work for us. in this game. because it's very much a physics based
game. So. next
thing you're going to need to know. of course. is what is a Rigidbody? What is
this Rigidgody thing. in a bit more detail? Well.
let's take a quick look! Let's see what Unity has to say about it!
"Rigid bodies enable your GameObjects
to act under the control of physics. The Rigidbody can receive
forces and torque to make your objects move in a realistic way..."
So. that's what's making our ball fall. at the moment. It's
the fact it's got a Rigidbody on it and some gravity. That's what's pulling
the ball downwards right now. You can read more
about Rigidbodies. in Unity's manual there. which I think
I have the page open over here for you. Yes I do!
It's probably worth a read. But the question
remains. what type of collider should we
be putting on our paddle?
I want you to think about that yourself.
And as a challenge for you. I want you
to find and add the appropriate 2D collider
to the paddle. It's not going to be a
Circle Collier. but it's pretty obvious what type it should be.
I then want you to find and
add the Rigidbody2D component to
the paddle. that we just created.
and then. play around and see
what happens. when you set the Rigidbody2D to Kinematic
vs. Non-Kinematic? And have a play with some of
those other settings. We can always reset the component. don't worry.
And then. come back to me after you've paused the video. See if you can get
to a point where the ball just stops dead. when it hits the
paddle. OK. pause the video and try that now.
So fantastic! Welcome back! I hope you paused the video. I hope you did your
challenge. Let's just start playing. Here's the Paddle.
We are going to firstly need to
add that collider. so Add Component. Physics 2D.
Box Collider. would clearly be the right one.
because it's a box. Now. let's just double click on the Paddle and
take a look! That collider is in green there. How do I know?
Well. I could disable and re-enable the Box
Collider. here in the Inspector. and you'll just see a green outline.
Another way is. I could increase the size of it to make it
bigger or smaller than the paddle. but I actually want it to be
default size. so I'm going to reset the collider.
because it did a good job of finding the outside of the paddle.
Good! So. we have a collider! Let's see what happens with just a collider!
Boom! It lands
and stops! That's good! So. what have we got
here. at this stage? What type of collider have we got
on the paddle?
Well. it's a Static Collider. It may seem like it's
doing the job. but it's not good. because it's a Static Collider.
This thing is not supposed to be moving. It's very inefficient
to use Static Colliders. So. we're going to go ahead and add
this Physics 2D. Rigidbody 2D
component. Let's leave all the settings
as default and see what happens.
Ooh. what happened there? We have to look really carefully. So. if you need
to look carefully. what you can do is you can hit pause
then play.
and then. you can step through. one frame at
a time and see what happens. using this button here.
See! The paddle was falling off the
screen as well. So. if we look at the Paddle.
it's because it has Mass
and a Gravity Scale.
So. you could set the Gravity Scale to 0. Let's see
what that does. How come is the ball...
Ah. so let's watch that again! Again. using
the slow motion. so pause then play.
Now. the paddle is not moving.
but when the ball excelerates down and hits the
paddle. the ball has mass the paddle has mass. so the ball knocks
the paddle out of the way. Not right either! OK.
so how about if we were to
have another look at the paddle and say. how about if it had no Mass?
Well then. it would just accelerate off really fast. How about if you had
massive Mass? Well. maybe it would stay in place
if it had a massive Mass. but that's a hack right. I don't like that.
So. don't do that. What we actually want to do is make
this paddle Kinematic. Now. you can read in the manual
what Kinematic means. I'll show you briefly.
Here! "If enabled the object will
not be driven by the physics engine. and can only be manipulated by its
Transform. This is useful for moving platforms or if you want
to animate a Rigidbody that has a Hingejoint". So. this is
basically a moving platform. this thing. So. if we
make it Kinematic. then
let's see what happens. Bump!
OK. so the paddle is ignoring the Physics
Engine. which is perfect. It's exactly what we want. We have
the ball. that has some mass. hitting this paddle that will not move
unless our script moves it. So. looking back into
the presentation. we have this
interaction here. between the Rigidbody Collider
and the Kinematic Rigidbody
Collider. So. the ball is a Rigidbody Collider
and the paddle becomes a Kinematic Rigidbody
Collider.
So congratulations if you got that far! Hopefully you understand more
about colliders and physics. And I shall
see you shortly!
=======
Hey welcome back! So, in
this video we're going to get our ball bouncing. Let's
see where we're starting from. So, we have
a Start Menu with some music, that
persists into the game. The ball falls out of the play space,
and we may have beaten the game, but personally,
it doesn't satisfy me very much. Not much of a challenge right?
So, we need to have a paddle in
place, at the bottom, to block the ball.
So, go into your level, focus on your background
framing, as Unity calls it.
And let's go and grab our sprite,
that is our full brick, and let's pop it into the scene.
Now, by dragging the sprite into
the scene and letting go, let's see what happens.
A few things have happened, it's created a GameObject
here, called full brick, the same name as the sprite.
It's positioned it, wherever we left
it, and I'm actually going to position mine 8 units in
and 0.5 world units up.
So, we're precisely under the ball here.
It has also got a Transform,
as all GameObjects do by default, and a Sprite Renderer
on it, so we can see it in the scene. And let's just look at it
in the game. It's all very well!
The ball passes straight through it, which is interesting,
but we'll deal with that in a moment. So, I'm going to rename
my full brick to simply Paddle.
And I would like to organize... Oh, you see the naming, you have to be
careful that you definitely hit Return, if you're
going to rename in the Inspector. There you go!
It's definitely changed. Now, I'm going to move it below Ball but above
the LooseCollider, so we have a logical sequence of Ball, Paddle,
Lose Collider. The ordering here, in the Hierarchy,
doesn't make any different to how the game operates, it's just for your
own sanity, keeping check.
So, we need to add a collider to our
paddle, to stop the ball from passing straight through it. The question is,
what sort of collider? Hmm, good
question? So, let's start by reminding ourselves what the Ball
is. The Ball has a Rigidbody
on it, which is not Kinematic,
and it has a Collider on it, that is not a Trigger.
So, what type of collider does the ball have? What do we call
it? Do you remember this table that we produced?
Well, the Ball,
as I've shown here vertically, is a Ribidbody
Collider, because it's not static
because it has a Rigidbody on it. It's not a Kinematic
Rigid body, because the Rigidbody is not Kinematic.
Kinematic Rigidbodies, basically, you have to more yourself.
The Physics Engine doesn't move them.
And it's not a Trigger. The Collider is not set to
a Trigger, so the column, the verticle we're dealing with
is a Rigidbody Collider, on the Ball. Now comes the
question, what type of collider should we put on the paddle?
Well, we're going to be moving the paddle right?
So, Static Colliders, at the top on the left, are
out, because we're not supposed to move State Colliders. They're
for things like walls. The walls of the game will be Static Colliders.
So, what's the next thing it could be? Could it be a
Rigid body Collider or a Kinematic Rigidbody Collider?
Well, you're going to experiment with that in a minute. It's definately
either a Kinematic Rigidbody or just a plain
Rigidbody, because we want a collision to come out of
this result, not just a Trigger. We actually want the Physics Engine to
work for us, in this game, because it's very much a physics based
game. So, next
thing you're going to need to know, of course, is what is a Rigidbody? What is
this Rigidgody thing, in a bit more detail? Well,
let's take a quick look! Let's see what Unity has to say about it!
"Rigid bodies enable your GameObjects
to act under the control of physics. The Rigidbody can receive
forces and torque to make your objects move in a realistic way..."
So, that's what's making our ball fall, at the moment. It's
the fact it's got a Rigidbody on it and some gravity. That's what's pulling
the ball downwards right now. You can read more
about Rigidbodies, in Unity's manual there, which I think
I have the page open over here for you. Yes I do!
It's probably worth a read. But the question
remains, what type of collider should we
be putting on our paddle?
I want you to think about that yourself.
And as a challenge for you, I want you
to find and add the appropriate 2D collider
to the paddle. It's not going to be a
Circle Collier, but it's pretty obvious what type it should be.
I then want you to find and
add the Rigidbody2D component to
the paddle, that we just created,
and then, play around and see
what happens, when you set the Rigidbody2D to Kinematic
vs. Non-Kinematic? And have a play with some of
those other settings. We can always reset the component, don't worry.
And then, come back to me after you've paused the video. See if you can get
to a point where the ball just stops dead, when it hits the
paddle. OK, pause the video and try that now.
So fantastic! Welcome back! I hope you paused the video. I hope you did your
challenge. Let's just start playing. Here's the Paddle.
We are going to firstly need to
add that collider, so Add Component, Physics 2D,
Box Collider, would clearly be the right one,
because it's a box. Now, let's just double click on the Paddle and
take a look! That collider is in green there. How do I know?
Well, I could disable and re-enable the Box
Collider, here in the Inspector, and you'll just see a green outline.
Another way is, I could increase the size of it to make it
bigger or smaller than the paddle, but I actually want it to be
default size, so I'm going to reset the collider,
because it did a good job of finding the outside of the paddle.
Good! So, we have a collider! Let's see what happens with just a collider!
Boom! It lands
and stops! That's good! So, what have we got
here, at this stage? What type of collider have we got
on the paddle?
Well, it's a Static Collider. It may seem like it's
doing the job, but it's not good, because it's a Static Collider.
This thing is not supposed to be moving. It's very inefficient
to use Static Colliders. So, we're going to go ahead and add
this Physics 2D, Rigidbody 2D
component. Let's leave all the settings
as default and see what happens.
Ooh, what happened there? We have to look really carefully. So, if you need
to look carefully, what you can do is you can hit pause
then play,
and then, you can step through, one frame at
a time and see what happens, using this button here.
See! The paddle was falling off the
screen as well. So, if we look at the Paddle,
it's because it has Mass
and a Gravity Scale.
So, you could set the Gravity Scale to 0. Let's see
what that does. How come is the ball...
Ah, so let's watch that again! Again, using
the slow motion, so pause then play.
Now, the paddle is not moving,
but when the ball excelerates down and hits the
paddle, the ball has mass the paddle has mass, so the ball knocks
the paddle out of the way. Not right either! OK,
so how about if we were to
have another look at the paddle and say, how about if it had no Mass?
Well then, it would just accelerate off really fast. How about if you had
massive Mass? Well, maybe it would stay in place
if it had a massive Mass, but that's a hack right. I don't like that.
So, don't do that. What we actually want to do is make
this paddle Kinematic. Now, you can read in the manual
what Kinematic means. I'll show you briefly.
Here! "If enabled the object will
not be driven by the physics engine, and can only be manipulated by its
Transform. This is useful for moving platforms or if you want
to animate a Rigidbody that has a Hingejoint". So, this is
basically a moving platform, this thing. So, if we
make it Kinematic, then
let's see what happens. Bump!
OK, so the paddle is ignoring the Physics
Engine, which is perfect. It's exactly what we want. We have
the ball, that has some mass, hitting this paddle that will not move
unless our script moves it. So, looking back into
the presentation, we have this
interaction here, between the Rigidbody Collider
and the Kinematic Rigidbody
Collider. So, the ball is a Rigidbody Collider
and the paddle becomes a Kinematic Rigidbody
Collider.
So congratulations if you got that far! Hopefully you understand more
about colliders and physics. And I shall
see you shortly!
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1:Unity/Section5/09-Choosing-The-Right-Collider.srt