So far. our ball is
falling and hitting our paddle but not
bouncing. So. how are we going to make it bounce? Well.
that's where physics materials come in.
Physics has an S on the end. Unity doesn't seem to realize that. as you'll
see. So. the physics material is used to adjust
friction and bouncing effects. of colliding objects.
Let's take a look at their documentation for it.
Here we go. you see they call it "Physics Material". you'll see that in
various places. but this shows you something
about Physics Material. So. let's go to
Unity and make this happen.
The first thing we're going to need to do is create ourselves a folder.
called materials. Now. later we
may call these type of folder Physics Materials. because there are
other types of materials. like Rendering Materials. but for now.
let's just call it materials for simplicity. And in there. let's
create a. not a Physics Material actually.
because that would be 3D. most things are 3D
by default. but a 2D Physics2D
Material. Physics2D Material. So. create one of those
and simply call it Ball. because it's the ball's
material. Let's take a look at it. it's got a friction of point
4. Well. actually we're going to set the friction to 0. We don't want
the ball to have any friction. What is the friction? Well.
Click the Blue Book. The Blue Book will
open the manual page for the Physics 2D Material.
very helpfully. and tell you what the friction is. Coefficient friction
for this collider. but we're not worrying about that. We're going to set that to
0. we don't need any friction on the ball. but what we do need is a Bounciness.
Now. what's the range of Bounciness? Click on the word
and drag left and right. you'll see we can set it between 0 and 1.
Great! If I click play now. nothing is going to happen.
Why? Well. because it's all very
well making the material. but we have not attached that material to the ball.
So. click on your ball. look under the Inspector.
under the Circle Collider 2D Section. and you'll see that it's asking
for a material. Drag the ball on there.
Now. let's play!
Boing. boing.
cool! Now look! Look how high the ball is bouncing! It's bouncing up at
exactly the same point every time. It has something
called a Coefficient of Restitution. which is the Bounciness of
1. that means it is perfectly bouncy.
We're also seeing another interesting fact here.
You see the ball is slightly interfering with the background. That's because
the ball and the background are at exactly the same
depth. and they're actually perfectly coincident with each
other. I'd like to push the background down a little bit.
to stop that effect. before exploring
this bouncing a little farther. So. go back
into your Scene View. Now. just for a moment. click 2D for
me and make it 3D. and then.
it'll spin around. I'm not sure exactly the orientation you'll have. you can
use the right mouse button to change. Just look. the camera
is over here. so if you move around. I'm
holding my Middle Mouse Button down now. and then. use the Right
Mouse Button to manipulate your position. you'll get the idea
that we have a camera over here. And then. we have a
background. at a Z depth of 0. and a
ball. also at a Z depth of 0.
So. why don't we push the background back a little bit. just give it a Z
depth of just say 1 World Unit. OK. so it's
behind the ball now. You'll find that when we play
now. the ball will just look that much more clear. and it
won't interfere with the background so much. And that's
because it's now in front of the background.
Alright. so we've just pushed the background away a tiny
bit. so it doesn't interfere with the ball. Great! So. back
over in the Scene View. let's take a look at the effect of changing
the Bounciness now. on the ball. So.
what is this Bounciness figure firstly? Click the Blue Book.
It'll take you back to Unity's manual page here.
and it tells you that the Bounciness is the degree to which
collisions rebound from the surface. "A Value 0 indicates no
bounce". Whereas a value of 1 indicates a perfect bounce with no loss
of energy. OK. so
said differently. I've got a slide here that explains exactly the
same thing. 0 no energy
conserved in the collision. Well. let's see that
happening.
If we set a Bounciness of 0. the game needs to be not running when you do
this by the way. Watch what happens.
No kinetic energy is conserved in that
collision. OK. and then the next thing it says is that a value of
1 means 100% of the energy is conserved in the collision.
Well. we've seen that happening. So.
it starts off with no kinetic energy. You'll probably remember this
from school. It has a certain amount of gravitational
potential energy relative to the paddle. and then.
as the game runs. that kinetic energy is converted
from the gravitational
potential energy and it keeps bouncing to the same height.
So. that's what it means by. all of the energy is conserved. it'll never decay.
the bouncing. Now. the question
is what would happen if I set the Bounciness to 0.5?
If it leaves the paddle with half the
energy it hit. then because kinetic energy is a half M
V squared. it's going to be going up to
only 1/4 of its height.
So. if you want it to bounce to half the height.
you're going to need to take the square root of the height you want it to bounce to. each
bounce. So. if you want it to bounce to 0.5 of it's previous
height. you're going to need 0.707 roughly. Let's
try that. a Bounciness of 0.707.
If that math is right. then it'll bounce to about here. in the
middle of the guys chest. on that triangle. Let's
try. expecting it to bounce to here and it does.
You see. every time it bounces to half the height.
In our game. of course. we want the ball to continue bouncing
forever. So. we want a Bounciness of 1.
in our case. So. don't worry about the details of
choosing bounciness. I just want to show you how you would
get in a Bounciness that you want. if you wanted to.
Now. if you do want to know more about the physics. of course. then pop
over to my little face here. take a look at the other
courses I've got. One of them is Game Physics - Extend
Unity 3D's Physics Engine. and in there I'm going to take you through
step by step. how to build your own Physics Engine.
You'll be in a much better position to understand things
like how this thing bounces. how high it bounces. how
energy is conserved. etc. So. take a look
in Physics 101. It's a course I'm really passionate about. I really
enjoyed putting it together. and the feedback that I'm getting already is really
cool. Run it! So. here we go. let's try the Bounciness
of 1 again. and it will just keep bouncing. which
is precisely what we want here. We want energy to be conserved
whenever the ball hits anything. So. congratulations!
We have a ball bouncing on a paddle. It's a bit more visible.
the ball now. And I shall see you
shortly.
=======
So far, our ball is
falling and hitting our paddle but not
bouncing. So, how are we going to make it bounce? Well,
that's where physics materials come in.
Physics has an S on the end, Unity doesn't seem to realize that, as you'll
see. So, the physics material is used to adjust
friction and bouncing effects, of colliding objects.
Let's take a look at their documentation for it.
Here we go, you see they call it "Physics Material", you'll see that in
various places, but this shows you something
about Physics Material. So, let's go to
Unity and make this happen.
The first thing we're going to need to do is create ourselves a folder,
called materials. Now, later we
may call these type of folder Physics Materials, because there are
other types of materials, like Rendering Materials, but for now,
let's just call it materials for simplicity. And in there, let's
create a, not a Physics Material actually,
because that would be 3D, most things are 3D
by default, but a 2D Physics2D
Material. Physics2D Material. So, create one of those
and simply call it Ball, because it's the ball's
material. Let's take a look at it, it's got a friction of point
4. Well, actually we're going to set the friction to 0. We don't want
the ball to have any friction. What is the friction? Well,
Click the Blue Book. The Blue Book will
open the manual page for the Physics 2D Material,
very helpfully, and tell you what the friction is. Coefficient friction
for this collider, but we're not worrying about that. We're going to set that to
0, we don't need any friction on the ball, but what we do need is a Bounciness.
Now, what's the range of Bounciness? Click on the word
and drag left and right, you'll see we can set it between 0 and 1.
Great! If I click play now, nothing is going to happen.
Why? Well, because it's all very
well making the material, but we have not attached that material to the ball.
So, click on your ball, look under the Inspector,
under the Circle Collider 2D Section, and you'll see that it's asking
for a material. Drag the ball on there.
Now, let's play!
Boing, boing,
cool! Now look! Look how high the ball is bouncing! It's bouncing up at
exactly the same point every time. It has something
called a Coefficient of Restitution, which is the Bounciness of
1, that means it is perfectly bouncy.
We're also seeing another interesting fact here.
You see the ball is slightly interfering with the background. That's because
the ball and the background are at exactly the same
depth, and they're actually perfectly coincident with each
other. I'd like to push the background down a little bit,
to stop that effect, before exploring
this bouncing a little farther. So, go back
into your Scene View. Now, just for a moment, click 2D for
me and make it 3D, and then,
it'll spin around. I'm not sure exactly the orientation you'll have, you can
use the right mouse button to change. Just look, the camera
is over here, so if you move around, I'm
holding my Middle Mouse Button down now, and then, use the Right
Mouse Button to manipulate your position, you'll get the idea
that we have a camera over here. And then, we have a
background, at a Z depth of 0, and a
ball, also at a Z depth of 0.
So, why don't we push the background back a little bit, just give it a Z
depth of just say 1 World Unit. OK, so it's
behind the ball now. You'll find that when we play
now, the ball will just look that much more clear, and it
won't interfere with the background so much. And that's
because it's now in front of the background.
Alright, so we've just pushed the background away a tiny
bit, so it doesn't interfere with the ball. Great! So, back
over in the Scene View, let's take a look at the effect of changing
the Bounciness now, on the ball. So,
what is this Bounciness figure firstly? Click the Blue Book.
It'll take you back to Unity's manual page here,
and it tells you that the Bounciness is the degree to which
collisions rebound from the surface. "A Value 0 indicates no
bounce". Whereas a value of 1 indicates a perfect bounce with no loss
of energy. OK, so
said differently, I've got a slide here that explains exactly the
same thing. 0 no energy
conserved in the collision. Well, let's see that
happening.
If we set a Bounciness of 0, the game needs to be not running when you do
this by the way. Watch what happens.
No kinetic energy is conserved in that
collision. OK, and then the next thing it says is that a value of
1 means 100% of the energy is conserved in the collision.
Well, we've seen that happening. So,
it starts off with no kinetic energy. You'll probably remember this
from school. It has a certain amount of gravitational
potential energy relative to the paddle, and then,
as the game runs, that kinetic energy is converted
from the gravitational
potential energy and it keeps bouncing to the same height.
So, that's what it means by, all of the energy is conserved, it'll never decay,
the bouncing. Now, the question
is what would happen if I set the Bounciness to 0.5?
If it leaves the paddle with half the
energy it hit, then because kinetic energy is a half M
V squared, it's going to be going up to
only 1/4 of its height.
So, if you want it to bounce to half the height,
you're going to need to take the square root of the height you want it to bounce to, each
bounce. So, if you want it to bounce to 0.5 of it's previous
height, you're going to need 0.707 roughly. Let's
try that, a Bounciness of 0.707.
If that math is right, then it'll bounce to about here, in the
middle of the guys chest, on that triangle. Let's
try, expecting it to bounce to here and it does.
You see, every time it bounces to half the height.
In our game, of course, we want the ball to continue bouncing
forever. So, we want a Bounciness of 1,
in our case. So, don't worry about the details of
choosing bounciness, I just want to show you how you would
get in a Bounciness that you want, if you wanted to.
Now, if you do want to know more about the physics, of course, then pop
over to my little face here, take a look at the other
courses I've got. One of them is Game Physics - Extend
Unity 3D's Physics Engine, and in there I'm going to take you through
step by step, how to build your own Physics Engine.
You'll be in a much better position to understand things
like how this thing bounces, how high it bounces, how
energy is conserved, etc. So, take a look
in Physics 101. It's a course I'm really passionate about, I really
enjoyed putting it together, and the feedback that I'm getting already is really
cool. Run it! So, here we go, let's try the Bounciness
of 1 again, and it will just keep bouncing, which
is precisely what we want here. We want energy to be conserved
whenever the ball hits anything. So, congratulations!
We have a ball bouncing on a paddle. It's a bit more visible,
the ball now. And I shall see you
shortly.
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1:Unity/Section5/10-Using-Physics-Materials-For-Bounce.srt