Hey hey hey! So. we
have our bouncing ball and our paddle. Now. we need to be able to
move the paddle. and we're going to do that with the mouse.
So. in this video. just as an overview.
we're going to learn about Input.MousePosition.
We're going to learn how to query the current screen width;
well. in our case that's fixed to 800 pixels.
We're going to move the paddle with this.
transform.position. We're then going to stop the
paddle flying outside of the game space. using Mathf.
Clamp. not colliders. and
we're then going to make a minor tweak to the paddle's
Pixels to World Units.
Cool! So. how are we going to do this? We need to just move this
paddle around. Well. let's start by
just fixing something I've noticed. which is that this paddle is
not quite the right size. How do I know that? Well. if I
list the left hand side of the Game Space. if the paddle
is exactly 1 World Unit wide then here.
when it touches the left hand side. I would expect it to be at point
5. not 0.65. And the reason
for that is we simply need to go to the
sprite. In fact. while you're at it. do that left and right brick.
and set their Pixels Per World Unit as 128.
which is what we calculated before.
Now. if you were to turn your grid gizmo back on.
you'll find that the paddle is precisely 1 World Unit wide.
And you see the paddle itself is 1 World Unit. 1 grid
square. Just as a mini super mini simple exercise.
I want you to fix that collider now. Bring it down
to precisely the size of the brick. Go ahead and
do that. The way I'm going to do it is
just by resetting it there. Reset.
Inspector. Box Collider 2D. Reset.
Cool! So now. we have the paddle the correct size. and now. if I
set it to the left hand side of the Play Space. my transform is precisely
0.5. And on the right hand side
of the Play Space. the transform will be 15.5
precisely. Let's just prove that.
There it is. Fantastic! OK!
So. varying between 0.5 and 15.5
is what we want to achieve. so
how are we going to do it? Well. we're defining paddle behavior
here. so we need to add a
script to the paddle. our own custom component
and we'll just simply call it Paddle.
I'm just going to pop that script in
the Scripts Folder. to be tidy and
I'm going to dive into it.
I want to know what this Input.Mouse
Position thing is. So. one of the first things I always do with a new method is just
print it; print (Input.
mousePosition); and see what we get. Let's take
a look. Printing every frame in the Update () method.
Well. as I move the mouse around. look at the very bottom left of my
screen. you see the coordinates. So. if I start at the bottom
left. I have a position of roughly 00.
If I go to the bottom right. in this case. it's 400
pixelse wide. my current game screen. And as I go to the top
right. it goes up to 400 by
300. If I was to take my Game Tab out
to detach it. and then to make it full
size. then you'll see the coordiates go from 00
to...
...800. 0. to 800
600. So. it's the X coordinate and then the Y coordinate
and then the Z coordinate. That's how that's working.
I'm just going to reattach my Game Window. because it's more convenient.
Great! So. that's what
Input.MousePosition gives us. which is just fine.
Now. I want to look at the X value of
that Input.MousePosition. so I do a .x and it takes the
X F for Field off.
And you can see from the tool tip. that that's a float.
so if I was to just do that and run it. you'll just see
now that I only have the X position being logged.
in the very bottom left of the screen. Great! So. that's
how far or long the screen the mouse is in pixels.
The...
current screen width is given by Screen.
width); like that. So. if I was to divide the current
X position in pixels by the screen width in pixels.
we'll get a number varying between 0 and 1. Let's take a look.
However big my Game Screen is.
when I'm on the left hand side of it. I log out 0.
In the middle 0.5 and on the right.
1. Now. we're only looking at the X position here. the X
axis. That's great! Now. if the window was to change
size like this. the same thing will happen.
0.51. So. this is our relative
mouse X position.
If you like. it's the relative mouse position in X.
to the entire screen width. Now. if we
multiply that by 16. it's going to tell us how many
Game Units we have. because the Game Space is
16 World Units wide. Let's try that.
Now. 0 on the left. of course. but 8 in the middle and
16 on the right. So now. we have the mouse position
in Game Units or in
blocks. you know whole or half numbers of blocks.
So. why don't we call it that. So. your first mini
challenge is to just. I want you to print out instead of this. I want
you to print a variable. and that variable is called
mouse pause in blocks.
OK. like that! Setup a variable of the appropriate type.
set the expression we just created to it. and print the
variable. not the expression. so you get the same behavior as
we just had. with the numbers in the console varying from 0
to 16 but you're using a variable instead. Try that now.
[Temporary Silence]
OK welcome
back! It's a pretty simple job. You cut that out. you
realize that it's a float from the documentation or from looking
around. you give it it's name. which
is mousePosInBlocks.
Nice long descriptive
name. with a small letter. Put a semicolon on the end.
and then. simply print mousePosInBlocks.
So. you're going to get exactly the same behavior as you had before.
OK. 0 to 16.
Fantastic! OK. so how are
you now going to actually
move this thing round. Well. let's get rid of the print statement. we don't need it.
Well. what is this thing? Well. actually it happens
that the keyword this refers to the current object.
so that's fantastic! That is the paddle. that's the context
we're in. Now. it's the transform we want to move.
and it's the position of the transform we want to move. OK.
And you may think you can just say .x the
field. and you may think you can just go
OK. set that to mousePosIn
Blocks. Well. it's a reasonable expectation. but it doesn't
work in C# in Unity. Let's see what error we get.
because you'll probably see this error in the future. "Cannot
modify a value type.
return value of Unity Engine transform.position"
"Consider storing the value in a temporary variable." It's telling
you the solution. and the problem is that this
transform here does not want you to set
its individual components. It wants you to set transform.
Position as a
Vector3. So. if we were to look at the docs for
transform.Position.
here it is a Vector3. So.
Vector3 I think is something you haven't seen before. so if you click
on the word Vector3. it'll take you to the manual page for
Vector 3. Note. the URL is now forward slash
Vector3. And Vector3 is something called a
structure. As it says. it's used throughout
Unity to pass 3D positions and directions around.
It also contains functions for doing common
vector operations. so basically. it's
three floats. We met float a minute ago. it's a floating point number.
It's a decimal number. and a Vector3
contains three floats. Even though these guys don't look like
floats here. because these are precise up. down. left. right
shortcuts. it is three
floats. And there's lots of stuff you can do with it but for now you just need to know
that a Vector3 is a way of compactly storing floats
in one place. that represent the X.
Y. and Z coordinates.
OK. And you we trying to
set a component of it. directly. Well. it wants you to build up
the Vector3 first. so let's do that. And if you
see that type of problem what you do is you come along and create yourself a local variable.
a Vector3. of type Vector3.
Now. what is a Vector3? It's just three numbers basically. it's a
struct of three numbers. and we're going to call
it paddlePos. It's going to be the full three dimensional
paddle position. and we're going to construct it with a new keyword.
There's a new Vector3. it's a very typical pattern you'll
use. and it's going to have three values. Well. the
first float. the X value initially will make 0.
Actually. let's make it 0.5. make it on the left hand side of the Play
Space. We need an f to signify float.
If we don't put the f. the system will try and store it as a double
and it won't fit. What do we want as the
initial Y position. Well. let's try 0 to start with.
and then. let's try 0 float for the Z. The
Z will always stay at 0. We
won't use this mouse position in blocks quite yet. but now try
this.transform.position =
paddlePos. which is what we're going to use as a variable for the transform position.
So. we've used this for the
first time. I just want to take a moment to explain exactly what this
is. This is the instance of the current
script. so it is the paddle script. the component
itself. So if you. for instance. were to destroy
this then what you would be destroying is the paddle
script. against the paddle object. So. that's what
this is. as per the diagram. I used
this dot throughout the section. but it's very much optional.
The command. transform.position =
paddlePos. without this dot would work just fine.
too. Let's try
it. it should end up a 0.5 on the left hand side. 0
Y and 0 Z. Let's see what happens.
So. there's your paddle here. let's just move it away from 0
Y. click play. and it moves
to the bottom left. I hope you saw that. If it's too quick for you. click
pause first and then play. Now. look at the paddle's position.
It is where we asked it to be 0.5 X and
0 Y. We actually don't want the Y to change. if I
set the paddle's position here. let's say when
I start in the Scene Editor. I don't
want it to change when the game runs. So. when we
construct this paddle position. instead of saying
0 in the beginning. why don't we just say
this.transform.position
.y. We're just saying
keep the current Y coordinate that you started with. Now.
when we run it. see how it
stays where it is in the Y. let's just do it in Pause Mode.
but moves over to the left. Great! So. we've
laid the foundation now to move this thing. left
and right. All we need to do now
is. we have a paddle position. it's of
three numbers it's an X. Y. Z. Vector3.
We just need to modify it's X value. so let's just go ahead and do
that: paddlePos.x
and we're allowed to do that here... = mouse
PosInBlocks. Now. if you were to just do that. let's try it.
and a surprisingly good result.
which is that the paddle moves around. But of course.
the paddle can go right outside the Play Space on either side.
so the final thing we need to sort out is that. I'm going to
reset my default paddle position to 8.
not 89... 0.5. so it's kind of below
the ball and there in the Game Space. right in the middle.
So. here's a challenge for you! I want you to
constrain the paddle to the Game Space. Use the Mathf.Clamp
method. The documentation for it is here.
This just gets you used to looking up documentation.
There are some examples here.
and what I want you to do is set the minimum to 0.5
and the maximum to 15.5.
OK. have a go at doing that! And when you're finished. what should happen
is you drag the paddle around. but it won't be allowed to leave the
left or right of the Game Space. Have a go at that now. and I'll see
you in a moment.
OK welcome back!
So. let's take a look at how we do that. So. using the pattern of
Mathf.Clamp. where you have
the value that you want to
clamp. it's minimum. and it's maximum. That's the pattern. so
let's take a look.
What we do is we say the
paddle position in X doesn't just = the paddle position in X.
as it was. but it's Mathf.Clamp.
the mouse position.
but comma 0.5 float is the
minimum. and 15.5 float
is the maximum. Let's try that!
I need to bounce the ball between each thing. but look. it won't leave the right
and won't leave the left. Congratulations!
We have the working of a player ball
Block Breaker game. So. I shall see you shortly. where
we'll continue to build on what we've learned. As a recap.
here is what we covered in this lecture.