Hey welcome back! So. we have
our ball physics sorted. We have our
ball firing off the bat. when we click the button. and
it's even bouncing off the bat. So. we now need
to get the side walls and the top wall sorted out
and to adjust up the speed so that the ball actually
has a chance of hitting the top wall. Cool! So.
how are we going to do that? Well. we could
build some walls out of bricks. In fact. I went down that root
with this project. and it's
a slippery slope. because once you start trying to build the wall out of bricks.
well I certainly very quickly wanted to
think about how to do it with a program
and that gets a bit technical for this stage in the course. So.
if you're really interested in how to build a brick wall with a program.
ask me in the discussions and I will consider putting
it in as a bonus video. But for now. we're just going
to use invisible colliders and use the background
as the visual
cue. as to where the play space ends.
Firstly. I'm going to turn off my Grid Gizmo. because
I don't need to see that grid. That's clearer! And now.
I'm going to create my first collider.
Before I do that. I'm going to make an organizing GameObject called Play
Space.
I'm fighting the Caps Lock Key and my fingers!
At last. woo hoo! I typed it
right! OK. Play Space. Reset the Transform.
And now. I'm going to put it near the top. and I'm going to put
the background into it. OK fantastic!
That's just for organization! Now. when I create the next empty Game
Object. I'm going to call it Left Wall.
There it is! OK now.
what is the Left Wall? It's nothing but a transform in the middle of the screen
right now. Not a lot of use. OK
so. what are we going to do with it? Well. I think I'm going to Reset it to the
origin. down here. and I'm going to add to it
a Box Collider 2D.
And now. I want to... I'm going to keep its origin
here. actually. but I want it to extend off to the left and
up to the top. So. it needs to have a Y size
of the height of our play space. which is
what? It's 16. I think it was 10
wasn't it? Let's take a look!
It looks like it's 12. the height of our play space. So.
we make our collider have a height of 12 and
that's all very well. but now. if you want the pivot
of this collider to be here. then you're going to
have to play around with the offsets. so let's do that!
Let's make the Center at X equals
0.5.
and that's about right
there! Perfect! And the Y Center at
6 let's try that or +6.
+6 great! Now. let's Reset it!
You get the idea! The combination of the Center and the
Size tells you how this collider sits.
It frankly really doesn't matter where it's transform
is. but I think that's a logical place for it to be.
OK fantastic! So. what I'd like
you to do now. as an exercise. is setup
the other two colliders. I'd like you to put a Top Collider
along here. and a Right Wall Collider
on the right hand side. which should be a mirror image of this one.
I don't mind how you do your Top Collider. as long as there are no
gaps. So. just to be
clear. I want you to pause the video and add a couple of colliders.
at the same width of the one I've done. which is 1 for the moment.
And ensure there are no spaces anywhere that the ball
could get out and test it by playing. So. pause
the video and do that now please.
Cool! Welcome back! So. the Right Wall I'm going to do by
duplicating the Left Wall. firstly.
Right Wall. hit Return.
and then. I'm going to move it across.
Now. the Left Wall is still there. don't worry. you just can't see it once you move
the Right Wall. And I wanted a position
of 17. by the looks of it. depending on where I put my origin.
And then. it looks like the Center is going to be + 0.5.
in this case. and 16. OK!
Well. that's logical because the Left Wall is at 0 and the Right
Wall is at 16.0. I like that!
Where would it make sense for the Top Wall's origin to be? Well. I
think in the middle maybe? It doesn't really matter. so let's
duplicate the Right Wall. Now. we
need to change it's Size. I'm going to go for a width of
16 and a height of 1. Perfect!
I'm going to call it a Top Wall.
OK. I'm going to Reset the Centers.
for the moment. just so I can get some sanity on where it is.
0. 0. Move
it up. OK. let's take the Y
Center down to +0.5. Note: It is +0.5.
OK.
that's fine! And then. I'm going to move the wall down
to precisely 12.
Oh dear. excuse me!
The problem is. I've got the microphone between my face and the
keyboard. so I can't see my fingers half the time. And
an X Position of 8. Ah. that makes sense! So.
the Left Wall is at 0. 0. It doesn't
really matter where it's transform is. but it looks right crucially.
I'm going to put the Top Wall in the middle. just
because I'm being OCD. The Top Wall is at 8.
12. It's in the middle at the top. that kind of makes sense.
and then. the Right Wall is on the Right Hand side. Awesome! So. they
are all colliders.
Now. are we safe here if I select all of them? Do we think that
the corner is good enough? Or do we want to make our Top Wall.
instead of 16 wide maybe we make it 18 wide.
like that. and then it overlaps completely? Oh. that
feels safe as houses! That's better! OK. are they
trigger colliders? No. they are not trigger colliders. we want it to
actually exhibit physics. So. let's try it!
Oh. it bounces off! Cool!
So now. we need to get our ball firing off with more velocity. bouncing
up higher and harder. It may be
worth spending a moment understanding the gravity
that's working on this thing right now. So. currently
the ball has a Mass of 1. What would happen if we made the Mass
1.000. notionally 1.000 kilos?
Well actually. here it doesn't make any different to how
high it goes. because remember. all object fall
at the same rate. in terms of acceleration. There's not air resistance
here. there's no linear drag. and there's no
actual collisions where the collision matters. because the
wall and the paddle are unmovable. The wall is just
colliders. they don't even have physics. and the paddle
is a physics body but it's Kinematic. which means it's not
allowed to move unless our script tells it to. So.
making the ball heavier makes no difference to how high it goes. and that's kind
of what you would expect. That is the
normal fact in a uniform acceleration. so
I'm going to set its Mass back to 1. So. what does this
Gravity Scale thing do? Well. it's very strange. their documentation
says that Gravity Scale is the "Degree
to which an object is affected by gravity."
But in the real world. objects don't
just choose to be affected by gravity.
to a different extent to another object. Gravity
is the curvature of space time. ultimately. and
that depends on the distribution of other masses around it.
So. it's a bit odd to change its
Gravity Scale but let's try it! Let's set its Gravity Scale to 10
and see what happens. You might want to use this to create
interesting effects in a game. Just bare in mind it's not
very real. So. that had a very high Gravity Scale and bounced
really really quickly. Or we could set the Gravity Scale to
the other extreme. which might be say 0.1.
And let's see what happens there!
Now it bounces
basically fine. roughly how we want it
to. But I am going to prefer to do this a different
way. because if we say have a brick in here.
that had some physics on it.
the brick will accelerate away
too fast. compared to how fast the ball is accelerating.
So. the ball and the brick would accelerate at different
speeds here. which is kind of weird. If I put
two bricks next to each other. this is like the feather and the
brick or the feather the golf ball. and they both have
Rigid bodies on them.
and one has a Gravity Scale of 0.1 and the other has a Gravity Scale
of 10. watch what happens! One accelerates very differently
to the other. and it's this second one that
has the same Gravity Scale now as the ball.
because we've divided the ball's
Gravity Scale by 10. So. because we want all
objects in the game to behave consistently. I don't
want to change the ball's Gravity Scale. I think that's weird and
I don't think it represents anything in the real world. and you may want
to use it in a game but I'm not going to do it here. But I do want it
to slow down. so let's give rid of these other two bricks.
Remind ourselves where we are. We''re back to where we started.
after having yet talked a bit. And we could just
send the ball off faster. but the fundamental problem is
not that it's not going off fast enough. it's that there's too much gravity.
So. what I want to do is show
you another setting. Edit. Project Settings.
Physics 2D. Click into that. and
at the top here. you've got a Gravity scale of -9.81.
That's roughly Earth's Gravity scale. maybe at the Equator.
9.81 meters per square second towards the center of the Earth.
Well. let's make that -1. about a 10th. and see what
happens. Now. this has exactly the same
apparent effect on the ball as what we did before.
which was change the ball's scale. but now. any
other objects we introduce into the game space will also
accelerate in this same way. Let's just try it by putting another
ball in here. and just drop a ball on
say there and give it a Rigidbody.
And with the default settings of the Rigidbody. which come with a
Gravity of 1. these two balls now behave
in a consistent way. I know that other ball is going slower
and it doesn't have a collider on it. but is it still
accelerating downwards at the same rate as this ball.
So. I much prefer doing it this way!
I hope that all makes sense for you. in summary.
Understanding Gravity Scale! It could be set in the RigidBody. but it's
a bit weird. I would use Edit. Project Settings.
Physics 2D. and without
any air resistance it basically uses the equations of Uniform Acceleration.
which you can read all about on Wikipedia.
Congratulations and see you soon!
=======
Hey welcome back! So, we have
our ball physics sorted. We have our
ball firing off the bat, when we click the button, and
it's even bouncing off the bat. So, we now need
to get the side walls and the top wall sorted out
and to adjust up the speed so that the ball actually
has a chance of hitting the top wall. Cool! So,
how are we going to do that? Well, we could
build some walls out of bricks. In fact, I went down that root
with this project, and it's
a slippery slope, because once you start trying to build the wall out of bricks,
well I certainly very quickly wanted to
think about how to do it with a program
and that gets a bit technical for this stage in the course. So,
if you're really interested in how to build a brick wall with a program,
ask me in the discussions and I will consider putting
it in as a bonus video. But for now, we're just going
to use invisible colliders and use the background
as the visual
cue, as to where the play space ends.
Firstly, I'm going to turn off my Grid Gizmo, because
I don't need to see that grid. That's clearer! And now,
I'm going to create my first collider.
Before I do that, I'm going to make an organizing GameObject called Play
Space.
I'm fighting the Caps Lock Key and my fingers!
At last, woo hoo! I typed it
right! OK, Play Space, Reset the Transform.
And now, I'm going to put it near the top, and I'm going to put
the background into it. OK fantastic!
That's just for organization! Now, when I create the next empty Game
Object, I'm going to call it Left Wall.
There it is! OK now,
what is the Left Wall? It's nothing but a transform in the middle of the screen
right now. Not a lot of use. OK
so, what are we going to do with it? Well, I think I'm going to Reset it to the
origin, down here, and I'm going to add to it
a Box Collider 2D.
And now, I want to... I'm going to keep its origin
here, actually, but I want it to extend off to the left and
up to the top. So, it needs to have a Y size
of the height of our play space, which is
what? It's 16, I think it was 10
wasn't it? Let's take a look!
It looks like it's 12, the height of our play space. So,
we make our collider have a height of 12 and
that's all very well, but now, if you want the pivot
of this collider to be here, then you're going to
have to play around with the offsets, so let's do that!
Let's make the Center at X equals
0.5,
and that's about right
there! Perfect! And the Y Center at
6 let's try that or +6.
+6 great! Now, let's Reset it!
You get the idea! The combination of the Center and the
Size tells you how this collider sits.
It frankly really doesn't matter where it's transform
is, but I think that's a logical place for it to be.
OK fantastic! So, what I'd like
you to do now, as an exercise, is setup
the other two colliders. I'd like you to put a Top Collider
along here, and a Right Wall Collider
on the right hand side, which should be a mirror image of this one.
I don't mind how you do your Top Collider, as long as there are no
gaps. So, just to be
clear, I want you to pause the video and add a couple of colliders,
at the same width of the one I've done, which is 1 for the moment.
And ensure there are no spaces anywhere that the ball
could get out and test it by playing. So, pause
the video and do that now please.
Cool! Welcome back! So, the Right Wall I'm going to do by
duplicating the Left Wall, firstly.
Right Wall, hit Return,
and then, I'm going to move it across.
Now, the Left Wall is still there, don't worry, you just can't see it once you move
the Right Wall. And I wanted a position
of 17, by the looks of it, depending on where I put my origin.
And then, it looks like the Center is going to be + 0.5,
in this case, and 16. OK!
Well, that's logical because the Left Wall is at 0 and the Right
Wall is at 16.0. I like that!
Where would it make sense for the Top Wall's origin to be? Well, I
think in the middle maybe? It doesn't really matter, so let's
duplicate the Right Wall. Now, we
need to change it's Size. I'm going to go for a width of
16 and a height of 1. Perfect!
I'm going to call it a Top Wall.
OK, I'm going to Reset the Centers,
for the moment, just so I can get some sanity on where it is.
0, 0. Move
it up. OK, let's take the Y
Center down to +0.5. Note: It is +0.5.
OK,
that's fine! And then, I'm going to move the wall down
to precisely 12.
Oh dear, excuse me!
The problem is, I've got the microphone between my face and the
keyboard, so I can't see my fingers half the time. And
an X Position of 8. Ah, that makes sense! So,
the Left Wall is at 0, 0. It doesn't
really matter where it's transform is, but it looks right crucially.
I'm going to put the Top Wall in the middle, just
because I'm being OCD. The Top Wall is at 8,
12. It's in the middle at the top, that kind of makes sense,
and then, the Right Wall is on the Right Hand side. Awesome! So, they
are all colliders.
Now, are we safe here if I select all of them? Do we think that
the corner is good enough? Or do we want to make our Top Wall,
instead of 16 wide maybe we make it 18 wide,
like that, and then it overlaps completely? Oh, that
feels safe as houses! That's better! OK, are they
trigger colliders? No, they are not trigger colliders, we want it to
actually exhibit physics. So, let's try it!
Oh, it bounces off! Cool!
So now, we need to get our ball firing off with more velocity, bouncing
up higher and harder. It may be
worth spending a moment understanding the gravity
that's working on this thing right now. So, currently
the ball has a Mass of 1. What would happen if we made the Mass
1,000, notionally 1,000 kilos?
Well actually, here it doesn't make any different to how
high it goes, because remember, all object fall
at the same rate, in terms of acceleration. There's not air resistance
here, there's no linear drag, and there's no
actual collisions where the collision matters, because the
wall and the paddle are unmovable. The wall is just
colliders, they don't even have physics, and the paddle
is a physics body but it's Kinematic, which means it's not
allowed to move unless our script tells it to. So,
making the ball heavier makes no difference to how high it goes, and that's kind
of what you would expect. That is the
normal fact in a uniform acceleration, so
I'm going to set its Mass back to 1. So, what does this
Gravity Scale thing do? Well, it's very strange, their documentation
says that Gravity Scale is the "Degree
to which an object is affected by gravity."
But in the real world, objects don't
just choose to be affected by gravity,
to a different extent to another object. Gravity
is the curvature of space time, ultimately, and
that depends on the distribution of other masses around it.
So, it's a bit odd to change its
Gravity Scale but let's try it! Let's set its Gravity Scale to 10
and see what happens. You might want to use this to create
interesting effects in a game. Just bare in mind it's not
very real. So, that had a very high Gravity Scale and bounced
really really quickly. Or we could set the Gravity Scale to
the other extreme, which might be say 0.1.
And let's see what happens there!
Now it bounces
basically fine, roughly how we want it
to. But I am going to prefer to do this a different
way, because if we say have a brick in here,
that had some physics on it,
the brick will accelerate away
too fast, compared to how fast the ball is accelerating.
So, the ball and the brick would accelerate at different
speeds here, which is kind of weird. If I put
two bricks next to each other, this is like the feather and the
brick or the feather the golf ball, and they both have
Rigid bodies on them,
and one has a Gravity Scale of 0.1 and the other has a Gravity Scale
of 10, watch what happens! One accelerates very differently
to the other, and it's this second one that
has the same Gravity Scale now as the ball,
because we've divided the ball's
Gravity Scale by 10. So, because we want all
objects in the game to behave consistently, I don't
want to change the ball's Gravity Scale. I think that's weird and
I don't think it represents anything in the real world, and you may want
to use it in a game but I'm not going to do it here. But I do want it
to slow down, so let's give rid of these other two bricks.
Remind ourselves where we are. We''re back to where we started,
after having yet talked a bit. And we could just
send the ball off faster, but the fundamental problem is
not that it's not going off fast enough, it's that there's too much gravity.
So, what I want to do is show
you another setting. Edit, Project Settings,
Physics 2D. Click into that, and
at the top here, you've got a Gravity scale of -9.81.
That's roughly Earth's Gravity scale, maybe at the Equator.
9.81 meters per square second towards the center of the Earth.
Well, let's make that -1, about a 10th, and see what
happens. Now, this has exactly the same
apparent effect on the ball as what we did before,
which was change the ball's scale, but now, any
other objects we introduce into the game space will also
accelerate in this same way. Let's just try it by putting another
ball in here, and just drop a ball on
say there and give it a Rigidbody.
And with the default settings of the Rigidbody, which come with a
Gravity of 1, these two balls now behave
in a consistent way. I know that other ball is going slower
and it doesn't have a collider on it, but is it still
accelerating downwards at the same rate as this ball.
So, I much prefer doing it this way!
I hope that all makes sense for you, in summary.
Understanding Gravity Scale! It could be set in the RigidBody, but it's
a bit weird. I would use Edit, Project Settings,
Physics 2D, and without
any air resistance it basically uses the equations of Uniform Acceleration,
which you can read all about on Wikipedia.
Congratulations and see you soon!
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1:Unity/Section5/13-Invisible-Colliders-Gravity-Scale.srt