Hey. so in this video we're going to talk
about snapping to grid. So. as we place our
blocks. in this play space. the challenge I have
with it is they're all a bit kind of messy. They're not
perfectly aligned with each other and we have too much freedom
of movement. So. what are we going to do about
that? Well. there's a not particularly well documented
Snap to Grid setting. You start by going to
Edit and then Snap Setting. down here.
And you need to setup your X and Y
movement. in this case. so that it's appropriate for our game space.
So. I'd like to be able to move our bricks by half a brick.
left and right. which is half a World Unit. so 0.5
and by
a whole brick. up and down. Now. what was a whole brick? Do you remember what
the amount of movement was? Well. if you're not sure
just try it. pop your brick somewhere.
Put another one exactly
one brick above. and if you remember. it was 0.32.
So. the difference between the Y position of this yellow
brick is 6. and the Y position of this red
at 6.32. So.
precisely 0.32 in the Y direction.
and rotation. well we're not doing rotation now. so let's
leave it. Cool! So. once you've set those Snap Settings. that's
a start. The next thing you need to do. before you start moving a brick
around. is snap the bricks to the axis. So. you could
select all of your bricks and snap to axis.
There you go! They're now all on the grid!
See if they weren't on the grid. then I could make a small change.
and then. when you hold down Control
or Command. and this is the real key
this is the bit that's not well documented. When you hold down the Control
or the Command Key while dragging.
that is when you snap to grid.
OK. so use the Edit. Snap Settings. set
initially to the grid. You can multi-select. as I've just showed you.
And now. hold down Control or Command. If I do that with this
brick. that's off the grid. it will move by the amount
we've said. half a brick sideways 0.32 upwards.
but it's still off grid OK.
So. this is why it is important to snap all of your bricks
to the grid. Great! So. now that we have
snapping in place. why don't you go ahead and build yourself
a first play space. Personally
the way I'm going to do that. in this first level. is I'm only going to
use two brick types. I'm going to use yellow and green.
and I'm just going to put some fairly unimaginative
even lines of bricks. Because remember. we want to
introduce the player to the game mechanics. slowly.
so I think the third brick type could come in later.
So go ahead now and pause the video and
build yourself a simple play space. of a few lines of bricks.
OK cool! So. I'm going to do that now. simply by taking say
the yellow brick. and duplicating it enough
times. Once. of course. you've done a few bricks you're
welcome to duplicate the whole lot. so sleek them all in the
Hierarchy and duplicate the whole lot. you see!
Now. OK it's pushed off
of the play space. but that doesn't matter. I could just move this all
back in. and if I continue to hold down this Control Key.
then I'm in good shape.
So. I think I'm going to just put another few bricks on the end.
I think I've got that right.
I've got one too many. So you get the idea. It's just lots of
holding down Command. while you
move things. or Control on the PC. and
of using Command or Control D to duplicate bricks. So.
I'll duplicate the green brick a few times. and then. once
I've go the pattern I'll start to...
I may even reorganize things in my Hierarchy
a little bit. For example. I might put a Sub-
GameObject in here. that says
Bottom Row. for instance.
And I would then reset the transform of that. because it's an
organizing object. I would pull it inside the Bricks
Object. and then. here's all the 1 hits
that are on the bottom row. so I can drag them into the Bottom
Row. collapse the BottomRow.
And now. you see I could easily make myself a new
organizing GameObjec. Reset it's transform.
call it Top Row. And
this is just a way of keeping everything really organized.
It goes into bricks there. the two hits go into the Top Row.
and now. when I work on the Top Row.
I'm a bit more clear about what's where in my Hierarchy.
OK. just one more brick!
Ah no. two more.
There we go! So. I've got two rows of
bricks. Now. the cool thing about having it organized like this is. I could select the Top
Row and Bottom Row together. like that. and then. I could
simply move them up a bit. you see.
You probably still want to hold down Command or
Control. So. maybe there? There you go! Now. let's test
that!
So. the bricks
aren't breaking yet. of course. because we haven't done that yet.
So. to test it properly. you need to kind of launch the ball so it
ends up through the gap. There you go! Perfect! So. we are really starting
to get the basics of Arkanoid going here. and you
have the freedom to start creating your own play
spaces. So. as a recap. the purpose of this video
was to teach you about the Snap to Grid feature. You
access it through Edit and Snap Settings. Snap
your thing initially to the grid. and you can do that with Multi-Select.
if you've already got lots of things in the scene and then hold down
Command or Control while dragging.
See you soon!