So now, we have the full basic
framework for a level. What I'd like to do now is make
everything a prefab, so in this lecture
we are going to prefabricate practically everything, apart from the
bricks. Make a few other tidy ups and changes,
like making the Main Camera's background black,
moving the Loose Collider into a group,
and moving it in the scene a little bit, and we'll test by making a new level.
So, let's take a look at this.
Each of these things, these instances here, like the Main Camera,
the LevelManager, they all have
value in them, and we want to capture that,
ready to start creating future levels. Sure our core
mechanic isn't finished yet. For instance, bricks can't break etc.
but we're going to sort that out later and I want
to use the fact that we're going to be changing core
mechanics to test and put pressure on the quality
of our prefabrication. If we've done it properly, then when
we change things, it'll change across all levels. So, we're going to
make several levels now, and then, we will
come and change the core mechanic after that. So, it's going to be fun!
Check it out! So, one thing I'm noticing is this horrible
blue cast to the background, and that's because the background
image, in the Play Space, has transparency,
has an alpha of 35% and it's,
if you look at the Main Camera, it has a blue background. So, first thing
I'm going to do is set the Main Camara's background to black.
Ah that's better, everything suddenly becomes more visible!
Now, if the background is too dark
now for your taste, then you can go into the Background
and increase its Transparency a little bit. If you
want. It's entirely up to you. Great!
So, this is going to serve as a kind of default background, for any kind of future
levels. Of course, it can be over-ridden. So,
I'm going to open up my Prefab Folder and go through and make
sure each object is tidy, one at a time, and then prefab
it, prefabricate it. So, this Main Camera,
it's good now that it's the right size. It's got a background color,
etc. So, I'm happy to prefab the Main
Camera, so we drag it into the Prefabs Folder.
Let's move down, the LevelManager. Well, this is a novel idea!
Why don't we prefab the LevelManager, so that if we
ever make any changes to it, we only have to make them
in one place, so I think that's a good plan. But before we prefab
it, let's Reset it's Transform, because
things like LevelManagers should really be at the origin,
just for tidiness, otherwise it looks good! Let's prefab
it. Play Space, OK the Play Space
is at the origin, which his good. It has a Background image,
a Left Wall, a Right Wall, a Top Wall.
I could select all of these and kind of see a visualization
of the Play Space. Something that strikes me is that
the Loose Collider is really part of the Play Space. So, I'm going to move
the Loose Collider into the Play Space object.
The next thing that strikes me is that there's a gap,
where the ball could sneak out down at the bottom
here. I don't really like that, so I'm actually going to
move the Loose Collider up a little bit
to -0.5 in Y,
like so, so it's
tight against the bottom. And I'm also going to make it a little bit wider,
18 units wide, like
so, so that it all fits snugly. Let's have a look.
When we highlight the Left, Right, Top
Wall, and the Loose Collider, look at that beautiful tight Play
Space! OK, so now my Play Space is as
a whole looks good! I'm just flicking through, it's got
a sprite on the Background
and a Left Wall a Right Wall. All of the transforms look good, so great!
This is a good time you see, as you prefab things, just to get them
tight and tidy. So, the Play Space looking good, prefabbing the Play
Space. Now, look what happens!
Under the Play Space you've got multiple items. You've got your Background and your
walls OK. So, that's a kind of nested prefab,
if you like, or at least it's a prefab of a
GameObject, with childed objects, so not strictly
a nested prefab. OK fantastic!
So bricks! Are we going to prefab this Bricks placeholder? We don't
need to, there's just no need. We already have prefabbed
individual bricks, so I'm going to leave that one. The Ball
I will prefab. Let's just check that it looks sensible.
This is a sensible default starting position for the ball.
Yes, it looks OK to me!
Is there anything else about the ball that we want to make sure is OK?
I don't think so. It's been working well, so let's prefab it
and the Paddle. Same deal,
it all looks OK, it's in a sensible position. Let's prefab the paddle.
Whew great! So, we have
prefabricated everything, apart from the Bricks
placeholder GameObject. If you look in the Hierarchy, everything
else is blue. Apart from the Bricks and it's
sub-placeholders, every other object in the scene is
blue, which is good because the only thing that really changes
between scenes is the layout
of the bricks and also the Background image, which of course we can change
on the next scene. Cool! So, what
I would like you to do now is create another scene.
Create a whole new blank scene, save it as
Level_02, put it in the
correct folder. Put it in here in the _Scenes Folder.
And then, drag in one of each
of all of the prefabs, and you might want to
just move your bricks, so they are not on top of each other.
OK, so go ahead and create that second scene
right now.
Cool!
So, the way I'm doing that is I'm just going File, New Scene.
It'll say do I want to save Level_01? Well, yes I do!
What do I want to call the new scene? Well, it hasn't asked,
because I haven't tried to save it. So, when I save scene,
it will be untitled at the top
here and here. You can see that
it's currently untitled. I'm going to call it Level_02. I'm going to put it
into _Scenes
and save it. Now, we've got a blank scene. All it's got in
it is a camera. We can delete that camera, because we
have a prefabbed camera. Let's take all of the objects.
Now as a hint, if you drop them straight into the Hierarchy,
rather than onto the scene like this, then they're going to
maintain their default positions. Let's see what happens! Ooh,
that's pretty cool! I'm going to move the Main Camera
up, I'm going to move the Paddle down,
and the Ball on top of it and maybe the LevelManager
up. OK
fine! So, that's absolutely fantastic! I'm going to create myself a
new empty GameObject called
Bricks
and just pop my bricks in it. So, nicely reorganized
scene here! Now, the beauty is watch this!
Just firstly let me spread my bricks out, like I suggested that you do.
Let's move them around a little bit, holding down Control
as I do, so that they snap to grid. Click play.
It nearly works!
You can nearly just play your game. Now,
what's happening is that your ball is not responding properly.
Why is that? Well, if we stop
we can actually see a hint at the bottom here,
"Object reference not set to an instance of an object"
in ball 19. So, what's
going on there? We could load the script,
or we could look at the ball. Either way, let's
wait for the script to load.
Ball 19, this.transform
.position = paddle
.transform. Ah, so we publicly expose Paddle
and something is going wrong with paddle, probably.
Let's take a look! The Ball is
asking for a Paddle and there is none. OK, so you need to drag the
Paddle onto the Ball. Now, that's a hassle to
do that every time you want to make
a new level. And you may think that why don't you
maybe go to the Ball Prefab and drag the Paddle
Prefab onto the Ball.
Well, you can try that. We could delete our Ball and
Paddle and see if it has worked. Unfortunately, that just
makes it worse, in a way, because the error. You still have
the problem but it's harder to see. Let's see it now.
We've still got the problem, but now if you look at the Ball,
it appears to have a Paddle attached. Unfortunately,
what it has attached is the Paddle Prefab, not this
instance of the Paddle. So, you would still need to
re-drag the Paddle. We're going to look at sorting that out in a subsequent
video, so don't worry about that for now. For this level just
do drag your Paddle instance onto your Ball.
so that we get into a situation where we can bounce like this.
But look, this is great news! We have done a fantastic
job of creating a new level, very very easily from
our previous assets. Just to finish off this new level,
let's change the Background image. So, go to your Play
Space Background, go and find the Background
image in your Finder,
in your assets that we give you, or just go and get one off the web.
I've got one here. I'm going to drag it into Sprites,
and then, once it's
in the Sprites, I'm going to set the Background
here to that.
And then, we need to make
sure that the size and shape of that Background image is right.
You see how it's come in and it's just sitting down on the bottom left here.
So, if we look at our Level_01 Background image, it's got
a Pixels Per Unit of 50 and a Pivot of Bottom
Left. Whereas this other one has a Pixels Per Unit of 100, so
it's half the size, so we sort that out. And
the Pivot is off as well, which is why it's down there.
If we set those the same as the Levl_01 Background, ah
how we're talking! You see, that looks just fine!
Great! So, we have a different level with a different
set of background
image. And I'm just going to, while I'm here,
move the blocks around a little bit, just so that they kind of are in
sympathy with the Background image.
Just something like that. OK, and
there you go! We have another level, which is also playable!