So. here we are happily creating
multiple scenes in our game. and we
have a great Prefabrication System. where we have all
the main things we need to create a new scene. setup
as prefabs. The challenge we have is
a couple of things break every time we try to make a new level.
One of them is the link between the
Paddle and the Ball. So. the Ball needs
to see an instance of a Paddle.
and there's no way that we can link the prefabs together.
We have to do this every time we create a new
scene. and we wouldn't want a designer having to think about
these type of details right. So basically.
we want a designer to be at very easily setup new
levels. to take the friction out of the process. So. that's
one problem. is that the ball and the paddle don't meet. and the other
problem. you'll see when the game ends. is that the LevelManager
here is similarly broken. So. if we
click on the LooseCollider.
it's expecting a LevelManager. and yes. sure I could
drag the LevelManager in but I don't want to
have to do that. so let's show you what we're going to do.
In this lesson. we're going to talk about why
linking prefabs programmatically helps. I've just explained
that. Unity doesn't support Nested Prefabs.
so we basically can't drag prefab to prefab and expect
it to maintain the connection. So. we're going to use something
called GameObject.FindObjectOfType&lt;&gt; OK.
and we're going to link things programmatically.
so our designers basically don't have to do it.
Cool! So. let's link the ball and the paddle this way.
If we go into the script for the ball. at the moment.
it's a public Paddle paddle; So. what I'm going to
do is. instead of public I'm just going to make it private.
so it's no longer exposed in the Inspector.
And then. in the Start method. the first thing I'm going to
do is say paddle =. Now.
follow me through with this one. It's GameObject.Find
and when you type that you'll see a load of options. We're going
to look for. it's a single object not a multiple object.
it's a single level manager. so we want FindObjectOf
Type. Now. you're very welcome to look at the docs for that
and see by example how it might work.
Here they are! And you can see it being used
here. This is one way. static "FindObjectOfType);"
In fact. it's the only one they show you. And let's
look at the example. While they do it like this.
I'm going to do it a slightly different way OK. So. just
follow my example through. because it's going to be more consistent
with other things. So. we're going to use a pair of
chevrons to do... Well. it's actually something called generics. it's
kind of like a filter. We're saying. I only want to FindObjects
that are or Type. whatever I put in the chevrons.
It's still a method. so we'd still need these curly brackets.
but we have the chevrons just before the curly brackets.
And what type of thing are we finding? Well. we're finding a &lt;Paddle&gt;.
It's actually as simple as that!
Yes. now that's right! There's only a single thing of type &lt;Paddle&gt; in the
entire game. So. when we say that we
declare our Paddle at the top here. so it's available to all of these
methods. because remember we're using Paddle down here. In fact.
if I do a search we can see all the places we're using Paddle.
So. we declare it there. and then. immediately when the game starts we go looking for
the Paddle. so that we don't have to associate it in the Editor.
Let's have a look at what happens now! If we run!
OK. we are getting
no exception error. Hang on. let's go to the Start Menu.
Let's run all the way through.
OK fine! So. that
level is working fine! If we look at Level_01.
and we look at it's LevelManager and we look at its Ball.
it no longer has a Paddle
associated. and when we look. when we move the paddle around
the ball sits on it. Level_02.
when we move it around it sits on it. and
if we were to create a new level it would work but we'll do
that at the end. as a complete test.
So. I want you to do the same thing for the LooseCollider. Let's fix
that other problem. I want you to make the public instance variable
private. That's the instance of the LevelManager.
remember the LooseCollider needs the LevelManager to load the next
level. So. make that private and then. do the same thing.
Find the LevelManager using exactly the same method
type that I used before. Obviously. it'll be a different type
in chevrons.
And test that it also loads properly and works. So. have a go at that
now!
OK welcome back! So. I'm going to go into
the LooseCollider. I'm
going to make my LevelManager private.
and then. in the Start here. I'm going to stop printing ("Trigger").
by the way. I just don't need it anymore. I'm going to go LevelManager.
[Laughs] Pirate. private!
OK. so levelManager
=
GameObject.Find.
It's a static method. ObjectOfType
What's the type? &lt;LevelManager&gt;
a bit weird looking function this. isn't it?
OK cool! So. let's try that! So.
hopefully our LevelManger now no longer needs to be associated
in the Editor. Let's go to the very Start Scene.
and make sure it works!
OK cool! Now. Start goes to
the End Scene. straight away. which is
fine. Let's just test it from Level_02 and make sure
Level_02 also works. Yep.
goes straight to the End Scene! So. obviously at some point we're going to want
Level_01 going to Level_02. and I'll show you that
in another video. For now. let's just make sure that we
can actually create a third level. that our prefabs are
right. So. let's create a new scene or level.
Scene and level are used interchangeably. It's
untitled. so let's save it straight into
Scenes.
There it is. Level_03! Now.
this is the proof of the pudding. Grab one of all of the prefabs. drop
them in. ditch the Main Camera.
You could. by the way. make an even higher order
prefab if you wanted. of all these things like that
but let's not bother with that. Just so that they're always in the right order. There is
no right order in the Hierarchy. It's just that I like to see
Main Camera. LevelManager. Play Space. Ball.
Paddle. or that could just be me bing OCD.
OK. so let's try this! Off it goes! Of course. it's got
a default background. and it goes to the End Screen.
Awesome! So. our prefabrication is working! Look. we have
fixed the issue with the ball leaving the paddle. By default they're
associated properly now. because they're associated in code.
And the other thing that's working is that the LevelManager is
now associated and linked to the
Loose Collider. so it's all working programmatically.
This is huge progress! We've not got three levels. it's now
become a trivial matter to create more levels. Of
course. in your new level. you can drop as many blocks in as
you want. Probably best. when you first drop them
in. to drop them into the Hierarchy
on the left here. because then they'll be on grid.
and then. you can drag them around
from there. If they ever get off grid. remember Edit. Snap Settings.
Snap All Axes.
In fact. saying they'll be on grid. look! We have a minor problem with our
prefab. They're not on grid! You see this guy
I just dropped into the Hierarchy. is not on
grid. So. why is that? That
is because. if we look at the prefab for these guys
for these bricks. their default position is
actually not on the grid and that's not very good. So. let's
fix that right now. Let's take a look at
what would be on grid. for instance. 9.92
is a position that's on grid. Let's apply that position
to the prefab. for the green brick.
for the yellow brick.
and we also need to make sure that
the red brick is on the tab. This is the default
position of the red brick. Again. being
careful! See that's slightly off grid! You see that?
You need to make sure that your prefab
default positions are on grid. Now.
they all are. provided that I Apply.
You see these have gone bold. they're different to the prefab.
Click Apply and it should
change the prefab. Now. all of the prefabs have a Y
position of 9.92 and slightly different
X positions. That's desirable. let's see the benefit.
If I now drop in three different
bricks. into the
Hierarchy. they all go in. in slightly different positions.
They're now not on top of each other. and they are
on grid. If I was to select one of them. Snap Settings.
Snap All Axes. it's on grid. Awesome! So. a little
bonus at the end of the video there now. We now have
three scenes all working perfectly! Congratulations!
See you soon!