Hey welcome back! So. we've done some great things here
with our prefabs and our ability to rapidly knock
out new levels. We have some things to
sort out. with regards to scene loading. For a start. when
we lose the game. it's currently going to a
Win Screen. It says "You beat Block Breaker".
you see and we haven't. We just
lost. so what are we going to do this level? Level?
Video even? We are going to
create a Loose Scene and modify our LooseCollider
to point to it. We're going to make a new method.
in the LevelManager. called LoadNextLevel(). so that
we don't have to have the very boring job of telling every
level what the next level is. We will add all our levels
to the Project Build Settings. Modify our Block.cs
to simulate winning. because at the moment we can't win
because we can't destroy all of the bricks yet. and then. test that
it all works. Cool! So. how are we going to
do this? That cool was very high pitched. wasn't it? Never mind.
Cool! So. let's do it! Firstly. we have
the Win Screen. As I say. it's not really a Win Screen. so
let's duplicate it. let's make oursevles
something called a Loose Screen.
Screen. scene. level. OK.
and where it says. "You beat Block Breaker". Well.
we don't want it to say "You beat Block Breaker".
We want it to say. "You
Lost!". as simple as that. So. that
is the Loose Screen. Now. another simple script
change. We need to think. what is responsible for
the Loose Condition? It's the LooseCollider! So. instead
of loading the Win Screen. it wants to load the ("Loose Screen");
and that's going to do the same. regardless of the level.
So. let's try that! If we are on Level_01
and we lose.
and what happens? Nothing
because we haven't added to our Build Settings. so that's
going to be a very very common error. The moment you
add a new scene. if you want it to be in the game. you're going to
need to add it to your Build Settings. So. let's go into the Build Settings.
I'm going to delete everything that's there and
put all of the scenes in the Build Settings. and while
we're here. let's bring the Start Menu to the top.
You may need to bring Level_01 below it. you may not
be able to drag it to the top. And then. what we want
to be able to happen is as follows. We want to go from the Start
Menu to Level_01. If we win. onto Level_02.
if we win onto Level_03.
and through all of the levels. however many we have. until eventually
you go to the Win Screen that says you conquered the game. If at any
point you lose. you want to leap frog straight down
to Loose Screen. So. that's the behavior we want.
If you look on the right hand side of the Build Settings we've actually
got a number starting at 0. which is a level index.
We start with level index 0. then 1. then 2.
then 3. Shortly. we're going to make very good use of that.
We're going to just increment the level index. every time we win.
But for now. let's just look at the Loose Condition and make sure that's
working. So. Level_01. run.
lose. "You Lost!". Great!
Just test it from Level_02. it should work exactly the same.
Great! So. let's recap why that's working!
It's working because in the Play Space.
we have a Loose Collider. On the Loose Collider we have
a script. It's the same script on all Loose Colliders. and they
always load the Loose Scene. Fantastic!
So. what we need to do now is simulate winning.
because we haven't actually built in the win
functionality yet. By the way. you may think the order in which
we're teaching this section is strange. Why can't we destroy
blocks? Why can't we win yet? Well. what I want to do
is. I want to prove that if we structure our game
properly. in quotes. then adding functionality
like the ability to destroy blocks will be possible
even though we've created multiple levels. That's what's going to be really cool!
We're going to actually create block destructibility.
after we've made a few levels. So.
you don't necessarily have to get all of your game mechanic completely
nailed. before you start building out levels. It's a
intermingled process right. The process of
creating levels may give you an idea about a new mechanic. and
the process of creating game mechanics may give you ideas
about levels and scenes. so they work together!
So. what would a natural way of
simulating a win be? Well. let's put it in the very script
we're going to end up with. which is on the Brick.
And what's going to happen is after some time on the collision
of a brick we are going to detect a win.
a destruction of the brick. and then. we're going to detect
that it's the final brick and we're going to somehow
win. So for now. I'm just going to create a new function
called SimulateWin(); OK. I'm just going to call that.
And then. I'm going to describe what I'm doing with a comment.
and I'm going to put TODO. TODO is a special comment that comes up bold.
And you could always do a search across your files for all of your TODO's.
"TODO Remove this method
once we can
actually win!". OK!
Now. let's define void. it doesn't need anything to come back.
SimulateWin(). checking that the red goes away.
when we do this.
There you go! So.
what are we going to do? Well. we're going to Level
Manager.LoadLevel. when we win.
but load which level? Well. and also well don't have a
LevelManager. so there's two things we need to do here.
Firstly. we need to create a LevelManager that is available
to the Brick. So. I'm going to let you
do that. as a challenge. We've done it a couple of times now. I want you to make
a private LevelManager at the top. and in the Start. find
it using FindObjectOfType. So. go
ahead and. as a micro challenge. do that now.
OK. so we have a private LevelManager
levelManager;
And then. on the Start. we find it in the scene.
levelManager = GameObject.Find
ObjectOfType
Left chevron LevelManager right chevron. It's a method.
so it needs brackets and everything needs a semicolon.
on pain of death. OK. so what we want
to call is LevelManager dot. Not with a capital L but
with a small l. it's the instance. We've got
this LoadLevel thing. but I don't want to be laboriously
going through and telling every level what the next level is. so
I want a new method called LoadNext
Level. It doesn't exist yet. But that's o.k.
That's wishful thinking. it's red. Let's go ahead and
make this levelManager.LoadNextLevel
method. Into your
Sprites. Scripts even.
Into the LevelManager. Let's make a new method called
public LoadNext
Level(). It doesn't need any information. so no
parameters coming in. Now. what are
we going to do? Well. here's a useful thing. Application
.LoadLevel()
OK. And then. what level
are we going to load? Well. we could pass a level index in. Let's look at
the docs for it for a second.
A couple of ways
it works. There are two signatures for this method.
One is. you pass an integer index in. which I showed you in the
Build Settings. and the other is. you pass in a string. We're going
to use the index. and where
are we going to get the index from? Well. this is the cool thing! We can just go
(Application
.loadedLevel. There you go.
and it returns an integer
+ 1); Hah. now that's pretty
cool. right! Now. LevelManager.Load
NextLevel will automatically
load the next level in the sequence.
What's this
error about him. when I did the build? "Class. struct. or interface method
must have a return type". Of course. we're missing void
OK. So. public void LoadNext
Level(). What that's going to do
is it's going to load whatever is the next level
in our Build Settings here. Boom boom boom boom!
So. Start Menu is going to explicitly
load Level_01. and then.
the rest of these. when we win. are going to use
the SimulateWin() method to just load the next level.
until we get to the Win Screen. Let's see if it works!
By the way. if you go back into
your Brick. this LoadNextLevel is no longer red. because it
exists. Alright. let's try it!
So. here we are! Actually. we'd better know which scene we're on.
Let's start at the Start. right. Start Menu.
Start Button.
As soon as we hit the brick we win. Let's try losing
on this second level. "You Lost!" Great! Play
Again! Hit a brick. "You Win!"
Hit a brick. "You Win!"
Can't win here. because there are no bricks. We lose!
Great! OK. just to finish that off
on Level_03. let's pop a single brick in.
There it is. so that you can win!
Just move it
a little bit.
...so it's easy to hit. I'm holding down Control. You always want everything
on grid. Level_03 "You
beat Block Breaker!" Fantastic! Let's just look at the whole flow
again. with Maximize on Play. just so it looks
right. Maximize on Play will only
take effect when you play a fresh game.
and you want to be starting from your Start Menu.
of course. Saving
scenes as you go. OK. let's
start! Win!
Win! Win! We beat Block Breaker!
Win! Now. let's lose here.
by not hitting a brick. Ha ha. "You lost!"
Perfect! Awesome awesome job! So.
I hope that all made sense to you. Let's just look at the slide as a recap.
We have created a Loose Scene and modified our
LooseCollider. so that it goes there rather than the Win Scene.
We've added a very handy new method to our LevelManager. called Load
NextLevel. which increments up to the next level index.
so that the soul place that we define our level
holder is in the Build Settings. We have to put things in Build
Settings anyway. in order for them to be loadable. so why
not have that as the place that we income the logical
order of the levels. Cool hey. all in one place! I love
it when you can have a single place for information and
everything in that single place. It's great!
Add all of our levels to the project Build Settings. Well. we did that.
of course. We added a SimulateWin() method to the
block. Later. the block will be responsible for detecting
the win condition. i.e.. all the destructible blocks are gone out
of the level. And we will replace that method later. but it's
the great way of testing the process and better
than sticking an ugly button in the level. And we tested it all
and it worked just great! So congratulations and
I'll see you soon!
=======
Hey welcome back! So, we've done some great things here
with our prefabs and our ability to rapidly knock
out new levels. We have some things to
sort out, with regards to scene loading. For a start, when
we lose the game, it's currently going to a
Win Screen. It says "You beat Block Breaker",
you see and we haven't. We just
lost, so what are we going to do this level? Level?
Video even? We are going to
create a Loose Scene and modify our LooseCollider
to point to it. We're going to make a new method,
in the LevelManager, called LoadNextLevel(), so that
we don't have to have the very boring job of telling every
level what the next level is. We will add all our levels
to the Project Build Settings, Modify our Block.cs
to simulate winning, because at the moment we can't win
because we can't destroy all of the bricks yet, and then, test that
it all works. Cool! So, how are we going to
do this? That cool was very high pitched, wasn't it? Never mind.
Cool! So, let's do it! Firstly, we have
the Win Screen. As I say, it's not really a Win Screen, so
let's duplicate it, let's make oursevles
something called a Loose Screen.
Screen, scene, level. OK,
and where it says, "You beat Block Breaker". Well,
we don't want it to say "You beat Block Breaker".
We want it to say, "You
Lost!", as simple as that. So, that
is the Loose Screen. Now, another simple script
change. We need to think, what is responsible for
the Loose Condition? It's the LooseCollider! So, instead
of loading the Win Screen, it wants to load the ("Loose Screen");
and that's going to do the same, regardless of the level.
So, let's try that! If we are on Level_01
and we lose,
and what happens? Nothing
because we haven't added to our Build Settings, so that's
going to be a very very common error. The moment you
add a new scene, if you want it to be in the game, you're going to
need to add it to your Build Settings. So, let's go into the Build Settings.
I'm going to delete everything that's there and
put all of the scenes in the Build Settings, and while
we're here, let's bring the Start Menu to the top.
You may need to bring Level_01 below it, you may not
be able to drag it to the top. And then, what we want
to be able to happen is as follows. We want to go from the Start
Menu to Level_01. If we win, onto Level_02,
if we win onto Level_03,
and through all of the levels, however many we have, until eventually
you go to the Win Screen that says you conquered the game. If at any
point you lose, you want to leap frog straight down
to Loose Screen. So, that's the behavior we want.
If you look on the right hand side of the Build Settings we've actually
got a number starting at 0, which is a level index.
We start with level index 0, then 1, then 2,
then 3. Shortly, we're going to make very good use of that.
We're going to just increment the level index, every time we win.
But for now, let's just look at the Loose Condition and make sure that's
working. So, Level_01, run,
lose, "You Lost!". Great!
Just test it from Level_02, it should work exactly the same.
Great! So, let's recap why that's working!
It's working because in the Play Space,
we have a Loose Collider. On the Loose Collider we have
a script. It's the same script on all Loose Colliders, and they
always load the Loose Scene. Fantastic!
So, what we need to do now is simulate winning,
because we haven't actually built in the win
functionality yet. By the way, you may think the order in which
we're teaching this section is strange. Why can't we destroy
blocks? Why can't we win yet? Well, what I want to do
is, I want to prove that if we structure our game
properly, in quotes, then adding functionality
like the ability to destroy blocks will be possible
even though we've created multiple levels. That's what's going to be really cool!
We're going to actually create block destructibility,
after we've made a few levels. So,
you don't necessarily have to get all of your game mechanic completely
nailed, before you start building out levels. It's a
intermingled process right. The process of
creating levels may give you an idea about a new mechanic, and
the process of creating game mechanics may give you ideas
about levels and scenes, so they work together!
So, what would a natural way of
simulating a win be? Well, let's put it in the very script
we're going to end up with, which is on the Brick.
And what's going to happen is after some time on the collision
of a brick we are going to detect a win,
a destruction of the brick, and then, we're going to detect
that it's the final brick and we're going to somehow
win. So for now, I'm just going to create a new function
called SimulateWin(); OK, I'm just going to call that.
And then, I'm going to describe what I'm doing with a comment,
and I'm going to put TODO. TODO is a special comment that comes up bold.
And you could always do a search across your files for all of your TODO's.
"TODO Remove this method
once we can
actually win!". OK!
Now, let's define void, it doesn't need anything to come back.
SimulateWin(), checking that the red goes away,
when we do this.
There you go! So,
what are we going to do? Well, we're going to Level
Manager.LoadLevel, when we win,
but load which level? Well, and also well don't have a
LevelManager, so there's two things we need to do here.
Firstly, we need to create a LevelManager that is available
to the Brick. So, I'm going to let you
do that, as a challenge. We've done it a couple of times now. I want you to make
a private LevelManager at the top, and in the Start, find
it using FindObjectOfType. So, go
ahead and, as a micro challenge, do that now.
OK, so we have a private LevelManager
levelManager;
And then, on the Start, we find it in the scene.
levelManager = GameObject.Find
ObjectOfType
Left chevron LevelManager right chevron. It's a method,
so it needs brackets and everything needs a semicolon,
on pain of death. OK, so what we want
to call is LevelManager dot. Not with a capital L but
with a small l, it's the instance. We've got
this LoadLevel thing, but I don't want to be laboriously
going through and telling every level what the next level is, so
I want a new method called LoadNext
Level. It doesn't exist yet. But that's o.k.
That's wishful thinking, it's red. Let's go ahead and
make this levelManager.LoadNextLevel
method. Into your
Sprites, Scripts even.
Into the LevelManager. Let's make a new method called
public LoadNext
Level(). It doesn't need any information, so no
parameters coming in. Now, what are
we going to do? Well, here's a useful thing. Application
.LoadLevel()
OK. And then, what level
are we going to load? Well, we could pass a level index in. Let's look at
the docs for it for a second.
A couple of ways
it works. There are two signatures for this method.
One is, you pass an integer index in, which I showed you in the
Build Settings, and the other is, you pass in a string. We're going
to use the index, and where
are we going to get the index from? Well, this is the cool thing! We can just go
(Application
.loadedLevel. There you go,
and it returns an integer
+ 1); Hah, now that's pretty
cool, right! Now, LevelManager.Load
NextLevel will automatically
load the next level in the sequence.
What's this
error about him, when I did the build? "Class, struct, or interface method
must have a return type". Of course, we're missing void
OK. So, public void LoadNext
Level(). What that's going to do
is it's going to load whatever is the next level
in our Build Settings here. Boom boom boom boom!
So, Start Menu is going to explicitly
load Level_01, and then,
the rest of these, when we win, are going to use
the SimulateWin() method to just load the next level,
until we get to the Win Screen. Let's see if it works!
By the way, if you go back into
your Brick, this LoadNextLevel is no longer red, because it
exists. Alright, let's try it!
So, here we are! Actually, we'd better know which scene we're on.
Let's start at the Start, right. Start Menu,
Start Button.
As soon as we hit the brick we win. Let's try losing
on this second level. "You Lost!" Great! Play
Again! Hit a brick, "You Win!"
Hit a brick, "You Win!"
Can't win here, because there are no bricks. We lose!
Great! OK, just to finish that off
on Level_03, let's pop a single brick in.
There it is, so that you can win!
Just move it
a little bit,
...so it's easy to hit. I'm holding down Control. You always want everything
on grid. Level_03 "You
beat Block Breaker!" Fantastic! Let's just look at the whole flow
again, with Maximize on Play, just so it looks
right. Maximize on Play will only
take effect when you play a fresh game,
and you want to be starting from your Start Menu,
of course. Saving
scenes as you go. OK, let's
start! Win!
Win! Win! We beat Block Breaker!
Win! Now, let's lose here,
by not hitting a brick. Ha ha, "You lost!"
Perfect! Awesome awesome job! So,
I hope that all made sense to you. Let's just look at the slide as a recap.
We have created a Loose Scene and modified our
LooseCollider, so that it goes there rather than the Win Scene.
We've added a very handy new method to our LevelManager, called Load
NextLevel, which increments up to the next level index,
so that the soul place that we define our level
holder is in the Build Settings. We have to put things in Build
Settings anyway, in order for them to be loadable, so why
not have that as the place that we income the logical
order of the levels. Cool hey, all in one place! I love
it when you can have a single place for information and
everything in that single place. It's great!
Add all of our levels to the project Build Settings. Well, we did that,
of course. We added a SimulateWin() method to the
block. Later, the block will be responsible for detecting
the win condition, i.e., all the destructible blocks are gone out
of the level. And we will replace that method later, but it's
the great way of testing the process and better
than sticking an ugly button in the level. And we tested it all
and it worked just great! So congratulations and
I'll see you soon!
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1:Unity/Section5/18-Level-Management-Build-Order.srt