Hey welcome back! So, in this video we're going
to make our blocks actually be destroyed when
the ball hits them, rather than just
loading a level. So, let's take a look at how we're
going to do that. If you pop into your Brick Script,
you'll recall that we already publicly exposed
a maximum hits variable. We're not using it yet.
If you look in Unity, under Prefabs
in the Inspector against the
script, you'll see a maximum hits number
exposed there, which should already be set to 1 for the
yellow, meaning it's going to be destroyed immediately.
Two for green means it goes on the second hit and three for red.
So, in this video what we're going to be doing
is, discussing how the Destroy() method works,
explaining why we destroyed
gameObject and not this, and then, I'm going to challenge you
to only destroy it, when the maximum number of hits are met.
So, back into our script then.
Let's get rid of
this SimulateWin(); line, we don't need that anymore!
That's gone. What we're going to do is firstly
think, well what are we going to destroy? Well, I'll tell
you for a start that the keyword we need is Destroy. Now, let's
go to Unity's docs for Destroy. Here
they are! They're expecting to destroy an object.
It's Object.Destroy, and there's no
example available. So, what have we got? There's
two possibilities, maybe. One would be this
which is a brick, actually not an object, and another
would be (gameObject), which is actually what we're looking
for. So, you need to Destroy (gameObject);
If you try and destroy this, it won't work because this is a brick
and (gameObject) is actually the object you're looking for.
Alright, so just remember when you destroy you Destroy(gameObject);
and save your script and let's try it!
Ah, that's good!
So, it's a start! Right now, the bricks are being destroyed. Now of course, the
green bricks are being destroyed on one hit, and that's because
we haven't told the system to do anything different
to that, but at least we have our first inkling of a
working Arkanoid clone. So congratulations
on that bit! Now, what I want you to do as a challenge is
I want you to put an if statement around the
Destroy line, line 24 on my screen, and
I want you to make sure that the
brick is only destroyed when you get to maximum
hits. So to be clear, yellow bricks should destroy immediately as they are,
but green bricks should only destroy on the second hit.
And if that's working red bricks should work as well.
So, test that by playing. Pop a couple of red bricks
in the scene and make sure that all of that works. So, please
pause the video and put that simple if statement around
the outside of the destroy line, now.
Cool and welcome back! So, this is how I'm doing it!
I'm going to say, if. And I will
do my brackets and my curly brackets first. Of course, the
second curly brace needs to go under destroy.
Now, this is only a single line code block here.
You can write it, if you wish, like this,
if something Destroy, but I would
really prefer you be in the habit of always using
code blocks, because if you do this the temptation could be
to do that, which is also OK.
If some condition Destroy the (gameObject), but then if
you go and write "some line here" that will
not get executed inside the if.
It will get executed outside of the if, i.e., this
"will ALWAYS BE
EXECUTED", because you've basically
indented wrongly and you should have indented like so,
and the if statement is separate. So look, that's all bloody
confusing! So, what I like to do is immediately
that I write the world if, I use
curly braces immediately, so
that I know I'm dealing with a code block. If I want to add another
line here, it's going to work as we expect.
Alright, so if something destroyed the GameObject, well
if what? Well, it's go to do with timesHit and maxHit.
timesHit starts at 0, so if (times
Hit is = to maxHits)
we destroy the object, right. So, in the beginning it's 0,
and for the yellow block the maxHits is
is 1. So, this doesn't occur and it doesn't destroy,
and then, when it hits 1 it will
destroy. Let's test it!
OK, so we have:
"Cannot implicitly convert type 'int' to 'bool'"
on line 25. So, bool is to do a
Boolean, it's a yes, no, true, false, and int is an Integer.
So, you double. Sorry line twenty-five
click on that error and it'll take you to the line. Another way of finding
the error is to go to Build and Build All, and it will show
you the error straight away. The problem is, I'm using =.
It's actually ==! You do a comparison
with ==. Equals itself
alone is an assignment. It was trying to set maxHit
into timesHit OK,
and then, the result of that was
an Integer and it was expecting a Boolean.
Very confusing, so == for a comparison please.
Let's try again!
OK, hit two
blocks at once. There you go! OK, so the yellow blocks appear to be working, but
that's not surprising, because they were working before. Now, let's see the green blocks,
when I finally hit one. Now, these boring play
loops that we can get in like this, we're going to fix those later.
For now, I'm just going to start the game again, because it got
into what I call a boring play loop. Let's just try again!
What we're aiming to do is hit a green
block, and then, see... There you go! One hit on
that green block. Now, to test it, I would like to hit the
same green block again, so it can be a little bit tedious, but at least
you're getting to play your game. That's interesting! I'm not
entirely sure which block I hit, so
you're just going to have to potentially play this a few times.
There you go! If you get it up in that gap then that's
great, so now we're hitting all of these blocks once. [Laughs]
It's here to test us! It doesn't want us
to see what happens if we hit a green block twice. I think
every single green block on the top there, or practically all of them got hit.
So, in a minute we're going to get our way, and we're going to get a
second hit on a green block. Oh no! It's here to test
my patience! Are we ever going to hit a
green block again! Oh wow, at last and it
gets destroyed! So it works, fantastic! That's
great news! So, what I would like to do,
rather than say == is, I would like to say
let's go greater than our =. Why?
Well, imagine that in the future we extend the behavior
and we have some super ball or something, that has the
effect of hitting a brick twice. You could completely
skip the limit. You could have had one hit initially,
and then, suddenly three or four or five and then,
you would never equal it. So, if we go greater than our equals,
we're guarding against the situation in which we end up
with more hits than the maxHits. I hope that makes
sense, so greater than or equals, just in case we skip over
maxHits. And then, in that instance we are going to Destroy
the (gameObject). So, it works! That's
great! What I want to do now is, pop a
red brick into the scene. So, I'm going to go to my Prefabs. I like
to do that by dropping it onto the Hierarchy, not into the scene,
because then it will end up somewhere
actually in the
correct place. Now, what have I done here? Why does this look weird?
Because I'm on the Start Menu Scene
it's indicated at the top of the screen here. Alright, common mistake,
so take it out of the Start Menu Scene, go into
the level that you want to test with, yeah.
Now, drag your prefab
into the Hierarchy, and it arrives in a predefined
place. That's great! I'm going to move it, holding down Control
or Command, to somewhere that I can hit it lots.
There. And I'm going to test that this red brick behaves, as
we expect. Ready? There's not music in this
case, because I started directly on this scene. I'm going to
stop and try again, just because I can't...
Ah, this is tedious. OK, so
it's quite tedious to test these things sometimes,
but in the early days it's not a
bad thing to be having to test your game
code a lot, because you're play testing while
you do it. So, what I'm going to do to make this easier
is, I'm just going to... Let's think of the
quickest way. Maybe the quickest way, actually, is to take my
Top Row of bricks here and duplicate it, move it
up a little bit like so, and
then, I could replace them all.
Well, I'm just going to cheat. I'm not going to replace the prefabs.
I'm going to just set the Max Hits of the green bricks.
If I want to, I can set them to a red color as well,
it doesn't really make any difference. I am accepting
that my color picker refuses to stay open, so
let's not bother changing the color. It has changed, actually, to gray.
So, these are gray bricks that have a three hit maximum.
I'm actually going to put one more on the top here, just so the ball
can't escape, and what I'm going to aim to do is fire the ball up this
gap. Whoop failed! Let's try again!
I'm going to try and fire up the gap, which is probably easier
said than done. There we go! Boom! There you go! You can
see, I mean I really didn't count there, but I'm pretty confident that it's three
hits and that after three hits it's going. And again, we're in a
boring loop, which we'll sort out later. Cool!
So, I'm going to take out my extraneous top row there,
because it's kind of ugly, save the scene,
and that's it! That is how you destroy objects
when you exceed the maximum number of hits. We have more
work to do, but hey, this is a good piece of progress.
So congratulations and see you soon!