Hey welcome back guys and girls!
So in this video. we want to give the users some feedback
about how broken the blocks are. So. the yellow ones
break immediately but the green ones you have to hit
more than once. but the use has no idea
how many times they need to hit them. So. what we're going
to do. in this lecture particularly. is
we are going to explain why a Sprite
Sheet is a useful thing. the key features
of a Sprite Sheet. We'll create the sprites'
partially broken blocks. and import them into Unity.
So. why is a Sprite Sheet a useful thing. and what is
a Sprite Sheet. Well firstly. what is a Sprite Sheet?
It's something like this. just a set of images
that are related. for the various animation
states. or just states of something in your game.
Here's a brick wall crumbling. in the top row.
So currently. if we look in our
Sprites Folder. we have a Full Brick. and
if you click the little arrow you'll see that
the image is called Full Brick and
it's being treated. if you look in the Inspector. as a single
sprite. You see under Inspector. Sprite
Mode. Single. and then. if you
pull the little drawer out. what you've got in the drawer is a single
sprite called Full Brick and it's actually that.
that we're referring to in the prefabs. If I was to
change the name of this Full Brick
sprite then. over in the prefab here.
that's what would change. When we select sprite
we're selecting the thing in the drawer. same with
the Left Brick and same with the Right Brick. So
where does it make sense for the ball to possibly be a separate sprite.
in the backgrounds? The brick is so related to itself
that there's some benefits. in terms of organization.
in having it all in
one Sprite Sheet. particularly when you
get to more complex scenarios. like you see here like
this bomb going off and the flames and things.
So firstly. I'm going to tidy up the
Left and Right Brick. into a single Sprite Sheet. so that we have
one. and then. I'm going to challenge you to create the
broken block effect. your way. So. how are we going to
do this. Well. I'm going to find where my Full
Brick sprite is in my File System.
and I'm going to open it. in my case. with Pixen. P. i. x.
e. n. That's a Mac program you can find
just by Googleing for Pixen. I think it's worth the
$10 if you're doing any Pixel art. The other
thing you can use. which is free and will work on Mac
and PC is Gimp. And even
though we introduced Gimp earlier in the course. I don't want this course to become too
reliant on Gimp. so I'm going to use a different Mac program
called Pixen. But if you don't have a
Mac or you prefer to use Gimp then one of our students. Okiliy
Dokily. has very helpfully provided
Gimp instructions. that you can see in the discussions
agaisnt this lecture or on the screen right now.
These are step by step. I've pretty much left them unedited. just as a
homage to Okiliy Dokily for his super helpful
set of instructions. The other thing you can do. of course. if you
think. I just want to crack on with making the game. is just go to the
resources of this lecture. and I've provided my
completed Sprite Sheet. attached to this very lecture.
So. you don't even need to bother making a Sprite Sheet for yourself.
if you don't want to. So. to recap. you can use
Gimp. you can use another editor of your choice.
but whatever image editor you decide to go for. it's important
it supports tranparent backgrounds.
You'll see why. It's important it's easy to resize your
Canvas. to resize the image to put more space around
the outside of it. and ideally it would support layers as
well. So. let's
take a look. I'm. as I say. going to open my Full Brick
in Pixen. which is my program of choice here.
so let's just do that.
And the principles
I'll show you in Pixen will apply very well to anything else that
you decide to use. So the mission is. and I'm going to
walk you through it. is to end up with all three the Full Brick. the Left
Brick. and the Right Brick. in the same image. So.
how big is this image? 128 wide by 41
high. I want to put two more bricks below it. both of
height 41. and I want at least one. I'm
going to go for two pixels of gap around. So.
4. 8. 12. 123
pixels. so if I go for
125 I'll be about right. So. I'm going to resize
my canvas. leaving the current image at the top
to 125.
OK cool! Then. I'm going to
go into my other bricks. I'm going to go find my Left
Brick. I'm going to open that in
Pixen. I'm going to copy it
and paste it into this image down here.
Like so.
And then. I'm going to go back. I'm going to find my Right Brick.
I'm going to open it with Pixen.
copy it all.
and paste it in here. Now. I can put it at the bottom.
which would be fine. It doesn't quite
look the same width. Let me just check that. I'm on different layers here.
I just want to make sure that you put your things down in exactly the right
place. That's OK. these are opacities I'm playing with
we don't need to change them. So. I can put it here in the Sprite Sheet
or I could put it here. For neatness. I'm going to put it there.
I've got a bit of extra space to use later. as long as you
understand what's going on. I've got three images in the
same image now. effectively. So . if I
was to then save this. and I'm going to save it as something
different. I'm going to save it as Bricks. in the
folder. in the Assets Folder. So. Block Breaker.
Assets. Sprites. I'm going to call it Bricks. and
I'm going to save it as a .png OK.
because that supports transparencies in the background. Let's go
back to Unity. and if you refresh
in here. you may see bricks appear. I do
see bricks. it's also changed my original file. It doesn't matter
because I'm going to delete all three of these. In fact. I'm going to boldly delete
all of the other sprites now. completely.
Everything will disappear out of your scene. don't worry about it. it's very easy to
fix. Bricks. what is this? This is an
image with three sprites in it. but currently the system only sees
it as one sprite. so this is how we chop out the
sprites. Watch this! Click onto Bricks. your new image.
under the Inspector in Sprite Mode click
Multiple. you're telling it there's more than one. You'll
recall that your Pixels Per Unit was 128 before
and click Sprite Editor. I
actually click apply first. and then it'll apply the 128.
You can do this at any time. you can do it later. Once you're
in the Sprite Editor. here you see it now. under the Slice options
at the top left. because we've left
a space around them and the background is transparent the Automatic
Slice will work. Click Automatic and you'll
see some very faint borders. If you click on each part of the image.
you'll see it's actually recognized all three images.
Now. all we need to do is name them. and I'm going to call this
one 0 hits. because it has
not been hit. I'm just going to call this one very clearly. simply
left. and I'm going to call this one right.
And the final thing I'm going to do is put their pivot points at the bottom left.
because that's where they were before. OK.
Cool! If  you click apply at the top here.
towards the top right. and then close this.
now look back in Unity. You have a single
Bricks Sprite Sheet image.
which is being interpreted as multiple sprites.
and when you pull out the drawer. you have 0 hits. left. and right
sprite. Awesome! Now. this is how you connect stuff back
up. Go to your Prefabs and your Paddle. it's missing
the sprite. so you just give it the 0 hits sprite.
Great! Now. what else is missing?
Well. the 1 hit. 2 hit. and 3 hit prefabs
are all missing sprites. so you can multi-select them
and give them all the 0 hits sprite. Now.
we are nearly back up and running. Now. what's going wrong with that
ball. Why is the ball sitting there? Well.
I don't know. but also these bricks look off. so I think it
has something to do with our Pivot Point. So. going back into the Sprite
Editor. it seems that actually we want central pivot
points. So. that's the sort of error you'll get if your Pivot
Point is wrong. It'll rotate around the wrong place.
and it's offset will be wrong. So. pop back into the Sprite Editor.
pop the Pivot Point for all of the sprites
back to central. and now observe that the ball
sits nicely on the paddle and that we're back to where
we were. with one important difference. which is that we now
understand Sprite Sheets a lot better
than we did before. So. what do we want you to do next? Well.
I want you to create the damaged bricks. I want you to add
two more sprites at the bottom. That means you're going to need to make a
little bit more space at the bottom of your image. for one more brick.
I want you to add one slightly damaged looking
brick. Now. you can do that by chopping out the brick.
into the background color and/or
painting over the top of the brick with maybe a dark color
for breakage. It's up to you. let the artist
within out. You can do the
break squiggles or the break colors
on a different layer. I don't care. You can even just write
numbers on the bricks. 2. 1. whatever you like. but just
make two different brick sprites that look like
they're being damaged. One for once a brick has been hit once.
and a very damaged brick that has been hit twice.
Then. reimport that same Sprite Sheet. the Bricks
Sprite Sheet. to include the 1 hit
and 2 hit. and then. just apply those to a couple
of the prefabs and make sure they display properly. So. that's
your challenge. Go away. have a play with sprites. Improve
your Sprite Sheet. make sure you understand how it all works. and when you finish.
come back and I'll show you how I do it.
OK congrats
and welcome back! I hope you managed to do it. I'm going to go ahead now
and see what's going on in Pixen. Here we go. here
is my Bricks sheet.  What do I need to do? Well.
first thing I need to do is add some more pixels to the bottom.
I need another 41 pixels at the bottom.
at least. so that would take me up to 166
pixels. Great! So now.
I've got the space to add two more bricks in.
I'm going to zoom out a little bit. I'm going to copy
the top brick. Now. I'm not sure which one the is. so trial and error.
I think it may be Main Layer? Nope. it's
not. Now. you of course could rename your layers
so that you don't have to mess around too much like this but
either way it doesn't really matter. I'm just going to do
a copy now. In fact. what I'm going to do. because I don't need layers is I'm
going to merge my layers together. I just don't
need layers. at this point. it's much easier without them.
So. here we go! I now can
take a Select Tool. I can copy
the brick. provided I select
everything perfectly.
There we go! I think my selection is
the right size. Paste that brick down. using the
Move Tool to paste my new brick.
There that's fine. and you must
have some space. some barber pole in between. and again.
paste the final one down. If I've done my sums right. it'll fit
with a little bit of space. OK. there's a slight
problem there with... Yeah something is not pasting
right. So. what's going on?
That one is good. So. you may have to fiddle
around with it. fight the editor a little bit. Great! So. I've got
now all the images I need. That's fantastic! Now.
how am I going to make these bricks look like they are broken? Well.
I'm just going to do this in a very rough and ready way.
Again. I'm going to merge my layers. I only need one layer.
So. it's a single flat image now. and I'm just for
the partially broken one. I'm just going to take some chunks out of it like
this. Just little little little bits like
kind of missing here. and in then the background will
show through in Unity.
And it doesn't really matter how it looks. This is where you could spend a long
time being very artistic with it. The other one. I'm going to take some
fairly major chunks out of. but
not break the edges of it too much.
And if you want to come in with a pen. as I said. possibly on a new
layer and just
kind of squiggle on these bricks a little bit. then you
can. And this one is looking really...
Well. I don't really know if you can
see. If you're not an artist. you would have to spend a lot of time to get this right.
but that's going to do. This is my 1 hit. this is my 2 hit.
I'm going to save that file and go back to Unity.
My Sprite Sheet has updated. but my sprites
haven't updated properly yet. I need to reimport them. it's
actually broken my left and right sprite. So. let's go
into the Sprite Editor and get this fixed up. You can do a new
automatic trim. deleting existing.
which is fine for this small sheet.
So. this one I'm just going to rename. I'm just going to start a
fresh. This is my 0 hit. This guy is
my left. this guy is my right.
this guy is my 1 hit.
and this guy is my 2
hit. Now. like a good student.
I'm going to check my brief to make sure that... Yes.
that is what I set to call them. 1 hit and 2 hit.
Fantastic! Alright. now I'm going to apply that and close.
Now. look this is a cool Sprite Sheet! We have left and right
and broken. We're probably not going to make much use of these left and right
sprites. It's more of an exercise in cutting and messing
around. but these 1 hit and 2 hits are certainly useful.
So again. let's go fix our prefabs. We fix our paddle
by giving it a no hit sprite.
We could fix our 1 hit block temporally by giving it
1 hit. Now. of course. it hasn't been hit so that's a bit strange.
but we're just testing that these
sprites work. And if I zoom in. they do
appear to. the background is showing through. Now. they look scraggy.
they don't look very good. but at least we have now two different levels
of brokenness in our sprites. Now. if you look
at them like I am. well they don't look sufficiently different.
Well. I'd agree with that. Look how flexible it is!
You can go straight back into your Image Editor and say. well
I haven't really got enough missing from
my 2 hit brick. So. I'm going to pull a
bit more out of this guy and say well. you know he's not
really looking decimated enough. So here
it goes. this guy is going to look a little bit worse. Now.
when I save and go back to Unity. it immediately updates. which is really cool!
So. I quite like that! I think that
you can very quickly get a good idea. as to
what it's finally going to look like. every time you save it
updates. And I think that's looking
sufficiently good. Maybe the thick one needs some...
Maybe the more broken brick needs some thick lines
on it. I don't know. I'm not going to embarrass myself as an artist.
too much longer here. because
you know. I just don't need to do a lot more on this brick at the moment.
But I'm just going to add a bit more kind of black breakage
in here. Try and keep it on
top of the brick. Here we go! Ah. really ugly!
And there you go. you have some really ugly art! Now. this is why you want to team
up with an artist. but I'm trying to show you the programming points here.
You have much nicer looking
sprites available to you. on the web for free. if you look around. And
I'm sure you've got mates who look at this and say: Yuck! I can do better!
Well. let them! Let them make you a Sprite Sheet like this. and do
better! All you have to tell them is that you want your bricks
to be 41 pixels high by 128 wide
and that you want them on a transparent background.
with a little bit of space. at lest one or two pixels of space around each
thing. And then. you can just import it yourself. So
cool! Congratulations! You have now achieved everything
we set out to. at the beginning. Hopefully you understand why a Sprite Sheet is
useful. the key features of it. how you create them.
and how you import them. I'll see you soon!