Hey guys! So, we're doing pretty well here.
What we want to do now is create a situation,
where we can actually win a level, when we've cleared all the bricks.
So, we can lose OK, but what we can't do
yet is win. So for example, if I go to Level
3 and maybe I'm going to ditch the red brick,
and put in just a single yellow
brick, like so.
Look, if I clear the level at the moment, well then
I'm here in perpetuity,
banging all around an empty space and I just cannot win.
So, it turns out that working out how to detect
the win conditions does take a little bit of thinking about
and that's what we're going to cover in this lecture. We'll talk about why loading levels
could be problematic. How a static
brick variable can help us. We're gong to keep track
of the number of breakable bricks in the level, using that static brick
variable. We're going to make a simple brick destroyed
message. It sounds scary but it's just a method. It's only a message,
because of the way we're using it. And we're going to
test, including what happens if two bricks get
destroyed, at once. Let me show you what I mean by that.
So, if I bring a second brick down, it turns out
that if you get your paddle in exactly the right place... Oh, that was
lucky! ...then you take out two bricks at once.
So, the challenge we have is,
we've got to be careful about who's responsible for
what here. Who should be responsible, as in
which object or which script should be responsible for
loading levels, in your opinion? Just take a look at the list of scripts.
Well, hopefully it's obvious right? Given
the names of the scripts, the Level Manager should actually
do the level loading, and it should even do the detection of
when the level loading should happen. Alright,
so which of these object would be responsible for
keeping track of the number of breakable bricks?
Well, a little bit more moot, but it seems
to me to make sense, that the Brick Object keeps track
of the number of breakable bricks. And this is where we're going to
introduce a static brick variable.
What that means is, there's going to be a single number,
on the brick template, that keeps track
of its children, and it's going to kind of count in and
count out every time a breakable child is created,
so that the Brick Object
knows about, it's actually the brick class,
the template knows how many breakable children do I
have at any one time. That seems fair.
And the things that cause challenges here are that
destroy game object takes some time to
happen. So, if we are in Brick
script, and we destroy a game object here,
it just takes a little bit of time. So, if we start trying
to load levels and things here and count bricks here,
we end up with a problem. We could for instance, try
counting all the objects that have the
breakable tag, but when you do that it's not so obvious,
because of timing issues.
The other thing that's an even bigger timing issue is, the fact that
Application.LoadLevel actually takes quite a long time to
happen. So, I've looked around
this and worked with Brice on it, and we've come up with a solution
that we think is the simplest possible but no simpler.
So, Einstein would be happy! So, let's...
The first thing I would like you to do as a challenge, to revise
what we talked about with statics before is, go into your Brick.cs script
and I want you to
add a static breakable count variable.
Choose the appropriate type of float and integer
or bool; declare it in the right place
in your Bricks.cs script. Initialize
it to 0 and then test by
playing and logging the number to the Console.
You won't be able to see this variable in the Inspector,
even if you make it public, because it's a static.
And then, as you break bricks, you want to see that number counting
down, and that will be your proof that you've done this
right. So, pause the video, do that now, and
when you come back, I'll show you how I did it.
You are pausing the video right? You're not just waiting for me to show you?
Yeah, I knew you were! Cool! OK, so here
we go! Let's talk about how we do this.
So, we're in Bricks, and we need a public because we want to be able
to see it in the Inspector and because we want
later the Level Manager to have access to it. So we want a public,
static is the keyword you need next,
and it's small S and we've
seen this in previous videos. It's an integer because you can
count it on your fingers basically. And if you can count it on your fingers,
or if you had lots of fingers, as an integer.
Brick count and then I said you can initialize it as well,
so far, with a semicolon on the end, that is a declaration. We have
declared it, we've made some memory space for it. Now,
initializing it, you can either do it in Start, you can say brickCount equals 0,
or actually in this case, you can also do it straight up here.
OK cool! So, we have our static variable
here, it's available to all our methods. That's a
Start. Now, the next thing we need to do is,
think about increasing and decreasing
this static variable, every time a breakable
brick is created or destroyed.
So, we already have a boolean somewhere, is Breakable,
down at the bottom here on line 24, on my script, on your
OnCollisionEnter2D. We're actually going to want to use this
across the entire class, across all these methods, so I'm
going to take it out of here altogether,
and I'm going to put the definition of it up here, as
a private bool isBreakable...
...private bool isBreakable. I'm
just going to declare it there, and then, I'm going
to initialize it, here in the
Start. So, I'm going to say
isBreakable.
When the brick first comes into existence,
when this particular brick, whether it's breakable or not, we don't know at this
stage, but if it is
tagged with "Breakable", then this particular instance of a brick
has this boolean: Is variable set to true? And
that's what that's going to do. Now, this is where we increment,
this is where we're going to keep track
of breakable bricks.
We're going to say if (isBreakable), which reads
really nicely. Hint, if things read
really nicely it's normally a good thing. No guarantee it's going to work
right, of course, but it's normally a good thing. So, if
isBreakable brickCount equals
brickCount plus 1 or ++.
Now, look back to the challenge definition.
I asked you to create a variable called breakable
Count, and I'm using brickCount. Well, big deal but let's
use the right thing; breakable
Count, breakable
Count. It's just a bit clearer. So, breakableCount ++
is a shorthand way of incrementing the
breakableCount by one. So, each brick, when it comes into
existence it says, am I breakable and if I am
increment the static. There's only one of these integers in the entire
game. There's only one of these, it's on the template;
it's saying OK, there is another breakable brick in
the scene. That's what that's doing.
So, that's fantastic! But for every time we increment it, we
also need somewhere that we're going to decrement it. So, where are we
going to decrease it? Well, we're going to decrease it
immediately before
we destroy it, OK.
So, where is that? It's going to be
if the times hits greater than = to the max hits, we're going to go
breakableCount --,
which is another shorthand. So, we decrease it
just before we destroy it. So, let's go over
into the game. I'm going to use a very simple level to
start with. I'm going to look at
any brick actually, as it happens. You'll notice that whichever
brick we click on, the Brick Script
is there but the static is not being exposed in the
Inspector. So you're going to have to work
around that issue and find some other way of logging
out the count. So, go back into
your Brick Script and I'm going to
just put it here: print (breakableCount); underneath
the increment, and then, I'm going to copy that
and do the same thing under
the decrement there. Paste in print
(breakableCount). OK, so what
we're doing here is we're saying, here look this publicly exposed
static does not get exposed in the Inspector.
So, maybe that's just to save confusion,
because every object would have the same number on
here, so it's not about the object, it's about the
class. So, it wouldn't kind of make sense, if you flicked through the Inspector.
It would be a bit confusing if every object had the same value, so they just
don't show it, and we're going to show it by putting it in the
Console. So, once you save your script now, you can see in the Console,
down at the bottom left, 2 and then 1.
And that went very quickly, but you can look at your Console history
and that's awesome! It works! Just quickly, if you want to check
that against a bigger level, you're welcome to. I'm
confident it's going to work, so I'm not going to bother. So,
as a recap. What we've done is we've talked about
loading levels being problematic. We've added a static
class level variable, called Brick. We have kept track
of these breakable bricks in the level. Now, we're going to
make a simple brick destroyed message. So,
what does that mean? Well, what we want to
do now is we want to message the Level Manager to
say, a brick has been destroyed, you decide
whether we're going to load a next level.
Yeah, we don't want to check it every single frame, and it definitely wants to be the
Level Manager that makes this decision. So, it's going to
have a public void Brick
Destroyed ()
message. Now, what's it mean that it's a message? Well nothing, it's just a method.
We're calling it a message, because it's kind of passing information to
the Level Manager. It's a pretty subtle difference in this
case, so don't worry about it. Sometimes we'll use the word message,
when we are passing information on to somewhere else for that
other thing to take responsibility for what to do with
it. So, it's up to Level Manager how to respond to this.
So, what Level Manager needs to do is, every time a brick is destroyed it
needs to ask a question. It needs to say
if, and I'm going to leave it for
the moment, if I'm going to put a comment in. Basically,
if this is the last brick,
or if last brick
destroyed. It's fine to write English
first in comments, and then, work out how you're going to do
it. Alright, because the important thing is right now you're thinking about the
logic. So, if the last brick was
destroyed, OK in there, then, what are
we going to do? Well, we are going to
simply load next level, and we don't need Level
Manager dot or anything, because we're in Level Manager.
So, if the last brick was destroyed, we load the next level. How do we
access that brick static from here?
So, there's an interesting question for you. Well, you don't
actually need to expose the brick or anything else. It turns out that, that
brick static is available to all other classes and all other
methods. You just need to use capital B,
it's a static method of brick. (Brick.
breakableCount) is what you're looking for. If it's
less than or = to 0, then we load the
next level. Why less than? Again, we guarding against
accidentally getting in a situation, where we have a negative
brick count. We certainly, if we have a negative brick count, want to load the
next level. So, it's just being careful, in case we've got a double
decrement somewhere, and we missed the 0 condition. Now, we're going to
catch it the next time. So, this is the message
inside Level Manager. Now, what Brick.cs
wants to do is just call that, every time
a brick is destroyed. So, I'm going to get rid of my print statement
here, and I'm simply going
to say, down here,
if the brick has had it
basically, then we decrement the breakable count. That's
fine but what we're also going to do is levelManager,
which is already exposed in here, .BrickDestroyed. I'm just going to
message it OK,
to say that, that brick has been destroyed. Now, this message and
this condition only gets checked when  brick is destroyed, which is pretty efficient.
You can't really do it any other time.
You know every time a brick is destroyed, someone's got to say well, was that the last one?
So, this is a pretty cool way of doing it! Let's try it and
see if it works! Firstly, for one
brick at a time. One, two, "You beat Block Breaker!".
Great! Now bear in mind, the reason your text is looking cut
is because your game window is not a
800 by 600 right. If you make it big enough, it'll be fine.
So, I'm doing that on purpose, because I want you to understand why
what you see here in this preview, is tied to the current
size of your game window. So,
let's go again!
Let's take a look back in this scene, back into my
contrive, little simple scene. You can have your own simple scene.
Now, let's check the condition
where both blocks get killed, at the same time.
Cool! That worked! Now, trust me there's lots
of ways you can try and do this, where that wouldn't work. Alright,
just trust me on that. Now, let's try another situation, which
is where you have an invincible brick in the scene, as well. Let's try!
One brick at a time, one, two. "You beat Block Breaker!".
Great! How about if we broke both bricks, and there's an invincible
brick in the scene? Does that work? Yes
perfect! They are all situations in which I had a
nightmare, when trying to decide exactly how to do
this for you, in the simplest way. And thanks to Brice's input, we've come
up with, what I hope you agree is, an elegant solution.
You could have just tried this on all the other levels, it will
work just fine. The other thing to do is to check your lose
condition. So boom, you lost!
OK awesome! So congratulations! I'm going to give you a
final recap, because there were lots of things in here.
That's what we've done! Let it sink in.
Start thinking about when statics
may be appropriate. Basically, when there's only ever going
to be one of these things, like one number of
breakable bricks, one in the entire
game, and that makes complete logical sense and this
is a good place to use statics. Congrats and see you soon!