Hey guys. I don't know about you but I'm starting to feel our game could do with some sound.
So if you look. it's got some music. but I'm
thinking of a different type of sound. I'm thinking of
some boings and some crashes and stuff. Now. you're welcome
to record these sounds yourself. Use any program that you can use. like Audacity
would be one or sound recorder. whatever you can get your hands on.
If you look in the Course Assets. which is a
lecture at the beginning of the section. you will find that we have given
you a download. Let me show you what it looks like. I go to
my folder. which is here: blocker-
breaker-assets v.3 is the one I'm going to be using. .zip. And if you expand that
under Sounds. you'll have already found the background noise. You've got boing and crack.
Now. these are my daughter doing boing and crack and they're quite funny. so we're just going to...
I'm going to use those. you can replace them with whatever you like. They don't have to be
.ogg format. they can be .mp3 or any other format that you find that
Unity supports. So. drag them into your Sounds folder.
so that Unity has at least got access to them. Let's make neither of
them a 3D sound. You're going to have to do this one at a time. so
click on the track. click into the Inspector under
3D Sound. turn it off because we're in a 2D game. and then. click Apply and it
may take a second just to process that. So. all of our sound clips now are non
3D. Cool! They're the only settings we need to think about. So what we're going to
be doing. in this lecture. is we're going to use audio.Play() to play the boing
sound. and then. we're going to talk about why a different method called Audio
Source.PlayClipAtPoint is useful. Then. we're going to use that one
for playing the crack sound. and then. we're going to demonstrate and test and stuff.
Cool! So. let's start with the simple one. the ball. The ball just needs to say
boing every single time it hits something.
So. where have you played music before? You've played music in the MusicPlayer before.
but we actually didn't do anything in script. if you look in here. If you look at the
MusicPlayer. yes it's a MusicPlayer. but the only reason it plays
music is because. if you look at the object in the game scene.
which is only on your start scene. then it
Plays on Awake. So. it's only playing repeating. looping music on
the basis that it's Playing on Awake. I actually haven't got it on loop at
the moment. If you find your music runs out too soon. you're welcome to put it on loop.
So that's one way to play sounds. but on awake is only appropriate
for something like background music. We're actually going to need to play music or sound even
from script. programmatically. So. let's start with a simple one.
which is the ball. Click on the Ball in the prefabs. and what you
need to be doing here is adding a component. And that component
is a Audio Source.
Let's take a look at that! Fantastic! We do not want to Play on Awake. in this
case. We don't want the ball to make a boing sound when
the game starts. but we do need to attach the Audio Clip to
it. so that you can click on this little circle next to the Audio Clip. choose boing.
It says it's a 2D sound. If it doesn't then you go to your clip to change it.
that's fine. and that all looks OK for now. that's great!
So. at the moment. if you played nothing will happen.
because the final bit is we need to go into the Ball
script. and we need to say audio.play.
And you could test it just by putting it in here. audio.play. It's a good
idea to break all problems down into small problems like this.
so Just check this
plays on start. Let's try that with
any of the scenes. that have a ball in them.
[Sound Effect] Boing! [Laughs] There she goes. good old Lucy! So that works
but we don't want it here. We want it only happen on collision or
is it on trigger mm hmm? So. this is what you've got to work out. What I want you
to do now is to. as a challenge. I want you to work out whether
you need to be putting this in the OnCollisionEnter
or in the OnTriggerEnter2D() method. Write the method
signature into bool.cs and then use the play audio
in the appropriate method. So just go ahead look at Unity's
docs about collisions. if you need to. and decide whether these are collisions or triggers. when the ball
hits both the bricks and the wall.
Hey welcome back! So.
is it a collision or is it a trigger? Have you decided? Well. let's
take a look back at the slide that we had about collisions. that we showed you.
The ball is a physics object and it's moving
and it's not a trigger. so it's a Rigidbody Collider. And when it hits the walls.
it's hitting a Static Collider and when it hits the bricks it's hitting a Static Collider. so it's a collision
we're dealing with. Alright. hopefully that makes sense.
So. what we want to do is. in the Ball script. we want to write the method.
Now. be careful with your brackets. Look. click next to the curly bracket and you'll see which one
it relates to. You see that? So. this one here is
the closing brace of the Update() method. I want to go under that but not
outside of the whole class description. Hopefully that makes sense.
just get used to the indentation. So. void OnCollision
Enter2D. Don't miss your 2D! And what it's going to pass in
is a. not a Collider2D. but a Collision
2D because it's a Collision. We're going to call it Collision!
That's fine! Now. none of that matters. it's just that you need to be in this method for it to trigger at the right
time. and what you want to say is what we did before. audio.Play();
like so. Let's try it!
[Sound Effect] Boing! [Background Music]
[Sound Effect] Boing! Boing! Boing!
Hmm. sort of working. A couple of issues. Firstly. it went
boing right at the very beginning. Why does it go boing right at
the beginning? Well. because we haven't told it not
to when it collides. when the ball starts off colliding with the
paddle. ahh you see. So. what we want to do here is we want to
guard against that by saying. only do this if the game is started.
So. here's a simple mini challenge. I won't even put a slide up for you. I want you to put an if statement around this
audio.Play(); that simply says if the game is started.
use the instance variable we have up here. hasStarted.
Cool! OK. hopefully you've got that it's pretty much as simple as this.
if (hasStarted) then audio.Play();
otherwise do nothing. Now let's try it!
No boing on start. that's good!
[Sound Effects & Background Music] But if you watch this bit carefully. you'll notice
the boing sound is only happening if the brick isn't destroyed.
Though in cases where the brick is destroyed. the boing sound is not coming out.
so why is that? Well. it's simply because the brick is being
destroyed before it has a chance to make the boing sound. If you're taking this
part of the course in Unity 5 and following the compiler's suggestions to change your code.
you might find slightly different behavior. in which case you'll need to work around that. But I do recommend
you stay with Unity 4.6 for this section. Remember. we're going to get to Unity 5 when we
need to. which is in Bowl Master. Cool. so let's move straight on now
and recap the beginning of the lecture. where we said we're going to use Audio
Source.PlayClipAtPoint for the crack sound.
Why. what's all that about? Well. it's because of exactly this problem! We're
going to have the brick make the crack sound. because ultimately it's the brick that makes the sound.
but when the brick is destroyed.
it can no longer play the sound and that's a problem.
So. how are we going to deal with that? Well. there's a great tool called Play
ClipAtPoint. You have to pass the AudioClip
into the brick. in order to do this. so let's start off
by publicly exposing an AudioClip. over here in the Brick.css.
And I'm going to do that above the sprite. public...
And you'll see how it works in a minute. for now. let's just get the AudioClip in.
AudioClip. I'm going to call it
crack; actually. just crack sound. There you go. Perfect! Now. when do you want
to play this crack sound? Well. firstly go attach it. go into Unity. get to
your Brick prefab...
You're going to actually need to do this for all of your bricks. and
look they're asking for crack sounds. So. select all of your bricks together. with a
multi-select holding down Control or Command. Go to your sounds. find your crack.
and stick it in. So. at this point. I'd like to clarify that the crack sound
is just the sound my daughter made. and it's not really a crack sound.
it's a sound of the brick being hit. So. I want this sound to play
every single time the brick is hit. so it can cause a little bit of
confusion for people. So. I'm inserting this to explain to you that crack is
being used every time the brick is hit and every time it takes damage. not just for
when it's finally destroyed. in my case. You could of course. as a challenge to yourself
towards the end of this section. arrange for a different sound once the brick is
destroyed. but I will leave that to you. OK cool! So. we have the
crack sound built in there now. When do we want to make that sound? Well. we make the sound
when we hit the brick. So. down here
we have OnCollisionEnter2D. We say if it's
breakable then handle the hits. but when do
we play the audio. Well. actually we always play the audio. So
if we just went audio.Play() and attached the AudioSource. it would not work
because what would happen is the audio may
start playing. but the moment the LevelManager notices that
at the moment the brick is destroyed rather. the audio will stop playing. OK. as soon
as it's destroyed down here it would stop playing. No good. we don't want that! So. what we want
to do is use this cool method. which is AudioSource
down here somewhere in our list. .PlayClipAtPoint. You'll
see what that does in a minute. by example. ...(crack.
which we just brought in. and we're going to play it at. just for simplicity.
transform.position); which is the position of the brick.
Now. look you have to see this to understand how it works. I've got my Game
Window right next to my scene. so you can watch this happening. See that.
let's see what happens!
Now. what I want you to do is look. next time I play this. at the
left-hand window. the Scene Window. and watch for little icons. the little
gizmos. If you can't see then. turn up the size of your 3D Gizmos
like this. Make sure your 3D Gizmos are big enough. and
watch them in the left-hand window as the ball bounces around.
[Crack Sound Effect]
You see what happened there! Every time it bounced.
an AudioClip was spawned where the brick was. and the
brick is allowed to disappear. That is the sensible way to do it. You do not want to
delay the disappearance of the brick. that would be weird. If the brick is destroyed while the Audio
Clip is playing. the AudioClip will stop playing. This allows us to say. hang on.
the brick doesn't need to be there for sound to play! So. we put an Audio
Source where the brick was! Wicked! It's a really really cool method!
So. that's AudioClip.PlayClipAtSource! I'm just going to turn down my Gizmo
size a little bit. because it's a bit rude as it is. And just a quick recap
for us. we've done a really cool job! So. we played the boing sound!
We got some weird stuff going on where it didn't play when a brick's destroyed.
It turned out to be pretty useful. actually. because we wanted it to play a different
clip when the brick is destroyed. which was the crack sound. and we used PlayClipAt
Point for that. We also left a comment in our code so that
should this issue with the sound not playing here.
in the bool.cs. ever come and bite us in the bottom. we have
a comment that will remind us of the experience. Then. we could dig into
it in more detail and solve the issue. if the issue ever comes up.
So congratulations. great video. and I'll see you soon!