Hey welcome back! So,
it feels like time for some play testing to me. So, we could go
through, by hand, and play all these levels,
and obviously, if our game was that fun we
would. But having just built it, I'm not sure
I want to sit here and break all of these blocks, it could take some time.
And also, I want to test the stability
of later levels at
high speeds. So, one way to do this is
to make the machine automatically move the paddle
under the ball, so that if
the game gets faster and faster or if we just want it to play test
itself it can do that. So, that's a pretty cool idea!
It's actually a very simple idea as well. If we go into our Paddle Script,
what we can do on every update
is look at what it's already doing first. Let's
consolidate what it's already doing. Well, it's
just moving the paddle, in response to the mouse.
So, let's start by factoring that out. void
MoveWithMouse ()
and then, there we go!
And what
we can do is take this code out of here, paste it into MoveWithMouse.
Maybe we don't need so many lines in it anymore?
And we can say, on every frame, we just Move
WithMouse. Well, that's
fine and boring and we haven't really done anything, but what we
could do now is, we could say well let's have a check box against the paddle.
And let's make a public
auto play, so it's a boolean. It's either auto playing it
or not. autoPlay =
false; So, by default it doesn't autoPlay.
Alright, let's get rid of this Start method, we don't need that.
Cool! Alright, so then what we
do, and here's a challenge for you! I want you to put an if statement in that
says, if autoPlay is false, then
MoveWithMouse, otherwise just do nothing
for now. So, go ahead and do that!
OK, so if
not (!autoPlay or another way you could have done
it is said, if autoPlay ==
false, then we're going to MoveWithMouse.
OK, so that's fine!
Just be sure we just test and make sure the game still runs. So far, we should
have done absolutely nothing, apart
from... Let me show you something! Let's not maximize on play,
let's go into the game,
let's click on the paddle,
and look, you've got an Auto Play Checkbox!
So, if Auto Play is unchecked the paddle moves,
if it's checked the paddle doesn't move, OK.
So, that's a start! Now we need, when Auto Play is enabled,
then what do we do? else we...
Well, let's write a wishful function, one that doesn't
exist yet. autoPlay
OK Cool!
I'm going to use a capital a for method. Now,
autoPlay is read because it doesn't exist. So, how is autoPlay going to work? Well,
it doesn't need to return anything,
it doesn't need to take anything, but it does need to do something
so what's it going to do? Well,
good question! It's going to
simply move the mouse to the
position, to the Y position of the ball, so this means the
paddle now is going to need to see the ball. Now, we could either drag
the ball in or we could find the ball
in the Start method, using the GameObject.Find
and that's what I want to do. So, I'm going to say private
Ball
ball; OK, now what I want you to do is put the Start
method back in, and then, use Game
Object.FindObject
OfType to find that Ball and assign
it to this ball variable. OK, so
pause the video and make the Start method find the ball in the scene, so
we don't need to drag it into the Inspector.
OK, so it's void Start (). I want you to rewrite this
so you start feeling confident in removing these things and putting them
back in if you need to. ball = Game
Object.FindObjectOfType
and then, now let's look at the docs for that!
What does it want?
It wants type of GUI
Texture. That's one way of doing it, you can do type of. Again,
I always tend to do it the way that's more consistent with the other things
that it does, which is &lt;Ball&gt; like that, and then just some brackets.
OK, so we've found the Ball, with any luck,
in the scene. If we're not sure that we have, we
just print (ball); We need the ball because we
need to know it's coordinates. Let's check that we are finding
the ball.
Ball (Ball), if you look in the Console, it's found a Ball! Great!
So, that's good! Pretty boring but it's good! So, this is
where the magic happens. What we want to do in simple
terms is, we say paddle... Well, why don't we
copy what we've done with MoveWithMouse, actually, because most of it's
going to be the same. So, we need a Vector3
paddle position. Yes, local to this method now,
different to this one. Here's a new Vector3,
starting at 0.5 and the
transform position in the Y. So, we're keeping the
Y position of the paddle. We are starting
at 0.5, but it doesn't really matter where we
start, and then, 0f in the
Z. That doesn't matter either! OK, now we don't
care about the mouse position. What we do care about
is the ball position,
= ball.transform.position;
Alright, so now
every frame we move the paddle's X position to
the (ballPos.x
clamping it
between... Now, it doesn't like this .x.
float ballPos... Sorry, I want a Vector3
ballPos is
the ball's transform. And then, we say let's move
the paddle to the ball's x position, not letting it go
outside of these bounds, which it kind of shouldn't anyway.
This .transform.position = paddlePos; because we
built up this paddlePos vector exactly as before. So, we're doing almost
the same thing as we did with MoveWithMouse. Let's try
it! Let's see what happens!
So, this is
me manual playing. If I pause the game, click on
the Paddle, and check Auto Play, let's see if it
works! Ah, look at that!
Watch what's happening there! So,
pretty cool hey! It's very simple, the system
is just settting the X position of the paddle
to be precisely the same as the X position of the ball.
This should, in principle, mean that it
misses, because it's a machine and it's
pretty fast. There are some instances in which
this could fail to do with the speed of the physics
calculations, etc. But for now, let's see how it
does at play testing this level for us. In fact, it should
play test the entire game for us. So, I'm
sitting here with my arms crossed, hoping this will work.
Now, this is nearly a boring loop, but because we've
got our special Random.Range code in this
boring loop should not persist. At some
point, we should get out of it. There we are! And
again, it's trying to get in a boring loop, but we have code that's preventing
that. There you go! And there's a really kind of weird bounce there!
So, this is
roughly what a human player would have to do.
You may look at this and think, how about if I want to knock the ball
off to more of an angle? Well, you could actually
change the collider shape on your paddle,
as a bit of extra credit, so that it has
some little kind of edges on it so that you can
actually hit the ball more off to the side.
If you're interested in knowing how to do that, then let me know
in the discussions, and I will consider posting a bonus
video, to show you how to make those fine tunings.
So, what I'm going to do is let it
play itself, and then, I'll speed up the video so we can watch the auto
play, hopefully running through all of the levels. So,
enjoy watching that, yeah, and see you
a moment!
I quite like the fact
it gets faster as the level goes on, because it kind of
gives you a time limit, in a way, to get the
level cleared, because the longer you leave it the harder the game gets.
So, that's a little bit of a mergent, a knid of unplanned
behavior. Another option would be that we could introduce lives
into the level. A score
seems a little bit contrived in this game, because
unless you involve time in the score,
if you just have a score based on the bricks, of coarse
you're always going to score the same for every level, which is a bit rubbish.
So, you could introduce a score system that involves time,
but I really think this game is just a completionism game. It's
about actually getting to the end of the level and
clearing the bricks and having the patience and tenacity to do that.
When you get to another level, you are
going to need to go back to the paddle and set Auto
Play on, and then, just
launch the ball.
OK, so that last level is pretty incomplete,
so I think we've seen enough of it there, actually. When I see a
level looking like that, I'm going to either remove
the level or embellish the level. So, I think what I'm going
to do is quickly embellish the level. So, I will start with
all of the bricks, that are nicely laid out in Level_02.
I'm going to delete my bricks in Level_03
here, because they're pretty ugly. I'm going to paste in Level_02's
bricks, and then, inside
the bricks I'm going to start looking at
maybe replacing a few of these, with invincible
bricks. So for example, what I could is go into the yellow
here, and replace maybe,
I don't know, let's say this one, those
two. Maybe that one and that one.
So, just replace a handful of these with something
else and that's how I'm going to do it. So, I'm going to drop
my thing into here, Bricks, and then I'll have
invincible on grid and then I'll start
duplicating them. And this already
will make the level a little bit more interesting.
And you can get a lot more imaginative than I am on this!
The other thing you might want to do is use a different background image again.
It's not very nice to have the same background image for every level.
So, the way you could do that its just say,
I don't know, background, for instance, would be very boring.
Images, Search Tools, Usage rights,
"Labeled for reuse with modification".
Size, Larger than 640 x 480.
Ideally, we want one that is just 800 by 600.
That would be easiest, if there is one that's
suitable. So, you have a quick flick through.
If you can't find one that's the right size, straight off the cuff,
then you just modify one or you go and make
one or you get artistic or whatever. I'm going to spend
another few seconds looking to see if there's an 800 by 600 image that's
suitable here. I'm looking for it more based
on size than I am based on whether it's an
interesting image. So, now let's see if we can do an
800 x 600
search, like that.
Ah, there you go! So, we could have another one from Wikipedia!
So, we could view that image, Save Image As.
Stick it in our downloads, if you like. That's
fine! but then, when you get to Unity, you need to be
going to your Sprites,
importing a new asset from
wherever it was, which is here.
I'm going to call it,
Level_03 bg,
like so, and then, on Level_03 I just want
to go to the Play Space, Background,
Sprite, and
make it Level_03 bg like that. Now, why is it down
on the bottom left? Why is this not working? If you ever want to
change your image, what do we need to do?
Yeah, you need to go to the Sprite Editor and do two things. One thing is, you
need to make the Pixels Per World Unit the same as the other images,
which I think is 50 actually. Yes 50!
And that will get the scaling right, but now, why is it in the wrong place?
Well, it's in the wrong place because the Pivot
point for the others is at the bottom left.
OK, so change the Pivot point, Apply, and exit.
And now, we have a different looking level!
OK, so now we have another unique
level. Cool! So, play testing has
worked pretty well! Auto play testing works well! And
we've gone all the way through the loop of the game. I didn't quite let it get to the
end, because the moment I saw a mankey scene,
I felt compelled to do something about it. I wanted
to feel that in Level_03 my bricks were organized
properly. In fact, they're still not! I want my Invincible bricks under
my Bricks Hierarchy, something like that.
And it's looking all a lot nicer now. So, we have this
level here, with a robot and two brick types.
Oh no! We have an invincible in Level_01! I'm going to take that out actually.
That's a bit of an odd one. So, no invincible
in Level_01. Introduce the complexity of
the red bricks in Level_02, different background. Level_03
introduces a third type, the invincible brick, and then, we
have a Win Screen and a Loose Screen. So awesome! Automated play
testing! We have a check box on the Paddle that allows
us to auto play!
We're in pretty good shape here, really now, to be thinking about
building our own version of this
to the web. So, I want you to get really creative with your levels. Build as
many levels as you want. Make sure your build
order here is... Not there, sorry!
...under your project, there! Your build
order, project Build Settings. File, Build Settings.
Make sure you start with your Start Menu, then, go through your levels
in order. Then the Win Screen, because remember, when you pass from Level_03
onto the next level you want it to be the Win Screen, and then,
the LooseCollider will leap frog us to the Loose Screen if
that happens. So cool! Congratulations on that bit, and I'll
see you soon!