Hey welcome back! So.
hopefully you've built your game and shared it with the world!
We've got a great service. gamebuck.io. that
Brice just built. It makes it really easy to share your game.
Just follow the three steps. and you're game will be hosted like
this. Just remember to keep a note of this URL.
which will last for 30 days. So. here's one of the
games our students made. and we really want you guys to
do the same. So. once it's out there with the
wider world. you're going to end up with bugs
and bug reports coming in for your game. So. the topic
of this video is how to deal with bug reports.
We're going to firstly
stress that we need to know how to reproduce the problem.
so we need to know from our users. how do we reproduce the
problem. Then. we Debug it to find the root cause.
We make a fix and retest everything. and then. we
remove any special code we put in. for those Debugging
purposes. An example bug report could be
this: "I've notice an odd behaviour... it works up until I
start a new game then it duplicate itself like a loop."
And thanks to Daniel. Nathan. and Marko.
in the discussions. for helping us find what this is all about.
So. you may get a slightly cryptic bug report like that.
and what you need to do is go into your game and find
out what's going on. Well. it turns
out that if you start and then you
lose and you play again. that if
you were to clear all the bricks this second time
the game would not load the next level.
And the reason is to do with the Brick breakableCount.
So. what we need to do is
firstly. reproduce the problem.
which we could do by playing the whole level. Or if we suspect
it's the Brick breakableCount. why not go straight to
step 2. which is put some Debug code in.
So. if we go into our Brick.
open your Brick.cs Script in Mono
Develop. Once
that loads up. have a look. This is the LevelManager.
make sure you choose the right script. Brick. where we
decrement the Brick breakableCount here. immediately after
we've reduced the breakableCount I want you to use Debug.Log
or print. They both serve about the same function.
(breakableCount); so put that out to
the Console. Now. let's take a look at what's happening!
We start the game!
When the first brick is destroyed. watch the
Console carefully. 27. 26.
this is the breakableCount. Great OK. Now. let's let
the game lose itself. At the moment. it seems to be
doing a fantastic job of playing itself.
OK. we're going to lose.
So. we had 18 breakable bricks left on the level. when we lost.
Let's play again!
Start! Now. remember there are fourteen
bricks per layer. on the 1. 2. 3. 4. 5. 6.
7. Yeah. 7. 14. so there are
28 breakable bricks to start with. Let's see what happens!
Watch the Console after
the first brick breaks.
What do we get logging? You may need to scroll down
41. 42. 43. 44. 45.
working backwards. That's not right! There are not that many
breakable bricks. and that is because
if you look in the Brick.cs Script again.
for a moment. at the top here in the Start
method. when a brick comes into existence
it updates the static breakableCount.
This static breakableCount
for every breakable brick. So. we had a number
of breakable bricks left over in the static.
so it just added to them. which is wrong. So.
what I want you to do is fix this
problem. Now. you don't do it in Brick.cs. you do it in another script.
but I'm going to leave it to you to work out which one.
Your challenge is to fix the bug. "When it's fixed
Brick.breakableCount will correctly reset to the number
of breakable bricks. even after you have died and tried again."
You better test this by checking the Console or playing
the level. So. go ahead. pause the video. and have a go at fixing
the bug yourself.
Cool! Welcome back! So. how did you get on fixing that bug?
Well. this is how I'm going to be attacking it.
Relatively simple. actually. we go
into LevelManager. and it's when we load a level here
or here. Whenever we load a level. we want
to reset the breakableCount OK. So.
what we do is we go capital B for Brick.
because it's the class in this case because it's a static.
Dot breakableCount = 0;
We need to do that when we load a level. i.e.. going
from the Start Menu to Level 1. but we also
need to do it just before we load the next level. which is called going
from Level 1 to 2. Level 2 to 3. etc.
Now. let's test.
watching the Console as we go.
Same drill!
We lose! There are 27 breakable bricks
at the end. We start again!
Ah 27! Good. we're back to where we should be! So fantastic!
Congratulations on fixing that problem!
You reset the static breakableCount to 0.
both in the LoadLevel Script
and in the LoadNextLevel Script.
And as a slide summary of what we've just done.
here it is! When you have
a bug. find out how to reproduce the problem. Debug it to
find the root cause. make the fix and re-test.
and then. finally. remove the Debug code.
Where was our Debug code? Well. it was back over
in the other script. which was the Brick.cs.
And it is down here
somewhere. towards the bottom. under
HandleHits. We can now remove the Debug.Log (breakableCount);
to tidy up our log. Fantastic! Congratulations
and I'll see you soon!