Hello hello. guys and girls!
So. in our game. we're doing really nicely.
There's something we could improve; there's not a lot of control
over the bounce of the ball. at the moment. because our
paddle is currently flat on the top surface.
So. what I want to talk to you about. in this lecture.
is what is a
Polygon Collider? How it could help us improve our game.
how to manipulate Polygon Colliders.
and then. I'm going to challenge you to chamfer your paddle. [Laughs]
Let me show you what I mean. So. if we
double click on Paddle. for example. in Level 1 in my case.
or click on it and push the F Key
for Frame. I sometimes say focus
but it's really Frame. You have to do this in Scene View.
Then. you will see the collider. very very faint
green outline. You can just see it if you
turn it on and off. Well. there's a Box Collider.
there's not a huge amount we can do when we edit it. We can make it
a little wider. taller. but we can't make it a different
shape. So. what I'm going to do and I'd like you to do is. go
into the Inspector for your paddle. but not in
a particular scene actually but as a prefab
of course. because you want to change your paddle everywhere. So. go
into your paddle. and what I want you to do
in your Paddle Prefab is. remove the Box
Collider all together. Scary!
And add yourself a new collider. so you can search for collider
and you'll find a Polygon Collider 2D.
That's what we want to add. OK.
Now. if we edit that Polygon Collider 2D.
let's have a look at see what we get.
Click back on the Paddle.
Just make sure you can see the green outline. it's very very
faint. it's almost invisible. And once you're sure you've
got the right thing. click Edit. Now.
it's still a box. but if you just
click the mouse and drag. you can now add
more lines to your polygon. Pretty cool hey! So
I can add a line out here. for example. and this is what I mean
by chamfering. Again. I can click on the other side and drag
out. So. I want us to modify our paddles
to look something like this. Now. if you make a mistake and you add
too many polygons. never fear. you can
always go back into the
Paddle. click back into Edit Collider.
and then. hold down the Control Key.
so that the segment goes red. and then. click and it will
remove that node.
Cool! So. I'm just going to quickly show you what would happen if we had these
invisible colliders now. like that.
It's difficult to see. but
you'll get to a situation where you can
bounce the ball differently. you've got more control over it. Let
me see if I can make it happen. Come on you.
I think it happened there! There you go and there!
But of course it's a little useless. because we can't see what we're doing.
So. here's your challenge then. What I want you to do
is create a new sprite. a new paddle
sprite. I would create an entirely separate
sprite sheet for that. with just a paddle in it.
with chamfered edges. so draw some chamfered edges somehow.
Adjust the collider. as I've just shown
you. to match that new sprite.
Then. I want you to ensure that the paddle is constrained properly
to the walls. because you're probably going to be making
your paddle wider. by doing this. I think it's a good idea to make it
wider. but we don't want it passing through the walls. so go
and find out where that constraint happens
and make the required change.
Then. check it all by play testing. So go
ahead. pause the video. and do that now.
Cool! Well. hopefully
you've got on well; I'm going to show you how I plan to do it.
So. looking at my sprites. I have a single
brick sprite sheet here. so I'm going to need to start with that.
I think. So. let me go and reveal that in my
Finder. I'm going to open it with my
program of choice. which is Picsend. at the moment.
Fine now. that's a starting
point. I think I'm going to immediately save this as
something else. before I start messing with it.
and I'm just going to call it paddle and it's a
.png. which is good it supports tnasparencey.
Great! Now. it's the wrong size and shape all together.
so let me make my window a little bigger and
start messing with this guy. So. first thing I'm going to do
is change the Canvas size.
It's 128 wide. I'm going to roll with 200.
It doesn't matter if it's wider than it needs to be. and remember that
our paddle is 41 pixels high and I"m going to keep the
top center of the image.
That looks about right. Actually. I want more width.
It's better to have more than you need. because when we cut it out in
Unity. it's going to ignore the transparent background. So. I'm
going to go right up to 300.
Fantastic! OK. so
we have a starting point for a chamfered paddle.
now what we need to do is change the shape. Excuse me.
Alright. so how are we going to do that? Well. it's entirely
up to you. You can use your artistic flair to draw some
lines and do whatever you like. I'm going to make a really ugly modification
mainly so that when you do your modification.
you can do better than us. and then. you can show off on the
discussion boards. by making something far prettier than I
have in this short video. So. let me see if
I can just make something. at least symmetrical.
which is nearly that.
You know what. I'm going to allow it to be rough
and ready and leave it at that. I'm just going to stick myself a
line along the bottom here. and I better get myself a
a Fill Tool and some gray color
perhaps and start filling it in.
Doesn't that look awful? That looks
perfectly awful! I think that's ideal.
I just want to demonstrate the point. and I think that having gray sides.
so that you can see the modification. is just fine.
So. I'm saving that .png file.
going back into Unity. and it's actually already here. paddle
.png. Now firstly. let's look at the World Units.
We want it to be consistant. so this bricks sprite
sheet used 1 to 8 pixels
per unit. so let's to the same with the new paddle.
Now. let's go straight into the Sprite Editor. It's a single
sprite in this case. That's fine and I'm going to
try. inside the Sprite Editor.
to make sure that the transparencies
are there. They are. we have checker boards; it all looks OK actually.
so there's nothing to do in the Sprite Editor. If I just
Apply that. Let's now try
going to my Brick Prefab.
and where it's asking for the sprite.
up here. instead of using the
0 hit sprite I'm now going to use the
Paddle Sprite. Great! So. we have a
new looking paddle. and it's very clear what's going on.
If you then go into the Paddle Prefab. remember we must do it
in the prefab. so it changes it across all the levels.
and we look at editing the Polygon Collider.
Let's see what we get now.
So. Paddle Prefab.
Polygon Collider. Edit.
Where are its current bounds? We need to be in the Scene View. which
we are.
And if you
click on it. there you go. Now. you can see that this isn't quite
right. at the moment. so with a bit of fiddling
around. you'll get to the point where you can edit it and you can zoom in.
And you can get your Polygon Collider
matching what you actually see in this
sprite. otherwise it's very strange when things bounce
off invisible objects. So
again. you can be more precise than me. if you wish.
I'm going for that. and it looks about right. You can see
that my Polygon Collider now is the same shape as my sprite.
I'm going to apply this change to
the prefab. like that.
Now. what would make sense would be to go into Level 1. for example. saving
as I go and have a look at my paddle. That
looks good! Now. look at Level 2 and look at your Paddle.
Again. they're all the same. Level 3 Paddle.
Good! So the Paddle has changed on every level. which means we
have updated the prefab appropriately. Now. let's just play for a moment.
Look the paddle
is going through the wall. You see the old extense of the
paddle are hitting the wall. so we'll deal with that in a minute. Let's just check the
bouncing for now. Actually. I'm going to do that
by bouncing off the bottom brick. so that I don't have to wait for it to
come back down again. Oh dear. there it
goes! So. this is the fun of play testing.
You've got to be accurate enough to... Ooh there it goes! Now. I've got a
lot more control over my bounce. You see that? That's pretty cool right!
I like it! I like it a lot! OK so
why is the paddle passing through the walls? That's
the question. Congratulations if you've already fixed it!
The reason is that. the position of the paddle is constrained in
code. and the paddle is now a different width
to what it was before. So previously.
when we moved the paddle to the left hand side of the Play
Space. it had a minimum transform position. if
you look here. of 0.5. Now.
when we move the paddle to the left hand side of the Play Space.
we have a minimum transform position of
about 1.18. by the looks of it
and a maximum transform position
of
in my case
about 14.8. So 1.18
and 14.8.
So. let's take a look. I'm just going to revert my
paddle back to the position that
it normally starts in. which is at precisely
8. in the middle. and then 0.5 in the
Y. Before I forget it.
I'm going to write down 1.18
and 4.8
believe that was right.
14.8...
OK. so they are my figures!
Now. where do you change that? Well. go to Scripts.
Paddle. and if you remember
the way that we constrained the Paddle was using Mathf.
Clamp. We couldn't use colliders. because actually the paddle never
moves. it never has any velocity during a frame. We
just move it frame by frame. using our script.
So. we use this Mathf.Clamp thing.
and our previous constraints were here.
And what we want to change them to is what I jotted down. 1.18 and
14.8.
In my case.
that's on line 26 of Paddle.cs.
in the Mathf.Clamp.
OK now. we need to do that both in AutoPlay and
in the MoveWithMouse () method.
Now. you could say is this a good
idea? Could we expose this in the Inspector?
Sure! Sure you can! In fact. this may be a
good idea! Why don't you do this as a mini challenge. Expose
these two float values. the min X and
max X. as instance variables
publicly in the Inspector right now. so that your artist
could make this change in the future. Go ahead. pause the video and do that
now. Cool! So I'm
doing it like this. I'm saying public float minX.
and maxX. I'm going to make
two variables at the same time.
And I'm not going to initialize them here. I'm going to leave them to the
Inspector. And then. I'm going
to remember that it's 1.18 and 14.8 and I'm going to say
minX down here.
maxX there. and then. the same
in the other method. So. whether we're doing it with AutoPlay
or with MoveWithMouse. then we still
use the same values. Now. of course you could
say let's refactor this line out to somewhere else but
we need to draw the line somewhere. This is going to get us what we want.
So now. in your Paddle Prefab. on the script.
with any
luck. we will see a minX
and a maxX.
Just check those against my
document. Perfect! They're also three significant figures. so that
feels right. Let's try it!
Ah hah! Ah hah! Perfect!
Awesome! Congratulations! So. we now have a paddle that is constrained
and even an artist could change those values. So as a
recap. what we have done here is we've learned what a Polygon Collider
is. We can see how it can help us improve our game.
We've learned how to manipulate Polygon Colliders. remember using
the Control Key to delete and just
by clicking to add new nodes. And hopefully you passed
the challenge and you chamfered your paddle yourself.
Cool! Enjoy the improved game play. See you soon!
=======
Hello hello, guys and girls!
So, in our game, we're doing really nicely.
There's something we could improve; there's not a lot of control
over the bounce of the ball, at the moment, because our
paddle is currently flat on the top surface.
So, what I want to talk to you about, in this lecture,
is what is a
Polygon Collider? How it could help us improve our game,
how to manipulate Polygon Colliders,
and then, I'm going to challenge you to chamfer your paddle. [Laughs]
Let me show you what I mean. So, if we
double click on Paddle, for example, in Level 1 in my case,
or click on it and push the F Key
for Frame. I sometimes say focus
but it's really Frame. You have to do this in Scene View.
Then, you will see the collider, very very faint
green outline. You can just see it if you
turn it on and off. Well, there's a Box Collider,
there's not a huge amount we can do when we edit it. We can make it
a little wider, taller, but we can't make it a different
shape. So, what I'm going to do and I'd like you to do is, go
into the Inspector for your paddle, but not in
a particular scene actually but as a prefab
of course, because you want to change your paddle everywhere. So, go
into your paddle, and what I want you to do
in your Paddle Prefab is, remove the Box
Collider all together. Scary!
And add yourself a new collider, so you can search for collider
and you'll find a Polygon Collider 2D.
That's what we want to add. OK.
Now, if we edit that Polygon Collider 2D,
let's have a look at see what we get.
Click back on the Paddle,
Just make sure you can see the green outline, it's very very
faint, it's almost invisible. And once you're sure you've
got the right thing, click Edit. Now,
it's still a box, but if you just
click the mouse and drag, you can now add
more lines to your polygon. Pretty cool hey! So
I can add a line out here, for example, and this is what I mean
by chamfering. Again, I can click on the other side and drag
out. So, I want us to modify our paddles
to look something like this. Now, if you make a mistake and you add
too many polygons, never fear, you can
always go back into the
Paddle, click back into Edit Collider,
and then, hold down the Control Key,
so that the segment goes red, and then, click and it will
remove that node.
Cool! So, I'm just going to quickly show you what would happen if we had these
invisible colliders now, like that.
It's difficult to see, but
you'll get to a situation where you can
bounce the ball differently, you've got more control over it. Let
me see if I can make it happen. Come on you.
I think it happened there! There you go and there!
But of course it's a little useless, because we can't see what we're doing.
So, here's your challenge then. What I want you to do
is create a new sprite, a new paddle
sprite. I would create an entirely separate
sprite sheet for that, with just a paddle in it,
with chamfered edges, so draw some chamfered edges somehow.
Adjust the collider, as I've just shown
you, to match that new sprite.
Then, I want you to ensure that the paddle is constrained properly
to the walls, because you're probably going to be making
your paddle wider, by doing this. I think it's a good idea to make it
wider, but we don't want it passing through the walls, so go
and find out where that constraint happens
and make the required change.
Then, check it all by play testing. So go
ahead, pause the video, and do that now.
Cool! Well, hopefully
you've got on well; I'm going to show you how I plan to do it.
So, looking at my sprites, I have a single
brick sprite sheet here, so I'm going to need to start with that,
I think. So, let me go and reveal that in my
Finder. I'm going to open it with my
program of choice, which is Picsend, at the moment.
Fine now, that's a starting
point. I think I'm going to immediately save this as
something else, before I start messing with it,
and I'm just going to call it paddle and it's a
.png, which is good it supports tnasparencey.
Great! Now, it's the wrong size and shape all together,
so let me make my window a little bigger and
start messing with this guy. So, first thing I'm going to do
is change the Canvas size.
It's 128 wide, I'm going to roll with 200.
It doesn't matter if it's wider than it needs to be, and remember that
our paddle is 41 pixels high and I"m going to keep the
top center of the image.
That looks about right. Actually, I want more width.
It's better to have more than you need, because when we cut it out in
Unity, it's going to ignore the transparent background. So, I'm
going to go right up to 300.
Fantastic! OK, so
we have a starting point for a chamfered paddle,
now what we need to do is change the shape. Excuse me.
Alright, so how are we going to do that? Well, it's entirely
up to you. You can use your artistic flair to draw some
lines and do whatever you like. I'm going to make a really ugly modification
mainly so that when you do your modification,
you can do better than us, and then, you can show off on the
discussion boards, by making something far prettier than I
have in this short video. So, let me see if
I can just make something, at least symmetrical,
which is nearly that.
You know what, I'm going to allow it to be rough
and ready and leave it at that. I'm just going to stick myself a
line along the bottom here, and I better get myself a
a Fill Tool and some gray color
perhaps and start filling it in.
Doesn't that look awful? That looks
perfectly awful! I think that's ideal.
I just want to demonstrate the point, and I think that having gray sides,
so that you can see the modification, is just fine.
So, I'm saving that .png file,
going back into Unity, and it's actually already here, paddle
.png. Now firstly, let's look at the World Units.
We want it to be consistant, so this bricks sprite
sheet used 1 to 8 pixels
per unit, so let's to the same with the new paddle.
Now, let's go straight into the Sprite Editor. It's a single
sprite in this case. That's fine and I'm going to
try, inside the Sprite Editor,
to make sure that the transparencies
are there. They are, we have checker boards; it all looks OK actually,
so there's nothing to do in the Sprite Editor. If I just
Apply that. Let's now try
going to my Brick Prefab,
and where it's asking for the sprite,
up here, instead of using the
0 hit sprite I'm now going to use the
Paddle Sprite. Great! So, we have a
new looking paddle, and it's very clear what's going on.
If you then go into the Paddle Prefab, remember we must do it
in the prefab, so it changes it across all the levels,
and we look at editing the Polygon Collider.
Let's see what we get now.
So, Paddle Prefab,
Polygon Collider, Edit.
Where are its current bounds? We need to be in the Scene View, which
we are.
And if you
click on it, there you go. Now, you can see that this isn't quite
right, at the moment, so with a bit of fiddling
around, you'll get to the point where you can edit it and you can zoom in.
And you can get your Polygon Collider
matching what you actually see in this
sprite, otherwise it's very strange when things bounce
off invisible objects. So
again, you can be more precise than me, if you wish.
I'm going for that, and it looks about right. You can see
that my Polygon Collider now is the same shape as my sprite.
I'm going to apply this change to
the prefab, like that.
Now, what would make sense would be to go into Level 1, for example, saving
as I go and have a look at my paddle. That
looks good! Now, look at Level 2 and look at your Paddle.
Again, they're all the same. Level 3 Paddle.
Good! So the Paddle has changed on every level, which means we
have updated the prefab appropriately. Now, let's just play for a moment.
Look the paddle
is going through the wall. You see the old extense of the
paddle are hitting the wall, so we'll deal with that in a minute. Let's just check the
bouncing for now. Actually, I'm going to do that
by bouncing off the bottom brick, so that I don't have to wait for it to
come back down again. Oh dear, there it
goes! So, this is the fun of play testing.
You've got to be accurate enough to... Ooh there it goes! Now, I've got a
lot more control over my bounce. You see that? That's pretty cool right!
I like it! I like it a lot! OK so
why is the paddle passing through the walls? That's
the question. Congratulations if you've already fixed it!
The reason is that, the position of the paddle is constrained in
code, and the paddle is now a different width
to what it was before. So previously,
when we moved the paddle to the left hand side of the Play
Space, it had a minimum transform position, if
you look here, of 0.5. Now,
when we move the paddle to the left hand side of the Play Space,
we have a minimum transform position of
about 1.18, by the looks of it
and a maximum transform position
of
in my case
about 14.8. So 1.18
and 14.8.
So, let's take a look. I'm just going to revert my
paddle back to the position that
it normally starts in, which is at precisely
8, in the middle, and then 0.5 in the
Y. Before I forget it,
I'm going to write down 1.18
and 4.8
believe that was right.
14.8...
OK, so they are my figures!
Now, where do you change that? Well, go to Scripts,
Paddle, and if you remember
the way that we constrained the Paddle was using Mathf.
Clamp. We couldn't use colliders, because actually the paddle never
moves, it never has any velocity during a frame. We
just move it frame by frame, using our script.
So, we use this Mathf.Clamp thing,
and our previous constraints were here.
And what we want to change them to is what I jotted down, 1.18 and
14.8.
In my case,
that's on line 26 of Paddle.cs,
in the Mathf.Clamp.
OK now, we need to do that both in AutoPlay and
in the MoveWithMouse () method.
Now, you could say is this a good
idea? Could we expose this in the Inspector?
Sure! Sure you can! In fact, this may be a
good idea! Why don't you do this as a mini challenge. Expose
these two float values, the min X and
max X, as instance variables
publicly in the Inspector right now, so that your artist
could make this change in the future. Go ahead, pause the video and do that
now. Cool! So I'm
doing it like this. I'm saying public float minX,
and maxX, I'm going to make
two variables at the same time.
And I'm not going to initialize them here, I'm going to leave them to the
Inspector. And then, I'm going
to remember that it's 1.18 and 14.8 and I'm going to say
minX down here.
maxX there, and then, the same
in the other method. So, whether we're doing it with AutoPlay
or with MoveWithMouse, then we still
use the same values. Now, of course you could
say let's refactor this line out to somewhere else but
we need to draw the line somewhere. This is going to get us what we want.
So now, in your Paddle Prefab, on the script,
with any
luck, we will see a minX
and a maxX.
Just check those against my
document. Perfect! They're also three significant figures, so that
feels right. Let's try it!
Ah hah! Ah hah! Perfect!
Awesome! Congratulations! So, we now have a paddle that is constrained
and even an artist could change those values. So as a
recap, what we have done here is we've learned what a Polygon Collider
is. We can see how it can help us improve our game.
We've learned how to manipulate Polygon Colliders, remember using
the Control Key to delete and just
by clicking to add new nodes. And hopefully you passed
the challenge and you chamfered your paddle yourself.
Cool! Enjoy the improved game play. See you soon!
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1:Unity/Section5/27c-More-Complex-Collider-Shapes.srt