Hey.
welcome back! So. in this video. we're going to talk about the coding trade
off triangle. It sounds mysterious. almost sounds like
the Bermuda Triangle. We're going to think about our
future self on the project. also mysterious.
And then. we're going to do the simple things. which are renaming a Game
Object and class. and we're going to use Debug.
LogError(). for the first time. So. what's this triangle thing?
Well. you've probably heard of a cost
quality time trade-off. in project management.
or even if you haven't. there's something similar when you write code.
You can write code that runs fast.
you can write code that's easy to extend.
and you can write code that's fast to write.
but you don't get to do all three.
The better you are. the closer you can get to
doing all three. but really you need to pick two.
So if code runs fast
and it's very easy for somebody to extend in the future. then it's
probably taken a long time to write. If it's
easy to extend and build on in the future. and it was very
fast to write. then it probably doesn't run very fast.
And if it's fast to write and it runs fast. then
it probably isn't easy to extend. So.
what we're going to do where is just think about it
extending our code. Imagine we come back to this in a few years
time. What can we do to improve it. so
that when we get back to it. it makes more sense to us?
Well. just a couple of simple challenges to you.
A thank you to John. for pointing out that I spelled
lose wrong. in the Lose Collider
Prefab. So. I'd like you to change the prefab name. it's a little
fidley. Also. change the script
and class name. and make sure the game still runs.
So. pause the video and change loose to
lose. throughout your game. now please.
[Temporary Silence]
So welcome back! There's a couple of good learnings in here. Let's
dive into Unity. take a look. So firstly. we go into
our prefabs. One of the beauties of prefabs is that. however
many levels you've got. when we change this Lose Collider we
only change it in one place. So. how do you find it? Well. it's
nested under the Play Space. so click on Assets.
Prefabs. Play Space. open the drawer with the little
triangle. and then. we're looking for Lose Collider.
Now. I'm going to rename it. up in the Inspector. and then. I'm going to hit Return.
And then. I'm going to check that in this particular level.
it has changed. It has but you'll notice a little bit of a
but or a querk of Unity is that. it hasn't yet changed.
certainly on my machine. within my Assets Drawer. but
if I save the projet it does update.
Great so. that's one place! Now. we 've got somewhere else
we need to change that. If we again go to the
Lose Collider Prefab. it's got a script on it. and the
script has got the wrong name. Let's go into the script here. Lose Collider.
There we go. Now. this is the class definition. You
need to change the class definition is one thing. save your script.
and then. you need to rename the script as
well. They need to be in sync in C#. so you
rename your script here. at the Asset Manager
and you change your class name. inside the script
at the top. where it says public class LoseCollider.
That brings it all into sync. Let's now that we've made these changes. have
a test that the thing still works and that we can
still lose. Good! And let's
just check a couple of other levels. to make sure that
the Lose Collider is still spelled correctly. Awesome!
Well done. if you've managed to do all those things yourself! You're really starting to
find your way around Unity. Got another challenge for you now! Here we go!
Let's take a look at the next one!
I want to add some "guard code" in Brick.cs.
so that when a sprite is missing. you get an error log to the console.
So at the moment. we check to see if
there is a sprite available to load.
for a given brick. but we don't log to the
Console. an error if there isn't. So. thanks to Ole
for pointing this out. So. I want you to do that.
Rather than using Debug.Log. like we normally do. just use
Debug.LogError. The only difference
with Debug.LogError is. when you look at your
Console. it will come up as a different
type. so it'll come up as an actual error. because it's quite serious. So.
you can choose what level of error you log out. and we're
going to be logging out a error. in this case. So. go
ahead and do that.
[Temporary Silence]
Cool! Welcome back! So relatively easy and it's going to be a good
revision of what goes on in Brick.cs. So. open up your
Brick.cs. I'm going to put an extra line
space in here. So. this if statement says. if (hit
Sprites[spriteIndex]). Well. that's really saying
if (hitSprite[spriteIndex]) does not equal
null... OK. let's just put that does not
equal null in. just to prove that it has no effect
on the game. the game still runs exactly the same.
OK. it still works fine.
But that's what it's really saying. It's saying if (hitSprites [spriteIndex])
doesn't equal null. i.e. that is.
a sprite at this sprite index. But how about if
there isn't a sprite? At the moment. it just does nothing. it doesn't load a sprite.
So. I'm going to say else.
This is where we put our Debug.Log. Now. look what we've
got. We've got errors. exceptions. and warnings.
They're your three types. well actually four types. you can just
log. You can log an error. an exception. and a warning. We're
just going to log an error here. It just comes up in a slightly different
filter. in a different color.
[Typing Sound]
("Brick sprite missing");  OK. you see what I've
done there. If it can't find a sprite. at that position in the index. when it
gets to it. it says there's a brick sprite missing. So.
obviously when I run as normal. we get no
problems no errors. If I pause and
look at the Console. we have no errors. but how about
if I was to go to my Prefabs
and bravely take. say off the red.
one of the
hit sprites. this Element 1 here. Let's
make that none. OK. now let's see what happens when we
run. When I click play...
Let's pause.
Here you go! In the Console. we have a red
warning. You can filter on and off these errors here.
and it says. error "Brick sprite missing".
OK fantastic! So. again congratulations
if you did that! If you've tested by taking a sprite off. like I did.
just pop it back on. just so that everything
works. And that's it! So congratulations!
Just by way of a quick recap for you.
we have looked at the coding trade off triangle.
Remember. things Run Fast. they're Easy to Extend. or they're
Fast to Write. but you don't get to really do all three.
We've thought about our future self on the project and said. well
if we see Loose Collider rather than Lose.
that's a bit confusing. so let's change that. We've also
said it's going to be a bit confusing if a
sprite doesn't swap out; it'd be much more useful to have an error.
And then. we've looked at renaming Game Objects and Classes.
and we've used a different type of Debug.Log. just so that you
can stream your logs into different
severities. levels of severity.
So congratulations. and I will see you soon!
=======
Hey,
welcome back! So, in this video, we're going to talk about the coding trade
off triangle. It sounds mysterious, almost sounds like
the Bermuda Triangle. We're going to think about our
future self on the project, also mysterious.
And then, we're going to do the simple things, which are renaming a Game
Object and class, and we're going to use Debug.
LogError(), for the first time. So, what's this triangle thing?
Well, you've probably heard of a cost
quality time trade-off, in project management,
or even if you haven't, there's something similar when you write code.
You can write code that runs fast,
you can write code that's easy to extend,
and you can write code that's fast to write,
but you don't get to do all three.
The better you are, the closer you can get to
doing all three, but really you need to pick two.
So if code runs fast
and it's very easy for somebody to extend in the future, then it's
probably taken a long time to write. If it's
easy to extend and build on in the future, and it was very
fast to write, then it probably doesn't run very fast.
And if it's fast to write and it runs fast, then
it probably isn't easy to extend. So,
what we're going to do where is just think about it
extending our code. Imagine we come back to this in a few years
time. What can we do to improve it, so
that when we get back to it, it makes more sense to us?
Well, just a couple of simple challenges to you.
A thank you to John, for pointing out that I spelled
lose wrong, in the Lose Collider
Prefab. So, I'd like you to change the prefab name, it's a little
fidley. Also, change the script
and class name, and make sure the game still runs.
So, pause the video and change loose to
lose, throughout your game, now please.
[Temporary Silence]
So welcome back! There's a couple of good learnings in here. Let's
dive into Unity, take a look. So firstly, we go into
our prefabs. One of the beauties of prefabs is that, however
many levels you've got, when we change this Lose Collider we
only change it in one place. So, how do you find it? Well, it's
nested under the Play Space, so click on Assets,
Prefabs, Play Space, open the drawer with the little
triangle, and then, we're looking for Lose Collider.
Now, I'm going to rename it, up in the Inspector, and then, I'm going to hit Return.
And then, I'm going to check that in this particular level,
it has changed. It has but you'll notice a little bit of a
but or a querk of Unity is that, it hasn't yet changed,
certainly on my machine, within my Assets Drawer, but
if I save the projet it does update.
Great so, that's one place! Now, we 've got somewhere else
we need to change that. If we again go to the
Lose Collider Prefab, it's got a script on it, and the
script has got the wrong name. Let's go into the script here, Lose Collider.
There we go. Now, this is the class definition. You
need to change the class definition is one thing, save your script,
and then, you need to rename the script as
well. They need to be in sync in C#, so you
rename your script here, at the Asset Manager
and you change your class name, inside the script
at the top, where it says public class LoseCollider.
That brings it all into sync. Let's now that we've made these changes, have
a test that the thing still works and that we can
still lose. Good! And let's
just check a couple of other levels, to make sure that
the Lose Collider is still spelled correctly. Awesome!
Well done, if you've managed to do all those things yourself! You're really starting to
find your way around Unity. Got another challenge for you now! Here we go!
Let's take a look at the next one!
I want to add some "guard code" in Brick.cs,
so that when a sprite is missing, you get an error log to the console.
So at the moment, we check to see if
there is a sprite available to load,
for a given brick, but we don't log to the
Console, an error if there isn't. So, thanks to Ole
for pointing this out. So, I want you to do that.
Rather than using Debug.Log, like we normally do, just use
Debug.LogError. The only difference
with Debug.LogError is, when you look at your
Console, it will come up as a different
type, so it'll come up as an actual error, because it's quite serious. So,
you can choose what level of error you log out, and we're
going to be logging out a error, in this case. So, go
ahead and do that.
[Temporary Silence]
Cool! Welcome back! So relatively easy and it's going to be a good
revision of what goes on in Brick.cs. So, open up your
Brick.cs. I'm going to put an extra line
space in here. So, this if statement says, if (hit
Sprites[spriteIndex]). Well, that's really saying
if (hitSprite[spriteIndex]) does not equal
null... OK, let's just put that does not
equal null in, just to prove that it has no effect
on the game, the game still runs exactly the same.
OK, it still works fine.
But that's what it's really saying. It's saying if (hitSprites [spriteIndex])
doesn't equal null, i.e. that is,
a sprite at this sprite index. But how about if
there isn't a sprite? At the moment, it just does nothing, it doesn't load a sprite.
So, I'm going to say else.
This is where we put our Debug.Log. Now, look what we've
got. We've got errors, exceptions, and warnings.
They're your three types, well actually four types, you can just
log. You can log an error, an exception, and a warning. We're
just going to log an error here. It just comes up in a slightly different
filter, in a different color.
[Typing Sound]
("Brick sprite missing");  OK, you see what I've
done there. If it can't find a sprite, at that position in the index, when it
gets to it, it says there's a brick sprite missing. So,
obviously when I run as normal, we get no
problems no errors. If I pause and
look at the Console, we have no errors, but how about
if I was to go to my Prefabs
and bravely take, say off the red,
one of the
hit sprites, this Element 1 here. Let's
make that none. OK, now let's see what happens when we
run. When I click play...
Let's pause.
Here you go! In the Console, we have a red
warning. You can filter on and off these errors here,
and it says, error "Brick sprite missing".
OK fantastic! So, again congratulations
if you did that! If you've tested by taking a sprite off, like I did,
just pop it back on, just so that everything
works. And that's it! So congratulations!
Just by way of a quick recap for you,
we have looked at the coding trade off triangle.
Remember, things Run Fast, they're Easy to Extend, or they're
Fast to Write, but you don't get to really do all three.
We've thought about our future self on the project and said, well
if we see Loose Collider rather than Lose,
that's a bit confusing, so let's change that. We've also
said it's going to be a bit confusing if a
sprite doesn't swap out; it'd be much more useful to have an error.
And then, we've looked at renaming Game Objects and Classes,
and we've used a different type of Debug.Log, just so that you
can stream your logs into different
severities, levels of severity.
So congratulations, and I will see you soon!
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1:Unity/Section5/27d-Making-Code-Extendable.srt