Hey welcome back! I want to
spice up our game. with a little bit of smoke. using Particle
Systems. When a brick is destroyed like that. I want to see
a smoke puff come out. and I'd like the smoke puff to
be the color of the brick that got destroyed.
So. let's look at how we're going to do that.
In this lecture we're going to cover the following: We're going to
create a simple Particle System. we're going to make a brick
look like it goes up in smoke. we're going to write the
code to trigger smoke puffs. and then. at the
end we will tweak the smoke prefab. while play testing
to get it looking right. So. what's a Particle System?
An extract from Unity's document say it's "for effects
like moving liquids. smoke. clouds. flames and magic spells...
Particle Systems can be used to capture the inherent
fluidity and energy." You can read more about it here.
So. let's start off by putting an empty Game
Object into our Play Space. and I'm going to call it smoke.
In the Scene View.
let's move it somewhere where we can see it. for a moment.
and add a component to it called Particle
System. Over in Inspector. Add Component. Particle System.
Now immediately. you'll get this default Particle System
here. Pretty fun hey! Let's take a look at some
of the settings. Duration 5 means that it's a
5 second loop. basically. that this
goes around in. and the Start Lifetime
is how long the particles last for. If the particles
say lasted for 1 second. let's see what happens.
Each one dies out. after 1 second.
but the effect has a lifetime of
5 but because we are looping you don't see that. So. if you take it off
loop now. now you will see that you get
5 seconds of emission. of particles that
last 1 second. I hope that makes
sense. The other option is we could turn that around the other way. We could
have 1 second of emission.
and it stops at particles that last 5 seconds.
Cool! So look. we're going to play with the details
of this later. so for now. I'm just going to set it to
1 second and 1 second. I think.
And then. I'm going to come
down and have a look at what other things I can change. Now.
one of the things I'm going to want to look at is the Emission Rate.
Are my particles coming out too fast or too
slow. and also the shape of the emission.
Well. I'm going to go for a box. in my case.
so let's have a look at that. Ah. that's kind of
more like it. So. imagine this
was where a brick was.
Yeah. that's kind of OK!
Yeah OK! So. let's use this
as a starting point. So. my settings are 1 second duration.
1 second lifetime. I haven't changed
the Emission criteria. but I've changed the shape to a box
and just left it at that for now. OK. so if we
were to just run the game. then that would just happen and go away.
So. that's all very well. but we're going to need this
to happen at run time. so because of that. we need to
prefab the smoke. So. let's go ahead and prefab the smoke now.
I'm going to do that. by dragging the smoke that I have
into my
Assets Folder. down here. I'm also going to
Reset the Transform on the prefab. And then. I
get rid of the smoke. from the scene. So now. if I
was to drop smoke back into the Hierarchy I would
end up with it down at the bottom left. which is what I'd expect. And it's
blue. so it's prefabbed. Awesome!
So now. what I want to do is I want to challenge you
to make the smoke get triggered. when
a brick gets destroyed. I'm going to get you started.
let's go into Brick.cs. and I'm going to tell you that we're
going to need to expose ourselves a GameObject.
and I'm going to call it smoke.
Alright. and then the moment we've exposed that
GameObject smoke. if you look at your brick prefabs on the
green. red. and yellow. all of those are going
to want the Smoke Prefab.
Alright. so I've made public GameObject smoke.
and then. I've come back to the Inspector and dragged the
Smoke Prefab into the green. red. and yellow. In
my case. all my breakable bricks now have a
smoke attached to them. We're using the same smoke. for all of them
at the moment. Your challenge is as
follows. I want you to instantiate smoke at
runtime. Here are some hints. Instantiate the Smoke
Prefab as a GameObject. It's position
should be the brick's position. When you check the
docs. you'll notice it needs a rotation. Just use Quaternion
.identity. and don't worry about what that means. for now. it just means it's
upright. And test that you get white
smoke puffs. when the bricks are destroyed. Don't yet try and make them the same
color as the bricks. One step at a time. let's just get white
smoke puffs. when bricks are destroyed. Here are Unity's docs
for Object.Instantiate. and
hopfully using those and a bit of willing. you can get that going.
So. pause the video and do that challenge now.
OK how
did you get on? This is how I've solved this problem.
I'm looking into my Brick.cs
script. firstly to see where I want to do this.
Well. I want to do it immediately before I destroy the GameObject.
so the method is Instantiate.
Then. we need the smoke.
which we defined up at the top and we publicly
inserted it. Now. what's the position... What's the
position of the brick? Well. it's gameObject. because we're on Brick.cs.
It's the instance of the current gameObject.transform
.position. And then. I said we're going to use Quaternion
.identity. for just a default
upright rotation. That's the line I'm adding.
Instantiate smoke. at the position
of the brick. with default rotation. Let's
have a look.
Oh yes. and that's exciting!
So. let's just make sure it works on other brick types. by firing
the ball up the side.
Of course. these guys take a few hits to go. There you go!
White puffs are being generated. so if you did
that all on your own. congratulations! Now. let's move onto the next
step. which is getting the puffs colored.
So. your challenge again is. store the smoke
puff. that you just generated. as a GameObject variable.
So. just add to the line we just created. so that you
store this thing. Then.
using the right dots. set the
smoke's start color to the same as the brick.
and test that different bricks make different smoke.
As a hint. the color that you want to set
comes from the brick's sprite renderer. So. pause
the video. and have a go at making colored smoke. right now!
[Temporary Silence]
OK welcome back! Let's take a look at how to do this thing!
Firstly. let's make this method...
Sorry. this Variable that captures the thing we
instantiated. So. it's a GameObject. and I'm going to call it
smokePuff
= that. So now. we have
smokePuff as a local variable. which is
the very smokePuff we just instantiated.
Now. we can start messing with it. smokePuff
dot. Now. smokePuff dot what?
Well. let's have a look in Unity. at a smoke puff.
Here's a smoke puff. so
it's a GameObject. and then. we need to look at it's particle system.
Dot particleSystem
dot. OK. let's keep going. Dot start
Color. Ah. that looks promising. smokePuff
.particleSystem.startColor =.
Now. the second half. where do we get
this color from. Well. we need to get it from the brick. And what about
the brick? Well. it's the brick's sprite renderer.
So. it's gameObject.
Now. you can't get to sprite
renderer. so we're going to have to GetComponent
Like that and then dot.
What do we go for?
Color. OK hopefully
that makes sense to you. So. we're taking the current
brick. we're getting the SpriteRenderer component off it.
and then. we're getting the color. whether it's yellow. green.
or red. and then. we're setting that to the color of the particle
System. Let's have a go and see if it works!
OK!
So. the error is on line 45. and it says it
can't convert a Unity Engine object to a GameObject.
Are we missing a cast? So. it's hinting at a possible
solution. Let's have a look at the docs for Instantiate.
very briefly. In fact. they're sitting here.
They return an object not a GameObject.
So. this line here is not returning.
This Instantiate method does not return a GameObject. it returns
an object. So. we need to
say at the end. as GameObject;
now. that line has got a little bit long. but actually you can remove
gameObject from .tranform.position.
because it's going to assume we're talking about the current GameObject.
So. your line 45. in my case. can become this.
The GameObject. smokePuff
variable. that we're going to use to store. is the result
of Instantiating a new smokePuff at the position of
brick with default rotation. but when we
Instantiate. we want to cast it from being a general object to
being a more specific GameObject. Then. we can work
on the smokePuff GameObject properly. Let's try
now.
Awesome! Yellow puff. yellow
puff. and off we go! Let's just test
other colors. make sure that they work OK!
Then. red bricks take a little
while to go. Great!
Look at that and all the colors are mixing together. Fantastic!
So. now that you've done that. you can go into your Smoke Prefab.
and you can mess around all you like with the
factors down here. You could
click Random Direction on your shape. for instance.
and see that. that has a dramatic effect on it. I find
that very distracting. but the great thing is that because we're
using prefabs. any changes we make to the Particle System now
will apply everywhere. I'm going to leave mine like this.
and I'm also going to do a quick tidy up of my
code. I don't think this HandleHits () is very
easy to read anymore. so I'm going to make a new method
called PuffSmoke.
which is just going to move out the code from that Handle
Hits () method; all of the stuff that deals with
puffing smoke. which is really simple. it's
just two lines there. So. I'm just going to do that and I'm
just going to say PuffSmoke(); just because
I want to be able to see. in the HandleHits what happens.
a bit more clearly. Just to prove that works.
and there it goes.
So congratulations! Let's just take a recap of what we've learned in
this lesson. We have
created a simple Particle System. made a brick look
like it goes up in smoke. written code to trigger those
smoke puffs. and tweaked the Smoke Prefab while play testing.
at the end. Awesome job! Well done! See you soon!
=======
Hey welcome back! I want to
spice up our game, with a little bit of smoke, using Particle
Systems. When a brick is destroyed like that, I want to see
a smoke puff come out, and I'd like the smoke puff to
be the color of the brick that got destroyed.
So, let's look at how we're going to do that.
In this lecture we're going to cover the following: We're going to
create a simple Particle System, we're going to make a brick
look like it goes up in smoke, we're going to write the
code to trigger smoke puffs, and then, at the
end we will tweak the smoke prefab, while play testing
to get it looking right. So, what's a Particle System?
An extract from Unity's document say it's "for effects
like moving liquids, smoke, clouds, flames and magic spells...
Particle Systems can be used to capture the inherent
fluidity and energy." You can read more about it here.
So, let's start off by putting an empty Game
Object into our Play Space, and I'm going to call it smoke.
In the Scene View,
let's move it somewhere where we can see it, for a moment,
and add a component to it called Particle
System. Over in Inspector, Add Component, Particle System.
Now immediately, you'll get this default Particle System
here. Pretty fun hey! Let's take a look at some
of the settings. Duration 5 means that it's a
5 second loop, basically, that this
goes around in, and the Start Lifetime
is how long the particles last for. If the particles
say lasted for 1 second, let's see what happens.
Each one dies out, after 1 second,
but the effect has a lifetime of
5 but because we are looping you don't see that. So, if you take it off
loop now, now you will see that you get
5 seconds of emission, of particles that
last 1 second. I hope that makes
sense. The other option is we could turn that around the other way. We could
have 1 second of emission,
and it stops at particles that last 5 seconds.
Cool! So look, we're going to play with the details
of this later, so for now, I'm just going to set it to
1 second and 1 second, I think.
And then, I'm going to come
down and have a look at what other things I can change. Now,
one of the things I'm going to want to look at is the Emission Rate.
Are my particles coming out too fast or too
slow, and also the shape of the emission.
Well, I'm going to go for a box, in my case,
so let's have a look at that. Ah, that's kind of
more like it. So, imagine this
was where a brick was.
Yeah, that's kind of OK!
Yeah OK! So, let's use this
as a starting point. So, my settings are 1 second duration,
1 second lifetime. I haven't changed
the Emission criteria, but I've changed the shape to a box
and just left it at that for now. OK, so if we
were to just run the game, then that would just happen and go away.
So, that's all very well, but we're going to need this
to happen at run time, so because of that, we need to
prefab the smoke. So, let's go ahead and prefab the smoke now.
I'm going to do that, by dragging the smoke that I have
into my
Assets Folder, down here. I'm also going to
Reset the Transform on the prefab. And then, I
get rid of the smoke, from the scene. So now, if I
was to drop smoke back into the Hierarchy I would
end up with it down at the bottom left, which is what I'd expect. And it's
blue, so it's prefabbed. Awesome!
So now, what I want to do is I want to challenge you
to make the smoke get triggered, when
a brick gets destroyed. I'm going to get you started,
let's go into Brick.cs, and I'm going to tell you that we're
going to need to expose ourselves a GameObject,
and I'm going to call it smoke.
Alright, and then the moment we've exposed that
GameObject smoke, if you look at your brick prefabs on the
green, red, and yellow, all of those are going
to want the Smoke Prefab.
Alright, so I've made public GameObject smoke,
and then, I've come back to the Inspector and dragged the
Smoke Prefab into the green, red, and yellow. In
my case, all my breakable bricks now have a
smoke attached to them. We're using the same smoke, for all of them
at the moment. Your challenge is as
follows. I want you to instantiate smoke at
runtime. Here are some hints. Instantiate the Smoke
Prefab as a GameObject. It's position
should be the brick's position. When you check the
docs, you'll notice it needs a rotation. Just use Quaternion
.identity, and don't worry about what that means, for now, it just means it's
upright. And test that you get white
smoke puffs, when the bricks are destroyed. Don't yet try and make them the same
color as the bricks. One step at a time, let's just get white
smoke puffs, when bricks are destroyed. Here are Unity's docs
for Object.Instantiate, and
hopfully using those and a bit of willing, you can get that going.
So, pause the video and do that challenge now.
OK how
did you get on? This is how I've solved this problem.
I'm looking into my Brick.cs
script, firstly to see where I want to do this.
Well, I want to do it immediately before I destroy the GameObject,
so the method is Instantiate.
Then, we need the smoke,
which we defined up at the top and we publicly
inserted it. Now, what's the position... What's the
position of the brick? Well, it's gameObject, because we're on Brick.cs.
It's the instance of the current gameObject.transform
.position. And then, I said we're going to use Quaternion
.identity, for just a default
upright rotation. That's the line I'm adding.
Instantiate smoke, at the position
of the brick, with default rotation. Let's
have a look.
Oh yes, and that's exciting!
So, let's just make sure it works on other brick types, by firing
the ball up the side.
Of course, these guys take a few hits to go. There you go!
White puffs are being generated, so if you did
that all on your own, congratulations! Now, let's move onto the next
step, which is getting the puffs colored.
So, your challenge again is, store the smoke
puff, that you just generated, as a GameObject variable.
So, just add to the line we just created, so that you
store this thing. Then,
using the right dots, set the
smoke's start color to the same as the brick,
and test that different bricks make different smoke.
As a hint, the color that you want to set
comes from the brick's sprite renderer. So, pause
the video, and have a go at making colored smoke, right now!
[Temporary Silence]
OK welcome back! Let's take a look at how to do this thing!
Firstly, let's make this method...
Sorry, this Variable that captures the thing we
instantiated. So, it's a GameObject, and I'm going to call it
smokePuff
= that. So now, we have
smokePuff as a local variable, which is
the very smokePuff we just instantiated.
Now, we can start messing with it, smokePuff
dot. Now, smokePuff dot what?
Well, let's have a look in Unity, at a smoke puff.
Here's a smoke puff, so
it's a GameObject, and then, we need to look at it's particle system.
Dot particleSystem
dot. OK, let's keep going. Dot start
Color. Ah, that looks promising, smokePuff
.particleSystem.startColor =.
Now, the second half, where do we get
this color from. Well, we need to get it from the brick. And what about
the brick? Well, it's the brick's sprite renderer.
So, it's gameObject.
Now, you can't get to sprite
renderer, so we're going to have to GetComponent
Like that and then dot.
What do we go for?
Color, OK hopefully
that makes sense to you. So, we're taking the current
brick, we're getting the SpriteRenderer component off it,
and then, we're getting the color, whether it's yellow, green,
or red, and then, we're setting that to the color of the particle
System. Let's have a go and see if it works!
OK!
So, the error is on line 45, and it says it
can't convert a Unity Engine object to a GameObject.
Are we missing a cast? So, it's hinting at a possible
solution. Let's have a look at the docs for Instantiate,
very briefly. In fact, they're sitting here.
They return an object not a GameObject.
So, this line here is not returning.
This Instantiate method does not return a GameObject, it returns
an object. So, we need to
say at the end, as GameObject;
now, that line has got a little bit long, but actually you can remove
gameObject from .tranform.position,
because it's going to assume we're talking about the current GameObject.
So, your line 45, in my case, can become this.
The GameObject, smokePuff
variable, that we're going to use to store, is the result
of Instantiating a new smokePuff at the position of
brick with default rotation, but when we
Instantiate, we want to cast it from being a general object to
being a more specific GameObject. Then, we can work
on the smokePuff GameObject properly. Let's try
now.
Awesome! Yellow puff, yellow
puff, and off we go! Let's just test
other colors, make sure that they work OK!
Then, red bricks take a little
while to go. Great!
Look at that and all the colors are mixing together. Fantastic!
So, now that you've done that, you can go into your Smoke Prefab,
and you can mess around all you like with the
factors down here. You could
click Random Direction on your shape, for instance,
and see that, that has a dramatic effect on it. I find
that very distracting, but the great thing is that because we're
using prefabs, any changes we make to the Particle System now
will apply everywhere. I'm going to leave mine like this,
and I'm also going to do a quick tidy up of my
code. I don't think this HandleHits () is very
easy to read anymore, so I'm going to make a new method
called PuffSmoke,
which is just going to move out the code from that Handle
Hits () method; all of the stuff that deals with
puffing smoke, which is really simple, it's
just two lines there. So, I'm just going to do that and I'm
just going to say PuffSmoke(); just because
I want to be able to see, in the HandleHits what happens,
a bit more clearly. Just to prove that works,
and there it goes.
So congratulations! Let's just take a recap of what we've learned in
this lesson. We have
created a simple Particle System, made a brick look
like it goes up in smoke, written code to trigger those
smoke puffs, and tweaked the Smoke Prefab while play testing,
at the end. Awesome job! Well done! See you soon!
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1:Unity/Section5/27e-An-Introduction-To-Particle-Systems.srt