Hi. so in this optional video. I'm going
to upgrade Block Breaker to Unity 5. So.
if you have Unity 5 installed. then you can
go ahead and upgrade the project to Unity 5. and then. I'm going
to do a Web GL buiild. So. when
you try and open Block Breaker.
in Unity 5. you're going to get this message that's saying: "The project contains scripts
and or assemblies that use obsolete API's". That sounds
a bit jargony. there are some changes in Unity 5. I'll
show you them. once we have actually made the upgrade.
So. before you do it. please do make
a .zip of your Unity Folder. Close your project. make a .zip.
or if you're using version control. take a commit and do make
that backup first. and then. go ahead. It won't break
it by the way. but if you want to be able to go back to Unity 4.
you need to make the backup. OK. so then what you do is you
click the button. and it will. in a moment. open up like so.
Now. here is Block Breaker in Unity 5. Let's go
to our Start Menu Scene. And as you can see it looks
largely the same. Let's try playing it. The music is
working. And is the game working?
[Boing Sound Effects in Background] Yep. my daughter's sound effects.
It's all working just fine. Now. there are some times
some things that are a little different in Unity 5. Like for
example. when you have a UI. then the
vertical order of things in this UI
Hierarchy can change what renders on top of what. but that's not
causing us a problem here. Let's just check both the Start
Menu and the Win Screen for that. and the
Lose Screen. all looks OK. So. the thing that you'll
notice that's actually changed is all just to do with
these scripts. There's been some minor changes to the
scripts. Let me show you. This is my Version Control System. but let's take
an example of. say the ball. and what
it's done for us is. instead of being able to just say
ribidbody2D. we now have to say.
GetComponent. angle brackets. Rigid
2D. and then. normal brackets dot.
So. that's the bit in the middle there. this GetComponent
and that goes for other things as well. like AudioSources  rather
than just saying AudioSource.Play when you say GetComponent
AudioSource.Play. So. basically
Unity has fire walled all of these different components. so the we actually
have to make an explicit get for them but that's fine.
That's a very minor change and it will actually do it for you. you can see
it everywhere. GetComponent. So. it's made those changes
for you. Great! So. what I want to show you briefly
now. is how to do a Web GL Build. Game Bucket
is all ready for a Web GL Build. so you just come to File. Build Settings.
here. Now. if you're in Unity
5 there's a new option. WebGL Preview there.
so we switch the platform to that.
And then. you'll see at the top. this is also
a difference in Unity 5. after the project name you get Web GL
as the platform name and then. personal is the edition of
[Fumbles Words & Laughs] Udemy. Udemy. Unity. Unity.
and then. we build and run. And it's going to say. where do you want me
to go? Well. I'm put it. say in my downloads.
for example.
[Typing Sound]
And there we go! If you compile it. and you'll get a file that
you can put in Game Bucket. in the same way as you put your other projects
in there. or as I showed you earlier in this section. and you
will be able to host your game. The difference with the Web GL
Build. of course. is that you do not need
or the player does not need to have the Unity Plugin. It
works purely off HTML 5. which most all
modern browsers support. So.
after a while you should notice your browser open like this.
You will be able to play the game in a web browser. but this is a
locally hosted version of your game here. and you
can see that it says Unity Web GL. at the bottom. And you can make it full
screen. and it runs beautifully. without using a Unity
Plugin. which is great. So. how do we get this
up to Game Bucket. Well. what you want to do
is look in the folder that you stored your project
in. So. in this case it was Web GL Build in my Downloads.
Just zip up that entire folder. just compress it. Now. you
can do that in Windows or Mac in a similar way.
Compress it like so. and then. once you have the
.zip file. you simply upload that .zip file
to Game Bucket. And It'll take a little while but when it's finished you'll
get something like this. you'll just get your game hosted inside Game Bucket.
You can take that URL. check it in an incognito
browser tab like this. just to simulate you not
being logged in. and then. you'll know that if you share that with your friends.
that this is exactly what they'll see. And they don't need a
Unity Plugin. So. there you go! Web GL Build and Unity
5. See you soon!
=======
Hi, so in this optional video, I'm going
to upgrade Block Breaker to Unity 5. So,
if you have Unity 5 installed, then you can
go ahead and upgrade the project to Unity 5, and then, I'm going
to do a Web GL buiild. So, when
you try and open Block Breaker,
in Unity 5, you're going to get this message that's saying: "The project contains scripts
and or assemblies that use obsolete API's". That sounds
a bit jargony, there are some changes in Unity 5. I'll
show you them, once we have actually made the upgrade.
So, before you do it, please do make
a .zip of your Unity Folder. Close your project, make a .zip,
or if you're using version control, take a commit and do make
that backup first, and then, go ahead. It won't break
it by the way, but if you want to be able to go back to Unity 4,
you need to make the backup. OK, so then what you do is you
click the button, and it will, in a moment, open up like so.
Now, here is Block Breaker in Unity 5. Let's go
to our Start Menu Scene. And as you can see it looks
largely the same. Let's try playing it. The music is
working. And is the game working?
[Boing Sound Effects in Background] Yep, my daughter's sound effects.
It's all working just fine. Now, there are some times
some things that are a little different in Unity 5. Like for
example, when you have a UI, then the
vertical order of things in this UI
Hierarchy can change what renders on top of what, but that's not
causing us a problem here. Let's just check both the Start
Menu and the Win Screen for that, and the
Lose Screen, all looks OK. So, the thing that you'll
notice that's actually changed is all just to do with
these scripts. There's been some minor changes to the
scripts. Let me show you. This is my Version Control System, but let's take
an example of, say the ball, and what
it's done for us is, instead of being able to just say
ribidbody2D. we now have to say,
GetComponent, angle brackets, Rigid
2D, and then, normal brackets dot.
So, that's the bit in the middle there, this GetComponent
and that goes for other things as well, like AudioSources  rather
than just saying AudioSource.Play when you say GetComponent
AudioSource.Play. So, basically
Unity has fire walled all of these different components, so the we actually
have to make an explicit get for them but that's fine.
That's a very minor change and it will actually do it for you, you can see
it everywhere, GetComponent. So, it's made those changes
for you. Great! So, what I want to show you briefly
now, is how to do a Web GL Build. Game Bucket
is all ready for a Web GL Build, so you just come to File, Build Settings,
here. Now, if you're in Unity
5 there's a new option, WebGL Preview there,
so we switch the platform to that.
And then, you'll see at the top, this is also
a difference in Unity 5, after the project name you get Web GL
as the platform name and then, personal is the edition of
[Fumbles Words & Laughs] Udemy, Udemy, Unity, Unity,
and then, we build and run. And it's going to say, where do you want me
to go? Well, I'm put it, say in my downloads,
for example.
[Typing Sound]
And there we go! If you compile it, and you'll get a file that
you can put in Game Bucket, in the same way as you put your other projects
in there, or as I showed you earlier in this section, and you
will be able to host your game. The difference with the Web GL
Build, of course, is that you do not need
or the player does not need to have the Unity Plugin. It
works purely off HTML 5, which most all
modern browsers support. So,
after a while you should notice your browser open like this.
You will be able to play the game in a web browser, but this is a
locally hosted version of your game here, and you
can see that it says Unity Web GL, at the bottom. And you can make it full
screen, and it runs beautifully, without using a Unity
Plugin, which is great. So, how do we get this
up to Game Bucket. Well, what you want to do
is look in the folder that you stored your project
in. So, in this case it was Web GL Build in my Downloads.
Just zip up that entire folder, just compress it. Now, you
can do that in Windows or Mac in a similar way.
Compress it like so, and then, once you have the
.zip file, you simply upload that .zip file
to Game Bucket. And It'll take a little while but when it's finished you'll
get something like this, you'll just get your game hosted inside Game Bucket.
You can take that URL, check it in an incognito
browser tab like this, just to simulate you not
being logged in, and then, you'll know that if you share that with your friends,
that this is exactly what they'll see. And they don't need a
Unity Plugin. So, there you go! Web GL Build and Unity
5. See you soon!
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1:Unity/Section5/27f-Unity-5Upgrade-Webgl-Build.srt