Hey guys! So, hopefully you've had a little
look at Git. So, in this video we're going
to talk about how Git can help you share your
project, not your final game yet, but just
your project state, how we use it for the
course, what's different about how you may
use it, and also worth reading this blog post
by Dan. Dan the man! So, we have Dan Reilly
here, he's written a really cool blog post.
There's a few posts on here, actually talking
about how to use GitHub with Unity. Alright,
so let's get on with that, so I want to firstly
show you how we use it. So, you've seen that
we have all of these different repos; well,
I'm going to show you setting up a repo firstly.
This is the remote version of things; we will
talk about your local software in a little
bit, but I'm going to just set up a remote
repo here. I'm going to call it 10 TwinStick,
because that's the section I'm about to work
on, and it's a... What should we call it?
Oh, here you go, I've typed it before! "A
cross-platform, twin stick control game set
in 2.5D as part of The Complete Unity Developer."
Fantastic! So, I'm going to make it public.
If you want to make things private on GitHub,
you actually have to pay, and I'm going to
leave out the readme file, just for now, and
I will show you what the readme file does
in a second, and I will put a read me in.
Cool! So, now we have a repository for Twin
Sticks, so when you watch the video you will
actually see that, but there is no readme
File and there's no commits to it yet. If
you look at Zombie Runner, then it has this
readme file .md. So, we'll be doing that shortly,
sorting out readme files, but Twin Sticks
has nothing. Alright, fantastic! So, what
I do when I make these courses is, I already
have a local repository for Twin Sticks, and
all I've done on it is some prototyping.
So, I have an initial commit, and then, I
have this PT branch, which I've just done
very little; I've just had a quick play before,
actually getting on with recording the section.
But this is just local to my machine, so what
I'm going to do is I'm going to connect that,
and again, you don't need to do any of this.
What I'm doing is I'm doing this, so that
the challenge I'm going to give you in a minute
will actually work. Your challenge is going
to be very simple. You're just going to go
to the GitHub website and download this prototype.
OK, but I've got to get it there, and to get
it there, I may as well show you how I'm getting
it there. So, I have a local databases on
my machine, that's what you're looking at,
and it has a couple of changes that I've tracked
and it's just sitting on my machine, so how
do I get it to the Web. Well, I make a local
repository, which I've already done, and I'm
just going to go and find it now, because
it's already connected to my GitHub account,
this piece of software. This is called SourceTree;
we'll look at that later, as well. And if
I call this 10... I think I named them differently
actually? Oh no, hang on. The remote name
is going to be GitHub, because that's the
name of the remote thing that I'm sending
this to, so there we go. So, all I've done
is just connected my local database to the remote
database. Now, if I do this push thingy here
and I say I want to push the prototype branch
to GitHub, remember the diagram from the last video. What's
happening is it's just sending my game state
and all of the snapshots through time, up
to GitHub. Now, it's very clever with the
way it deals with snapshots, it only takes
extra space to record differences, it doesn't
take like a snapshot of your entire project
for every single state that you take. So,
it's a very conservative backup like that.
It's like a differential backup, it's pretty
cool; in other words, incremental you data
people will tell me I'm sure. Some sys. admin
will come on and tell me whether it's incremental
or what. So, it's just pushing, obviously
it's taking a little while. Why is it taking
so long? Because when I did this prototyping,
I imported a lot of packages. You can see
it's sneaking it's little head here, and the
first thing that I did was import a bunch
of packages and they're quite big, they're
hundreds of megabytes. So, right now, while
I'm speaking it's pushing hundreds of megabytes
to that remote repository, but when it's finished,
you will actually be able to do the challenge
and just go and download my repository, at
that point in time. And this will server two
purposes, one you will be able to download
our repositories from any previous point in
time for any section of this course and any
future section of this course or any other
course I make. But also, as you start to use
Version Control for your games, you will be
able to say to your friends, hey check out
my game as it was here, or if you're trying
to get help, inside maybe Unity answers or
something, you can give people a link that
will allow them to download your project or
bits of your project and it's pretty cool!
Once you're under Version Control, and you understand it.it's incredibly
powerful, you won't feel right doing any project
without the help of Version Control, from
that point. So, I'm just going to wait for
this to finish pushing to GitHub. There we
go, that was good timing. And let's go back
to the website now, refresh this page, go
into Twin Stick, and here it shows me the
current state. Now, this is at the end of
the journey; there's three things I did, but
this is the current state alright, of the
prototype branch. And that's cool, because
what anybody can do now at the bottom right,
is they can download a .zip, so if you go
to a repository and you just download .zip,
your downloading the latest version. If you
want to get a version at a previous point
in time, you click into Commit, so I'll just
go back and show you, where that was here,
three commits. And then, you choose your branch,
we only have a prototype at the moment, and
then, you use this little guy here. Browse
the Repository at this point in time, and
we can go back in time, and it looks very
similar, but it's how it was back at that
commit and you just download it. So, that's
going to be your challenge now, I just want
you to go and download what I've just done.
So, go to Complete Unity Developer, find the
Twin Stick Repo, download the latest commit
from the pt branch, there's only a pt branch
so just download it basically, use that Download
Zip button, and then, open the project in
Unity and just make sure that it works. You'll
have a ball flying along a little kind of
line, it'll be very simple. OK, pause the
video and make sure that you can download
things from GitHub. Now, you don't even need
a GitHub account to do this, but if you've
got one it will work just as well. Coolio!
Welcome back! So, this is how you would do
it. I will assume you are logged into Git,
it'll be very similar whether you are or aren't.
If you want the latest commit, then you just
go back to the main repo here, or you manually
go and find the latest thing, but anyway all
you basically do is come here: CompleteUnityDeveloper/10-TwinStick,
go to the bottom right, Download Zip. Download
a Zip file of the project, which is going
to be quite big, and then, all you do is open
the .zip file. When I say open the .zip ,
of course you're having to open the scene,
the Unity scene, so you'd go into Assets,
and then, you will find a .unity file, like
this game.unity. Open that and the game will
open. I'll let you open that. It's not a game
really, it's 5 minutes of me playing around
just so that you've got something to download.
So, here it is, you would have a .zip file
like that, it would unzip itself into a folder,
and then, inside that folder you'll see something
like this. Go to Assets and then find a .unity
file, double click it, Unity will open up
like so. it may have a funny code on the end,
that's just GitHub's way of tracking this
particular snapshot, that's what that massive
commit idea is. And then Unity will take a moment
to open. The reason it takes a while to open,
it's opening in the background now, is because
we'll see in a future video how we exclude
the Library Folder, when we keep things under
Version Control. The Library Folder in Unity
is a bit this guy here and the Project Temp
Folder are like cache folders, they're things
that Unity can recreate, so I actually don't
upload them. We keep it simple, and there
it is! That's what we've got! And if you hit
play, you can probably use A and D just to
move this ball around, and I don't think it
does much else. In fact, in this particular
version we haven't even got a cube on there,
so very boring, but I just wanted to show
you that you can pick up a project at any
state using GitHub. So, that's cool! So, moving
forward it's going to be a very useful thing
to store your code in GitHub, so that if you
get in trouble you can go back, so that you
can see you're own progress, so that you can
save the state of your game, as you go. If
we look at Block Breaker here, you'll see
that here are all the videos for Blocker Breaker,
but you'll also see that if I show all the
branches that we had a lot of fun prototyping,
playing, fixing, and we will later be talking
to you about how you would use this in your
game. You would come along with a game like
this, and you would go ooh, I'm going to create
some sort of a side feature and then, what
you would do in making a game rather than
a course, is you would merge this side feature
back into your game. We never merge in the
course, because what's happening here is,
I'm doing something, doing something, doing
something, then saying ah, I need to think
ahead, so I do some prototyping, but then
of course, because you need to see the progress,
I need to go back here and start afresh. So,
this is what is different about how we use
GitHub and when you see our repositories to
how you would use it, is that we never merge
back in. All of our branches terminate like
this, because we need to go back in time and
show you the process, whereas if it was a
kind of normal piece of software, it would
look something more like this. Let me show
you a piece of like commercial software, that
I've downloaded. If I can find something,
software, here we go Subler, here you go.
So, these are merging back in here, this guy
here, so if we look down further down the
repository somebody has come along and they've
been in parallel building some side features,
and at some time they've decided to merge
this back in, and say OK, let's take everything
we've developed plus all the things we've
developed on the side and put them together.
And that's how you would normally use things,
but we don't do it in a course like that,
as I said, because it just doesn't make sense.
Once we've prototyped something, we actually
have to go back in time and show you what
we did, so making a course is very different
and leads to all of these unattached ends.
So, that's it! I hope you've got some sort
of overview of how this Version Control works.
It's massively useful and you can even later,
when you go back to Dan Reilly's blog that
I gave you that link to, you can even use
Version Control like this to host your game,
as an alternative to bitbucket, if you wanted,
but we'll talk about that later in the section.
Cool! So, good luck with GitHub, and I will
see you in the next video, where we'll show
you how to setup this software, so you can
use it yourself.