Welcome to using CrossPlatformInputManager!
In this video we'll be talking about what
is this CrossPlatformInputManager thingy.
how a Virtual control layer works. and we'll
be setting-up and reading control values.
Cool hey! By the way. how did you get on with
the Version Control stuff. with all this Source
Tree Log? So. there's three possibilities.
I guess one is you've gotten along great.
discovered a new thing and it's fantastic!
So. well done. and you will not regret it.
it will just get better and better as you
uncover it's mysteries! Another possibility
is you're already into Version Control. and
it was a complete waste of time for you. so
sorry about that. Ah. I guess another possibility
is you struggled or didn't do it. so don't
worry if you didn't. it doesn't matter. It's
peripheral to this section. but it's something
I wanted to introduce. I will show you how
I use Version Control. as we go through. you
can always go back to the beginning and watch
again when you're ready to start using it.
Maybe you need to wait until you're sold on
the idea. OK. so let's talk about Virtual
Controls. and then. actually do some coding
in Unity. That would be cool wouldn't it!
So. here's Keynote. my presentation program.
I want to show you this. it's a slide made
up of the Virtual Controller. So. imagine
four different controller types. one called
Touch. it's a touch screen on your mobile
device. Mouse and keyboard. you're very familiar
with for web. Mac or PC. Limux. etc. Gamepad
of course. you could use a Gamepad on a console.
you can use a Gamepad on a Mac or PC. I've
got a PlayStation 4 controller sitting right
next to my Mac. as we speak. and it's tethered
by Bluetooth. which is kind of fancy. An Etc.
Controller. an Etc. Controller is a very advanced
form of controller. that I can't possibly
go into here. So. all of those things could
feed into a Virtual Controller; well. they
do in terms of the CrossPlatformInputSystem.
and then. what you do is you read from the
Virtual Controller Layer. You use methods
like float to get access. which will feed
in a string like horizontal or vertical and
it gives you back a number between -1 and
+1. Or you could use the method with signature
Bool GetButton. and you would say Bool GetButton
() fire. for example. or use a virtual name.
layer of indirection in the Virtual Control
Layer. So. buttons have names like Fire. Jump.
etc. And axis have names. like Vertical. Horizontal.
etc. and they can all be renamed and you query
that layer. Now. regardless then of what control
system is in use. whether it's touch or mouse.
keyboard. etc. then. you use the same methods
in your code to query the virtual layer. so
that provides a layer of indirection. which
means that when you change platforms. you
don't need to change your code. Wicked hey!
Another thing that's cool about this is that
you can use code to drive commands into the
Virtual Control Layer. therefore you could
control your characters purely by code. Think
about replays. think about rolling demos.
hmm exciting. Alright. so let's just get this
stuff working. Fantastic! So. let's go into
Unity. I have an empty Unity project here.
just gagging for me to play with the Virtual
Control Layers. So. let's setup a really really
simple Game Space. I'm going to put a cube
in the Game Space. it's right at the origin
there. and I think what I'll do is just scale
it so it's rather large in the Z. so for now
100 Z. there you go. If you downloaded my
prototype in the early bit. then this is just
what I did. I just made a big cube. I might
double its. Y height just so it looks like
a kind of beam. you know. like a steel beam
or something. OK cool! So. there it is! Now.
let's add to that. just a... What shall we
have for now? A sphere! I'm going to plunk
a sphere on top. Now. where's on top? Well.
on top is bound to be some idealistic place.
Let's make a material! I'm going to move through
this quite quick. because you guys know this
stuff. I'm just going to call it blue. for
the moment. [Sings] Blue daba dee daba die.
[Starts Talking] OK and just anything to just
distinguish this thing from the ball. This
just looks a bit too boring. when it's all
one color. so blue. you can drag it straight
onto the thing in the scene. Now. that's blue.
Do I want it to look metallic? Yeah. I think
so why not smooth. Who cares. not very smooth.
I just want it to look reasonable. OK. so
where should the ball live if it's going to
be sitting right on there? Well. obviously
it's going to have an X depth of 0. and then.
normally what I do is I drag and see where
it starts clipping and then look at the numbers
and kind of make a rationalization of where
it should be. It should probably be at 1.5.
Now. I like things to start just off the surface.
because they can get stuck in a surface. so
there you go. There's a ball sitting there
on a beam. and this is going to be the beginning
of the essence of a 2.5D game right. So. there's
a Play Space that's 3D. in theory we could
put backdrops in. we could put all sorts of
other things in here. but then. there's a
Player that can only move in two dimensions.
Now. we'll worry about the physics of that
later. let's just get control values being
read. So. I'm just going to call the cube
Beam. and I'm going to call this sphere Ball.
Perfect! OK. let's add a script! What shall
we call it? I'm going to call it Player. By
the way. when you add a script you can just
type the name of it. as if it exists here
and then click New Script. And because it
doesn't recognize it. it'll give you the option
to attach. etc. Now. we have a messy Assets
for now. but we'll go with that for now. So.
here's an overview of the three stage process.
we need to apply. This is in your slides.
and I'll recap it at the end but you need
to Import the Package. Import the name space
number 2. and number 3 access the class. So.
let's do it. and I'm going to show you a possible
caveat that may catch you in how to solve
it. So. let's start by Import Package. CrossPlatformInput.
like that. And that brings in a bunch of stuff.
we'll take the lot. Now. there's a few things.
it puts an Editor Folder with some Editor
Scripts. and then. under Standard Assets we
also get CrossPlatformInput Scripts. and this
one here. CrossPlatformInputManager.cs. if
we just look at it. then it actually defines
a new Name Space called UnityStandardAssets.CrossPlatformInput.
The code is a bit strangely laid out here.
but you can see the methods in it. Boolean
access exists... What else have we got? GetAxis.
like I showed you before. so that it returns
a float. etc. So. we don't really need to
mess with this or even understand it. but
it does list all the methods. Of course. there's
an easier way to get to the methods. so step
1 is done. We have now imported the package.
Number 2. we need to use this command. using
Unity... Oh. it's not there! UnityStandardAssets.CrossPlatformInput.
Now. in your case it probably will be there.
when we try and do Unity standard. but if
it's not for any reason. because maybe you've
been messing around with packages. I just
want to show you this gotcha. This is how
you would fix that. Close Mono. come to your
directory that your game exists in. Now. remember
I told you that all of this stuff in the Root
and your Library and your Temp can all be
deleted. I wouldn't delete Library and Temp
right now. while Unity is open. but you can
when you've closed Unity. But what I would
do is just delete all this stuff. because
what's happened is something has gone wrong
with the Solution Cache for MonoDevelop. so
if you just delete all those files and then.
go back into Mono like that. Now. let's try
using it again. UnityStandardAssets. there
it is. so that's a useful tip. in case for
some reason your name space disappears; just
delete all the files in the Root of your Project
Folder. .CrossPlatformInput; there we go.
So. step 2 of the 3 step process is done.
And then. how do we access it? Well. we just
do the following. Well. I'm going to get you
to do that. I've started it. but it's your
turn to finish. [Laughs] So. here's the challenge
for this section or this video. I just want
you to log out Virtual Control Values. Look
up how you would use Input. you've used it
plenty in the course. so you can refresh yourself.
if you like. Just instead of using Input.
replace it with CrossPlatformInput. There's
not a huge amount of documentation on the
web about CrossPlatformInput. but wherever
you would use Input.GetAccess. for example.
you can use CrossPlatformInput. and just replace
it. Import the appropriate namespace. well
I've kind of done that for you. I just want
you to print control values to the console.
so that W. S. A. D. and maybe your Gamepad.
if you've already got one set up. print the
control values to the Console. So. go do that
now. just get printing values to the console
and I'll see you in a sec. Hey. welcome back!
So. look I hope you are doing the challenges.
even at this late stage in the course. right!
So. please no wiggling out of those. that's
really important. So. it's a bit of a mouth
full. but what we're doing is (CrossPlatformInputManager.GetAxis
and then. I'm going to go ("Horizontal");
Now. how do we know there's such a thing as
a Horizontal Axis? Well. go back to Unity
and I'll show you that code in a moment. by
the way. And if you go to Project Settings.
Input. you can see what has been defined.
Horizontal is one of them and Vertical is
another. so these are the standard ones. So.
this is the Layer of Indirection. we're calling
it ("Horizontal"); Now. I'm on a mouse and
keyboard. at the moment. because I'm on a
Mac. PC. Linux build. So. let's see what this
does. We're going to print. Axis. Horizontal.
OK. and let's just have a look on the Console.
Now. it's saying it has an unexpected symbol.
so I've done a boo boo. Where's my boo boo?
There you go. my boo boo. you can tell I've
got kids. is that I didn't close two sets
of brackets. Simple stuff. let's try again.
So. look at the Console. The reference script
on this behavior is missing. I have probably
just not attached my script. there you go.
to the Ball. Perfect! So. look at the Console.
Here we go -1 and then. you have to be clicked
in game remember. I'm just going to watch
this value at the bottom left. not bother
trying to watch the Console. just watch at
the very bottom left. So. as I hold the Left
Key. it goes from -1 to +1 and it actually
has some speed with it. and that speed is
because a setting called Gravity. which we'll
explore a little bit later on. You can go
find that Gravity setting. if you wish. it's
here under Input and then Horizontal. you
see this Gravity. That tells you how quickly
it returns to normal. so you could change
that value if you want to. and that's so that
your keyboard acts a bit more like a controller.
Imagine you let go of the stick of the controller.
it wouldn't return to center immediately.
so that's what this is simulating but anyway.
-1 +1 all very well. So. may as well go and
do the same thing for the Vertical Axis. so
I'm going to just go H: concatenate like that;
take that whole command. I may upgrade myself
from print to Debug.log. What's the difference?
There' s a lot more things you can do with
a Debug.log. it's a lot more flexible in the
long term. and it's better to get into the
habit of deciding whether you want to be logging
a warning. an exception. etc.. so. Debug.log
is a little more professional than just print.
And I'm going to go ("Vertical")); so we're
going to get the Vertical Axis. And now. let's
have a look. Now. in the next lecture I'll
show you how to use a Gamepad. so we won't
do that right now. but H and V. of course
it's coming out in two separate Console lines
but you can see from the history. not that's
working. Fantastic! So. it's pretty much as
simple as that. You can also use GetButton
of course. and again. if you refer back to
your Input Manager. then it will tell you
what buttons are already assigned. Now. you
can also allow your player to change these
things. I think I will just quickly show you
that. so I'm on a Mac. PC. Linux Stand Alone
Build; if I just build this level for now...
I'll just need to put the scene into the Build
Settings. of course. and if I just build and
run this. watch what happens. So. I'm going
to make a folder called Builds inside this.
and I'm going to call it Mac. OK. so it's
going to build a Mac version of this game.
It should be quite quick. take a little bit
longer because of the CrossPlatformInput stuff.
Standard Assets always slow down builds and
things. Look what happens! This is the actual
game running this window that's come up. Let
me quit and show you actually. it's actually
a Mac executable here. So. if I just run this
Mac app that's completely un-customized. look
I get a target resolution. which is very well
but I also get this input. so this is where.
just straight out of the box. you can help
people customize. So. the Horizontal and Vertical.
the keys. it's already mapped to the Cursor
Keys. and to D and A. and even if I used a
Gamepad this would work. So. Gamepads are
the subject of the next video. which is cool!
So for now. all that remains is for me to
show you how I use the Version Controller.
at the end of the video. Save the scene and
save the project. for which there is not a
keyboard shortcut. Over to your Version Control
System. look at the uncommitted changes. there's
loads of them. so you stage them with this
button. right there where I've go the mouse.
Stage all un-staged files. all the stuff we've
done gets added. loads of stuff. mainly because
we've imported a package. And then. what I
do here is. I actually name these things the
very same name as the video in question. which
is Using CrossPlatformInputManager. So. mine
tend to come with an actual .mp4 and a name
in the beginning. which is just fine. In this
case. mine is TS07. This is just so that they
have a sequence. This would actually look
like that. but who cares. and we commit it.
And then. that is done! The end state of the
game. for this video. is committed to the
repository. It's going to take longer than
usual because it's having to push all those
Standard Assets up to GitHub. for the first
time. but of course now. when you go over
to the GitHub website. to the Complete Unity
Developers' team page. which we can get to
via me and to Unity Developer. Twin Stick.
and Commits. In a minute. when it's finished
committing. which it has now if I refresh...
Ah now. if you don't see it. it's because
we're on the wrong branch. Now. we're talking
about Master branch. so branches are ways
of creating side features. but here you are
Using CrossPlatformInputManager.mp4. And that
is the state of the project. at the end. and
that's all pushed up to the web. So. this
is how we use the Version Control. OK. so
that's that. I shall see you in the next video.
where we'll talk about using analog Gamepads.