Hey! Hey! Using an analog game-pad. brackets
optional! So. in this video. we'll be talking
about using game-pad input. setting up a PS4
controller on a Mac. Yeah! Yeah! I'm a Mac
guy. I'm sorry. Using an Xbox controller on
a PC. I'm not going to be showing you that.
but I believe it's incredibly simple on a
PC. to get an Xbox controller working. and
in case you haven't got a game-pad. we'll
talk a little bit more about the Gravity setting.
so that you can simulate having a game-pad.
They're pretty cheap. but in different countries
then. you know maybe it's not cheap to spend
10 to 15 dollars on a game-pad.. I appreciate
that. so you don't have to have a game-pad.
to take this section. because we won't be
deploying to Console. so you're not kind of
forced to have a game-pad. by any means. You
can always use a keyboard! So. let's just
take a look. How do you get this working?
Firstly. the game-pad needs to be working
at a system level. so on a Mac. that basically
means. with example. a PS4 game-pad that you
go to Bluetooth. you pair your wireless controller
with it. Now. how do you get a PS4 controller
into Pairing Mode? You hold down the PlayStation
Button and the Share Button. until it goes
into Pairing Mode. You pair it by Bluetooth.
and actually it'll just work. pretty much.
So. once it's connected and it's confirmed
as connected here and you're light is on.
on your controller. then it should just work.
Now. if it doesn't work. like this. nothing
coming out in my Console. then you just need
to quite Unity and reopen it. because actually.
Unity will typically not notice that you have
a controller installed. unless it was there
when Unity opened. So. I'm just reopening
Unity now. and then. if I play the game. make
sure you're clicked into the Game Window.
and then. here you go. Now. let's watch this
Console more carefully. I'll clear it. My
left stick is going to the left now. and I'm
getting -1. halfway left I get -1/2. centralized
I get nearly 0. so. sue me it's just a round
0. In fact. every time you let go of the stick.
it'll settle on something different. Here
it's settled on 0.002. now 0.01. so it's not
going to be precise. and then. vertically
the same thing. OK. so you get numbers between
-1 and 1. depending on your stick position.
OK. that's all very well. so how about if
you don't have a game-pad. Well. regardless
you want to customize the input for a player
on mouse and keyboard. So. go to Project Settings
and Input. and let's just take a look at all
of these different things here. that you can
get to control for each of the 18 inputs.
So. there's an array of 18 things. Horizontal.
Vertical. Fire. etc. I'm going to look at
Horizontal for now. and it's basically the
same for the rest. apart from buttons are
simplified. but basically they're very similar.
So. this thing is called Horizontal. it doesn't
have a descriptive name. we could give it
a descriptive name. What does that mean? Well.
here is Unity's doc here. just search for
Input Manager on Google. and it'll go through
and explain. So. it's a detailed definition
that's displayed in the Game Launcher. you
know that launcher I showed you in the previous
video. the descriptive negative name. So.
that's for the negative button. the button
that does the reverse of what we're asking
it to do. and then. the positive button. is
the... So. let me put this a different way.
Negative and Horizontal is left and positive
is right. if that makes sense. and in Vertical
of course negative would be up and positive
would be down. etc.. or the other way around.
you get the idea. So. you can also have alternative
buttons. so you can either use the Left or
the Right Arrow. or you can us the A or the
D Key. Now. Gravity. what is Gravity all about?
It's actually the number of inths of a second
that the control takes to read the center. so
this is a third of a second. It could be a
1/15 of a second. if you put 15. it could
a oneth of a second. if you put 1. let me
show you. So. if we leave it at the default
and we hold the key off to the side... I'm
actually going to make you focus just at the
very bottom left here. If I hold it to one
side and get -1-ish. and then. when I let
go it should take a 1/3 of a second to go
back and it does. about a 1/3. If I set this
to 1. not Sensitivity. Gravity to 1. then
it will take about 1 second. 1.000 and it
gets to about 0. OK. let's prove this is right.
by setting it to 0.1. and it should take 10
seconds now. Off to the side. 1.000. 2.000.
3.000. 4. you get the idea. OK. and then.
it moves down in quite small steps. which
means that if you set your Gravity too high.
a number. so I want it to go back to the center
in a 1/20 of a second. watch what happens
now. I go to -1. I let go and it ends up a
0.3. because it's got so few time steps. it
has to reduce the value. so much in each time
step that we get a rounding problem. depending
on your current frame rate. So. avoid graveties
that are large like that. and 3 is a sensible
Gravity that is probably about as long as
it takes a controller's stick to return to
center. which is probably why Unity would
have used it. Alright. so that's what Gravity
is. I'm going to leave it at 3. Dead is Dead
Zone. that's saying when you're on a controller.
how much of the stick movement do we ignore?
So. that's that central Dead Zone. Sensitivity
has to do with the scaling of the way the
stick works. again. if you're not sure. look
in here. OK. so when I say the stick. the
Virtual Stick. it's only for virtual input.
The same with Gravity. only for mouse and
keyboard. OK. the same with the Sensitivity.
so the Sensitivity is like you've got a stronger
stick. so it just moves up faster. basically
as a simple way of looking at Sensitivity.
and Gravity is how fast the figure moves back
down. So. if you want it to take 10 seconds
to move up to Maximum and 10 seconds to move
down. then you set 0.1 and 0.1 and look at
how long it's taking. Alright. so this is
the easy way to think of it; 1 divided by
this number tells you how many seconds it
will take to get to full control displacement.
OK. so you might want it to go to full control
displacement. on the way up. quicker. you
know in 1 second. for example. or in a 1/10
of a second. but we may end up with the same
rounding problem here. You see we're only
getting to a Maximum of 0.83. that's the disadvantage.
because of a rounding issue. Not very good
really. to be honest. but something that can
combat that is Snap. So. what Snap does. is
it means if you hold down both directions.
like I'm holding down Right now. if I then.
hold down Left at the same time as Right.
what it'll do is it'll Snap back to 0. in
theory. but again. it's not super reliable
but that's the idea of it. You can invert
the axis. you can change it's type. and we'll
look at all that later. if need to. OK. so
we've had a good overview of how this works.
Remember that any changes you make here. when
you're in Play Mode. when you come out of
Play Mode. then. they are likely to be lost.
So. I said 0.1 of the Gravity. I come out
of Play Mode and of course it's lost. So.
that's your normal gotcha. that's why we use
a Play Mode Tint. OK. so there you go. Fantastic!
We understand more about Gravity and controllers
now. and in the next video we will look at
responding to the platform. We'll start to
think about creating a menu system that depends
on the platform in use. That'll be fun! See
you soon!