Hello hello hello and welcome back! We're
going to be talking about using the RollerBall
prefab! We will import the Character's Standard
Asset Pack, again! We'll use the RollerBall
prefab, and explore how it works basically!
And then, after this lecture, we've got a
treat for you! We're going to start talking
about Replay Mechanics. OK, so let's get into
the Roller Ball. Here we go! Let's Import
the Standard Asset Pack for the characters.
Now, we've used this before, a couple of times.
We've used it twice in Zombie Runner, actually
once for the AI Third Person Character Controller
and once for the First Person Character Controller.
Now, we're going to use another character
controller, which is a RollerBall, so here
it comes, bloating out our Unity project.
By the way, the extra information that comes
in when you import all this stuff, does not
get built into a build, like a Web Build or
a Mac or PC Build, unless you specifically
use those items. So, it may bloat your project,
but it doesn't bloat your final build. Alright,
so I'm going to get rid of my old ball. Just
before you delete something like that, especially
when it's not a prefab, just have a look at
the Inspector, make sure it hasn't got anything
clever on it. It's got a script, that won't
go. So, that's all good, let's just zap it.
And then, under Standard Assets, Characters,
RollerBall here, you have a RollerBall prefab.
Let's stick that in the scene. Fantastic!
Now, what I'm going to do with this beam is
just drop it down a little bit, I think. How
wide is it? It's too high. Nah, I that's OK,
no I'll leave it there. I'll leave it there.
I'm going to put the RollerBall right on top
of it. What happens if I put the RollerBall
at 0, 0, 0? Well, it sits there. I would rather
the floor was at 0, so I'm going to move,
I am going to move the beam down by -1.5.
There you go, so all we've done is move the
beam down to -1.5 and popped the RollerBall
at the origin. So, the RollerBall is quite
fun, It has like a tennis ball kind of relief
to it. It actually has three dimensionality
to it, but it also has a lot of stuff on it.
Take a look at this RollerBall. It has a Mesh
Filter and a Renderer, and a Collider and
a Rigidbody, but it also has a Ball Script
and a Ball User Control Script. And actually,
it's all cross platform ready anyway, which
is fantastic! So, there's our RollerBall.
How's our camera looking? Not so clever, so
I'm going to align the Main Camera like that.
You select the Main Camera, Game Object, Align
with View, and then, it will look a bit like
the Scene View, very like the Scene View.
So, now if I play the game and use the arrow
keys, ah hah! Now, first thing that happens
using either the Cursor Keys or W, S, A, D
or even using the your Control Pad, is that
the ball falls off the side, so the first
thing I want to show you here is, how do we
constrain an object's movement to 2D. Well,
the Physics Engine has a very useful facility
for this, and this is at the heart of making
a 2 and a half D game, in a way, is that we
don't want the thing moving in X, we want
it to be frozen in X. So, click on your RollerBall
and then, come along to Constraints Freeze
Position in X, like that. Now, let's try it.
Play the game and use your Cursor Left and
Right Keys. Fantastic! Now, if you notice
if you hit the Space Key or whatever the currently
assigned jump key is, it goes far too high,
so lets turn the Jump Power down to say 2
or 1 even. Fantastic! So, you get the idea!
We have a RollerBall prefab, it does quite
a lot for us and it's kind of fun. I'm also
going to turn up my motion power or my Movement
Power to say 10, just so it's a little more
responsive, you could also make it lighter,
that could be another way. See it's got friction
and everything. Wicked isn't it! OK, I quite
like it! So, that's that! Now, you have of
course been making modifications to this instant
of a prefab, that came from the Character
Pack. I don't like that, let's tidy up our
organization here, and I'm not going to do
the standard boring thing of making scripts
folders and all the rest of it, because look
we can use this filter tool here. If I want
to see all my scripts, I can just click there,
and it will show me all the scripts across
all folder. So, I'm not going to duplicate
that in my folder structure, for this project.
I'm going to make a different folder structure,
I'm going to have a Player Folder and put
the Player Script in it, for example. OK,
and then, we will see later on what we do,
but maybe Beams, maybe have a folder for Beams,
if we're going to call all these blue things
beams, and then the blue material goes in
there and the beam ought to be prefabbed.
Drag it down here to prefab it and pop it
in Beams. We also ought to be re-prefabbing
this RollberBall, so we've got our own prefab.
So, let's drag that down. There we go, RollerBall,
into Player, so that's now attached to a different
prefab; this guy here independent of the Standard
Asset Pack. We have the script in there, it's
all looking better. Do we want our Scenes
Folder? Well... one folder no, one scene no,
Editor yes, we need to leave that as it is,
it's a special reserved folder name. Standard
Assets I'm going to leave it as it is OK.
So, I'm just going to organize things a little
differently for this game. So, what I want
you to do now is just to explore all the control
options, in this thing. I want you to go into
the scripts, into say this Bool Script, and
take a look and see how much of it you understand
how much you don't understand, as to how the
bool script works. Also, have a look at the
Bool User Control Script in here, again see
what makes sense to you, what doesn't. OK,
and then, anything that you discover or any
questions that you've got, I want you to share
them in the discussions. So, basically tune
the RollerBall for your 2.5D game. Try out
all the controls, look at the scripts, see
if you can modify them to do something a little
different, and ask any questions you may have
in the discussions. So, I really want you
to stop now and use everything you've learned
in this section, so far to put together something
a little unique. I want you to start being
a bit more creative, about what this game
is going to look like. OK, fantastic! I'll
see you in a moment!