Hey guys welcome back! We're going to talk
about classes vs. struct, which is short for
structure, in C#. So firstly, for storing
these key frames, these positions of our Game
Objects, I'm going to tell you why we're not
using Unity's Keyframe struct. We'll be comparing
classes and structures as options briefly,
and then, making our own MyKeyframe struct.
OK, so what is this Unity KeyFrame struct
thing? Look at it in the docs, Keyframe struct
in Unity Engine. So, Unity Engine is the name
space, and we always have Unity Engine in
all our scripts. Remember at the top of the
script... Let me show you briefly. We have
in whatever script we're in, if I just look
for scripts here, as a search, find any old
script, bring it down into the screen; you'll
see that everything has using Unity Engine.
So, that's what that bit means. It's in the
Unity Engine name space and it says struct.
Now, what's a struct? Well, it's something
a bit like a class, but it is stored as a
value rather than a reference. So, classes
are stored as references, so they have to
point to look off somewhere else, in order
to find the actual values, where structs are
value types. And a Vector3 for example, is
a struct. So, this Keyframe thing has four
values in it. It has an in tangent and out
tangent. What are they? Well, they are floats.
And then, a time and a value. Now, this is
to do with the Animator. This is saying that
at a particular time I want, say the X component
of the transform or something to do with the
rotation to be a particular value, and optionally
I want to determine the in and the out tangents
inside the Animator. So, you have in the Animator
an option when you're laying down key frames.
I won't show you now, but you have an option
to drag little handles, which allow you to
determine the smoothness of the curve, and
that's what that Keyframe in and out tangent
business is. OK, it's like they're called
Bezier Curves, but we don't need all this
basically. We don't need all those things,
and also, in our code we only want a single
entity per frame, for it to store a position
and rotation. We don't want to have to set
in X, Y, Z for position X, Y, Z for rotation.
So, we're going to make our won structure,
alright. And then, it's a question of how
we're going to do that and how that's going
to look. So, we've had a look at why we're
not using Unity's Keyframe or the Animator.
We could use the Animator for all this, but
it's just slower and cumbersome. Classes are
stored as references; structs are stored as
values. The impact in this particular use
case is not very much, they both perform very
similarly, and we'll be creating our own MyKeyframe
struct. So, let's get into some code now,
and start putting this together. So, here
we have our player or our roller ball. I think
I'm going to rename it Player, so go ahead
and rename your roller ball to Player. Fantastic!
And then, what I'm going to do is, I'm going
to create myself a new script here, and I'm
just going to call it Replay. I'm going to
attach that Replay Script to the Player. Let's
have a look, it's complaining about something.
Let's have a look at what it's named it, replay.
So, maybe Replay is a reserved word? That's
possible let's try MyReplay, for now and save
that. Now, let's try adding that to the Player.
Oops! Fantastic! So, I've added it to the
beam by mistake, but crucially we just simply
have a My Replay Script on the ball on the
Player. OK, let's go into this and take a
look. So, we want to make our own new class.
Now, to make our own class, you define it
down here public class... and we did this
in Bowl Master or maybe we didn't? I certainly
considered it. public class MyKeyFrame () OK, and it doesn't
need to inherit from anything. So, up here
in all of your scripts, you say your script
name, colon, which means it inherits from
MonoBehavior. It means it picks up, it's a
child of MonoBehavior and it picks up a lot
of behavior from MonoBehavior. We don't need
that for this simple thing, we're just going
to say public class MyKeyFrame. And then,
what I want you to do, is I want you to just
try and define this class for me, as a challenge.
You may need to go away and do some Google-ing,
but at this stage in the course, you need
to learn to find things out for yourself.
So, in the Replay.cs script there's a helper
class. I've already shown you where to put
it. Define it as a class not a struct, for
now. Try and provide a constructor as well,
so you can say from the outside from the main
class, keyFrame = new key frame passing in
a time as a float, a position as a Vecto3,
and a rotation as a Quaternion. So, see if
you can do that, so that somewhere else in
your code you can say, oh I want to make a
new key frame and it just works. Have a go!
Go on be brave, look up constructors C#, and
making my own frame in Unity, and beware of
the difference between mono, which is a open
source version of C# designed for use with
Unity and C# itself. It may make a difference
and just have a look. Go on look at the docs.
OK, look if you can't do this one it's fine.
It's for bonus marks anyway, so look. Welcome
back! Let's show you how to define your own
class now, and we start off just with some
public variables. We want a public float framtTime;
OK, which is going to be the time at which
we're storing this event, this state of say
the Player. We want public 3 Vector 3 position;
And a public Quaternion, we still don't know
what Quaternions do, but we know they store
rotation. rotation; Fantastic! So, that's
fine, that's the a start, but what we can't
do yet is say MyKeyFrame I don't know testKey
= new MyKeyFrame and then try and give it
like (1.0f as a float, followed by a Vector3.up
followed by Quaternion.identity); Now, that
should be valid, but look what happens when
we try and compile this. MyKeyFrame does not
contain a constructor that takes three arguments,
so the way you make a constructor is you make
a method with the same name as the class,
MyKeyFrame. Now, we just say (float aframe
or aTime, will do. Vector3 I'm just using
a because it wants to be different to these
guys up here, so I'm just putting a in front.
It takes in aPosition, and aRotation) OK.
And then, all this very simply does is say
that frameTime = aTime; and I think you can
guess the rest. position = aPosition; and
rotation = aRotation; Now, what that does
for us, is when we now build this code, up
here I can make myself a new key frame, and
it will have a time or whatever this float
is, Vector3.up and Quaternion.identity, i.e.
no rotation and it works. So, this is the
constructor, so I make myself a new key frame
here. Alright, that's fantastic! So, well
done, if you got that far! Now, how about
if we wanted it to be a struct rather than
a class. How difficult is it to change it?
Well, have a look, struct build, works exactly
the same. OK, so you can just change class
for struct there, and it will work exactly
the same. And this is value type, rather than
stored as a reference, which of course is
very wasteful if lots of different things
are creating the same values, you want all
of those things to point off to the same instance
in memory, but in this case, we are OK to
use a struct, because we are just storing
values; we are using this as a structure.
So, hopefully that makes sense. I'm going
to get rid of that line there, now that we
know how it works. We have now our key frame
structure set up, ready to store things. So,
that's fantastic! In the next video we'll
actually get the Recording System going and
make sure that it works.