Welcome back! After a reasonable amount of
thought and planning, we're ready to start
creating a ReplaySystem. So, we will give
you an overview of our ReplaySystem code,
and then, we'll be implementing a ring buffer
for the frames, and testing and recording
our Playback. So, let's just get on with it.
MyReplay now, MyReplay is a weird name.
I'm actually going to rename it ReplaySystem.
Now, remember you can use Command or Control
R to rename a class, and that will not only
rename the class up here, but of course it
will rename, as we know down here, the actual
script. Now, I'm going to put this on the
Player, but also to prove that this is going
to work for more than one object, well let's
put another cube down here, for example. And
let's find out where that guy has gone,
he's kind of disappeared. [Laughs] I'm going to
reset his transform and go look at him. Hey,
there he is, and then, move him out of the
way. Fantastic! Now, I'm going to add a Rigidbody
to this cube and make it really lite. Now,
let's just test an interaction with it, so
I just want to see that there's something
else in the scene. OK, that's cool! That's
fine! Now, this ReplaySystem is going to get
slow, if we start putting our ReplaySystem
code on lots and lots of items, but for now,
I'm OK with it. So, I have a missing script.
We want to end up, with on your player, just
a ReplaySystem script on the player, but also
a ReplaySystem script on the cube. We want
this replay to work for both the Player and
the cube, the two things that currently move
in this game. OK. Fantastic! Cool! So, let's
go in and do the coding. So, if you've got
Code Folding turned on, and it's in a slightly
different place on a PC, but on a Mac it's
MonoDevelop, Preferences, just find your preferences,
TextEditor, General, Enable Code Folding here.
Then, you can just collapse down the key frame
definition, we don't need that anymore. We
have already defined it, so we don't have
to keep looking at it, necessarily. OK, so
what are we going to need in here?
Well, we're going to need a private constant integer buffer size, or bufferFrames, to be more specific,
and let's make it 100 frames to start with.
OK, so we're going to store 100 frames. Now,
why private? Because we don't need access
from the outside. Why const? A couple of reasons,
firstly wherever you can use a constant, instead
of a variable, do it, it's good practice,
and secondly, look the next thing we're going
to need here, is we're going to need an array,
a private array of my key frames, so that's
the definition of an array; I'm going to call it keyFrames,
but look what we can do if we've
had a constant for the buffer size. Is a
new array of my key frames, but how big? [bufferFrames]; big. OK, and we can use that. If this was
a variable, if we didn't have constant and
we tried to compile this watch. Initializer
cannot reference a non-static field, because
at the time of compiling, it doesn't know
what bufferFrames is, make it constant and
it does. Hmm, cunning as a box of frogs, aye.
No, that's funny as a box of frogs. Ah well,
anyway, so what else are we going to need
access to? Well, we're going to need to be
able to get the Rigidbody off the thing, so
that we can make it Kinematic and non Kinematic
right, so when we are in Record Mode, then
we're going to want the Player and the cube
to be Non-Kinematic, but in Playback Mode
we're going to want them to be Kinematic,
so the Physics Engine isn't kicking in.
So, getrigidbody, now we do this so often I've made myself a keyboard shortcut. It does private
Rigidbody rigidBody; and then in Start it
goes and finds it. Alright, so that's all
I was doing there, I was cheating with a keyboard
shortcut, but that's all you need to do is
you define Rigidbody and then, you go find
it in the Start. This is new to Unity 5 of
course, that's probably all we need right
now. So, now let's think about recording the
frames. I'm going to do it inside Update to
start with. Alright, so how are we going to
do that? Well, let's start with thinking about
what the frame number is going to be. The
frame number, some integer that we're going
to store into, is = Time.frameCount What is that?
That's the number of total frames, that
have passed since the game started. Yeah,
modded with, remember we said a couple of lectures
ago, the size of the buffer, which is bufferFrames;
So, this frame number will just keep. Well,
let's print it and see print (frame); It'll
just keep looping around between 0 and 100.
Let's try it. Watch down here, bottom left.
Yeah, it's just going to go around and around
0 to 100, because the remainder between
the actual frame now, which will just keep going
up and up and up into the thousands, modular
with bufferFrames tells you the remainder,
when you do these divisions, and then that
gives you what you want. Cool! So, this is
the frame we actually want to store at, which
is pretty cool. So, I'm now just going to
say print ("Writing frame " + frame); just
so we know what that log entry is all about.
Fine. Now, how are we going to write it? Well,
good question. What we need also to know is,
what are we going to store as a time? It's
all hardly worth creating, but I'm going to
do it just for clarity. float time = Time.time;
We're going to store the time, since the game
started. Alright, so we're going to have
a frame number and a time since the game started.
So, what do we do each frame? Well, we say
keyFrames at frame frame. Remember, that's
going to keep going around and around in circles
from 0 to 100, so we'll never store more than
100 frames, which is good, because we've only
got an array of size 100, so we've got a limited
amount of memory taken up. Here's a new KeyFrame,
or new MyKeyFrame, not KeyFrame. KeyFrame
is the Unity built in one that we discussed earlier,
so we want a MyKeyFrame, which is
also a struct, you see. By the way, you see
how they have a summary here, we didn't put
a summary on MyKeyFrame; we could, three forward
slashes, and then, we can say "A structure
for storing time, rotation and position" or
position and rotation. OK now, if I say = new
MyKeyFrame, you see I have a summary. Look
how much alike MyKeyFrame looks to the Unity
one now, they look identical, with a different
summary. Pretty cool aye! So, we're making real
kind of code here. So, we're going to make
a new MyKeyFrame at time time, which is why I
said it was hardly worth doing, with position
transform small t. Oh, it won't let me do
a small t. Why is that? Well, good question,
let's have a look down... Something is broken
about our class, frameTime is in red, frameTime
is not commented, hmm weird? OK, something
went wrong, when we put this triple thing in,
so how are we going to sort that out?
Something is wrong between here and here.
Let's just delete everything between there
and there, and return again. Ah, that's better!
OK, so there was something wrong in the white
space between here and here. I'll do the same
for the next line, just in case, and maybe
even this. Something hanging on the end of
these lines or something like that. Alright
that's fine. So, that's all tidied up, that
works, and now hopefully I can go transform,
I can with a small t dot position, and transform,
oh with a small t again please. Hmm? Maybe
I need to rebuild, before it realizes that
I should be able to accept a small transform.
I do, transform.rotation); So, weird
sort of stuff you may come across. OK fantastic!
So, we are creating now our key frame, into
frame number frame, and there it goes. That's
wicked! Let's see if it's working.
How are we going to know if it's working? Well, good
question. We're just going to run and see
if we get any errors, for a start. It says
it's writing these frames. Cool! That's pretty
good! So, if it's really writing the frames,
then we should be able to go into some sort of
Playback Mode and see those frames coming
back out. So, how are we going to do this?
Well, we're going to need to think about how
we're going to trigger into and out of a
Playback Mode. So, let's start by doing a
little refactoring, and then, I think I'll
do the management of playback and recording,
in a separate video. So, I'm going to highlight
all that code and refactor it out, as Record
(); as simple as that, which is just Record
Mode. And I also am going to want a Playback
method, so let's make a Playback method. What
are we going to do, when we playback? Well,
we're going to do something like this. We're
going to say rigidBody.isKinematic = true;
Actually, we want to also make on Record the
Kinematic not true. Yeah, so we want the Physics
Engine to move it, while we're recording,
and we want to move it ourselves when we're
playing back. OK, on playback, what's the
frame number going to be? Well, it's going
to be the same sort of thing, it's going to
be exactly the same actually. It's going to
be Time.frameCount, not just with buffer frames.
So, we're just going to go around exactly
the same loop, when we playback. You'll see
that, that will work; we'll start in the right
place, it'll all just work. How do you
get to that yourself, if you weren't just
following me? Well, just experiment, just
try and see how this works. If you think about
it, if you were on frame 9, then here when
you stored the last thing, then you went to
Playback Mode, you'd end up back on frame
0, in my example from a couple of lectures
ago. So, you'd start playing back in exactly
the right place, so it's fine, it does work.
Let's print out the fact we're ("Reading frame
" + the frame number. And then, what we do
there is we simply say transform.position
= keyFrames at frame number frame .position.
And the rotation, you can do yourself. Go
ahead, pause the video, and recall the rotation
from the appropriate member of the keyFrame
array. Go for that now. Pause the video and
recall the rotation. OK, so it's transform.rotation
= keyFrames at frame frame .rotation. Now,
these are Quaternions flying around, but we
don't care, they should work. So, we set and
we release Kinematic, that's absolutely fantastic!
So, all we need now is a way of getting into
and out of Playback Mode. So, we're going
to do that, by having a GameManager, that
determines whether we're in Playback Mode
or not, and I'll do that in the next video.
So, well done getting this far! Hopefully
you've followed what's going on there. You
only had a very minor challenge in this video,
which was to write this line, but in the next
video I'll set you up for a nice challenge,
where you sort the GameManager out and reference
it in here. So, we're good to go! Fantastic!
It's coming together!