Welcome back guys! In this video, we're going
to be building a GameManager. So, we'll make
a simple GameManager, use it to keep track
of whether we're in recording or playback
state, wire it into the ReplaySystem that
we just made, and then, test the playback.
So, it's a series of challenges for you, really,
to make up for the micro-challenge, in the
last video. You've got two in this one. Firstly,
I want you to create an empty GameObject called
GameManager, attach the GameManager script
to it, have it keep track of a Boolean called recording,
and while holding down the "Fire1"
button, as defined by the Cross Platform Input Manager,
I want you to be in Playback Mode,
i.e. recording is false, otherwise when we're
not holding down any special keys, we just
want the normal game play, so recording becomes
true, in normal game play. Alright, so go
ahead, pause the video, and have a go at
that now! Welcome back! So, let's make ourselves
a GameManager! It's fairly easy, you're going
to create an empty object; I'm going to call
it Game, if I can type, Manager. I'm actually
going to move this up to 100 Y, I want it
out of the way. You don't have to put these
things at the Origin, if you don't want to
see their transforms, when you click on them.
Fantastic! Let's make a new script. GameManager,
OK. Game Managers come with a slightly different
icon, it comes with a little cog, because
it's quite a common script name, is GameManager.
Alright, so there it is. Let's go into our
GameManager and take a look and see what we're
going to do with it. Fantastic! So firstly,
it needs a member variable. It's going to
be a public, because we want to be able to
see it from the outside, Boolean called recording,
and in normal case it's true, i.e. we're just
playing the game. We don't need a Start method,
I don't think, but in the Update, we're just
going to simply look at the, oops not
the off mesh link. if (Cross platform input manager...
Where has it gone? Well, of course you need
to import this name space, using UnityStandardAssets.CrossPlatformInput;
Ah Now, we've got a chance of it working,
using (CrossPlatformInputManager.GetButton...
Now, GetButtonDown, just when it goes down,
or Button? Now, we want a persistent state,
so you GetButton, call ("Fire1") whatever
we've defined that to be, so when the ("Fire1")
button is held down, recording = false;
So, we're not recording, when we're holding the
button down, we're playing back. You could
have used playback, it doesn't matter, either
way as a Boolean, but I'm using recording.
Otherwise, recording = true; so by default
recording is true. Fantastic! So now, that's
pretty simple right. Shall we just check it
works. There's the GameManager, should have
a public recording Bool there, click play.
Oh, Control is the button for ("Fire1")
by default, in this Mac and PC, but when I hold
down Control, this guy disappears. When I
let go of Control, it comes back. Alright,
so Control key on my keyboard is doing that.
Fine! So now, the second challenge is, I want
you to wire this into the Replay.. It's not
Replay.cs actually is it, it's ReplaySystem.cs,
so I want you to wire this into ReplaySystem.cs.
Get your ReplaySystem.cs reading this state,
we just defined, ensure "Fire1" goes into
playback, and then, celebrate, if it all works!
[Laughs] OK, go ahead and work on your ReplaySystem
now, to reference that variable in the GameManager.
Wicked! OK so, you should be fairly used to
wiring scripts together, by now, so let's
go into the ReplaySystem and see how we're going
to do this. We're going to make a private
GameManager. We want to start doing things
without dragging them into the Inspector,
unless it's specifically something that our
designer can choose, without breaking the
game, whether it works on object A or B, or
whether he drags A or B in. If it's something
the designer doesn't want to be making a choice
about, don't drag it any more, let's just
start using private. So, how are we going
to find it? manager = GameObject.FindObjectOfType
should do the job, and there should only
be one GameManager. So, there we go we've got a GameManager stored in this manager reference
here. So, all we need to do here really is
just say, if (manager.recording By the way,
you might be tempted to use a static or something horrible, why bother, why bother, why not just find
the manager. Make the link between the manager
and the ReplaySystem explicit. If you used
a static, over in the GameManager, then you
wouldn't know what was reading it. You'd have
no check on what's reading it, whereas here,
we know if we search through our code for
the things that find GameManager, for example
or just for the word GameManager, we would
know there was a reference in here, this is
much safer. OK and if we're not in recording,
then, what are we doing? Well, we're playing
back, so or else PlayBack (); Now, let's see
if it works. It may just work if we've got
our code down here right. We may need to tweak
some stuff, let's see what happens. [Sings]
Skippity beepy dee... So, move it around,
hit the cube, hold down Control. Ah look!
Awesome! And all the time I hold Control,
it loops the PlayBack. That's pretty cool
isn't it! Now, we can change the PlayBack
time, by going into our ReplaySystem, because
it's a property of the ReplaySystem, and
I may go to 1,000 frames, and then, let's see
what happens. [Sings] Skippity beepy dee skippity
beepy do. Back and forth, Spacebar to jump,
a bit of friction, boing! Here we go, hold down Control,
and now, the reason I'm not
seeing anything yet is, because it's such a
long PlayBack term, that we haven't even finished
a single right loop yet, so it's still reading.
There you go! And then when it gets all the way
around, OK. So, that's something we're going
to need to sort out. We need to sort out the
idea that, actually if it hasn't even done
a complete right loop yet, how is it going
to know to go back to the first frame?
So, where's this problem? It's somewhere around
here, about these key frame numbers here and here.
So, we're going to somehow need to specify
a starting frame, when we hit that button,
when we hit Playback, we need to know, well
where do I need to be going back to. So, rather
than in Playback reading from Time.frameCount,
it needs to read from some start frame, possibly
some start frame that's been parsed in, or
something like that. So, let's have a think
about how you're going to do that. Pause the
video for a second. Think about how you're
going to fix this, so that even if we haven't
recorded a full Playback loop, i.e. we haven't
filled up 1,000 frames yet, that it works.
Let me just show you that, that's the problem.
If we go down to just a 10 frame loop, then
of course, we go through 10 frames so quickly it's ridiculous.
So, if I do Playback it's
just tiny, right, just 10 frames, and we don't
have a problem, but if we put it up to 1,000
and start recording and watch the frame number
at the bottom left in the Console, at frame
100 and something I start playing back. Well, we're
still waiting for this to go around
the loop, but we need to go back to the start
now alright, if that makes sense. So, how
are we going to do that? Pause the video and
have a think about how you're going to do
that.