Hey guys! So. you can't get rid of me that easily. I have
decided to do a little bit more in this section. because I want to teach you some
new things. So. somebody quite rightly pointed
out that there is no second stick in this game right now. so it's not really
a Twin Stick game. So. this is what we're going to do in this
video. We're going to end up in a situation where we can not only
control the ball like this. but we can also
pan the camera around like so. and also vertically.
Alright. so that's what we're going to be doing. The way that we're going to do that
is we are simply going to
read from the second and third... Sorry. the
third and the fourth joystick axis.
import and explore a Selfie Stick Prefab I've
made for you guys in Blender. write some code to make the camera track
the player. and then. write some code to make the right stick
orbit the camera around. actually do that movement.
And we'll make sure it all works. so let's dive in and
do that. So. let's get this done! I'm going to go through this quite
quickly. at least the bits that you've seen before. So. the Project Settings.
Input. At the moment. we don't have the
right stick setup. so you will be in a situation where
you have 18 elements in your Axes Array.
and we need to take this up to 20. So. if you change that to 20.
you get room for a couple more. In my case. they both
come out as Cancel. but we're going to call them something different.
So. I'm going to describe the first one as right.
as in right stick.
Horiz. so as in the Right Stick Horizontal
Axis. Now. I've got my game controller connected right now.
Remember that if it's not connected and paired by a Bluetooth. or
however you've got it connected when you start Unity. you won't be able to see it.
so just bear that in mind. Alright. so I don't need any buttons. so I'm going to hit
the buttons away. and for gravity and dead zones. I'm going to refer
back to see what the other sticks
have had. So. these horizontal and vertical axis
historically have had a Gravity of 3. a Dead
Zone of 0.01. Let's just make sure quickly that's working OK.
So. that feels OK. so I'm going
to go with that 3.001 and 3 for
Gravity. Dead Zone. and Sensitivity. So. let's just do
that down for this new axis.
Fantastic! Now. it's a keyboard or mouse. you may as well just change it
to Joystick. because it's going to be a Joystick Axis.
Now. which axis is it? Well. it's going to be the third axis.
probably for the righr horizontal. Now. if we're not sure. we're going to just test it
by writing to the log. so I'm going to assume it's the third
axis. for the moment. And I'm just going to now write a
scritp. that's going to try and verify this. So. I'm going to make a new folder
called Camera. because in this project. we're orgnizing
things by game entity. And I'm going to make a
script that is attached to
the camera for now. and I'm just going to call it
CameraPan.
OK. you can Create and Add that script. Now. what
I want to do. I just need any script in a folder and
attached to the GameObject. that I can use to log to the
Console. So. against the camera. we now have this
CameraPan Script. Let's take a look and see if we can work out which axis
we're talking about. So.
we're actually going to use a different method later. LateUpdate. but for now. I just want
to get printing and make sure that I've found the right axis.
So. print and I'm just going to say right horiz
to remind myself of what I'm printing. Input
dot oops GetAxis. Now. I'm going to challenge you in a moment.
to do this yourself. and I'm going to use the name
that I put in. which is RHoriz.
for Right Horizontal Stick. And let's just
see if that logs out properly. saving the scripts.
Let me close the Solution. Back into Unity.
let's play. Now first. before you just make sure the left
stick works. i.e. that you're connect to your thing. to your
gamepad. and then now. look at the Console. Right Horiz. now that's
-1. 0. +1. Good! So. our Horiz
works. That is fantastic news! That is progress!
So. here's a pretty simple challenge for you. I think you can guess what this one
is going to be. Just add the vertical axis now; get the vertical axis
logging to the Console. So. go ahead. pause the video. sort
the vertical axis out for yourself. to make sure you've understood what I've done.
Cool! Welcome back! So. I think that getting this vertical
axis working is pretty simple right. I'm going to do a cut and paste
of the horizontal axis. I'm going to call it
RVert.
And same here. and then. over
in the Input Manager of Unity.
Edit Project Settings. Input.
we're going to go down. and under our Horiz we're
just going to change the next one to RVert.
And then. go for the same settings 3 Gravity.
Dead Zone. and Sensitivity. same as the one above.
Just so that it's a Joystick Axis. we don't need a mouse
button or button in this case. and let's just test. So.
left and right gives RHoriz figures. and then. up and down
isn't giving any RVert figures.
So. if that's the case for you. a few things
to check. Check your script is saved.
which it does appear to be. Make sure that you've spelled it all right.
RVert. it's worth copying and pasting that
into here. Check the
settings against the Horizontal Axis and make sure they're basically
exactly the same. and this is the problem. it is the
axis. Instead of the X Axis. I want the Fourth Axis.
OK. so Third Axis for X. Fourth Axis for
Y. If we save that and try.
now we have Vertical. working fine
and Horizontal working fine. Good! Fantastic!
We can delete these log entries. because we don't need them anymore!
And that part of the challenge is sorted. That's great!
Now. next challenge I want you to do is. I want you to make the camera point
at the player. So. find the player by tag
in script. Make the camera look at the player. every frame.
we can do this in the same CameraPan Script for now.
And then. consider using the LateUpdate() method. rather than the Update
method. This does things a little bit later. so that if the player has moved
during the frame. then the camera doesn't point at it until the
end of the frame. you just get a smoother result. So. pause the video. see
if you can get the camera tracking the play now. for the first time.
OK!
Welcome back! So. this is what we're going to do to make the camera
tracking work. It's pretty simple. the camera
tracking. it doesn't take a huge amount of code to get
that working.
So what we're going to do is. we're just going to have ourselves a private
GameObject. We're going to find this in script. and I'm just going
to call it player. Then. at the Start. we're going to go find that
player by tag. so it's simply player =
GameObject.find object
with tag. object single object
with tag. and it's going to be my name ("Player");. Now. at this stage
I would want to be going to Unity. checking that my player
indeed is tagged with player. which we did earlier in the project. There it is
and then. coming back. Fantastic! Now.
I'm going to use LateUpdate. not Update. I'm going to
delete the comment. because it's no longer quite the same thing.
And I'm going to use transform.LookAt. a very useful
method. which we'll use again later. Now. you're welcome to look at Unity's
docs for that. and we're going to look at the player's transform.
OK. so
constantly look at the transform. Let's see what effect that has!
As I move the left stick now. you see the camera just
keeps the ball right in the middle. Let's just over the block! Wee!
That's pretty cool! So now. we've got the camera tracking.
The final thing we want it to do. is for the right hand stick
to pan up and down.
OK. so let's take a look at how we're going to do that. I've given you a Start Pack.
which you may or may have not unzipped by this stage.
So. in that Start Pack you have got
a couple of things. Let's go get the Start Pack and
download it and unzip it. So.
here we go. your Section Assets
Start Pack. And it's got a few things in it. let's just
put all of those into say the Camera Folder.
because they're all going to be related to the camera. Now. I've given you this selfie
stick thing. both as a .blend file and a .fbx. If you haven't
got Blender installed. you can use the .fbx. Let's take a look at what
it is. I'll use the Blender one. It's an arm. literally like
a selfie stick you use to take photos. and an
empty. just to make sure all the rotations and axes work properly.
Alright. so what we're going to do with this
guy is we're going to use. quite literally. a selefie
stick attached to the
ball. So. I'm going to drag the selfie stick into the scene.
like that. And you see. there it is just sitting attached. especially if I
look in Scene View. It's just kind of sitting over where the ball is. If we play
and go back to Scene View. it will just move.
The ball will move but the selfie stick won't.
It's just a thing. it's literally just a mesh
that's the shape of a cylinder. with some round ends on it. sitting in the world.
but crucially this thing has its axis at the
very bottom. which is why I made it in Blender. rather than just using a cylinder.
Now. look what happens when we rotate it. If we rotate in X. it rotates
around the bottom. If we rotate in Z. it rotates
around the bottom. You'll see why that's useful in a minute.
OK. So. the first thing I want you to do in code. with this selfie
stick. is just to get it to lock itself to the
ball's position. So. we need the selfie stick
literally locking to the ball's position. so
I'm going to create a script called Camera Arm.
for instance or SelfieStick. is easier.
SelfieStick. there we go! So. there's my SelfieStick
script. I'm going to go tidy it away into the Camera Folder.
because it's all related to the camera.
And what I want you to do is just. move the selfie stick.
every frame. to the position of the player.
Very similar to what we just did by the LookAt. so go ahead and make the selfie
stick move to the position of the player. every frame.
Your not even getting a challenge slide this time. you're just going to have to do it.
OK. so I'm going to go ahead and start making that work now.
So. I'm going to have myself a private GameObject
player; I'm going to
find it in script again. because this is something you don't want your designer doing. because if
it's not done. the whole code breaks right. So. this is something
that's not negotiable. We're going to go and find it in
code. Find object with tag player again. same as before.
OK that's fine!
We literally. in the LateUpdate again. because this is...
Well. actually here no. we're not rendering. I'm going to leave it in
Update. OK. we're moving something here. we're not rendering a
result of the movement. that's when you choose between Update and LateUpdate. When you're moving
things. use Update. When you're rendering the result of movement. use Late
Update. So then. we're just going to say the transform.position
of this very thing. of this selfie stick. is the player's
transform.position. Let's see
how that works. and if it does work. I'll show you
the code again. because I know I did that very fast. There you go. selfie
stick is stuck in the middle of the ball. Now. you might say. why
don't you just child the selfie stick to the ball? Good luck. Go ahead.
Have a go. You'll see what happens. if you do that is this. watch.
Of course. the ball rotates. so the selfie stick rotates.
Not good! Alright. that's why I've done it in script.
So. we are actually very
nearly there now aren't we. We've got nearly everything we want. What we
need to do now is make this orbit properly. so
I'm going to get you setup. for the mouse orbiting
on the right stick. and then. once I've got you set up. I'm going to get you to
do the final bit of this. alright. So. I'm going to have myself
a public float PanSpeed.
and that's going to be
= to 10. as a default. I don't know. that's just a guess as to
something that's the right speed.
OK. and another thing we're going to need is a private
Vector3. to represent the armRotation.
Now. let me must show you. in Unity. what I mean by that.
Here is the selfie stick. and we're literally talking about
this Vector3 here. We want to bring the arm down.
we want to bring the arm around. and then. we're going to put the camera
on the end of the arm. Yeah. that's the idea of this
whole scheme. is that we put the child. the camera. to the end of
this arm. literally like a selfie stick. So. we're going to need an
arm rotation vector. right. Now. we want the designer
to be able to set up what this arm rotation is. so in the Start
we go and find the arm rotation. from the transform
.rotation. of the thing we're on. What are
we on? We're on the selfie stick OK. But if
you just do that what are you going to get? What data type do you get out of transform
.rotation? Well. you get a Quaternion.
We want to be dealing with eulerAngles here. so luckily we have a method
.eulerAngles; that's actually a property. in this case.
because there are no brackets. so property of the rotation is eulerAngles.
So. this thing is simply this Vector3 here of the stick
OK. Fantastic! I'm
over using that word! I know. you can tell me off in the discussions. So.
let's get half of this done. and you're going to do the last bit.
What I'm going to do is build up a Vector3. that says armRotation.
Y. How do I know it's Y? Well.
let's play with it. Is it this guy here?
Probably. if the rotation is working? There you go!
That's your horizontal movement. around there. OK.
So. armRotaton.Y +=
so we're adding Input dot
get axis
("R... Now. what was it called. let's look over here.
And I've forgotten. so we need to go to the Input Manager.
I think it was RHoriz and RVert.
but we should check and copy and paste. RHoriz and RVert. there you
go in the Input Manager.
So. we're going to take.
not Input.GetKey but Input.GetAxis.
with this
string ("RHoriz") times
that panSpeed that we set up. Now. I don't know that's the right panSpeed.
but let's try now and find out. So. every frame we just
add whatever the right stick is to the rotation.
Let's try it. So it starts at a reasonable place.
Play! Now. the camera is not childed to it yet but we don't mind.
Go out to the Scene View. perhaps. and move the right stick and
see if we get what we want.
Get the ball moving. but the right stick isn't
doing what we want. so let's check the panSpeed.
The panSpeed is sensible. and let's go
back here and break this problem down. Why are we not getting
anything? Well. the simple reason we're not getting anything is because
we haven't told the transform.rotation
to change. Now. we need it to be
the arm rotation. We want the rotation
of the selfie stick to become the arm rotation.
but unfortunately. again we've got to give this a
Quaternion. So. there is a static method on Quaternion
called euler.
And you can give that a Vector3 and it'll spit back
a Quaternion. OK. so this is going to and from a Quaternion.
So. let's try this. We're going to look in
Scene View. so we can see what's happening.
Ah. see the right stick is doing that. Awesome!
Everything is awesome! So. we are nearly nearly
there. Guess what I'm going to challenge you to do now? Of course. it's
make the vertical pan work. Right stick vertical movement should
work. Camera will move up and down. at the same distance.
or at least the stick will move. we'll put the camera on the end.
at the very end. And see if you can do it in one line of code.
It's basically repeating what I've just done but for the vertical axis.
Go ahead! Have a go!
Cool! Welcome back! So. I'm going to try and do this in a simple cut and paste
operation. So. it's literally saying that the arm
rotation in... Now. we need to think about whether it's in X or Z.
Let's go over into Unity and see.
There. looks like X. so the
X component will track the RVert
axis. Confident in that? Maybe? Don't
know. try it! Don't worry about it too much just. go pop over.
give it a go! This is lean and simple. There you go!
I've got a little bit of drift going on. which means I haven't got enough
Dead Zone. So. if you're getting that drift. that means there's not enough
Dead Zone on the controller. So. you go to Input. and
for both I think. actually. I'm going to give a little bit more Dead Zone. I'm going to
move that down. to say 0.01. That's a
10 fold increase in the Dead Zone on the stick.
and you may
need to even further. I'm going to make a Dead
Zone of 1. I know it's a 100 times bigger Dead Zone. but
still I think that's going to be too much and it won't move at all. No. it's OK!
Feels about right on my stick. Obviously. you can see how much my stick
is moving but that's fine. All we need to do to make this work now guys
is to take the camera and stick it on the end of the selfie
stick. And you just need to make sure it is actually on the end
of the selfie stick. So. at 0. 0.
0 has almost done it. but the selfie stick is 10 units long. So.
there it is look! Let me maximize this. so you can see what's going on.
The camera is on the end of the selfie
stick. and then. when we rotate...
When we move the ball you see. there it goes. Now. of course. you
can delete the mesh of this selfie stick but I'm just going to leave it in.
If I jump it works. but if I use the right stick.
now horizontally I move around. You see the camera
preview down at the bottom there. and you see what's happening. It's too
fast. by the way. so if it's too fast you know what to do.
Let's un-maximize. come
down to the selfie stick's publicly exposed property. turn it down
to maybe 2. and let's have a look in the Game View.
There you go. you see that!
And the ball can be moving and we can move around. Now we have
proper twin stick control. All I'm going to do
to tidy this up is to go and find the Arms. Mesh Renderer.
and turn it off. so that the Arm is now invisible
and doesn't cast any weird shadows. Cool guys. congratulations!
That really is the end of this section! Now. you have a genuine Twin Stick game!
Go and include these mechanics in a game of your own. and I'll see you
on the other side!