Hey welcome back! So, finally for this section
I want to show you how to pause your game,
t's been a common request. So, I'm going to
show you one way of pausing your game in Unity.
We'll look at OnApplicationPause message and
understand Time.timeScale better. Cool! So,
here we are in the game. We want to pause
the game, so let's look at a few of Unity's
methods that may help with this. When it's
Time.timeScale, which you've used before,
and you can use it to slow down the game,
but you can also use it to stop the running
of the game altogether, by saying Time.timeScale
= 0. It also says here, that you better lower
your Time.fixed.DeltaTime by the same amount
so, if you're pausing, you want to set Time.timeScale
to 0 and Time.fixed.DeltaTime to the same
amount, like 0, in this case. So, I will show
you that practically in just a moment. We
also need to understand does the Unity execution
still work? I did the fixed update loops still
and the update loops still run, when Time.deltaTime
is set to 0. Well, let's find out shall we.
Let's go into the Game Manager and just do
a little experiment. This is the sort of thing
I would encourage you to do. So, we can some
along here and we can say on Update, we can
do another look for if (Input.GetButtonDown
and then (KeyCode.p for pause, let's say.
OK, or we could actually use whatever has
been assigned to pause, but be careful with
this one, this guy here is the Pause Button
on PC machines. So, I'm just going to use
the P key, directly, but of course what you
would normally do is actually assign this
to a re-mappable button if it's that type
of game but for now, let's just use the P
key. Here we go. So, if we go for P, then
we want to pause the game, so I'm actually
going to write a method to make it clear,
all the things we're going to do when we pause.
So, void PauseGame () OK, and we'll just call
PauseGame. So, what are we going to do in
PauseGame? Well, let's try this, Time.timeScale
= 0; OK, so let's try setting Time.timeScale
= 0, and while we're at it, every single update,
let's just print ("update"): And of course,
my challenge is, I'm saying GetButtonDown,
when I meant GetKeyDown. OK, let's have a
look. So, we play the game, we observe the
Console, we get lots and lots of updates coming
out here, we hit P... What happens? You have
to be in the Game Window, of course. Do the
updates keep coming out and does the thing
move? So, let's take a look, more carefully.
I'm going to collapse the Console, clear it,
play, move left and right, hit P... That's
frozen there, but it's still running the Update
Loop. So, to be clear, the Update Loop still
runs, when you go into Pause Mode, but the
timescale is set to 0, so all of these frame
updates and physics updates will be set to
0. OK, so you'll not have any movement going
on, but the Update Loop is still being called.
So, that's one clarification for you. So,
we have set Time.timeScale = 0. We better
show a way of resuming the game, so let's
just do a very similar thing, and let's just
say if (Input.GetKey... Actually, you do this.
Pause the video and sort it out, so that if
you push P again, or if you push R, either
way.. either separately you push R for resume
or if you Push P again, the game resumes.
OK, go ahead and pause the video, as a mini
challenge, and arrange to come out of Pause
Mode now. Common, do it! [Laughs] I mean,
I'm going to show you how, but I'm just going
to give you an opportunity to do it for yourself.
OK, I'm going to do it the easy way, which
is GetKeyDown, and then, I'm just going to
use a different key, otherwise we could just
use a Boolean to store the state. (KeyCode.R))
And then, just pop in a new method, which
I'm going to say ResumeGame. The purpose of
this, really is to show you what needs to
be done to pause and resume the game right.
So, resume the game doesn't exist, because
we haven't written it yet. So, here it comes,
and then, we're just going to kind of undo
what we've done. And Time.timeScale = 1 float.
OK, so let's just check pausing and resuming
now. So, I'm playing away, left and right,
I hit P, the game stops moving, the Update
Loop is still running, although we've moved
the log entry. We hit R and the game continues.
Perfect! OK, now is that enough? Remember
back in that entry, here, it said... I'll
come to that in a minute. It said we should
also lower Time.fixedDeltaTime by the same
amount. So, how do you do that? What is Time.fixedDeltaTime,
and how are we going to change it? OK, it's
"the interval in seconds at which the physics
and other fixed frame rate, i.e., things in
the Fixed Update Loop are performed. So, what
happens if we set fixedDeltaTime to 0? Let's
try that, and see whether it likes that, because
strictly speaking we're not setting the fixedDeltaTime
to 0, we're setting it to infinitely long,
but I think it will interpret this 0 appropriately.
There it goes, still running fine, and then,
the fixedDeltaTime is now 0, as well, which
makes sure that all the physics loops are
not being called as well. So, we have what
we need. Of course, in the resume of the game,
we need to undo the Time.fixedDealTime = 0.
We'd better set it back to what? Now, that's
a good question. That depends on what it was
set to in the Project Settings, in the first
case. Under Project Settings and Time, you
have Fixed Timestep equals 0.02. So, what
you'd better do is save that at the very beginning
of the game, so we'll have a private bool
fixedDeltaTime; OK, not a bool, well done
if you've noticed that. It's a float. And
then, on Start we'd better go and save it
the fixedDeltaTime = Time.fixedDeltaTime;
I'm also briefly going to print that, and
just confirm that it's 0.02, as we expect.
I'll comment out this line, and then, we'll
make on the resume, we'll make it go to whatever
it found it to be at the Start. OK, 0.02,
that verifies it's the same as the project
setting there. So, what we need to do, at
the end, is not set Time.fixedDeltaTime, i.e.
the rate at which fixed update loops are called
to some arbitrary value, but we're going to
set it to the fixedDeltaTime that we found
initially. OK, which is this guy here. And
if you don't like that name fixedDeltaTime,
I'll refactor it, initialFixedDelta; OK fantastic!
So, let's just make sure all that works, and
then, I'm going to tell you one more thing
about pausing and we are done, for this section,
in fact, for my involvement in this course,
because Brice is doing the next section. So,
we Pause and it pauses and we Resume and it
resumes. Fantastic! That will all work nicely.
There is one other thing to tell you. There
is a documentation here about OnApplicationPause.
Now, this is a message that will get called
on all of your scripts, when the operating
system pauses your game. So, for example,
if somebody leaves your game in iOS, this
will get called. OK, these are not something
you can call and pause your game, and you
will have to decide how to handle this. So,
you might want to call another message inside
your game, you might want to set a Boolean
flag in your Game Manager, that sets pausing,
for example. That would be a good one, so
let me just show you that, as a final thing
here. So, imagine I didn't use KeyCode.P and
R, imagine I actually had a Boolean flag,
right. So, just go private isPaused = false;
So, the game starts not paused, and then,
if I say if KeyCodeDown and P, so if KeyCodeDown
pause is paused... I need to give this guy
a type. OK. So, if you put the KeyCode down
and it's paused, then, you ResumeGame (); and
then, there's an else if in here. If you push
the (KeyCode.P)... and I could possibly avoid
repeating this code here, but who cares...
and if it's not paused, then you pause the
game. So, all I've done there is done it the
other way, the challenge the other way, which
is we're just using a P key and a Boolean
flag now, so we can go left and right, we
can hit P, we can undo P; I hope, unless I've
done something silly, which I have. What's
the problem? So, if we get key code P and
it's paused, we resume. If it's not paused.
Ah OK, so of course, what I'm not doing is
setting this, so isPaused = so if it was paused
then, we're going to set it as false, and
if it wasn't paused we're going to set it
to true. So, we're just keeping track of this
Boolean, and this will allow us... In a minute
I'll show you what this is coming to, it's
coming to this OnApplication thingy here,
so hit P. Hit P again, that all works beautifully.
Now, what we can do, when we've got a structure
like this is we can intercept this message
that we've just found, this OnApplicationPause.
OK, and if I just do that, I can just say
isPaused = pauseStatus; that gets passed into
this message. So, now if the system pauses
this game, i.e. if the iOS, Android App close,
etc., it will just put this game into pause
status, over here. But this is not quite finished,
of course, because if you look at the logic,
this is responding to a key press and calling
ResumeGame (); and PauseGame (); whereas this
guy here, if we just set the Boolean, it's
not actually going to call pause or resume
game, if that makes sense. So, what you would
need to do is just take this out. You would
just need to say if (ResumeGame) then, we
need to... Well, you need to look at whether
or not the PauseGame and the ResumeGame have
changed state in the last frame, but look
that's simple, it's simple coding, well below
this point in the course, and I'm going to
leave that as an exercise to the reader. I
think I've covered everything I need to about
pausing for now. You are good to go, with
a little tiny bit of extra work, which I really
want you to do, because again, I'm weaning
you off me. OK guys, I'll see you later! [Laughs]