So, I am both very sad
but also super excited, as you can see from this smile!
This is the last section you're going to see from me in this course.
The next section is going to be from Brice, Ahoy Matey,
a real-time strategy game. And I
just want to say, well done getting this far!
Now, I know this particular game hasn't even been
a game, it's been a sandbox. Now, my intention is to be weaning
you off me holding your hand, every
single step of the way. Now, the reason I'm so excited is
because it's not by any means the end of the journey for you
or for me. In fact, I'm about to dive into the production of
a course on the Unreal Engine and also to help
Michael finish off the Blender Course and it's so much
more to do. So, anyway 2.5D games,
I think you have all the tools that you need now. It's really
up to you to go and use your tenacity and your
inventiveness, to go out there and apply your
idea for your 2.5D game, using everything
you can find in the course so far, and in any future content
and really go out there and consider making a 2.5D
game, because they can be a huge amount of fun. So, I hope
you've enjoyed the course to this stage, and I will see you soon!