Welcome! In this lecture we are going to be installing Unity! That's this
beauty here. We're going to be opening the Editor for the first time and
learning how to play in the Editor and also installing Visual Studio
too, as a side effect. So, let's get stuck right in!
So, let's get started with installing Unity!
Let's get stuck in. Let's open Google Chrome, and I just
want to, before we start, give you a cautionary tale about
versions. So, here I'm using Windows 10; that shouldn't
matter too much, you could probably do it all the way down to Windows 7, but why would you want to
when Windows 10 is so cool. Or you can do it on
OSX, both platforms should have pretty much exactly the same
setup process. So, you can follow this video for both Windows and
OSX. Now, the thing I do want you to be careful about though is that you get the right
version of Unity, because it's going be new software, you might not be familiar
with it, so it's very important that we have exactly the same setup
as what you see in my videos so there's no confusion
around different versions. So, the important thing to be looking for
is Unity 5.3. That's the version we're
using, and you'll notice that if I search for 5.3, we've got all
this. Now, what we actually want is
"Unity 5.3 archive download".
And now, this is going to bring us to a spacial page on the Unity
3D website, where they have the archives
of all the previous versions of Unity. So, you can see, you could go all the way back to
version 3 point something, 4 point something, and we are using
5.3. Now, you'll notice that the versions are
actually three digits long, 5.3.4
or 5.3.2. Now, this doesn't matter
so much, the last decimal point doesn't matter. So, just get the latest of
these decimal points, as long as these bits are 5.3. So, Unity
5.3 is what we're looking for. Now, they've got an interesting
system here with drop-down menus, so if you're using a Mac you'll want to drop-
down from this menu. If you're using Windows drop-down from here, and what we actually
want to select here is the Unity Installer itself. So, click on
that and that will just download
a little small installer here, which we can run.
Give it permissions. OK, so now
we're in the Download Assistant.
So, it's your turn to check or install your environment.
I'm leaving this as a challenge for you to do. I will show you later how
I do the particulars, just in case you do get stuck, but hopefully
you'll manage to install this by yourselves. So,
I'd like you to check, so by that I mean if you've already got
Unity then I want you to check it's Unity 5.3; if not, finish downloading
Unity 5.3. Then, I'd like you to install
Unity using the default components. That just means going through that installer
and leaving the default check boxes. Then, I
want you to find out, while that's downloading and finishing off the installation
process, I would like you to find out which VR games are actually
made in Unity, i.e. you doing relevant Google searches,
sharing in the discussions the ones that you think look most intriguing,
and that you would like to take inspiration from. So, go and get inspired,
and then, when it's finished, I'd like you to launch the Unity Editor
and try and run, see what that does. Try and see how you
can run in the Unity Editor. OK, so pause the video
and go and have a go at this challenge.
OK, welcome back! I hope you've all had a go at installing it for yourself.
If you're stuck, let's dive in and have a go with me.
OK, so fairly easy. We need to step through
this installer. Now, these are the components I was talking about.
For now, we're going to leave them all checked. Later on, we will want some more of these, but
we can always come back and add more later, so there's no
need to do that right now. I'm going to just go through leaving
all the default locations as they are. We need to
accept the terms and conditions on Visual Studio, if you're on Windows;
otherwise, on Mac you won't need to do this, it will
install MonoDevelop for you instead. So, let's just go through!
That's the only difference between Mac and Windows, so we'll be seeing
how that differs later on in the course. But no need to worry, it is
pretty much identical otherwise. Just the thing that you edit, the code
bin will look slightly different. OK, now
we have to leave this downloading and doing the install. It's all
fairly autonomous, so we don't have to press any buttons really past this point,
which is great very easy install procedure.
So, like I said, I would like you to do a little bit of research about
Unity VR games and see which ones you might use as
inspiration. So, first port of call, let's just search for Unity
VR, and now, there's a few interesting links
here. These ones are from the documentations but might not be too helpful for you right now.
This is about learning as well. Well that's what you're here for, so you don't need to
do, look at the learning links, but this link about multi-platform VR
is actually quite interesting. So, it talks a little bit about
what Unity's support has, what the list of devices it has
support for. That's all the common ones. You've got the Rift, you've got your HTC
Vive, you've got your Gear VR, your Cardboard,
PS VR, etc. But if we scroll down,
there's also a list of games. So, here you go! We see this installer
has moved on to the next step. It's actually installing now. But we've got the games
that have actually been made with Unity
and are VR enabled, VR compatible. So,
have a look through these. Some of them have got videos attached,
so take a little watch while the installer is happening,
and then, just share in the discussions which ones you think
you're going to be taking some inspiration from.
OK, so I'm just going to fast-forward through the installation,
at this point, and we'll pick up
from there.
So my installation has finished and it is time to launch
Unity, so I'm just going to make sure that checkbox is checked and hit finish.
And we will get Unity launching for the first time,
so you'll be able to take a look at what this Unity Editor is all
about. This thing that you have probably heard a lot about and have seen
how many great games can be produced for it, and
you'll see why it's so powerful and why it's so great!
OK, enough of my ranting and raving. I hope this is going
to load soon, so you don't have to keep listening to my voice.
OK, so just allowing some access
because Unity will want us to log in. This is an optoinal
step. You can create a Unity account, and that allows you to buy things like
assets, so you don't have to do everything just for
yourself.
OK, so this was the login screen I was telling you about, and I misspoke when I said
you don't need to log in, you actually do. You need to create an account,
if you don't have a Unity account already, and then,
let's just log in. So, I already have one,
so I'm just going to type in the details for that.
Let's go ahead and sign in. And that's the only time you
should have to do that. Subsequently, the Unity Editor will
in fact remember you. OK, so it doesn't look like my Unity Editor
is actually launching after the login, so I'm just going to quit Chrome
and go and launch it from the Desktop.
You could also do it from the Start Menu, up to you. Just launch the
Unity Editor. As you see, it will be checking the license. You
want to select the Personal Edition, because that's the
free one, and then, we can go on next and
say: "I don't use Unity in a professional
capacity". Hopefully you don't yet,
seeing as you're just starting out and just starting to learn. So,
let's go through and we can start our first project.
So, I'm going to create a new basic project, and we can leave
all these defaults for now, just to see what it looks like to play.
That was my challenge to you, to get it to play in the Unity Editor.
So, we get through to this stage. So, it's going to load up
all this craziness which is the Unity Editor. We'll dig into this in later lectures, but
the thing I was hoping you might have noticed is there's play button. So if you hit play,
we've got all the way to playing or previewing our first game.
Congratulations! That is, you're also up
to work with Unity now and move on to the next two sections!