So, hi and welcome to
Text101. In Text101 we're going to be digging into
a lot of the scripting stuff we went through in the previous
section and to take it a little bit further. So, what
is that we are building in Text101, Ben? Well, it's a good old fashioned
text adventure game, so it's just going to have the tiniest
bit of graphic at the top but after that, it's entirely text,
and you're just going to be doing the old school, reading something
and then hitting a key to decide what to do next.
And it could be one thing you could do next or it could be three or four things
you can do next, and by the end of it, you'll have written over 200 lines of
code. They're very similar lines of code, but it's still 200
lines of code, so you're going to have a great hand,
at the end, and realize you're a proper programmer, already. So, it's like a
choose you're own adventure game, basically. Yeah, exactly! Just like you choose
you're own fiction book. And it's really interesting, because what we're
actually going to be doing is some fundamental computer stunts,
and they way we're going to be doing it is building a state machine, in the background.
and you won't notice it, until the end, that you've got something that's actually quite
generic. Yeah, and the state machine is a really cool way
of doing it, on one hand, because you can
be very specific about every path you've taken
to get to a current state, and you can make very rich
output and a very rich response to what the guy
is doing. So, it's basically a tool for your tool box, that you can use
in the future as well. We're just kind of building your tool box slowly. You've
had scripting, now we're adding some Finite State
Machines, and we'll be adding into your tool box, throughout the course.
So yeah, and really the point of this particular section is they
can build and share. People can build and share their own game, right, and you can
build your own game and then share it. So, I really want you to
kind of, once you've finished this section, make your own adventure.
Create your own adventure, extend it, make cool
stuff with it, and share it with your friends. Share it with the other
people on the course. Share it on the website,
share it with the world, basically. Yeah, well maybe even get a friend of yours to write this
story, and they can write the text and just tell you what keys they
want to be able to allow the player to press, and
write their own text, whatever. Please create a game,
build it for the web, and share it both on
the Udemy discussions and on
www.completeunitydeveloper.com/community or wherever
you want to put it on www.completeunitydeveloper.com. We're not fussy, just share it
with the world! So, go ahead, follow our game,
write your own story, share it with the world, and we'll see you on the other side!
Awesome!