So, let's get started with Text 101, you're
own text adventure game, and more importantly
text adventure engine! In this game we're
going to, even in this video, we're going
to recap how to create and save projects,
just to get you really confident with that,
setup and save your Text 101 project, talk
a little bit about what gets carried over
to new projects, when you start a new Unity
project, and we'll import your Prison Image
Asset but not use it yet and then save your
project. OK, so let's dive into Unity for
a moment. If you open Unity, you'll probably
find that it's exactly where you left it,
and if you're following the course through
in order, then you'll have left it at the
end of Number Wizard Console, like this. So,
you're obviously going to need to start a
new project, so let's be very clear about
where that project is going to get stored
on your hard drive. Firstly, I want my project
to be in a directory over here, in Ben, and
then, under Repos for Repositories, because
of the way that I manage my code. And then,
I want it right in here, I want a folder right
in Ben Repos, this is a Mac by the way, and
I want that to be caled Text101. And so how
do I do that in Unity? Well, let's take a
look. Here we are in Number Wizard Console.
Let's go ahead and create a new project from
the File Menu. When you do that, you'll have
several options, as you've seen before. Let's
start at the top set, that's going to set
the project directory. So, I go to this Repos
Folder, and I'm going to call it Text101.
Now, if I'm selected on the Repos Folder and
I call it Text101, let's save and see what
happens, in a moment. Firstly, we need to
decide not to import any assets and set up
a 2D project. It's not super important whether
it's 2D or 3D, because things can easily be
changed in Unity, but so that things are consistent
with my videos, please choose 2D. OK fantastic!
Click on Create Project. Now, let's just firstly
check that folder. There you go, actually
you could see the folder while Unity temporarily
closed. It has created a Text101 folder, as
I wanted and within that it's got all the
stuff that Unity sets up by default, so that
is fantastic! We've achieved our first goal,
which is to recap how to create and save project
and to save our Text101. So, what gets carried
over to new projects? Well, one of the things
that's kind of lingering from the Number Wizard
project is that your Console Tab or your Layout
in general or as a whole will be persisted,
so however your layout was in your last project,
the window layout will be the same in this
new one. So, the easiest way to get back to
default is click at the top right, on the
button layout, and then, click Default. Now,
you'll be back at the Default Unity Layout.
We don't need the Console on the right hand
side anymore, that was just for a previous
project. OK fantastic! The other thing that
will get carried across are all of your Unity
Preferences, which are here on a Mac and they're
here on a PC. Thanks to Christo for pointing
this out for us. As you know, this course
is recorded on a Mac, and there are very few
differences between Macs and PCs, but things
like location of the Preferences Menu is an
example of one of the differences, so if there'
s difference that you would like me to insert
into the course, please do share it in the
discussions, like Christo has, and it would
be ideal if you didn't annotate it so that
I can annotate it myself, afterwards in a
way that's consistent with the course. So,
just a plain vanilla full screen screenshot
would be fantastic in the discussions, and
I'm happy to edit it into the course, like
I have done this bit. The only thing we have
changed is the colors. We've changed the Play
Mode Tint to whatever you chose, I chose a
red. What that means is, when you click play
the system will indicate all parts of the
interface where changes will be lost if you
are to make them during the play. So, you
need to stop playing before you play with
or change anything around here, around the
outside hierarchy, or Inspector, because those
are only temporary changes, and the reason
I changed the Play Mode Tint is to make that
really really clear to you. So, that's what
gets carried over. In summary, your current
layout, and it's easy to reset as I just showed
you, and anything under your Unity Preferences,
i.e. the Play Mode Tint or anything else in
that Unity Preferences Dialog Box, which is
there. Any of these tabs, External Tools,
Colors, Keys, any of this stuff will get persisted,
when you start a new project. OK, so I hope
that's clear for you. The final thing we're
going to do, as I've promised, is to import
your Prison Image Asset. So, if you're anything
like me, you've downloaded your Prison Image
Asset, from a lecture very close to this one
in the course. Probably immediately before
this or before the Dame Design Document, and
when you download from that lecture, from
the Resources Button, you will see a prisonword.png
or possibly .png.zip. If it's a .zip, obviously
just unzip it, so that you find this prisonword.png
file. If you double click it, it should look
something like this, it's just the word Prison.
And all I want you to do for now is just grab
that and drag it onto your Assets section
of Unity. So, that is under the Project Tab
at the bottom of the screen. You've then got
Assets, drag and let go in there, and what
you should find is you get prison world like
that, which you can click on and see in Unity.
When you drag this image in, just be absolutely
sure that it has come in as Texture Type Sprite brackets
2D and UI. Look up on the top right, under
your Inspector, with your prison word Image
selected over here, and just make sure this
says sprite. If it doesn't please click the
drop down and change it to Sprite brackets
2D and UI, as mine is. That's going to be
really important in a future video. The final
thing you're going to need to do is to actually
save your scene; it'll ask you to do this
when you quit Unity. You know that it's not
saved, because firstly there's no scene here
in the Assets Folder, and secondly, it says
Untitled up here, which is your scene or level
name. So, let's go ahead and say just Save
Scene in Unity, and it'll come up and say,
what do you want to call it? Well, it wants
to go in the Assets Folder, that's correct.
Let's just call it Game. This game is going
to have a single scene, so that's it. Now,
we have a new thing in our Assets Folder called
Game, and it looks like a Unity logo, and
that is a scene or a level and we're having
a single one here. So, now the real test is
if you try and quit Unity, then it should
just go and disappear like that, which is
just fine. So, that means that you have successfully
left Unity and nothing else needed saving
and it's all good to go, but for now, congratulations!
You've done really well in this video! You
understand a lot more about creating and saving
projects and getting them to go where you
want them, you know actually getting control
over the directory. You have saved your Text101
project, you understand what gets carried
across and our image is in. So, well done
and I'll see you in another video!