Hey welcome back! So, now we're going to use
the Unity Engine for the first time. We're
going to be adding 2D User Interface Text.
So, we're going to start off by adding a UI
Text Element into our scene. I'll show you
how to set the Camera Background Color, it'll
default to blue it needs to be black or it
would look better black. We'll then move and
scale our text and go on to show you how to
programmatically change it, before challenging
you two ways. Firstly, to change the text
only on key presses, using if statements,
that you should already know about, and secondly,
to add and scale the image we've given you
or an image of your choice. So, let's dive
in and take a look. The first thing we need
to do is get a UI Text Element into our scene,
so this is probably the first time you've
ever seen the Scene View in Unity. There's
a few things that I need to just make sure.
Firstly, I want to make sure you're in 2D
Scene View, so on the Scene Tab, if you click
2D or 3D. 3D will give you a different gizmo,
at the top right. It'll look 3 dimensional,
and you will just better see perspective,
whereas when you click 2D and the button is
depressed, this gizmo will actually disappear
and you'll just see a grid system, which you
can zoom in and out with the mouse and a camera
in the middle of it. So, we want you in 2D,
because we're going to be doing a 2D game
here. Fantastic! So, let's add our Text Element.
We go to Text Object. Sorry, Game Object Menu,
UI, and then, text, so that's Game Object,
UI, Text. And that's what we want to add,
let's do that. Now, look what happens when
we add the UI Text, lots of crazy things happen.
You get let's start at the top, you get something
called a Canvas, in your Hierarchy on the
left, and inside of that you get the Text
Element you asked for. And you also get something
called an Event System. Now, leave that Event
System there, we're not going to be making
use of it in this game, but it does need to
be there, so just leave it. The Canvas is
just for organizing all your objects, and
then, the Text Element is the thing we're
interested in, so that's where we're going
to focus. Now, at the bottom of your Inspector,
you may see Layout Properties. You can get
rid of that by just clicking. So, the other
thing I want you to check, quickly before
we look at the Canvas, is up at the top right.
You have a Layers Drop Down, just click on
that, and make sure that this little UI eye
is actually an eye. You'll notice the white
Canvas that you can just see, appears and
disappears. Another way to do it is just to
make sure everything is ticked, so we want
everything except for nothing, ticked in the
Layers. If you click Nothing, you wouldn't
see anything. If you click Everything, you
see everything. The important thing is that
this UI Layer, that we've just added, is visible.
The other thing to know, in your scene view,
is that we're very zoomed in at the moment.
You've got a white outline, depending on your
zoom level, which indicates your Text Box.
Now, there are several ways to get the Text
Box filling the screen. One is to click into
the scene and to roll the mouse wheel forward,
if you have a mouse wheel, zooming out until
you get too it. Another way would be to double
click on the word Text, and that will go straight
to the Text Element or double click on the
Canvas, will go to the entire Canvas. So,
what's a Canvas? What's a Text Element? Well,
the Canvas is where we're going to be operating.
Our entire game is going to be inside a User
Interface Canvas, so I'm going to fill the
screen with that, and the Text Element is
actually, in my case, sitting outside here.
So, I want to move that Text Element into
the Canvas, just grab it and drag it. Now,
there are a couple of different tools that
could do that. One is this Transform Tool,
the second tool at the top left of Unity,
which could be selected with the W Key or
by just clicking on it, and you could then
grab the blue box and drag this in. Another
way that you can move it is to use the UI
Element Tool, which is accessible through
the T Key, and then, you can also then just
drag. As we're doing UI stuff, it's probably
better to get in the habit of using the UI
Tool here. Fantastic! OK! So, let's just recap
what we're doing. We're trying to add some
text to the scene. So, what I told you we
would do is add UI Text, we've done that.
Secondly, setting the Camera Background Color.
Well, let's do that now. So, if we were to
run the game now, look what happens. We get
a Game View that says New Text, it's fuzzy
text and it's on a blue background. Now, we
want this to be on a black background. Why
is the background blue? It doesn't look blue,
over in the Scene View. It's because we're
getting the color of the text, the background,
the background of everything, from the camera,
so if we were to click on the Camera, you'll
see that it has a blue background color to
it, at the moment. Now, remember if you're
going to make a change to this background
color, you want to do it when your not in
Play Mode. That's the purpose of this red
tint. Let me show you why. If I change that
to black in Play Mode, and then, stop look
what happens. The moment I stop playing, it
goes back to blue, so this is why we must
make permanent changes outside of Play Mode.
And then, we want to be able to change the
text, by a program, so let's move our text
box and resize it. Now, you'll only be able
to resize it if you're sufficiently well zoomed
in, so use the Right Mouse Button to drag
around, zoom into your Text Box, until you
get little blue handles, and then, grab those
handles. Now, as the thing gets bigger, you'll
better see the handles at increasing zoom
sizes. And what I want you to do is set the
Text Box, so that it fills, about two thirds
vertically, of the screen like that, and so
that it's centered. And you'll see it's centered,
because you'll get the blue snapping action,
when it's centered like that. Alright, so
now you have a Text Box in here, and I'm just
going to type, for the moment, some rubbish
in here. Lorem 2, there we go Now, why is
this text so ugly? It's partly because the
font size is far too small, so we'd need to
turn the font size up, by going into the
Inspector and dragging up the Font Size, and
that will make your text look a lot prettier.
Let's look in the Game View. That's getting
much better, so it's still not particularly
readable and that's to do with the colors
that we have on the text but it's much better
than it was before. So, let's just try setting
our Text Color to white, so you do that in
the Inspector by going Inspector Text Script,
and then, down to Color, under paragraph and
make it white, in your color picker. Now,
that's much better. So, we have white text,
in the bottom of the box there. So, how are
we doing on our objectives for the video?
We've added text. We've set the Camera Background
Color, in Edit Mode not Play Mode. We've moved
and scaled our text around, do have a play
with that with the UI elements there, get
used to moving that around. The final thing
we need to do is programmatically change the
text on here, so how are we going to do that?
Well, we're going to need a script to do that,
so here's our text. Where do you think we're
going to add a script that changes text? Well,
to me it makes sense to add that on the text
itself. So, go to the bottom of the Inspector,
when selected on Text, and Add a Component,
New Script, and I would say TextController
like that, with a capital T and a capital
C and no space. OK, that's because it is a
class, we always call all scripts or classes
capital T capital, letter at the start. OK,
so we have a TextController Script. Where's
it gone? It's in our Assets Folder. So, what
we need to do is work out how we're going
to get access to this text, so let's go into
our script and let's take a look. So, this
script currently doesn't have any access,
direct simple access, to the text. The way
that we're going to make it do that, is we're
going to do something called publicly exposing
the text. So, public Text text; OK. You're
going to need to add that line at the top
of your TextController class, above your Start
function at the same level. That's going to
make a variable called text of type Text,
available to all the methods inside the TextController.
Don't worry about what this class stuff means,
at the moment. Now, our text here should be
Because Line 6 causes quite a lot of confusion, I just want to walk through it
once more from left to right carefully. So firstly the word
public. The word public is an "access modifier"
This makes this Text field visible in the inspector
so that we can actually change the value over in Unity in a very
human and organic way. The next word Text with a capital T
(you need to tune your eye into that capital T). This is a type
and it of type Text.
The next word text with a small t, is just the variable name we are using.
We could choose anything, and perhaps we could chose something less confusing than
text, but I'm using the same word because what matters is that
you read the code the way the compiler reads the code, and that is
it depends on the order of the words. Public is the access modifier, next
it's expecting a type, Text with a capital T, then it's expecting
you to provide any valid variable name, and I'm using text. We could choose
something else but our compiler is gonna expect that to be a variable name. Now, our text here should be
a different color, and the reason it's not
is we actually need to say using UnityEngine.U at the top hereI;
and then, save. OK, and when we do that, every
time we do anything to do with Unity UI we're
going to have to put this line in at the top,
to bring in the User Interface information.
The text here has gone blue, which it means
it's recognized text. If I hadn't of put this
using UnityEngine.UI line in, look what happens,
the text is red. So, when your text is red,
you put UnityEngine.UI, the text goes blue,
it's recognized, and we're in good shape.
So, what we want to do on the Start here is
just make sure we've got access to the text.
And how do we do that? Well, it's simply text.text,
as it happens, = "Hello world"; Let's try
that with a semicolon on the end of the statement,
save our script remember, and go back to Unity.
We have this placeholder Lorem text in here,
now let's run, and what happens when we run?
Nothing. "Object reference not set to an instance
of an object". What's going on there? Well,
let's revisit the script. At the top here,
we said public Text text; Now, I told you
that that's making a variable that is available
to all of these methods, of type Text called
text. The problem is, where is it coming from?
To make the attachment between this text object
here and the actual text, we're going to bring
in, we have to do a slightly strange thing,
in the Inspector. Go to the bottom of your
Inspector, and you'll see that the TextController
Script, at the bottom here, is asking for
text. Well, just drag from your Hierarchy
the Text Element onto that. Now, there are
much more elegant ways of accessing this,
which we'll talk about later, but for now,
I want you to get used to exposing things
when you need to and connecting them like
this, so we drag our text on there. Now, let's
try running. "Hello world!" Great! So, let's
recap how far we've got. We have programmatically
changed text. OK, next thing is we're going
to change text, only when we press a key.
Now, you have looked at if statements previously,
so what I want you to do is change or put
in here an if statement, in the Update function,
so that it starts by saying "Hello world",
but if I press the Space Key, let's say then
it's going to change to Space Key pressed.
OK. So, I want you to put an if statement
around this command. I'm going to say text.text
= "Space key pressed"; This is going to be
set every frame, so right now if I run, we
won't see the "Hello world", because it goes
away immediately and keeps getting replaced
every single frame, with "Space key pressed."
OK, so what I want to happen is for "Space
key pressed' not to come up until you press
the Space Key, using an if statement around
line 16. So, I'll put the challenge definition
on the screen for you. There are some hints.
We're not actually starting with the text
blank, we're starting with "Hello world",
but that's OK and we're going to change to
"Key pressed", when we press the Space Key.
So, go ahead and do that challenge now. Pause
the video. OK, how did you get on? Let me
show you how I'm going to do that simple challenge.
What we do is we come back in here and we
say if and then the brackets. Now, I like
to do all my brackets to start with, the brackets
are like that remember; if is a statement,
it takes in a condition, and it has a code
block. I'm going to put the code I only want
to execute with the if happens inside the
code block, and then, I'm going to write my
condition, which is (Input.GetKeyDown and
then (KeyCode.Space)) That's how we're going
to be doing that. Make sure you have as many
closing circular brackets as you do opening.
Save your script and let's try now. What we
hope will happen, is when we first run, it
says "Hello world!", when I hit Space it changes
to "Space key pressed!". Fantastic! Congratulations!
Let's look back at the script, make sure we
understand how that works. This whole script
gets called, because it's a script on an object
in the game, so that's what is going to happen.It's
hanging off the Text Object. At the Start
of the game, it sets the text to "Hello world",
and then, every single frame it asks the question,
have we currently got the Space Key down?
If not, it does nothing it skips right over
this code block right down to here. If we
have got the Space Key down, then it changes
the text to "Space key pressed". OK, as a
final challenge for you I want you to get
this image onto the Canvas and then, scale
it appropriately. Now, I'm going to have to
tell you how to do that. You could just drag
it on, but if you just drag it on it's going
to become the wrong type of thing, and you
can tell that because the Transform is not
the same as the Text, which is a Wrecked Transform. So that's not how to do it.
You're going to need to go Game Object, UI,
Image, so let's do that. Then, the image comes
under the Canvas, and then, what I want you
to do is replace this white image with this
Prison Word Sprite here. OK, so I want you
to drag the Prison Word Sprite, this thing
here, onto that, and then I want you to resize
it so it looks decent, using the UI Element
Tool, so that it's taking up about a third
of the screen, at the top and it kind of looks
the right proportions. So, in summary what
I want you to do is add an image to the Canvass,
scale it to around 1/3 of the height, center
it on the Canvas, ensure the background of
the image is transparent, if you're using
the image we supply it will be, and then,
make sure your game runs. So, how did you
get on? Hopefully you've managed to do that.
This is how I did it. I just simply stuck
the image on, and I'm going to grab it, drag
it, until it looks about right, move it till
it snaps to the center, and then, just click
play to make sure my game is running. How
do I know the background is transparent? Well,
try putting it over the text for a minute.
You can see the background of the image we
supplied. Well, you can see it here in the
Scene View is transparent, because we can
see the text behind. So, fantastic! You've
had a very good video here, I believe. You've
learned a lot, and hopefully you're a lot
more confident with UI Elements now. Here's
what we learned, and I look forward to seeing
you in a future video.