Welcome back! So. in this video we're going
to be talking about word wrapping. when we
have a long string of like this Lorem Ipsum
Text. we have here in this Text Box. It's
all very well. when we try and set this directly
in the User Interface. but I want to talk
about what's going to happen when we try and
set long strings in code and how we're going
to deal with that. in our code. So. let's
firstly stay here in the User Interface for
a minute and just have a quick look at a setting.
In your Inspector. when you're selected on
your Text Field. you will see under the Text
Box that you have an option. if you scroll
down. that says Horizontal Overflow under
Paragraph. And it's currently set to Wrap.
If we were to set that to Overflow. look what
happens to the text. if I zoom out. it's just
one long line. It ignores the fact that it's
escaping the right hand side of the Text Box.
So. you're going to want that on wrap. if
you want to see it all. Alright. so now let's
imagine we want to set a slightly longer story
scene. because we're trying to build a text
adventure here. and we want to do that programmatically.
so let's see where we are with our script.
So far. when we hit the Space Key. in this
condition. we are just saying "Space key pressed".
Let's try pasting all of that Lorem Text in
there. with a semicolon on the end. Now. let's
just have a look. it's a horrible dirt to deal with.
so text.text =. Now. I've got to scroll all
the way across. I don't want to close brackets.
I need to make sure I've got a semicolon on
the end of the statement. Now. let's just
see if that works; I think you'll find that
it'll work OK. but let's just make sure. How
are we going to know. by the way? Because
it's going to start with the Lorem Text. and
then. end up with the Lorem Text. when we
hit Space. so I'm going to take it out in
Unity. So. what we have now. in the starting
state. is no text. And then. if we look over
at our script. it's going to go to "Hello
world" on Start. so we'll know that's working
and then. it's going to go to this very long
string. when we hit the Space Key. Let's see all
this happening. click play. "Hello world!".
as expected. Now. let's hit the Space Key.
OK. now our Lorem Text comes in just fine.
if we paste it into the script. so that's
good. and the wrapping continues to work as
we left it. The problem I have here is I don't
really want any of my script to be more than
a screen width. and having to scroll all the
way across to see my text is just horribly
unusable. Now. I'm afraid there's no really
elegant solution to this. without doing something
pretty esoteric. so I'm just going to show
you how I suggest we layout text. in script.
Alright. so what we're going to do is we're
going to say well. where have we got about
a screen full. over here somewhere. and we're
going to close the string. put a + on the
end of the line. and then. remembering that
C# ignores white space. we can put a new line
in. Now. we've got a style question as to
where do we start typing the next line. Well.
I'm going to indent it to the same level as
the previous quote was on the line above.
and I'm going to put some quotes in like that.
Now. we need to be careful with our spaces.
there's either a space on the end or the beginning.
better to have the space to my eye on the
end of the previous line. So. that's the pattern
you want to continue in. Let's just make sure
that this works for one concatenation or join
of the strings. and then. we'll talk about
what to do next. Let's check it. "Hello world!".
yep. all fine. this transition is happening
just fine. Great! So. hopefully you can see
what's happening here. We have a statement
here. we have a + on the end. C# is ignoring
the white space. it would be exactly the same
if we left it like that where we just have
a close of quotes and reopening of the quotes.
You'd say what's the point? You'd be quite
right. what's the point if it's all on one
line? But the point is that if we want to
put it on two lines. then we need to do this.
You may say why don't we just leave the quotes
and the + out. like that and just put a new
line. Let's see what happens. if we do that.
It just won't compile. it says we've got a
new line in constant. You can't put a new
line in the definition of this Text Element.
Alright. so you're going to have to close
the quotes and concatenate. So. this is the
best we've got for you in terms of how you
build a long text string. So by this pattern.
what I would like you to do. I'll do just
the next one for you. is I would like you
to repeat this for the rest of the string.
alright. so that none of it runs off the end
of the screen. A little mini challenge for
you. Pause the video and continue to bring
all of this string down into a single screen
width. Now. while you're at it. why not start
writing your story. Why use my horrible Lorem
Text? Certainly don't sit and try and write
that out. Start writing your own story into
here. Now. I'm going to pause the video. write
my own story into this paragraph. and then.
I'll see you when we have both written our
first screen of story. This is your starting
screen on your story. in my case my prisoner
in his cell.See you soon. So. welcome back! So. here's
my little story. You're in a prison cell and
you want to escape. There are some dirty sheets
on the bed. a mirror on the wall. and the
door is locked from the outside. You may have
the question. how do I actually put a new
line in now. if I want to. because you may
want to go on to give the user some instructions
about what they can do. So. here is how you
put a new line in. You use a back slash like
that. and then. an n and it should come up
in red. like that. And you may end up needing
two of them. So. if you do that. then you're
going to want to just continue in this pattern
now. something like this. So. press. I don't
know. M or L to look at mirror. What we need
to do here by the way. is look at our Game
Design Document and see what we decided in
our State Transition Diagram. So. we're in
the cell and there are some sheets. so V for
view R for return. so let's make that happen
over in the text. "Press V to view sheets".
Now. let's look at our State Diagram again.
See we need to modify our State Diagram. take
a look at this. and you realize and this stage
it's all very well saying view you're sheets
and return. view the mirror and return. but
look. if we're using V for view. what are
we viewing. OK. so we're going to need to
us S for sheets. M for mirror. and L for lock.
So. if you've got your own sketch diagram.
go ahead and change that. otherwise I will
change mine now. This is exactly the sort
of thing you'll come across. you draw a diagram.
it seems logical at the time. but when you
come to implement it there is an issue that
doesn't make sense. so just update your diagram.
So. I'm going to go ahead and update the diagram
now. OK. so I've made that improvement in
my diagram. Take a look now. Let's start with
the cell. Do we have a unique key press every
transition we want to make? S for sheets.
M for mirror. L for lock yeah. and if you
were to look around the diagram. you'd find
the same for mirror. For mirror. once we have
the mirror. you know once we're looking at
the mirror. we could T for take or R to return
and so on. Cell mirror is where we're in the
cell. holding the mirror. at which point we
can S to look at the sheets. holding the mirror.
We can M to. I'm sorry. L to go to the lock.
OK. I'll change that to L for lock and you
can see that you have a unique key press for
every state. which is what we want. OK. fantastic!
So. let's go back to our code. and now. we
know what we're going to say. This is the
value of planning. so V to view sheets. well
it's S to view sheets right. "S to view Sheets.
press M to view Mirror and L to view Lock."
Now. before we carry on. check it back at
our diagram. I'm just going to change this
to lock for us. one second. The mirror becomes
lock. Now. how do you draw your game design
diagram documents is entirely up to you? You
may want to use a piece of paper. a notebook.
you may want to use Google Documents. you
may want to use Word. whatever you like as
long as it works for you. OK. so we have S.
M. and L. Let's just check that that's right.
S. M. and L. OK. and I'm putting the capital
letter in front of Sheets. Mirror. and Lock.
just to emphasize that the L goes with Lock.
the M goes with Mirror. and the S goes with
Sheets. Fantastic! Let's look at this in action
now. Hit the Space Bar. You're in a prison.
blah blah. OK fantastic! So. that's it really.
we've done what we want to do here. We've
understood a lot more about long strings.
about how they fit in UI Text Elements. about
Wrapping in terms of the Paragraph Horizontal
Overflow. and then. over in code we found
a way of dealing with paragraphs of text by
concatenating in consecutive lines like this.
being careful with our spaced. inside the
quotes. And by using backslash n as the escaped
new line character. in order to insert new
lines. I've put two new lines in. because
if you look in the game. there are actually
two new lines. One brings you onto this next
line. after the first paragraph. The next
new line creates that nice separation between
the description and the affordance. as to
what you should be doing next. So. well done
with that! You've learned a lot that lesson.
and I'll see you shortly!