Hey. welcome back! So.
our little text adventure game is a fantastic
start and it basically works. The
challenge is. it's possibly a little too basic.
Once you realize that you just press M.
T. L. and O
and that you're out and free. it's a little
unsatisfying. So. what I'd like to do now is lay
the foundations to make the game a fair amount more complex.
It's the same logic. the same code.
we're just going to get used to
some slightly tedious work of
adding more assets to our game. because this is
too thin. This is too simple. So. let's
take a look at the Game Design Document. So far.
this has been our State Diagram. and as you
just saw. if you go M. T.
L. O. then you end up
out of the prison. really quickly.
So. what I want to do is introduce a new level. if you like. We're not actually going to
use Unity's levels here or scenes. we're just going to add
more code. but I want to introduce a new dimension.
which is a new section called the
corridor. So. instead of freedom. what we're going to do
is we're going to go to a corridor
state. which used to be called freedom.
and that's why we start on the left hand side with corridor_0.
And from
there what can we do? Well.
we can look at the stairs. but we decide we don't want to go up them.
because we're going to get rumbled or put straight back in
prison. We could look at the closet
but realize the door is locked. We can
look at the floor and on the floor we see a hair clip.
which we can choose to ignore. returning to the corridor. or we can
pick up the hair clip. That takes us to a new
corridor state. I'm calling it corridor_1.
to represent progress.
So. from there we can look at the stairs again. for a
slightly different reason. We can reject the idea of going up
them. or we could choose to pick the lock
of the closet. with the new found hair clip.
When we do that. we can either
dress up in cleaner's clothing
with what we find inside. going straight to corridor_3.
or we can return to
the corridor but it's again another new corridor
state. because this time the closet's open.
So. we can use that opportunity to give people
yet another reason why they shouldn't climb the
stairs. But if they do decide to dress up.
then they're back in the corridor with a dilemma.
Do they make their run for freedom. going up the stairs
to the courtyard. or do they undress and
end up back in the closet. tempted by the cleaner's
clothes again? So. this is just my simple
convoluted story. and you can see how already this
State Machine is getting quite complicated.
So obviously. this is the last game we're going to do like
this. In other sections we are going to use Unity to
keep track of the states. but it's very useful early
on. as a coding exercise to use a
complete Finite State Machine.
So. what are we going to do in this video? Well.
we are going to prepare ourselves for
adding this complexity.
So. we need to change
all references of freedom to corridor_0 firstly.
And this is a challenge. so what you're seeing on the screen.
with this green outline and the Pause Button at the bottom right
is a challenge slide. So. I want you to go
and rename all references to freedom to corridor_0
and get it running. Some hints for you. you need to change
the line in Update (). You'll need to rename your statement
method. You'll need to update your text.
and you'll need to update the key press options.
And have a think if there's anything else that
you need to do. For example. what
does lock_1 go to? What state does
lock_1 go to? And also. don't forget your enumerated list.
OK. so pause the video and go ahead
and make those changes now.
Fantastic! Welcome back! So. let's do that
to start with. Let's dive in and
obliterate this freedom
and call it... What are we going to call it?
corridor_0!
So. when I first change that in the if
statement there. I'm going to get a red indication
in that. that is not in the enumerated list. Well. you're quite right.
it's not! Now. we're running out of space in this enumerated
list. so I'm going to go into a new line and start
putting my next state in here.
corridor_0. something
like that! And actually. I'm just
for layout I'm just going to bring... There you
go! I'm going to do it like that OK. and I'm
actually going to put my curly brace on the line below.
The final thing that's missing is a comma.
on the end of line 10. OK!
Fantastic! So. we have our corridor_0
in our enumeration now. Another thing I'd like
to do is indent this first if statement. so
that they all line up. It's a very simple
change. but now all of our states line up. I prefer that!
Alright. so where else have we got freedom?
Well. we have state_freedom()
here. and what I'm actually going to do
is I'm going to change all of these state prefixes. I'm going to
remove all the state prefixes. Let's do that first.
How are we going to remove the state prefixes?
So. we go to the Search Menu.
and then Replace and anywhere that
we see state_. I'm
just going to take it away. Now. let's just check this. Hit this button
here. that says Replace.
and you should find it's just removing the state_
prefix. It seemed like a good idea before. but the whole
point of this video is getting used to refactoring
and reorganizing your code.
Fantastic! OK. so now that looks like it's
all good! We could run right
now. before we carry one. to make sure that that Find and Replace worked.
so let's just do that.
View the scene. Return. Mirror. Take.
Lock. Open.
OK. the only one that doesn't work is Open.
which is fine because we've already changed that method.
Fantastic! So.
now that we've got rid of the state prefix. we can now get rid of
this final freedom bit and call it corridor
_1()
which. of course. is red. So. let's go to
down to what was our freedom method
and rename it corridor_1 ().
And now. we need to change the
text and the key options. so refer to your GDD.
I spent a lot of time in creating this
second part of the game. thinking
about how it's all going to work and trying it.
And a lot of that time was spent staring at and
reorganizing this diagram. And I
would much prefer. when you're designing your game.
that you spend time looking at a diagram and editing
and changing a diagram. I don't mind if it's on paper
or the computer. then spending
a lot of time messing around with and changing your code. because
if it's not right in principle. at the
diagram level. then the code will not be right either. So. you're much
better off getting the plan right first. it's worth taking a little bit of
time. So. diving back to our code.
let's complete this obliteration of
the freedom state. So. this method needs to be corridor_0().
I'm just going to say you are
in a corridor. for now.
We will leave "Press P to
Play again" for now. Let's just leave that where it is.
Of course. more needs doing but I'm going to do that in
a different video. because it's quite a lot of work. and you may well
have a different story. In fact. I hope you're creating
your own story here. And if you are.
I don't want you to have to watch me fill out my tedious story.
so that's why I'm going to leave that till later. But what we need
to do. for now. is complete the job of getting rid of freedom.
So. do a search. Control F or Search and
Find for the word freedom. and you'll see straight away here is the
reference. So. from lock_1. where should we be
going? Let's have a look! Well. it's actually in the previous part
of the State Diagram. Lock_1 should
take us to what was called freedom. I won't change that other
diagram. that is now called corridor_0 on the
left hand side here. So. this is one more
reference that needs to be changed.
So. let's just do that now.
This is on my line 87. against the lock_1() method.
OK. now let's keep searching for freedom.
The only final thing to tidy up is. there's still a freedom
left in the enumerated list. I'll take it out.
No more references to freedom.
so all that remains is to run the game. after building
while saving.
OK. so building does not work because corridor_1()
does not exist. this is a simple typo.
I'm saying if we instate 0. go to corridor_1().
No. corridor_0(). Well done if you picked
that up before. So. the code builds
and it has no references to freedom. If I
now go back to Unity
and run. let's just make
sure it works. Now. when you're checking your code. here's a
tip for you. in this type of State Machine. Explore
like this. Start at corridor_0. go to
all of the side things before you progress. So. I'm going to go to
stairs and back and closet door. and...
Sorry wrong State Diagram. I'm going to go to
sheets and back. lock and back. and then mirror and back.
Then. mirror again and take. sheets
and back. lock and back. and then
I'm going to go to lock and then open.
Then. I've transitioned through every state. so let's just do
that to be fully sure it's working. S for Sheets.
R to Return. L for Lock. R to Return.
M for Mirror. R to Return. M for Mirror.
T to Take. S for Sheets. R
to Return. L for Lock. O for Open. etc.
You get the idea! Go through the whole lot! OK fine.
it works! We have made our foundational
change. Our simple. very very simple change of code.
our I wanted to show you the techniques like Find and Replace.
I wanted to show you the idea that you can indent your
if statements. Let's go ahead and do that consistently.
You can indent them slightly differently. even the first line can be
indented. so all the states line up well.
I wanted to show you how you can put your enum states onto multiple lines.
at the top here. if you want to. so that
everything reads nicely. And
now you are in a position where you really can create your
own game and just come back to me. when you want
to learn how to build and share it on the web. I really encourage you
to skip the next video actually altogether.
and to just get on
with writing your own logic and your own games.
Spend some time scratching your head over a state diagram
please. but if you really do want to watch me
fill out another 100 lines of code to
get my full game working. then you're very welcome
and there's a video waiting for you.
=======
Hey, welcome back! So,
our little text adventure game is a fantastic
start and it basically works. The
challenge is, it's possibly a little too basic.
Once you realize that you just press M,
T, L, and O
and that you're out and free, it's a little
unsatisfying. So, what I'd like to do now is lay
the foundations to make the game a fair amount more complex.
It's the same logic, the same code,
we're just going to get used to
some slightly tedious work of
adding more assets to our game, because this is
too thin. This is too simple. So, let's
take a look at the Game Design Document. So far,
this has been our State Diagram, and as you
just saw, if you go M, T,
L, O, then you end up
out of the prison, really quickly.
So, what I want to do is introduce a new level, if you like. We're not actually going to
use Unity's levels here or scenes, we're just going to add
more code, but I want to introduce a new dimension,
which is a new section called the
corridor. So, instead of freedom, what we're going to do
is we're going to go to a corridor
state, which used to be called freedom,
and that's why we start on the left hand side with corridor_0.
And from
there what can we do? Well,
we can look at the stairs, but we decide we don't want to go up them,
because we're going to get rumbled or put straight back in
prison. We could look at the closet
but realize the door is locked. We can
look at the floor and on the floor we see a hair clip,
which we can choose to ignore, returning to the corridor, or we can
pick up the hair clip. That takes us to a new
corridor state. I'm calling it corridor_1,
to represent progress.
So, from there we can look at the stairs again, for a
slightly different reason. We can reject the idea of going up
them, or we could choose to pick the lock
of the closet, with the new found hair clip.
When we do that, we can either
dress up in cleaner's clothing
with what we find inside, going straight to corridor_3,
or we can return to
the corridor but it's again another new corridor
state, because this time the closet's open.
So, we can use that opportunity to give people
yet another reason why they shouldn't climb the
stairs. But if they do decide to dress up,
then they're back in the corridor with a dilemma.
Do they make their run for freedom, going up the stairs
to the courtyard, or do they undress and
end up back in the closet, tempted by the cleaner's
clothes again? So, this is just my simple
convoluted story, and you can see how already this
State Machine is getting quite complicated.
So obviously, this is the last game we're going to do like
this. In other sections we are going to use Unity to
keep track of the states, but it's very useful early
on, as a coding exercise to use a
complete Finite State Machine.
So, what are we going to do in this video? Well,
we are going to prepare ourselves for
adding this complexity.
So, we need to change
all references of freedom to corridor_0 firstly.
And this is a challenge, so what you're seeing on the screen,
with this green outline and the Pause Button at the bottom right
is a challenge slide. So, I want you to go
and rename all references to freedom to corridor_0
and get it running. Some hints for you, you need to change
the line in Update (). You'll need to rename your statement
method. You'll need to update your text,
and you'll need to update the key press options.
And have a think if there's anything else that
you need to do. For example, what
does lock_1 go to? What state does
lock_1 go to? And also, don't forget your enumerated list.
OK, so pause the video and go ahead
and make those changes now.
Fantastic! Welcome back! So, let's do that
to start with. Let's dive in and
obliterate this freedom
and call it... What are we going to call it?
corridor_0!
So, when I first change that in the if
statement there, I'm going to get a red indication
in that, that is not in the enumerated list. Well, you're quite right,
it's not! Now, we're running out of space in this enumerated
list, so I'm going to go into a new line and start
putting my next state in here.
corridor_0, something
like that! And actually, I'm just
for layout I'm just going to bring... There you
go! I'm going to do it like that OK, and I'm
actually going to put my curly brace on the line below.
The final thing that's missing is a comma,
on the end of line 10. OK!
Fantastic! So, we have our corridor_0
in our enumeration now. Another thing I'd like
to do is indent this first if statement, so
that they all line up. It's a very simple
change, but now all of our states line up. I prefer that!
Alright, so where else have we got freedom?
Well, we have state_freedom()
here, and what I'm actually going to do
is I'm going to change all of these state prefixes. I'm going to
remove all the state prefixes. Let's do that first.
How are we going to remove the state prefixes?
So, we go to the Search Menu,
and then Replace and anywhere that
we see state_, I'm
just going to take it away. Now, let's just check this. Hit this button
here, that says Replace,
and you should find it's just removing the state_
prefix. It seemed like a good idea before, but the whole
point of this video is getting used to refactoring
and reorganizing your code.
Fantastic! OK, so now that looks like it's
all good! We could run right
now, before we carry one, to make sure that that Find and Replace worked,
so let's just do that.
View the scene, Return, Mirror, Take,
Lock, Open.
OK, the only one that doesn't work is Open,
which is fine because we've already changed that method.
Fantastic! So,
now that we've got rid of the state prefix, we can now get rid of
this final freedom bit and call it corridor
_1()
which, of course, is red. So, let's go to
down to what was our freedom method
and rename it corridor_1 ().
And now, we need to change the
text and the key options, so refer to your GDD.
I spent a lot of time in creating this
second part of the game, thinking
about how it's all going to work and trying it.
And a lot of that time was spent staring at and
reorganizing this diagram. And I
would much prefer, when you're designing your game,
that you spend time looking at a diagram and editing
and changing a diagram. I don't mind if it's on paper
or the computer, then spending
a lot of time messing around with and changing your code, because
if it's not right in principle, at the
diagram level, then the code will not be right either. So, you're much
better off getting the plan right first, it's worth taking a little bit of
time. So, diving back to our code,
let's complete this obliteration of
the freedom state. So, this method needs to be corridor_0().
I'm just going to say you are
in a corridor, for now.
We will leave "Press P to
Play again" for now. Let's just leave that where it is.
Of course, more needs doing but I'm going to do that in
a different video, because it's quite a lot of work, and you may well
have a different story. In fact, I hope you're creating
your own story here. And if you are,
I don't want you to have to watch me fill out my tedious story,
so that's why I'm going to leave that till later. But what we need
to do, for now, is complete the job of getting rid of freedom.
So, do a search, Control F or Search and
Find for the word freedom, and you'll see straight away here is the
reference. So, from lock_1, where should we be
going? Let's have a look! Well, it's actually in the previous part
of the State Diagram. Lock_1 should
take us to what was called freedom. I won't change that other
diagram, that is now called corridor_0 on the
left hand side here. So, this is one more
reference that needs to be changed.
So, let's just do that now.
This is on my line 87, against the lock_1() method.
OK, now let's keep searching for freedom.
The only final thing to tidy up is, there's still a freedom
left in the enumerated list. I'll take it out.
No more references to freedom,
so all that remains is to run the game, after building
while saving.
OK, so building does not work because corridor_1()
does not exist, this is a simple typo.
I'm saying if we instate 0, go to corridor_1().
No, corridor_0(). Well done if you picked
that up before. So, the code builds
and it has no references to freedom. If I
now go back to Unity
and run, let's just make
sure it works. Now, when you're checking your code, here's a
tip for you, in this type of State Machine. Explore
like this. Start at corridor_0, go to
all of the side things before you progress. So, I'm going to go to
stairs and back and closet door, and...
Sorry wrong State Diagram. I'm going to go to
sheets and back, lock and back, and then mirror and back.
Then, mirror again and take, sheets
and back, lock and back, and then
I'm going to go to lock and then open.
Then, I've transitioned through every state, so let's just do
that to be fully sure it's working. S for Sheets,
R to Return, L for Lock, R to Return,
M for Mirror, R to Return, M for Mirror,
T to Take, S for Sheets, R
to Return, L for Lock, O for Open, etc.
You get the idea! Go through the whole lot! OK fine,
it works! We have made our foundational
change. Our simple, very very simple change of code,
our I wanted to show you the techniques like Find and Replace.
I wanted to show you the idea that you can indent your
if statements. Let's go ahead and do that consistently.
You can indent them slightly differently, even the first line can be
indented, so all the states line up well.
I wanted to show you how you can put your enum states onto multiple lines,
at the top here, if you want to, so that
everything reads nicely. And
now you are in a position where you really can create your
own game and just come back to me, when you want
to learn how to build and share it on the web. I really encourage you
to skip the next video actually altogether,
and to just get on
with writing your own logic and your own games.
Spend some time scratching your head over a state diagram
please, but if you really do want to watch me
fill out another 100 lines of code to
get my full game working, then you're very welcome
and there's a video waiting for you.
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1:Unity/Section3/06-Re-Organising-Your-Code.srt