Hey. in this video I'm going to be completing
my code. in accordance with my Game Design
Document. using my story. but we do encourage
you to create your own stories. So. just skim
through this video and bear in mind there's
some useful code folding tips at around 11
minutes and 20 seconds. All I'm going to be
doing is taking this GDD here. and then.
hopping over the MonoDevelop and embellishing
this code with a lot more states here. and
a lot more methods. at the bottom. And then.
I will be testing the code. just to make sure
it works. showing it to somebody else. which
I encourage you to do by the way. Show somebody
else locally first. and then. when we go on
to build and share on the Internet. of course.
show a small group of people. so they can
look for typos and things that are confusing.
But that's about all I'm going to do in this
video. so as I say. if you want to follow
our story through. pick up a couple of tips
along the way. feel free to watch it. but
otherwise skip ahead and you know that you're
succeeding when your game is running and working
to your satisfaction. OK. so let's dive in
and get this finished. So. the first thing
we need to do is make sure that we have all
of our states in our enumerated list. We already
have shown you how to put the states onto
two lines. so to save you watching me type
it. I'm simply going to copy and paste across
all of the states. They're just simply every
state that we see in the Game Design Document.
you need to make sure is in your enumerated
state. Fantastic! So. that's the first thing
that we need to do. Then. what? Well. our
Start method is absolutely fine. it just sets
the state and moves on. Then. we've got this
list of ifs. so if you haven't already indented
on the first if. the brackets. you're welcome
to just to make things line up. So. what do
we need here? Well. we just need to add a
few more things in. We've got as far as corridor_0.
what we need to do next is add all of the
rest of the states that we just added to the
list above. So. again to save you the pain
of watching me type it all. there it goes.
just pasted. So. when you type these you'll
notice that they go red. They are red why?
Why are these method calls red? Because the
methods don't exist. So. a little tip for
you. is it may be easier to add the method
at the top here. immediately after the Update
method. so that the second you've added one
it disappears or the redness disappears. Let
me show you that in action with the first
in question. which is stairs underscore 0.
So. again to save you watching. I'm going
to put my story text in. Now. all of this
final code is available for you to download.
just like it was before. So. if you want to
do that. that's available on the next lecture.
You can just download the final code state.
so you don't need to type all of my story
out. if you do want to use my story. but I'm
no creative genius. so please consider writing
your own. So. here you go. the moment I put
the stairs_0 method in. this one goes black.
I think you get the idea. Alright. so now
the thing is to just paste all of the rest
of the methods in. checking a few things as
you go. and this may be useful if you're still
watching and you're doing your own story.
The things to be careful of is does the text
make sense? Firstly the first part of the
text. the description. does it make sense?
In context. when you look at what stage of
this story you're at in the diagram. make
sure your text fits. The next thing to say
is. make sure that your command here matches
up with your if statement. so when you've
told people. after the new lines. what they
can do then make sure that matches up with
what you've actually got. So. for example.
here we have three transitions S. M. and L.
Make sure it matches up. And then. the third
thing is make sure that the destination states
are correct. So. if we look at cell. for example.
and we look at our Game Design Doc. we should
be going into sheets. mirror. and lock_0 respectively.
which we are in this case. So. they are the
main things to check and make sure look right.
Alright. so that's the process of adding the
new methods in. So. then what do we need next?
Well. I'm going to add a stairs_1 in next.
There it is and I'm just going to indent.
so that it's all clear and consistent. and
stairs_1 has gone. And then. I would be continually
referring back to the Game Design Document
to think about what I want to say. what I
want to offer the player. etc. and what I
don't. OK. so the next method in question
is stairs_2. I'm just going down this list
in the Update function and just adding them
in one at a time. So. at stairs_2 is where
we start talking about the paper clip and
the options we have there. which at this stage
is just to return. It says that we're armed
with the paper clip. but we're still not willing
to go up the stairs. we're not brave enough.
OK. now it's out of order in terms of the
story. but as it's the next in my list. I'm
going to put courtyard in now. That doesn't
matter which order you put these in. it's
to say if you keep putting them at the top.
at least you don't have to keep scrolling
up and down. to see how far you're going.
in terms of the other methods you've got to
write. and then. floor comes in. Again. all
of these. I'm liking the text to be indented
consistently. OK. and then. corridor_1 and
corridor_2. Now. it's difficult to. because
it's a kind of nested loop with lots of. you
know. lots of different ways you can go around.
It's difficult to test it. until you finish
this. so you might feel nervous writing this
many lines of code without testing. and if
you want to you can stop and test. but it's
difficult because you need all of the methods
to be there. in order to be able to do all
of the state transitions. So. I would just
carry on with confidence. if you can now.
and just get all of these written in. And
immediately. that you see that something needs
changing. that's the time to change it. That's
the spirit. as they say here in Britain. [Laughs]
So. that's what you want to be doing. So.
this is the graph. the hard graph. and hopefully
you like writing and you like being creative.
If you don't. then maybe one of your friends
could do the actual story bit for you. If
you're going to make games. a huge part of
it these days is about creating the assets.
It's particularly the case now that we have
such powerful game engines; you tend to need
much less development effort than you did
before and much more artistic effort. So.
this is the artistic effort. you know. There
is a better way. of course. of creating this
engine and of an artist entering this information.
but it would use code structures that are
a little bit beyond this stage of the course.
This is a little bit cumbersome but it's not
bad. It works and it's pretty flexible. It
allows you to create an adventure game. with
a pretty good branching story. you just need
to be careful your Game Design Doc doesn't
get too crazy and convoluted. So now. I have
a method for every single state. Do I have
if statements for everything that's in my
enumerations? So. let's try building. It seems
to work. let's go into Unity and try running.
OK. so what I'm going to do is I'm going to
go into and out of every state. so Sheets
and back. Lock and back. Mirror and back.
then Mirror and Take. OK. Then. Sheets and
back and Lock and back and Lock and Open.
"You're in a corridor. "Press P to Play again."
So. we have a problem. Now. what state are
we in? Look at the Console. it's logging out
to corridor_0. so there's something wrong
with our corridor_0 function. and I think
that's just because I didn't update it. So.
where's my corridor_0? You can use Control
F to find remember. and I'm going to do that.
Corridor_0 and just you can go up and down
in the Up and Down Arrows. until you find
the method. There you go. so corridor_0 is
just incomplete. it doesn't make sense. it's
a hangover from the freedom method that we
had before. so corridor_0 needs to be a lot
more exciting than that. so let's change it
and embellish it. There you go. Now. we have
these three different options and all the
key states. Fantastic! So. now let's try playing
again. Now. by the way. if you were still
in Run State. actually which you are. look
what happens. Even if you're leaving Unity
running. if you save your script. actually
it will update so you can just carry on from
here. "C to view the Closet.". but you must
be click into the game. for this to work.
C to view the Closet. R to Return. F to inspect
the Floor. R to Return. S to climb the Stairs.
R to Return. Good! So. F and then H takes
us forward. P to Pick the lock. or S to climb
the Stairs and retreat. pick the lock. return
revisit the closet. dress up. undress. seems
to work. Dress up. stairs. Great! And we're
free! Yipee! OK. so I did a very quick flick
through there. making sure that the navigation
worked. What you'd want to do. as well. is
go through very carefully proofreading everything.
Very very common errors here. there are going
to be with spaces. a missing space. because
when you look at your code it's very easy
to miss this space on the end of a line here.
right here. before you concatenate on. So.
make sure you've got those spaces in. that's
going to be your most common probably cause
of error here. Your other cause of error is
just not going to the right destination states.
So. this would be a great time to scroll up
and down your code and make sure the indentation
levels are consistent. the text all looks
good. I'm looking that this orange line here
is aligned and that these brackets form a
line. and I'm just generally making sure that
I'm leaving this code. I could indent as if.
if I wanted to. wherever there's two ifs together.
I could choose to indent them. together if
you see what I'm saying here. so that I can
see the key codes right next to each other.
This is just style. this is just choice. it's
all just white space. But what I'd like to
do. before I did anymore with my game. is
make sure that the code is really consistent
and clean. and it's this kind of attention
to detail that tends to reduce errors. The
other thing you need to do and suck up sometimes.
like we did in a previous video. is sometimes
you need to just make a bulk change to some
naming that you settled on before. like state_
for these methods and just realize that's
a hassle. It's a hassle to copy and paste.
it was just genrally a hassle. so we got rid
of it. So. the moment you get an inkling.
you'd be better off doing a renaming somewhere.
just go ahead and do it. straight away. because
it's almost certainly that you're right and
it will save you a lot of trouble later. But
I think that's looking pretty good now. It's
all there. it's all indented nicely. it's
all looking consistent. and just going up
and down the code a few times just to check
can really help you to see any patterns and
spot any errors. So. now that we've got quite
a lot of code. this is a great time to introduce
a couple of suggestions made by students.
Just to show you that we listen to students
feedback. here is a suggestion firstly by
Trevor Stocks. He's saying that we should
show you how to collapse sections of code.
so let me show you how to do that. If you
go to MonoDevelop and Preferences and then
down to Text Editor and General. you can see
Enable Code Folding. this option here. MonoDevelop.
Preferences. Text Editor. General. Enable
Code Folding. Once you've done that. you'll
get these little tree like icons. on the left.
and it lets you collapse down your entire
code. so the imports. the main class. and
then the Update method. for example. and then
each of these sub methods. So. that can be a really
helpful way you of seeing what the state of your
code is. so have a go with code collapsing.
And then. I want to show you a second suggestion
from another student here. which is Anthony
Mckeever. Thank you. Anthony. he suggested
using the Hash Region Syntax. so let me just
show you how to do that. and that's particularly
useful in this game. So. we have our definition
of our enum. our Start method. our Update
method. but then below that we have something
that's basically a whole massive group of
state handler methods. So. if I put #region
then State handler methods. it'll come up
in purple. and then. at the very bottom of
the code I go... Probably here would make
most sense. #endregion. Now. look what happens.
If we scroll to the top we can go to our Update.
but then. we can collapse down our state handler
methods. You see that? So. now it reads really
nicely. we have the main class. which if we
collapse it down everything has gone away.
And then. we have all of our methods. our
Update. and then. all of our state handler
methods can be expanded out. So. you can logically
define this however you like. so try #region
and #endregion. Thank you very much. to both
Anthony McKeever and Trevor Stocks for these
great suggestions. It all looks good go me.
so that's fantastic! We have a much much more
interesting much more nuanced story now. so
I really hope that if you've followed it to
this point. with my story. I hope that you'll
stop and that you will make your own story
now. Maybe make a new project together and
write your own story in that. or just go ahead
and get the code. so that you know the structure
is right. You could have your own story. with
the same structure. So. what that would mean
is that you have exactly the same branching.
you just change my wording a little bit or
translate it maybe. If you're not English.
how about you translate it to your native
language. that would be a great thing to do.
And what I really really want you to do is
show you how to build and share this game.
that you build it and that you share it and
that you let other people see it and you share
it on the course. and we'll talk about that
in another video. So. get creative. get going.
You now have an engine to build an arbitrarily
complex or large text adventure. Just as you
do so. make sure you put plenty of points
in where the thinker is allowed to simplify.
like the transition from the cell out. When
we left the cell here. we decided not to allow
people back to the cell. We also decided to
ignore that we're carrying the mirror. etc..
otherwise the whole thing just goes crazy.
very quickly. Cool! Thanks for following this
far. and I'll see you soon!