Hi, I'm Sam and you may not have heard from me before, but I'm
helping you out with upgrading the Text 101 project
to Unity 5. I'm going to be showing you how to do that in
this lecture, and I'm also going to be showing you about the cool new build
target that we have in Unity 5, which is Web GL, and that is here.
It basically allows you to run your games in a browser, without any plugins
installed. OK, so let's have a go at that and dive right in!
So, the first thing you'll notice here is that I have two versions of Unity
installed. This is relatively straightforward to do, even on a PC.
What we need to really do is rename this folder, before
installing. And the default folder, where you installed, is called Unity,
and then, you can rename that folder too, so you can keep track of which versions
of Unity you have. This is great if you are going through sections
which are on Unity 4, then you want to stay in Unity 4 so that you're on the same
version as Ben. Otherwise, if you want to
try and upgrade things into Unity 5, you want this Unity 5 version as well.
So, that's what we're going to be using today. I'm going to fire that up!
As you can see, this screen looks a little bit different from Unity 4, and
if we go to open our project, if you don't
already have it open, we can go and find that folder. Hit Open
and what it's going to do is, it's going to prompt us to upgrade.
Now, this is a very cleaver little tool that will even reach into your code
and change that as necessary, refactor that as necessary, in order
to make the API work. There are some things that it can't do, but
for the most part, it will actually be able to do a good job of upgrading your project
for you. So, let's hit that button and see what happens, and then, I'll
walk you through some of the changes that it has made to the
project folder. OK, so as you can see, everything seems to be working. If
we open up the Game scene and hit play, it's
indeed exactly the same game as we left it. Now, I'm going to
go into an app called SourceTree, which is
here, and SourceTree basically just
keeps track of changes to my files in the project. So,
here are the changes, since we've done the upgrade, and you can see them in this little
area over here. No code changes,
none of these are code files. There are a few, these question mark files are new files,
and basically, they are
things like well Clusterinput, we're not really interested in. Project
Version is quite interesting, because now this file tracks which
version you were using when you created this project. Unity adds and
connects our new services by Unity, and then, obviously the project settings have
changed in format slightly and that's what's been upgraded there. But
not really very much to speak of, and certainly no code changes. We'll
be seeing code changes in later sections, but in this one very
simple game, very simple upgrade process as well.
So, let's take a look at one of the really cool new features, that is available
in Unity 5. So, I'm going to switch over to Unity,
and then, I'm going to go to File, Build & Run.
In fact, I'm going to go to Build Settings, rather, and
I'm going to go to select the WebGL
platform. Now, this is new, you won't have had this in Unity 4,
but what this does is, essentially like the Web Payer but allows you to run it without
installing plugins, so it does it entirely using web technology,
the new WebGL technology in fact. So, if we select this
as our build platform, and then, we hit Build And Run,
we want to create a build folder here. So, I'm going to create a new folder,
call it Build, and in here I'm just going to give it the
name of Text101, simple.
Save that and it's just going to go through the build
process very quickly. And it's very cleaver, it's going to be compiling down to Java
script, which is the language of the web, and once that's done, it
should pop up a browser window for us to play our game in.
As you can see now, it's actually compiling that C++ code that it was just generating
into Java script, as I said, and after this step,
it should be done. Now, how long this takes is going to depend
very much on the speed of your computer, but it shouldn't take longer than about
5 minutes in general.
And this is the result! A webpage just pops up
and allows us to play the prison game, just like
this, right there in our web browser. And there is no plugin installed
here. I don't have a plugin installed, like Ben does, so you can know for sure that
this is just using standard web technologies.
OK, now it is your turn to
create this Web GL build and share it with your friends. I'd like you to
check your game in Unity 5 very carefully. Make sure there are no bugs that
have been introduced by the upgrade process. Then, I'd like you to make
a Web GL build, just as I've shown you, using these
instructions and share that build on social media for your
friends. OK, so you can pause the video, have a go at this, and
when you're done, it is time to move on to the next video.