So. welcome to the end of Text101!
Did you write your own story. or did you just copy out ours?
If you copied out ours. great! You've learned a lot. but please
go ahead and write your own stuff. because the whole point of making games is being creative
right. Be brave. do it. be fun! So. maybe
you could ask a friend to write it. build it for the web. and share it
on Udemy's discussion groups and/or on
www.completeunitydeveloper.com right. That sounds about right. Yeah!
Yeah absolutely right! A game isn't a game unless people play it.
and it's not going to be played unless you share it with other people. So.
you have to take the courageous step of actually
putting your product. what you've created. out there.
And it's painful and it's hard and it's tough and you have to do it.
because that's the only way you're going to grow. So. share your game.
just make sure you do that throughout the course. and make sure you share your games.
Cool. not much more to say. I hope you enjoyed Text101.
We'll be revisiting the story. at another point. as a surprise for you.
but for now. see you soon! Bye!