Hi, and welcome to Battle Tank! This is going to be an open
world, head to head to head, tank battle game, just you against one
other tank, with only the terrain to get in the way. They'll be a heavy
focus on the control systems here and how we really get into the nuances of
controlling something like a tank, but there will also be some basic AI in the enemy
tank or another local player can take control. We're going to be looking
at a simple User Interface. We're going to be looking at creating and sculpting a
very simple terrain and there's going to be a lot more stuff, apart from
that in this section. So, what I want you to do is start
off with a little challenge, even in this intro video, which is I want you to go ahead and
do some research about tank games. Watch at least one YouTube
video of a tank moving. Watch at least one YouTube of a tank game,
Why not play World of Tanks! World of Tanks is free and it's multi-platform.
Take some notes on the controls, on the features of the game,
and on the challenges that you may come across when you're trying to develop
this game, and then, share your notes with us, before moving on,
and we'll look at the Game Design Document next!