So. welcome to Game
Design Document or GDD. In this video. we'll
talk about and create the concept rules and initial requirements for the game.
In fact. it's going to be your challenge to write that stuff out. once we've discussed the game a little bit.
We'll iterate around a loop. by the way. while making this game. which I'll introduce
you to in a moment. We'll be constantly asking
what's least fun. so as we go around this loop of working
on the terrain and the tank and the weapons
and that sort of stuff. we'll keep coming full circle and say what's least
fun and try to make sure that the thing is always getting more and more fun! All the time
it's getting more fun. it's worth developing. Remember that we're not
triple A studios here. right. We don't have a million dollar art budget.
so we need to try and do the best we can with our lower budgets and focus on our
game being fun. So. let's find the essence
of the fun in this game. is basically what I'm saying.
So. we're going to write out concept rules and requirements. but before we do. let's
go and take a look at the research that we did from the last video. So.
I've played some World of Tanks. I've actually really enjoyed it. Probably played it a bit longer than I should have done.
I've had a look at some tank videos. done a lot of things I've asked you to do. basically. Did you
note how the controls work in World of Tanks? The left stick moves your tank around
in a forward. backwards. left. right sort of
way. but the gun stays pointing in the same position.
Your right stick actually moves the gun aim point.
so that's quite a novel form of control. We'll experiment with a few different ones. before deciding
for sure that this is what we want to do. So. this is like a fly by wire tank that they're
using. where the turret will always point in the same position.
unless you either tell it to point elsewhere or you climb up a piece of
terrain that makes it impossible for the turret to point in that position. So
It's quite interesting. it works quite well. it's certainly good for shooting. It doesn't really give you
much of a sense of driving the tank. I don't feel. I would quite like to have independence.
be in control over the two tracks perhaps. on the two triggers on a controller.
but you know. we can play with different types of control. But the general idea we're going to
have is just single tank vs. single tank in an open terrain. something like we're seeing here.
with hills in the way so that we can get some cover. And you could
take a certain number of shots. before you're dead. and you'll have a simple indicator on the screen saying
how much damage you've taken. And then. the other tank will either be an AI
or it'll be another player on split screen. possibly on a second
monitor depending on how we get on. And the idea is to position yourself. get in range.
and then shoot the other tank. and it's going to be a lot of fun! So.
what I'd like you to do is write out what you think. in
your words. the concepts. rules. and requirements are for this
game. And remember that the concept is just like a paragraph. saying what
it's all about. The rules are how you win. how you lose. what you're allowed
to do. what you're not. And the requirements. think about sound effects. think about
art. think about music. think about things like that.
And then. when you're finished come back. share those things. by the way. with your
fellow students in the discussions. so that we can see what your ideas are
for the game. It'll also steer the direction of this section slightly. for those people who are taking it as
it's produced. and then. pop back in and I'll talk you through my concept rules
and requirements. Hey. welcome
back! So. I'm just going to say that the concept is a simple tank battle in an open world.
and it's a head to head tank combat game. And the terrain will be used for
tactical advantage and the focus will be on flow and feel. We just want this to flow
well and feel good. The rules. well you can move anywhere in the terrain. which is surrounded by mountains. so you
can't get out of the terrain. Both players start with finite health and ammo.
and each direct hit takes away health and the last player standing wins.
So there are the simple rules and the requirements. Well. sound effects wise. we're going to need
a gun firing. an explosion. maybe the barrel going up and down. the turret moving.
and the engine sound. Static
meshes. we'll we're going to need a simple tank comprising of tracks. body.
turret. and barrel. But in the first place. I'm just going to use primitives inside Unreal. and
we'll actually build up the mesh requirements later. might buy in an
asset have some custom assets made. We'll see as we go through but I want to show
you how to start with just using primitive objects. just to test the control system and test the audio
of your game. Later on. we'll want to add some textures for visual flair
and we'll want some sort of background music to create some tension in here. which will be fun
of course. Cool. so that's the GDD done! It's easy isn't it
GDD's! They are worth doing. they don't take long. and they do make you think about
what's involved. You'll probably never look at it again. You might look at it again and update it.
but it's not to be stressed about. but it's definitely worth the exercise of just doing.
So. how are we going to build this game? Well. let's do an Iterative Cycle.
Let's go around and around and around making sure that it's always fun at every stage. So. we'll build the world
first. just get a very simple terrain out there. Then. we'll put something
representing a tank. It'll probably start just as a cube. just a block. Then.
we'll think about the controls. because a block sitting in a world is a bit boring. so we'll think about how
we're going to control this thing and we'll try at least one. perhaps a couple of options for control schemes.
Then. we'll think about this Player 2 thing. which is either a
human player or an AI. We need something to shoot at. alright. even if it's not moving anywhere
in the beginning. Then. we'll get some basic User Interface. We need to
know whether the other player is nearly dead and how many bullets we've got left and when we can fire next.
Before going back to the world and saying: Right the world is probably really boring. Let's make it a bit
more interesting a bit more challenging. and then. we'll keep going around the loop again
and again and again. Weapon systems will be included over here in Tank.
Controls will be everything to do with controls. Player 2 is Player 2 in AI. UI
is User interface. So. you get the idea! We're going to go around this loop again and again and again. until
we've decided our game is good enough for an initial shipping.
So that is is! That's a Game Design Document. that's pretty cool! Your challenge was earlier on; you've already
written out your ideas. So. if you haven't done it already. write
and share your GDD. Write your understanding of the concepts. the rules. the requirements.
and share your work with us. And I will see you in the next video. where we'll actually set this
project up in GitHub. on the web this time. and
take a little look at Version Control a bit more deeply. before diving into the project!