So, welcome to
Creating & Deleting Landscapes. In this video, we're going to be creating
an Unreal project in an existing repo, which is a little bit different to what we've done
before. We'll talk about what's good about landscapes in the Unreal Engine, straight after this
slide. I'll show you how to add a landscape in Unreal, which is
slightly trickier to find than you'd hope. I'll show you how to delete a landscape in Unreal.
So, what's good about landscapes?
Well, they use 1/6 or so of the storage of a Static Mesh.
Another way of doing a landscape, you may think, would be to use Blender or Maya or 3D Studio or
ZBrush or blah, to make a Static Mesh, and then, import that as a
landscape. The problem is that a Static Mesh uses 24 to 28 bytes per
vertex of data, whereas an Unreal landscape only uses 4. So, you
end up with about 1/6 of the storage space, much better.
It supports Level of Detail and level streaming, if done properly, so it can
break the landscape up into parts and decide which of those parts to show at
what level of detail and which to load when and which to not even try
and render when. And we'll be talking about that in the next video, exactly with the details, but it's really good
for this. It can support up to 8196 x 8196
pixel heightmaps for import. Now, what's a heightmap? A heightmap is a black and white image
that tells the system, for each part of the terrain, exactly what
height it should be. Now, if you were to use a typical scale in Unreal of 1
meter resolution on your terrain, then you could potentially
specify up to 8 x 8 kilometer maps, and make
them in an external program and then import them in to Unreal. So that's pretty cool, but it's also got
very good built in tools for sculpting and manipulating terrain, and that's what we're going to be
using. And the landscape or terrain system works very well with mini-maps.
If you do want an example of an external tool that's great at making procedurally
generated, very believable, terrains, then look at Terragen or World Machine.
So, remembering our iterative Cycle. We're here in World.
Then, we're going to move onto the Tank controls, Player 2, and then, back to the World. So, we're only going to
make a first look at this world, this time. We're just going to make a very basic world,
then get some type of a tank down and then go around and around this iterative cycle.
OK, so let's take a look at how to do it! We need to go back a step,
of course, because where were we? Well, I was busy adding these very boring files to Source
Control, that were just documentation files, to show you how to use the readme. But what
has this done on my disc? When I said Clone Stroke New, I had a
Destination Path in here of my standard repo directory, which meant
that SourceTree has kindly made me a directory called 04_BattleTank, which just has these
three files in it. What we need to do now, just as we did back in Building Escape, is make
a subdirectory that actually has our Unreal folder. And then, we need to talk about a subtlety,
while it all loads with the .gitignore. So, let's open the Epic Games
Launcher, and we're going to point it to our repos
folder that we just made, where the repository already exists. The smoking
gun for a repository is the .git file and the .gitignore file, but the
.git file is the reliable one. So, here we are in
the Epic Games Launcher. Let's launch the engine! I'm using 4.10.4
Any 4.10 will do. You could even use a slightly later version, but I do recommend
not going to far ahead of that, if you're watching this at some time in the distant future.
So, we're going to make a new project! Let's think about how to make our decisions
on the new project. Always a C++ project because we can derive Blueprint
classes from C++, so we can always just have very thin
C++ classes and extend in Blueprint later. So, I always go
C++. Basic Code, we don't need any of the rest of this stuff. We can actually add any of this
content later on, and I'll show you how. Desktop, Maximum Quality,
No Starter Content, from the moment, that's cool! In the Battle Tank
folder, let's make a subfolder called BattleTank.
Now, just check the paths look right, and go ahead and Create
Project. Fantastic! Now, it's going to spend a little bit of time creating the
project, and then, eventually Unreal will open and Visual Studio will open. So meanwhile, let's go and
look here in the File System. Of course, a BattleTank folder has
been created, with all these files in it. That's great! Now, the .gitignore file. The
difference with this one, we got from the GitHub website, is it has a different syntax. It
says, all of these actually say Intermediate/*,
which means ignore anything in an Intermediate/* folder that is in this directory that I'm in,
in the .gitignore. And if you know there is no Intermediate/* folder, here in this
directory, it lives here in the subfolder. So, Intermediate/*
will actually not be ignored by this one. Hold on, it's just popping up
in front of me. If we can trust this with the .gitignore we had back in Building Escape,
we said */. Now, that means ignore Intermediate/*, including
in any subfolders, so we have a slightly different .gitignore file  in this case.
So the way to make sure that this operates properly, with this slightly different .gitignore, is
to simply move the .gitignore into the BattleTank folder. Before I show that, let
me just show you the problem and solution. Here, back at Source
Tree, now that all of these files have existed, look at the un-staged files. They include tons of Intermediates,
for the reason I've just explained right. So, what I'm going to do is move
the .gitignore into BattleTank. The advantage is it will now work, provided
that of course we stage our .gitignore file.
So, find anything that refers to .gitignore, stage it, and then you'll see
no mentions of Intermediate/*. Great, so that's working well! The disadvantage of this
method, of course, is that if we put anything at this top-level of the folders that will
be put under source control, but that's fine, we're doing everything inside of the BattleTank folder.
So, that's a perfectly good solution for now, and let's crack on with the
actual job of making a terrain. So, here we are in Unreal!
What map are we in, for a start? Well, we're in an untitled map, so I'm going to save
that, and I'm going to call it BattleGround.
OK, and of course what you always want to do, when you make your first map, is you go to your Maps & Modes
under your Project Settings, and then, make sure that both your default game map
and your default editor Map are the new thing, BattleGround. Cool! So, we
have a nice skybox here, but we don't need this floor. So, delete
the floor from the world, and you're in this situation now, where we just have
pretty much nothing in the world apart from a Light Source, some Atmospheric Fog,
and a Player Start point. So, what I want you to do, slightly strangely,
as a challenge is I want for you to try and add your own landscape, without even telling you how.
See if you can find where it is and how to add it. The reason is, it'll help you get familiar
with the interface. I want you to start without using a web search or any documentation.
Use any settings for the landscape. When you do find it, we'll delete
it and re-add it later, because you need to have that skill, and then, share how long it
took you to find it, with the rest of us, and whether you need it to go to the web. So go ahead, try
and add any old landscape now!
So welcome back, where is the landscape?
Well, it's actually under Modes. Like a lot of things, when you first start, you're either going
to get content like pre-existing assets from some starter pack, which we
don't have right now, or you're going to Modes. Now in modes, you can do
things like add Actors, Box Triggers, Lights, Visual Effects,
BSP Binary Space Patricians, which can be useful for meshing out levels,
Volumes all sorts of cool volumes, and then, All Classes.
And under All Classes, if we
scroll down, we'll find Landscape. So, one way of doing it is, you
just drag a landscape in. Then, we do that and there it is!
Now, it'll come in at a weird position, depending on where you let go of it,
but this is a perfectly valid way of doing it. Note, by the way, that once you
do that, it'll switch across to the Landscape tab, and then, you'll be on the Manage
part of that. And it's basically saying to you, do you want to create a landcape
here? So, I'm going to do it, because this is like you creating one in a rough way. It's the wrong
size, etc., but at least we've got a landscape in. Now, notice
that under Modes and then the Landscape tab, the Manage tab does something
slightly different. It has different options on it. It doesn't have very many options.
OK, so let me show you a second way, while
showing you how to delete a landscape. Deleting is easy. You just find it in the World
Outliner, right-click, Edit, and Delete.
So that's why you can add a landscape with confidence, because it's pretty
easy to delete it later. So, how else could you add a landscape? You could
go to the Landscape tab, from the Start. Now, the Manage sub-tab
will recognize there is not landscape in the scene and say, well, you obviously want to create one
or import a Height Map from a file, but we're going to create a new one.
And we're going to think about exactly the size that we create
this at, in the next video, because we want to think a little bit carefully about
where this is, i.e. at the origin or not,
how it's rotated, how it's scaled, what this section
size, the number of sections, and number of components. What does all this stuff mean? It's the topic
of the whole video, because we want to get it right, and we want to understand our constraints on our landscape.
So well done on getting this far! Hopefully you now know how to add a landscape
and delete it and where to find everything, and your project source control is all setup ready
to go. All that remains, of course, is to close everything.
It doesn't matter whether you've got a landscape, not got a landscape, we know how to delete them now. We're going to be
doing it in the next video. So with everything closed, I'm not going to stage everything. Now, I'm getting a warning
that my BattleTank.VC.db is bigger than 10 MB.
Well, we chose to ignore that before, so let's go ahead and edit the
.gitignore. Find
hmm generated by the engine. Where should be put it? Because we didn't write this, we need
to think about where to put it. It's not under any of these, so I'm
just going to put it at this top *.VC.db. This only
applies, of course, to you Visual Studio users, and this is the database file,
250 MB. That's the one we want to ignore. So save that.
I'm going to cancel the staging, re-add the .gitignore,
now stage everything, and now we're happy! We don't have any big files,
OK. So, there's two approaches of getting to your .gitignore. You either build it up from the scratch
yourself or you start with somebody else's and modify it, but you still need to know how it works,
otherwise it becomes a weird black box. So go ahead, make your commit, and I'll see you in the
next video!