OK, so welcome to
Landscape Setup & Scaling. What we're going to be doing in this video is looking at the
impact of scale on our landscapes, and eventually building ourselves a 1 by 1 kilometer
terrain like this, that's going to have detail down to the
half meter scale in it. And the lighting will be built so that it looks
clean like this, and we'll be making sure that we can preview at a reasonable
performance, including using something called a Light Mass Importance Volume,
which you can see in the middle here, which is just a little hack to get the lighting to build faster.
So, let's dive in and talk about terrain scale!
So, we really want to think about the scale of the landscape now. So, I'm going to demonstrate
a few things with some dramatic different scales, so you can see the effect,
and then, I'll put you into a challenge where you can generate your landscape. So, just watch along for now, and I'll
explain my thinking. So, what's going on? What are we seeing on the screen? We're seeing little squares.
Now these little squares are called quads. They're quads because they have four vertices,
and they happen to be squares at this point. Although, as soon as we start deforming the terrain, they
actually deviate from squares. We'll see that in a moment. The scale
relates to the size of those squares. If I made that 1,000 in the X,
it will automatically change the Y, by the way, because it wants to keep the
quads square, rather than long rectangles. Now the terrain is
ten times larger. So, what this is saying to us is,
we have a section size of 63 by 63
quads. So, if I was to turn that down to 7 by 7, you could see it, the 7
by 7 in each section. OK, a section is
also known as a component, so
the component, there are 8 by 8 components at the moment just like a chess
board, if you look along. The large squares are 8 by 8, so there are 64 large squares,
each of which has 49 or 7 by 7 inside.
So, how big is the terrain overall? Well, the scale is what sets
that. Again, if I set that down to 100, it gets ten times smaller. At 1,000
it gets ten times larger. At 1,000 we're saying, it's 1,000 centimeters
per quad, so it is
10 meters per quad. Alright, now you don't have to do the calculation yourself.
The 7 by 7 or the 7 by 8 is 57 here.
There's an off by one error but it's close enough. So, it's 57
by 57 squares, each square of which is 10 meters
or 1,000 centimeters. So, it's 570 by 570 meters
this terrain. Let's try creating it at this scale and see what the impact is!
So, I'm going to create it at this scale, and then, I'm going to just do some stuff with the brush.
OK, then we're just going to go into the world by playing and have a look.
Now, these squares on the floor are 10 by 10 meters, 33
by 33 feet, and that is the maximum resolution to which we can
adjust the terrain. So, if we look around very closely...
By the way, these strange effects we get in between the big lines, that's just the fact that the lighting
hasn't been built. So, if we look these are the quads, you can see them here.
What it is, when it's deformed, is it is four vertices. Let me just go to
a different tool. You can see in the square in front of me, that there's four
vertices, but they're bent in the middle. So it's two triangles. Basically a quad is
two triangles, and that's how it meshes them all together.
Now, if we're 10 by 10 size blocks, then it gives a very jagged outlook
to all of the terrain, because the maximum or the minimum size at which we
can adjust anything is these 10 by 10 blocks. The most that we can do is kind of pull up the middle of one of these
10 by 10 blocks, to create a sharp effect like you see in some of
these quads, if you know what you're looking for. Here a lot of them are flat, called Planer Quads.
Like here, these guys are flat, and then, these quads are bent down the middle.
It's a little bit tricky to see, but if you look closely, you'll see that there are
two triangles butted up against each other. Alright, so that's one extreme! I'm going to delete that
landscape. The disadvantage of that is, we can't quite get enough detail
in our landscape, and our hill outlines look very jagged.
So, let's go right down to another extreme, and just say, well how about we have 10 centimeter quads!
What's the problem with that? Well, one of the problems with that is that your landscape ends up
very very small, and you need a lot of sections and a lot of
quads per section to even get a reasonable sized landscape. Now, we have a landscape which
has an overall resolution of about 2,000 by 2,000. 2,000 by
2,000 what? 10 centimeter blocks. So, it's 200 by 200
meters only. Now, let's create it!
Sculpt it a little bit with a much smaller tool this time, because it's related to the
size of these quads. I'm getting really fast action on this
now. You can kind of see that this is not exactly the
scale that the tool is setup for. Now, if I go in and have a look at it,
what we see is look at this amount of detail! It's huge, because
each of these little squares is only 10 by 10 centimeters. It's almost too
much, you're almost getting artifacts or noise from it. Now, the advantage is
massively more detail. Look how smooth the hill outlines are! The disadvantage
is, you're actually going to hit a maximum terrain size like this! Let me show you!
If we delete the landscape, and let's go back and say, OK we're going to mandate
a 10 by 10 centimeter and we're going to hit Fill World. How big does it get? Well,
it's already as big as it can get. The maximum number of components we can have is 32 by 32.
OK, so that's what Fill World does, it just maximizes the number of components.
You could turn the selection size up in quads, and that would make the world
effectively larger, until you get to that 8196 by 8196
maximum OK. But that's 8,000 by 8,000
10 centimeter blocks, so only 800 by 800 meters. It's not even a
kilometer square and we've hit Unreal's maximum. So this
is one of the principle reasons you don't want to use such a small tile size, is you're not going to be able to
make a reasonably large city scale terrain like that.
So, just before I challenge you to create a terrain of a specific
size, I just want to show you a handy trick, which is, of course, that you could place in the scene
a cube for example. Now, if we
just drop that in the scene, set it to the origin,
go look at it, and then, say to ourselves, well how big is this cube? Well, they
are 1 by 1 meter, as standard,100 by 100 centimeters.
So if I scale this cube to say 1,000 on the X
axis and maybe 10 meters wide, then we have a kilometer
long cube. I could zoom out to see that, and back at the
landscape creation tool, you can still see this cube if I
zoom out. Remember that when you're trying to move around in the
W, S, A, D regime while holding the Right Mouse Button, you can use the
Mouse Wheel to change the speed that you move, so rolling the Mouse Wheel up or down will change your movements.
So here we see this 1 kilometer by 10 meter
long rod, and then, we can corroborate that with the fact that the landscape
is 8,000 by 8,000, 10 by 10 centimeter blocks. So, the landscape
is 800 meters and the rod is 1,000. So, that look about right.
OK, so that's quite a cool way of helping you scale. Alright, your challenge!
The way that you'll bring all of this together and really understand how the scale relates
to the overall resolution, etc. is by trying to get a specific landscape
to a specific spec that I'm going to give you, so I want you to create your own landscape.
Make it about 1,000 meters square. I say about because
we're dealing with powers of 2 here. Make each quad half a
meter in size. We're going to go for a compromise, a little bit more detail than we would have at
a 1 meter size. Use 8 by 8, that is
64 components, like a chess board, and go ahead and see if you can make the
terrain of those specifications right now.
OK, welcome back!
So let's take a look! So, we're going for 1,000 meters in half meter
quads, with an 8 by 8. OK, so we can set the 8 by 8 straight away, so
we're constraining ourselves to that. We want 50 centimeter quads,
so there you go! You might ask, what do you do about the Z scale? It's not super important, it doesn't
change the way that the terrain sculpting tools work, so
you can leave the Z scale at the default, if you wish.
Right so, how big is this terrain? Well, we want a kilometer. It's actually the
right size right now, because we've got 2,000 things at half a meter. So that
is a kilometer by a kilometer. Remember that you can look at this rod.
Now the rod is still here, but it is a little bit hidden,
so if I could just drop the terrain down. There you go! You can see it's about a
kilometer now. Alright, so you want to leave your terrain
with those settings that I've got on the screen there. You're going to end up needing a section size of 255
by 255 quads.
One section per component is fine, that's a
further optimization we don't need to worry about, for the moment, to do with how the level of detail handling works,
and let's just create that terrain! Great, so we have a
terrain! Now, I'm going to delete my funny rod measuring tool thing,
Cube it's called. I don't need it. This
weird effect we're getting here is a lighting effect, and
you may right now, depending on your machine, be having performance issues,
so let me just show you something. If you go to Settings and
then you can come down here to Engine Scalability Settings,
and if you're having performance issues, you can choose Low or Medium or
High, Epic, or Auto. Auto may work for you, and that will determine
what this ends up looking like and how fast your editor operates, alright,
so bear that in mind. Now, these issues here will go away if we do
a lighting build, so we want the lighting quality to be just down at Preview for now.
And if we build the lighting, it's going to take away these funny issues
between the sections, once it's finished. But I suspect that building this lighting may
give us a warning that we've got too large of a scene to be
doing what they call indirect or bounce lighting, without something called a Light
Mass Volume, which you may have come across if you've been exploring volumes here.
There's something called a Lightmass Importance Volume there. So, we may get a
warning, in a moment, that we need to use a Lightmass Importance Volume, because otherwise,
it's trying to do indirect or bounce lighting over such a large area that lighting building
is going to take forever. And it actually turns out that we don't really
need bounce lighting across our entire scene. We could arguably turn it off entirely
or put just a very small importance volume, which will
mean that only a tiny part of our scene actually has very detailed
bounce lighting. Let me show you their webpage, while my lighting builds.
You can read about it here just by clicking. I'll show you where I clicked. You go to
the Modes, Place, Volumes, Lightmass Importance, and click the question
mark, and that will come down here and show you that typically you have a massive terrain
they show around the outside the grid but only a tiny scene where the lighting needs to be calculated
fully and properly. So, we could do that! One way to speed
up our building time would be to just cancel the light building.
It actually is saying, "No importance volume found", the scene is massive, yada yada.
We could, for the moment, just in the middle of our scene... I'll just reset the position
of it, pop a Lightmass Importance Volume there, just a tiny one. Then,
you'll find that when you go to build the lighting that the whole
process of building the lighting will be a lot quicker, because it's saying well I'm going to ignore indirect
light bounces beyond 1, anywhere apart from in this tiny little volume.
And it may not look like it's quicker at first, but I think you'll find that it'll quickly
whip through. Remember before, I was chatting away for probably a minute and it only got to 50%
on my machine. This time I suspect it'll be a lot quicker than that, once it gets going.
So a couple of tips on speed optimization for you here,
if your machine is struggling with these larger terrains. Remember our goal here is to try and make a city
scale terrain, and so we are pushing a little bit. That's quite a
large area to be playing in, but it's perfectly appropriate for a tank game. So that's what we want to be doing.
So, we're coming to the end of the lighting build now. Actually, it still took
quite a while, but you'll see that all the components or sections have now
disappeared, and it's one homogenous terrain and I can now wonder around on it and
it looks fine. You shouldn't find that where you've put that Lightmass Volume is going to create any significant differences.
We'll worry about further terrain optimization later. What I'd like you to do is just
share with us whether this terrain is giving you reasonable performance.
One more objective way to do that is to go to the top of your viewport and click Show FPS
and play the game. So that you can see that here, my 1 by 1
kilometer, unmodified terrain is holding 120 frames a
second. I'll be interested to hear what your frame rates are, at this stage. Please post that in
the questions, and I will see you soon.