So, it had
to happen eventually, it's time to upgrade our engine version, this time, mid-section! We're
going to go to version 4.11. Now, in the online slides you'll see 4.7 on all
the slides, because I've changed the template, but of course, it's only version 4.11 I was using
from here but the differences are minor. We haven't done anything in this section yet that
makes any difference. So, in this video, Epic Games Launcher helps
you manage versions of the engine. It's pretty good at that, so we'll briefly see that!
Before you do anything, for you to remember to commit your project or take a
backup of your project first. Then, you can do a convert in place, which means that we
don't create a copy of the project, because you've got a backup, that is your copy.
And then, we're going to check our project runs OK in the new version, and then, close everything and
recommit. I'll also show you how to tag a commit in Github, so let's dive in and do it!
Unreal 4.11 has dropped, and one of the features amongst
many... By the way, if you want to know what's in there it's in your slides, but you could also just
go Unreal 4.11 and look for
this here, Unreal blog Unreal Engine 4.11 Released! There's
lots and lots of improvement. Most of them are runtime improvements, but it also has some improvements
relating to the speed of lighting builds, and as we're doing quite a lot of lighting builds,
inside the landscape creation, let's go ahead and upgrade
to 4.11. So, you come into your Epic Games... Oops, into your Epic
Games Launcher. You'll probably see a little 1 here. And if you don't already have
4.11 here then you click Add Versions, and the thing that comes up will allow you to choose
4.11. I already have it, so I can just go ahead and install. I'm going to go
with the Starter Content and the templates and Feature Packs, in my case,
because I want all the latest stuff. So, once you click
install, you're going to have to wait for it to download. If you're wondering what the progress is, you can read it here,
but you can also see that little black bar filling up. So, let's just let that finish and install
now, before we move over and upgrade our project.
OK, so now that download is done! Let's go ahead and click Launch!
It's going to open version 4.11. It may take a little while longer than usual,
and it's going to ask you which project you want to open. Now, before we go any further, go to
Source Control and make sure you have a commit
for your project, because we're going to want to make sure that if it
breaks anything that we can go backwards. Now, Unreal manages that for you. You can,
when you say Open, just say Open a Copy, which will make a copy of the game.
We've already got a copy, we've got a previous commit right, so I'm going to look for the thing
that says Upgrade in Place. So, let's try under More Options.
Here you go, Convert in-place! So, I'm going to use Convert in-place, which means it's actually
going to change my project file, and over in the Source Control,
we'll start to see those changes come through. There you go, it's started to detect them! Let's watch it, just for
the fun! So, the uproject itself, it's made a small change inside that text
file there, saying that the engine association is now 4.11. It's quite
cool! We can see the exact things that it's actually going through and changing. Now, what's it doing?
Let's take a look. Too busy to tell us right now. [Laughs] There you
go! It's compiling some C++ source code. OK, what else has changed?
We'll probably know once the actual game opens. So, here we are,
our battle ground in 4.11! Let's just have a look around, just make sure everything is superficially
works OK. It does seem to, that's good news!
Alright, let's take a look at Source Control, and it looks like, actually, the only thing that changed
was the engine association. Nothing else appears to have changed. I would be slightly
more comfortable, if I actually opened my source code and recompiled that or
just simply click Compile inside Unreal. And let's see if...
Yep, that seems to have compiled. There is no source code that we've written, of course. So that's it,
super simple! Let's crack on with the landscaping now!
So, here we are! What we need to do is to create ourselves a
special type of material first, in order to be able to produce
the landscape paint. Now, I'm going to just
do this for you, and then, I'll put you into a challenge where you can go ahead and do it. You can follow
me through if you wish, but again, I'm going to give you the opportunity to do it all for yourself, inside the
challenge. Now, something slightly strange has happened with all my panes here, in Unreal
4.11. I'm just going to kind of regroup things, so that
they are a bit more manageable on such a small, low screen
resolution. So, the Content Browser, I'm going to put it all up here. There you go! I've got my, kind of, basic screen layout back!
OK, so once you're convinced you're back where you were and everything is right with
the world, just close Unreal, and close Visual Studio, if you haven't already.
So, I'm actually going to do the commit with you this time, because I want to show you now to use tags
briefly. This is a good time to introduce it, so I'm going to go and get my file
name, over here, and I'm going to come back to the Source Control.
Try and get focus back. I'm going to Commit just as normal,
pushing up to the web. That's fine! Or I'll leave the push, for now actually, because I want the tag to go with it.
OK, so I've made a normal commit, but what I want to do now
is I want to click on Tag here. And then,
I'm not going to show you how to do this on the command line, because you probably already know
if you know how to use the command line. So, I'm just going to put tag v.4.11
and then, I'm going to tag a specific commit, i.e. this commit, not
a whole branch. So, what that's going to do, when I choose the commit
the top commit and then put 4.11 on it, it's just going to put this neat little tag here,
and tags will come up on the left. And then, what will happen as more commits come into this line,
the 4.11 tag will stay there, provided I've tagged a specific commit,
and that just reminds me when I upgraded to 4.11. I mean,
it's quite clear from the name of the lecture, in this case, but I just wanted
to show you how to use tags. So, that's it! In case you haven't already done it, your challenge is to upgrade your
project, go through the upgrade process I just showed you, ensure the new project runs
OK, and then, commit the changes and optionally tag the specific commit
with 4.11 or something similar. So, go ahead and do that now. Recap
the video if you need to, and I will see you in the next video!