So, welcome to Using
Landscape Layers. By the end of this video, you will have a very simple
visual metaphor of a landscape, with some very unrealistic grass and dirt, but
you'll have learned how to actually setup landscape materials,
which are multi-layered. I'll just show you the end result. We're going to create a blueprint that looks
something like that. This is a two layered material. And then, we're going to learn how to paint
it onto the landscape. So, let's dive in and see that work!
OK, let's get this landscape painting done! You can either follow me
through, or you can wait until the challenge, about midway through where I will recap, on
the challenge slide, the six major steps. So, it's up to you which way you do things. Do let me know in
the Q & A, by the way, whether you prefer to follow me through or just to watch me and
then to have enough details on the challenge slide to complete the challenge without
needing to be doing it as you go along in the video. Just let me know which you prefer. So
let's go! What we do in the Content tab is make ourselves a new material, because
the landscape is going to need a material. We're going to simply call it Landscape.
we're going to go into the material, and then, the next thing we need is, it must
be a layered material. So, we go into
Landscape, as a category, and we want Landscape
LayerBlend. OK, it adds a LayerBlend node to the Landscape.
What that allows us to do is have multiple different things feeding into the base color
of the landscape. In our case, we're just going to have green for grass and
just a brownie color for dirt, but you could have snow colors, you could have
all sorts of things. You could have textures, any complex materials could be blended in
here. We're just going to start with plain colors for now
OK. So, that's the Layer Blend Node. Also, if you
click on the Landscape Node, there's going to be an item for you to set, which is
under usage you've got Used with Landscape.
Again, they're both of the challenge slide. So that sets it as a Landscape Material, which means
that it doesn't accept more than one indirect balance of light for optimization,
and it also make various other behind the scenes changes, which make it suitable for landscapes.
OK, so we've set the Landscape Node as a Used as
Landscape, and then, the Layer Blend Node, we need to start creating layers on, because at the moment we
have no inputs to this node. So, I'm going to create a layer called Grass,
and then another layer in the Details tab, in the layers where it says
0 or 1 elements, you add another element. And we're just going to call that
dirt. Fantastic! So, how do we set the colors of these? Well, they're
accepting an input. What do we want to put in there? Well, we want a color
and the way to do that is to look for something called a VectorParameter.
And that's one way to do it, VectorParameter. It adds a VectorParameter node.
Again, that's on the challenge slide. You take the white overalll
parameters, it's a four element parameter R, G, B, and Alpha, which is the
transparency. That's all combined into that white node. You pop that into the grass,
and then, go ahead and set the grass as
a greeny color. Now, I'm
just going to exit Steam, because I don't want to be hearing about other people
playing games, and then, add another node. So, a way of adding a node is...
Another way of adding this VectorParameter node is to hold down V, and then, to click
in the map. So, that gets you a VectorParameter node, holding down V and
just clicking. Wire that one up to dirt and then go and set its color,
and there we go. So, what that
is now is, it's made the Landscape Material a two layered
material, and the landscape itself is set for use as
a landscape type. So, that's all we've done so far. Let's go ahead and save the material.
So, it's created a material, set the
usage, added a landscape layer blend mode, and added a couple of Vector
Parameters. Now, we're going to actually add the layer
information. Let me show you what that means. If we go into the Modes tab, back to the Landscape,
and then, where we want to go into Paint,
it's saying Target Layers here. And we don't actually have currently
any Target Layers to paint on. Well, that's because we haven't actually assigned this
material to the landscape yet. So, you go to the World Outliner, find
Landscape. Then, where it's asking for the Landscape
Material, let's give it the material we just created. So, now the landscape has the
material we just made. Back in the Paint option of the
Modes tab, where it says Target Layers, look there are our layers! Now, we're nearly there! We
can 't quite paint with them yet. Why not? Well, let's try! "The layer
has no layer info. You must create or assign a layer info".  A layer info is
both basically a map of where this paint is going to go. So, you click
a little plus here.
Sometimes it's a little bit buggie actually, in this 4.11 version,
so let me just see if I can get it to behave off back into
Paint, and then, it's the plus sign you want to click there. Create Layer Info.
Weight Blended, we want blended layers. We're not going to go with Non-Weight Blended, that's
more advanced. Let it just give, it's going to create a folder, and let's just let it use the
default name, Grass_Layer Info, nice and clear. Let's go back
and make another layer info for the dirt.
So those two assets it's just created, if we look in the Content,
are in a folder called BattleGround_sharedassets, and they're basically
maps of where this stuff is going to end up. Cool, so with all of those
steps in place, we're not able to come along and say right. Let's zoom out a little
bit. I'm just going to unlock my Mouse Wheel. There you go!
OK cool! Zoom out, pick yourself a brush size,
it's quite large in my case, and then, just start painting it in.
OK, so that's how you would paint the grass.
Now, remember you can roll the Mouse Wheel up to move faster. And then, the other thing
that we need to be painting, of course, is the dirt, which I'm going to be doing with a much smaller brush.
Now, if you get this type of
artifact, just wait for the lighting to recompile. There you go!
So, back down to Dirt.
So, if you're having any trouble painting like this, then you need to think
about A your brush size, B the brush falloff. So, if there's no
falloff, then we are painting purely with the new color.
And then, if there's maximum falloff, then we have a blend between the two colors, but
the reason we're having trouble here is because our tool strength is so low. If we're painting
with dirt and we want dirt to override everything, we need our tool strength to be very high.
So, with a 0 brush falloff and a maximum tool strength, look what happens. Everywhere
it touches, it puts pure dirt. You see!
And if we turn the target strength down, then
what happens is we end up with the green potentially showing through, depending
on where it has cashed into it. It's slightly messy the
way that it arrives. So, you want a pretty strong brush, all the time here, certainly for
this pass. I mean there's a whole lot to painting landscapes right, and all we want to do for the moment
is show you that this is a multilayered texture and that you can paint it on.
So, I'm going to finish this off after the challenge. I want you to paint your landscape. Create
a material for your landscape, if you haven't done it already. Set the usage used with landscape
on the Materials Node. Set
the Landscape Layer, well add in a LandscapeLayerBlend node, and use
Vector Parameters to set at least a couple of colors. As I said, add at least two layers
and create their layer infos. Remember when you come back out and go into the Modes tab, we're
going to need to create layer infos, so it knows what layer goes where on the map.
Then, paint the landscape from the Modes tab, and screenshot and share with us.
So, go ahead, pause the video, and get your landscape working now!
Welcome back! So, I'm just going to very rough and ready
get this landscape going. By the way, one problem that you may have is in the lee of these
hills, there's not enough light. So, the way that I'm going to combat that, very quickly,
is to come to Modes and then across to Lights. I'm going to add a
Directional Light. Now, it turns out it doesn't matter where in scene a Directional Light sits,
all that matters is its rotation. So, rotate it around till it fills
in the shadows a little bit for you, and then, you can
turn its intensity all the way down, till it's a subtle fill in effect.
And then, I'm going to move the light out of the way, so that it's not annoying me.
So, let's just move that right out, say underneath the world,
or if that's irritating to you, you can move it right up in the air. OK,
so that's a way of just being able to see what's going on in these hills. Now, it's just a
question of probably first painting the hills with a brown. And as
I say, you could go ahead and make a third material in here and make a white for snow if you wanted
to, but I'm going to do a really rough landscape to start with, so that we can iterate rapidly
around our circle and get on with the tank and then come back and
revisit the landscape and repeat. I'm making sure I have a strong tool but
also no Brush Falloff, so that I can just put this on the
mountains. I can go ahead and paint. Now, there are ways that you can do this, based on height
of terrain, which is possible and fine as well, but for now, I just want to go ahead
and do a really simple painting just of the hills just to differentiate them,
assuming the grass isn't growing on the hills. I'm going to do the hills first, and only
what matters from the ground level. If it's not visible from the ground level, it doesn't really matter, which is why I'm
doing it from down here right. And going to paint them. Now, this also landscape
could be a nice low poly landscape, which we could achieve by turning our number of
quads all the way down. It's a little harder to work with low poly, in a way, because the
tooling isn't completely default setup for it, so I'm not going to cover low poly
right now. But if you're really keen to know, well look. I want to make a simple landscape here
and not go for anything too real, and I want to know how to do a low poly, then let me know
and I will look to
potentially introduce that a little bit later.  But for now, I'm trying to give you the more general landscape
tools, which is that you can work with any landscape. And this stuff can be a little bit laborious,
you just paint it on. There's a lot more we can do with different layer modes, with different
brush types, etc. etc. We can tag things by height
yada yada, but the idea is that you just need to get the feel for painting
landscape, from where you're standing. Obviously,
this landscape is too glossy, we can sort that out later. It's reflecting too much sun, it doesn't look like
the grass at all because there's no image material in it. We can add
images in. It's not a problem, you need to add another node inside the Blueprint Editor,
and we'll iterate on the landscape as we go, as I say.
The purpose, for now, is just to get something really simple down
so that we have a landscape that is a visual metaphor,
for the type of landscape that we ultimately are going to want. Now, that may
be a photo real landscape, or it may be a really simple landscape,
like this one. That's entirely up to you. Now, I think from ground level the tank is not
going to be able to see that, so I'm going to come down a bit, using my W, S, A,
and D and just only paint
what we're going to be able to see. Now, I'm bound to have left some bits, but that's
absolutely fine for now. I'm just going to roll out. I've got one
of these mouse wheels. You can click a button, it's a Logitech and you can free the mouse wheel,
which is pretty handy. And then, I'm very roughly now with some
brush falloff going to just paint the
edges of the grass now. Now,
the potential problem with the Brush Falloff is, on the inside of that brush, we're going to get a little bit
of dirt color painted, but we can then come along with the
brush with no falloff and then we can sort that out later on.
Also, when we're painting with actual textured materials, we're
going to have a different type of node in the blueprint, which is going to control something called a
UV Map, which you haven't seen yet. And then, that will allow us to be a lot more
controlled with this, but for now, this works absolutely fine. So
now, I'm going to go to a high tool strength, but no Brush Falloff and a very very large
tool and just fill the grass in in the middle, taking out any of those
little problems we had with the green. And really, for now,
I just want a flat... If you make a mistake, Control Z, by the way. Make a really flat
messer, if you like, a table landscape area, so that we can get our
tank movement working on a piece of flat ground, without worrying about getting
stuck on things, etc. That's good, so were done! Go down to the ground level, have a
quick look around. Of course, we're moving relatively slowly because  it is a big terrain, and this has
given us a simple visual metaphor of a terrain and that's all we're looking for.