Hey guys and welcome to bonus video 1. Switching Cameras!
In this video I'm going to show you how to switch from first to third
person view. like that. Third person. first person. third person. first person.
and it's surprisingly simple.
Hey and welcome back! So I have solved my 100 lecture
limit challenge! I'm going to dive into BT100 now. and I
am going to show you how to change to a first person camera. that's been popularly
demanded over on our voting site. So if I just show
you that. if you go to voting.gamedev.tv. and you click
on UnrealCourse. you can see all the suggestions and things that people are talking about. And
quite high up here is "Switching from Third to First Person" views. and it got 35
votes but it's enough that I want to do it and it's pretty simple enough to show you.
So here we are inside Unreal Engine! The first thing I'm going to do. actually.
while we talk about feedback from you guys. is to fix a little bug. and for that
I want to thank DanM. who on community.gamedev.tv has
told us that if you change the way you do the UI. slightly. from the
video. then your line traces in the PlayerController may end up hitting the UI
effectively. And we want to change ECC_Visibility to ECC_Camera to get
around that. that will give you guys more options. So let's just do that! We
go into VisualStudio. we go into the TankPlayerController C++
under the GetLookVectorHitLocation or whatever you've called your method. and
when we do our line trace. instead o ECC_Visibility we change it to ECC_Camera.
And that just changes what it hits. and what it doesn't hit it changes the filtering
and can remove a bug for you. So I'm going to compile! While I'm
compiling. I'm just going to remind you that when you are at our side. like community
.gamedev.tv. or voting.gametv. you can actually switch between them if it stops
loading this thread. At the top here. you can just click
Voting there. Community there. and so on and
Udemy just takes you to the courses. OK. so let's see if that compile
has finished! I think it has! And if we just play the game. it should play exactly as
it was before. [Laughs] apart for our ego. that's fine. I was just inside the
terrain. So what I had there was. my camera was just inside the terrain. OK. so
nothing's changed. but if you decide to say put your health bar rather than
where it is here. on the tank. which kind of floats if the tank
depossess like that. Some people are putting their health bar in the corners of the screen.
If you're doing that then there's a risk that you line trace and hit your own User Interface.
and then things go wrong. then your barrel ends up sticking up in the air. So
that small change to the code that I've made there. inside the TankPlayerController
C++ will solve that. O.K. Now. how do we
get a first person camera working? You go to the tank blueprint. Let's
go duplicated the existing camera that's there. and then. with the new camera.
let's just move it and stick it on top of the tank and rotate it till its
about horizontal. Now. I don't know exactly where we want it until we look through it.
but something like that is going to be OK for me. So now. we have two cameras.
Camera and Camera1. I'm just going to Compile and Save. If I show you now.
nothing changes because we've not told the system to switch to the other camera yet.
So in order to be able to switch to the other camera we need some new input. so I'm going to go to the
Project Settings. Input. and I want you to bind an action. In my case. I'm going
to use a controller button. so I'm just going to say Switch or
Swap Cam. and then. I'm going to use the Gamepads
Face Button Top. which is the
Y button on an Xbox controller. triangle. I think. on a PS4
controller. Or use a key. no problem! So you've got a new Action Mapping.
so that gives you a Swap Cam thing there! Now I don't like these cameras being named the same. that's
really named meaninglessly. That is confusing. so I'm just going to say
3rd Person and then I'm going to say 1st Person on this guy. F2.
by the way. is a shortcut to rename. Oops. not F1!
F2. 1st Person. There we
go! Let's just Compile and Save that blueprint and go
into the Event Graph! Now. in the Event Graph. you will now have. if you right-click. a
Swap Cam event. of course. Now what I want
you to do is to see if you can make this camera swapping work. If you search for toggle.
come off the depressed and search for "toggle". you're going to find
some Toggle Active. Activation methods. which pretty much do
it for you. So look. why don't you just finish it off for the satisfaction of it. Search for
"toggle" node. See if you can make it work. [Laughs] it's as simple as that.
and you'll be surprised how easy it is. Of course. you're going to need to toggle both cameras. so go ahead.
pause the video. see if you can make Camera Swapping work then!
Awesome welcome back!
So let's see how this works! So if I push the Camera Swap button.
then I want to Toggle Active the (1st Person) camera.
and it automatically drags in a reference to it. You see that? And then. immediately after that.
it doesn't matter which order because it's going to happen so quickly we're never even going to
realize we Toggle active the (3rd Person).
And that's it! Now if we want to comment that block. we can just say Camera
Swapping. and that should
pretty much be it. Now. arguably Camera Swapping is a...
I'll just put that note back. sorry. Edit. Undo Delete selection.
What I want to do is take this Camera Swapping stuff. cut it. and put it in
Input Setup. because really it is just Input Binding isn't it? Why have it over
in the Event Graph. when it could be in Input? And that's the thing. these are all just Event Graphs and
you can move them around. That makes more sense to me. OK. Compile and Save and
let's see if it works. it may need a minor adjustment but let's see! So there I am. I...
Oh. I need the controller on. so I'm just turning the Xbox controller on now.
and as soon as it comes alive. which it has now. I can push
Y and there you go I swap! Now this other camera. there's something wrong with it. and that
is because the camera we are starting with. and well done if you
worked this out. this 1st Person camera is starting as active
and we don't want it to be active in the beginning. OK.
We want it to be inactive. in the beginning. so that the 3rd Person camera is active. in the
beginning. and the 1st Person camera is inactive. The problem with the 1st Person camera
being active is. we're just getting some arbitrary default camera view that we're switching
to. which is of the root transform of the tank in the middle. if both cameras start as active.
The whole point of this toggle here is that we're toggling the activity.
You see Toggle Active. so you need to start 3rd Person
active and 1st Person inactive. OK. so let's try that!
If I hit Y now. ah hah. and actually that's not far off.
that view. I'm going to stick with that and now I've got a 1st Person view! So there you go.
that has been done! So well done and I will see you later!
=======
Hey guys and welcome to bonus video 1, Switching Cameras!
In this video I'm going to show you how to switch from first to third
person view, like that. Third person, first person, third person, first person,
and it's surprisingly simple.
Hey and welcome back! So I have solved my 100 lecture
limit challenge! I'm going to dive into BT100 now, and I
am going to show you how to change to a first person camera, that's been popularly
demanded over on our voting site. So if I just show
you that, if you go to voting.gamedev.tv, and you click
on UnrealCourse, you can see all the suggestions and things that people are talking about. And
quite high up here is "Switching from Third to First Person" views, and it got 35
votes but it's enough that I want to do it and it's pretty simple enough to show you.
So here we are inside Unreal Engine! The first thing I'm going to do, actually,
while we talk about feedback from you guys, is to fix a little bug, and for that
I want to thank DanM, who on community.gamedev.tv has
told us that if you change the way you do the UI, slightly, from the
video, then your line traces in the PlayerController may end up hitting the UI
effectively. And we want to change ECC_Visibility to ECC_Camera to get
around that, that will give you guys more options. So let's just do that! We
go into VisualStudio, we go into the TankPlayerController C++
under the GetLookVectorHitLocation or whatever you've called your method, and
when we do our line trace, instead o ECC_Visibility we change it to ECC_Camera.
And that just changes what it hits, and what it doesn't hit it changes the filtering
and can remove a bug for you. So I'm going to compile! While I'm
compiling, I'm just going to remind you that when you are at our side, like community
.gamedev.tv, or voting.gametv, you can actually switch between them if it stops
loading this thread. At the top here, you can just click
Voting there, Community there, and so on and
Udemy just takes you to the courses. OK, so let's see if that compile
has finished! I think it has! And if we just play the game, it should play exactly as
it was before, [Laughs] apart for our ego, that's fine. I was just inside the
terrain. So what I had there was, my camera was just inside the terrain. OK, so
nothing's changed, but if you decide to say put your health bar rather than
where it is here, on the tank, which kind of floats if the tank
depossess like that. Some people are putting their health bar in the corners of the screen.
If you're doing that then there's a risk that you line trace and hit your own User Interface,
and then things go wrong, then your barrel ends up sticking up in the air. So
that small change to the code that I've made there, inside the TankPlayerController
C++ will solve that. O.K. Now, how do we
get a first person camera working? You go to the tank blueprint. Let's
go duplicated the existing camera that's there, and then, with the new camera,
let's just move it and stick it on top of the tank and rotate it till its
about horizontal. Now, I don't know exactly where we want it until we look through it,
but something like that is going to be OK for me. So now, we have two cameras,
Camera and Camera1. I'm just going to Compile and Save. If I show you now,
nothing changes because we've not told the system to switch to the other camera yet.
So in order to be able to switch to the other camera we need some new input, so I'm going to go to the
Project Settings, Input, and I want you to bind an action. In my case, I'm going
to use a controller button, so I'm just going to say Switch or
Swap Cam, and then, I'm going to use the Gamepads
Face Button Top, which is the
Y button on an Xbox controller, triangle, I think, on a PS4
controller. Or use a key, no problem! So you've got a new Action Mapping,
so that gives you a Swap Cam thing there! Now I don't like these cameras being named the same, that's
really named meaninglessly. That is confusing, so I'm just going to say
3rd Person and then I'm going to say 1st Person on this guy. F2,
by the way, is a shortcut to rename. Oops, not F1!
F2, 1st Person. There we
go! Let's just Compile and Save that blueprint and go
into the Event Graph! Now, in the Event Graph, you will now have, if you right-click, a
Swap Cam event, of course. Now what I want
you to do is to see if you can make this camera swapping work. If you search for toggle,
come off the depressed and search for "toggle", you're going to find
some Toggle Active, Activation methods, which pretty much do
it for you. So look, why don't you just finish it off for the satisfaction of it. Search for
"toggle" node. See if you can make it work, [Laughs] it's as simple as that,
and you'll be surprised how easy it is. Of course, you're going to need to toggle both cameras, so go ahead,
pause the video, see if you can make Camera Swapping work then!
Awesome welcome back!
So let's see how this works! So if I push the Camera Swap button,
then I want to Toggle Active the (1st Person) camera,
and it automatically drags in a reference to it. You see that? And then, immediately after that,
it doesn't matter which order because it's going to happen so quickly we're never even going to
realize we Toggle active the (3rd Person).
And that's it! Now if we want to comment that block, we can just say Camera
Swapping, and that should
pretty much be it. Now, arguably Camera Swapping is a...
I'll just put that note back, sorry. Edit, Undo Delete selection.
What I want to do is take this Camera Swapping stuff, cut it, and put it in
Input Setup, because really it is just Input Binding isn't it? Why have it over
in the Event Graph, when it could be in Input? And that's the thing, these are all just Event Graphs and
you can move them around. That makes more sense to me. OK, Compile and Save and
let's see if it works, it may need a minor adjustment but let's see! So there I am, I...
Oh, I need the controller on, so I'm just turning the Xbox controller on now,
and as soon as it comes alive, which it has now, I can push
Y and there you go I swap! Now this other camera, there's something wrong with it, and that
is because the camera we are starting with, and well done if you
worked this out, this 1st Person camera is starting as active
and we don't want it to be active in the beginning, OK.
We want it to be inactive, in the beginning, so that the 3rd Person camera is active, in the
beginning, and the 1st Person camera is inactive. The problem with the 1st Person camera
being active is, we're just getting some arbitrary default camera view that we're switching
to, which is of the root transform of the tank in the middle, if both cameras start as active.
The whole point of this toggle here is that we're toggling the activity.
You see Toggle Active, so you need to start 3rd Person
active and 1st Person inactive. OK, so let's try that!
If I hit Y now, ah hah, and actually that's not far off,
that view. I'm going to stick with that and now I've got a 1st Person view! So there you go,
that has been done! So well done and I will see you later!
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1:Unreal/Section4/BT100 Bonus - Switching Cameras.srt