So. welcome to
More Landscaping Tools! In this video. we're going to be showing you how to make flat
shading optional inside your landscape material properties. Importing and exporting
landscape heightmaps. which are an image file that represents the landscape layout.
Reducing the resolution of the landscape. There's one very simple way of doing this.
in a few clicks. If you want to go from high to low poly. with some limitations.
And importantly. using a texture in a landscape material. rather than
just having completely flat shading. So. by the end of it. I'll have
a finalized low poly landscape like this. which will actually have some material still
flat shading but actually have a material that has some texture to it like this.
and it will be an inescapable terrain where all the
sides are too steep for the tank to leave. So. that's important and we
have our battle arena. So. see you in there!
So. let's start with how to add a texture to our terrain. This
technique will apply to high and low poly terrains. In fact. I'm going to leave the
landscape material. so that you can either make it flat shaded or not flat shaded
very easily. So. let's go find a texture first! One easy way to do that is to go
to the Content tab. Add New. and then. Add Feature or Content
Pack. and this is a way of getting our starter content in after the events.
So. no point in starting the Starter Content. if you don't need it. but if we want it now we can just go to
Content Packs. Starter Content. and add it to the project.
Now. in that Starter Content under Materials. notice a couple of things. We've got
a couple of useful things in here. One is M_Ground
_Grass. So that's the grass material. If we look at it. we'll
see that under the Usage section. it does have use with landscape ticked.
so it is designed to be used as a landscape. And we'll find the same with the gravel. M_
Ground_Gravel. So the question is. how do we use these actual textures
rather than these flat colors? We want the flat shading still.
potentially. We want to be able to choose flat shading. on or off. Solid colors like. we might want
a solid color for snow. but we're also going to want some textures. so let me show you that.
What we do is. we go ahead and find our material. so
that's in Content. and then let's work on the FlatLand
one for now. And what we're going to do is replace these flat colors
here with actual textures. So what you do is you do a search for texture.
and you'll find Texture Sample. That's the one we want.
OK. so I'm going to get myself a couple of texture samples. Just
Duplicate and we're going to take the output of the
Texture Samples into the layers. So. that's the same as
using flat colors. The only difference is they're going to want some UV maps.
and that's going to tell these textures where on the landscape they're going to be. So. we look
for the Landscape section. Then. we're looking for
LandscapeLayerCoordinates. That's what we want! And you plumb that into both
of your texture samples. for both the grass and the dirt. And then.
all you need to do is. for the grass. you go and find the grass. So. you go over to
the Details tab. under the Material Expression Texture Base.
and then. Texture. use the dropdown. type grass.
and choose that. And then. the same for the
gravel. Now you've got two on the gravel. You've got a normal map and
a detail map. We're going to use just the detail. for the moment. that's just the color the albedo the
base color. The normal map would allow you to set some roughness.
Now talking about roughness. we have this absolute world position here.
We are not going to use that now. the flat shading. or we want the option to be able to use
it. so in a moment we're going to kind of find a way of commenting this out in Blueprint. But for now. let's just
check the effect of changing to Texture Samples. instead of flat
colors. So. I'm just going to save this up.
minimize. and then. when this recompiles.
we'll see the effect. I quite like the effect of having flat shaded low poly
but with a texture. The game The Witness. that fantastic puzzle game that came out in
2016. that has this type of effect. low poly but with
textures on it. And now you can see the effect. OK. We have
exactly the same painting as we had before. but now. we
can. with a sufficiently small brush. we can come in and paint
dirt where we want it. grass where we want it. and get quite an interesting looking effect.
I think. Fantastic. so that is how you use textures. You can use that on a high
or a low poly landscape. The other thing I want to show you is. how to make flat shading
optional. So. one very simple way of doing that is if you come in and hit
C for Comment. you can then put a Comment block. It's better. actually. if
you just. before you hit C for Comment. if you select the blocks that you want to comment
about. then hit C. and it'll put a Comment block around this. And you can
say. Wire to... Oops. if I can type correctly. Wire to
Normal for flat shading.
OK. Wire to Normal for flat shading. and then.
that gives you a group that you can move around. And if we just break the link. by right clicking.
and then save. we've got some nodes here that are ready to use if we want to enable
Flat Shading. So. that's pretty cool! Let's just save that up and see what that looks like.
and what's going to happen now is. we won't have the flat shading anymore. So.
on a high poly landscape this is what you would want. You'd want to turn off the Flat Shading like that.
and have smooth shading and this will look absolutely fine. There you go!
So. this is ready to go for a high poly style. alright.
You may get some repetition of your textures. it looks a bit odd on a large landscape.
and isotropic filtering on your graphics card will help with that.
But at the moment. we're just trying to make the first iteration of this landscape. alright.
So. I'm actually going to stick with low poly. so I'm going to delete my landscape material.
I don't need that. I'm going to leave FlatLand. I'm going to rewire it to Normal. like that.
I want to stick with low poly because I want to get off landscapes now. I want to move
onto the tank and moving and controlling the tank. The least fun thing about this game.
right now. is not the landscapes. it's the fact it hasn't even got a tank in it. right. But I want
to show you a couple of other landscape tools. just before we leave this. So. the first thing I want to show you
is the concept of exporting your own height map. So. you come to Landscape
tab to sculpt and then down to the target layers. You right-click. it's a bit
hidden on the height map. and you can say Export to File. So. I'm just going to do that quickly.
I'm just going to call it test. and if I go look at this
test. let's go look at the .png. you can see it's a small .png.
I need this one. because my landscape is relatively low res. You can see the
tiny bit of landscape I've built up on the right-hand side here. just a slightly lighter
coloring. Alright. so that's what a height map is. it's a top-down view. Now. luckily one of
our students. Chris. has provided us with a much more detailed height map. You're welcome to import
that. There it is! So. that is a height map that
has got a lot more detail. and it's created with something called TerraGen. Let me just show you how you would
import that. if you wanted to. What you could do is. you could add a...
Well. actually one of the easiest things to do here is just to create yourself
a new scene altogether. So. just make a new level. a new
empty level. saving what we've got. and then. work on another level if you want to
experiment high versus low. if you're not decided yet. So. in this new level.
we can then come to Landscapes. Manage. Import from File.
go grab the file that's attached to this very lecture. There it is!
Now. notice this is a 5 by 5 kilometer landscape. but we're just going to go with that.
for the moment. just so I can demonstrate what this would look like.
Now. what we need is a landscape material here. so let's go
and find the World Outliner. find the landscape.
Go assign a material to it. which I'm going to use Flat
Land here. Now. the other problem. if you look. is why
is this rendering so poorly in this new scene. Well. if you go compare it to the
other scene that we've got. which is the BattleGround. so I better save this scene
as BattleGround_High.
Let's just go look at the other scene and see what's missing.
right. So. if you look in this scene in the World Outliner. we've got Atmospheric Fog a Directional
Light. a Light Source. a Lightmassimportance volume. a Player Start.
Sky Sphere. We've got all this stuff that we don't have over here
in this new BattleGround_Hight. because it was empty when we created it.
So. one thing you can do is just paste all that in.
I just copied those from the other scene or level
and pasted them in here. Now. you can see the beauty of what TerraGen has created. This landscape
really does look like it's been crafted with water basically
or something like that. It looks very natural. The problem with this landscape. as it stands. is that you
could easily drive a tank. say up this valley here. over the top. and then.
down the back. and you could end up discovering the end of the world. And we don't want to be discovering
the end of the world. So. I just wanted to show you how you could do this type of import. I'm actually not going to use
this landscape right now. It's setting the bar too high. It's too beautiful. I'd have to do too much
work with materials and textures. and this could turn into a whole course on landscaping. which it
isn't. So. I'm going to pop back to my BattleGround. my low poly
battleground here. having showed you that. Oh hang on. one more thing!
There is one other thing I want to show you. which is you may want to convert a high poly landscape to a low poly landscape.
Let me show you a really quick way of doing that! You can go into the Landscaping tool of modes.
you can go into Manage. and then. down to Change
Component Size. and you can go from 255 quads. say down to 15
and select Resample. So. you would reduce your selection size and
then Resample. If you apply that. let's just see what that looks like.
There you go! So. now we've got a TerraGen generated low poly
style landscape. which is quite interesting. but the resampling can
lead to some really inconsistent polygon sizes. So. it is a possibility
for you changing size but it's not recommended. I would rather you just built low poly
landscapes from scratch. because you could get some really weird artifacts that you're seeing here.
But you may be interested in that. so I wanted to put it in for you. Let's go back to my
low poly landscape here. I'm going to stick with this style
for now. and I'm just going to really quickly make it what I'm looking for. which is
just a really simple mountainous area around the outside. that
prevents us from leaving. So. I'm just going to go ahead and sculpt
with a large brush and a strong
a strong large brush. and just get it all sculpted up.
And it's surprising
how well just going around and roughly destroying around the edges of the landscape can
actually work. and if you do low poly landscapes like this. then you
get to see your geometry and you get a more consistent set of polygon
sizes. OK. now Unreal is really good with high poly stuff and you can make
beautiful interesting looking high poly landscapes and
we'll cover some more of the things like post processing effects and the lights later. But to
keep my time down and the amount of time you need to watch me just
sculpting landscapes. I'm going to stick with this low poly stuff. but all of the techniques
I just showed you apply to high poly as well.
So. a little hint for you. if you're having trouble seeing things
in shadows. is you can switch from lit to unlit mode. and that will allow you to really
quickly just see the landscape without worrying about where the shadows are.
Then. you can paint your gravel on the shaded or sloped sides of the
mountains. really quite easily. It really only matters what it looks like from the middle of
the arena. because that's the only place that the tanks are going to be judging it
from. It's quite usual for things that you can't see to not be looking right.
that just saves time in the production.
So. I'm just going to quickly pop these gravel kind of colors down here.
on the sides. making sure that it's good enough for now bearing in mind that
you can change everything. and iterate and want to be changing and iterating regularly.
And then. we are done. we have an arena! You've seen high poly. you've seen low poly.
you've seen flat shaded. you've seen smooth shaded.
you've seen using materials that use either textures or just
flat colors. and basically you have everything you need to create simple
landscapes. or even go and get yourself a trial of TerraGen or the like and make something
really really fantastic looking. So. if I go back to Lit now. then we have
a pretty cool looking low poly layout. It's fine
for me. it's a great arena. and I'll see you in the next video where we'll
start actually making the tanks work!
=======
So, welcome to
More Landscaping Tools! In this video, we're going to be showing you how to make flat
shading optional inside your landscape material properties. Importing and exporting
landscape heightmaps, which are an image file that represents the landscape layout.
Reducing the resolution of the landscape. There's one very simple way of doing this,
in a few clicks. If you want to go from high to low poly, with some limitations.
And importantly, using a texture in a landscape material, rather than
just having completely flat shading. So, by the end of it, I'll have
a finalized low poly landscape like this, which will actually have some material still
flat shading but actually have a material that has some texture to it like this,
and it will be an inescapable terrain where all the
sides are too steep for the tank to leave. So, that's important and we
have our battle arena. So, see you in there!
So, let's start with how to add a texture to our terrain. This
technique will apply to high and low poly terrains. In fact, I'm going to leave the
landscape material, so that you can either make it flat shaded or not flat shaded
very easily. So, let's go find a texture first! One easy way to do that is to go
to the Content tab, Add New, and then, Add Feature or Content
Pack, and this is a way of getting our starter content in after the events.
So, no point in starting the Starter Content, if you don't need it, but if we want it now we can just go to
Content Packs, Starter Content, and add it to the project.
Now, in that Starter Content under Materials, notice a couple of things. We've got
a couple of useful things in here. One is M_Ground
_Grass. So that's the grass material. If we look at it, we'll
see that under the Usage section, it does have use with landscape ticked,
so it is designed to be used as a landscape. And we'll find the same with the gravel. M_
Ground_Gravel. So the question is, how do we use these actual textures
rather than these flat colors? We want the flat shading still,
potentially. We want to be able to choose flat shading, on or off. Solid colors like, we might want
a solid color for snow, but we're also going to want some textures, so let me show you that.
What we do is, we go ahead and find our material, so
that's in Content, and then let's work on the FlatLand
one for now. And what we're going to do is replace these flat colors
here with actual textures. So what you do is you do a search for texture,
and you'll find Texture Sample. That's the one we want.
OK, so I'm going to get myself a couple of texture samples. Just
Duplicate and we're going to take the output of the
Texture Samples into the layers. So, that's the same as
using flat colors. The only difference is they're going to want some UV maps,
and that's going to tell these textures where on the landscape they're going to be. So, we look
for the Landscape section. Then, we're looking for
LandscapeLayerCoordinates. That's what we want! And you plumb that into both
of your texture samples, for both the grass and the dirt. And then,
all you need to do is, for the grass, you go and find the grass. So, you go over to
the Details tab, under the Material Expression Texture Base,
and then, Texture, use the dropdown, type grass,
and choose that. And then, the same for the
gravel. Now you've got two on the gravel. You've got a normal map and
a detail map. We're going to use just the detail, for the moment, that's just the color the albedo the
base color. The normal map would allow you to set some roughness.
Now talking about roughness, we have this absolute world position here.
We are not going to use that now, the flat shading, or we want the option to be able to use
it, so in a moment we're going to kind of find a way of commenting this out in Blueprint. But for now, let's just
check the effect of changing to Texture Samples, instead of flat
colors. So, I'm just going to save this up,
minimize, and then, when this recompiles,
we'll see the effect. I quite like the effect of having flat shaded low poly
but with a texture. The game The Witness, that fantastic puzzle game that came out in
2016, that has this type of effect, low poly but with
textures on it. And now you can see the effect, OK. We have
exactly the same painting as we had before, but now, we
can, with a sufficiently small brush, we can come in and paint
dirt where we want it, grass where we want it, and get quite an interesting looking effect,
I think. Fantastic, so that is how you use textures. You can use that on a high
or a low poly landscape. The other thing I want to show you is, how to make flat shading
optional. So, one very simple way of doing that is if you come in and hit
C for Comment, you can then put a Comment block. It's better, actually, if
you just, before you hit C for Comment, if you select the blocks that you want to comment
about, then hit C, and it'll put a Comment block around this. And you can
say, Wire to... Oops, if I can type correctly. Wire to
Normal for flat shading.
OK, Wire to Normal for flat shading, and then,
that gives you a group that you can move around. And if we just break the link, by right clicking,
and then save, we've got some nodes here that are ready to use if we want to enable
Flat Shading. So, that's pretty cool! Let's just save that up and see what that looks like,
and what's going to happen now is, we won't have the flat shading anymore. So,
on a high poly landscape this is what you would want. You'd want to turn off the Flat Shading like that,
and have smooth shading and this will look absolutely fine. There you go!
So, this is ready to go for a high poly style, alright.
You may get some repetition of your textures, it looks a bit odd on a large landscape,
and isotropic filtering on your graphics card will help with that,
But at the moment, we're just trying to make the first iteration of this landscape, alright.
So, I'm actually going to stick with low poly, so I'm going to delete my landscape material.
I don't need that. I'm going to leave FlatLand, I'm going to rewire it to Normal, like that.
I want to stick with low poly because I want to get off landscapes now. I want to move
onto the tank and moving and controlling the tank. The least fun thing about this game,
right now, is not the landscapes, it's the fact it hasn't even got a tank in it, right. But I want
to show you a couple of other landscape tools, just before we leave this. So, the first thing I want to show you
is the concept of exporting your own height map. So, you come to Landscape
tab to sculpt and then down to the target layers. You right-click, it's a bit
hidden on the height map, and you can say Export to File. So, I'm just going to do that quickly.
I'm just going to call it test, and if I go look at this
test, let's go look at the .png, you can see it's a small .png.
I need this one, because my landscape is relatively low res. You can see the
tiny bit of landscape I've built up on the right-hand side here, just a slightly lighter
coloring. Alright, so that's what a height map is, it's a top-down view. Now, luckily one of
our students, Chris, has provided us with a much more detailed height map. You're welcome to import
that. There it is! So, that is a height map that
has got a lot more detail, and it's created with something called TerraGen. Let me just show you how you would
import that, if you wanted to. What you could do is, you could add a...
Well, actually one of the easiest things to do here is just to create yourself
a new scene altogether. So, just make a new level, a new
empty level, saving what we've got, and then, work on another level if you want to
experiment high versus low, if you're not decided yet. So, in this new level,
we can then come to Landscapes, Manage, Import from File,
go grab the file that's attached to this very lecture. There it is!
Now, notice this is a 5 by 5 kilometer landscape, but we're just going to go with that,
for the moment, just so I can demonstrate what this would look like.
Now, what we need is a landscape material here, so let's go
and find the World Outliner, find the landscape.
Go assign a material to it, which I'm going to use Flat
Land here. Now, the other problem, if you look, is why
is this rendering so poorly in this new scene. Well, if you go compare it to the
other scene that we've got, which is the BattleGround, so I better save this scene
as BattleGround_High.
Let's just go look at the other scene and see what's missing,
right. So, if you look in this scene in the World Outliner, we've got Atmospheric Fog a Directional
Light, a Light Source, a Lightmassimportance volume, a Player Start,
Sky Sphere. We've got all this stuff that we don't have over here
in this new BattleGround_Hight, because it was empty when we created it.
So, one thing you can do is just paste all that in.
I just copied those from the other scene or level
and pasted them in here. Now, you can see the beauty of what TerraGen has created. This landscape
really does look like it's been crafted with water basically
or something like that. It looks very natural. The problem with this landscape, as it stands, is that you
could easily drive a tank, say up this valley here, over the top, and then,
down the back, and you could end up discovering the end of the world. And we don't want to be discovering
the end of the world. So, I just wanted to show you how you could do this type of import. I'm actually not going to use
this landscape right now. It's setting the bar too high. It's too beautiful, I'd have to do too much
work with materials and textures, and this could turn into a whole course on landscaping, which it
isn't. So, I'm going to pop back to my BattleGround, my low poly
battleground here, having showed you that. Oh hang on, one more thing!
There is one other thing I want to show you, which is you may want to convert a high poly landscape to a low poly landscape.
Let me show you a really quick way of doing that! You can go into the Landscaping tool of modes,
you can go into Manage, and then, down to Change
Component Size, and you can go from 255 quads, say down to 15
and select Resample. So, you would reduce your selection size and
then Resample. If you apply that, let's just see what that looks like.
There you go! So, now we've got a TerraGen generated low poly
style landscape, which is quite interesting, but the resampling can
lead to some really inconsistent polygon sizes. So, it is a possibility
for you changing size but it's not recommended. I would rather you just built low poly
landscapes from scratch, because you could get some really weird artifacts that you're seeing here.
But you may be interested in that, so I wanted to put it in for you. Let's go back to my
low poly landscape here. I'm going to stick with this style
for now, and I'm just going to really quickly make it what I'm looking for, which is
just a really simple mountainous area around the outside, that
prevents us from leaving. So, I'm just going to go ahead and sculpt
with a large brush and a strong
a strong large brush, and just get it all sculpted up.
And it's surprising
how well just going around and roughly destroying around the edges of the landscape can
actually work, and if you do low poly landscapes like this, then you
get to see your geometry and you get a more consistent set of polygon
sizes. OK, now Unreal is really good with high poly stuff and you can make
beautiful interesting looking high poly landscapes and
we'll cover some more of the things like post processing effects and the lights later. But to
keep my time down and the amount of time you need to watch me just
sculpting landscapes, I'm going to stick with this low poly stuff, but all of the techniques
I just showed you apply to high poly as well.
So, a little hint for you, if you're having trouble seeing things
in shadows, is you can switch from lit to unlit mode, and that will allow you to really
quickly just see the landscape without worrying about where the shadows are.
Then, you can paint your gravel on the shaded or sloped sides of the
mountains, really quite easily. It really only matters what it looks like from the middle of
the arena, because that's the only place that the tanks are going to be judging it
from. It's quite usual for things that you can't see to not be looking right,
that just saves time in the production.
So, I'm just going to quickly pop these gravel kind of colors down here,
on the sides, making sure that it's good enough for now bearing in mind that
you can change everything, and iterate and want to be changing and iterating regularly.
And then, we are done, we have an arena! You've seen high poly, you've seen low poly,
you've seen flat shaded, you've seen smooth shaded,
you've seen using materials that use either textures or just
flat colors, and basically you have everything you need to create simple
landscapes, or even go and get yourself a trial of TerraGen or the like and make something
really really fantastic looking. So, if I go back to Lit now, then we have
a pretty cool looking low poly layout. It's fine
for me, it's a great arena, and I'll see you in the next video where we'll
start actually making the tanks work!
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1:Unreal/Section4/BT10 More Landscaping Tools.srt