So. let's talk
about the Tank Control System! In this video. we're going to have a bit of an overview of what's
going on. We're going to talk about how we're going to support keyboard. mouse. and the gamepad
controller. We'll be talking about mapping player intentions. to control
inputs. Mapping control inputs to actor actuators. Actuators
is a bold sounding thing. Really we're just rotating actors or moving actors.
And we'll be introducing the content of "fly by wire". so let's just start talking
through it. Basically. as part of this iterative cycle. we've had a go on the World. there's a huge amount
more we could do a landscape. but we're done enough for now. So next. we're going to do.
look at these three steps kind of all in one. the Tank. the Controls. and Player 2.
We need to come up with a control paradigm that obviously
moves the tank. and we need to think about the different components of the tank. We then
need to come up with some controls that make sense. and then. we need to.
at the same time. think about how Player 2 whether that Player 2 is a human
or an AI would actually control the tank. So. that's what we're going to look at now. Later. we'll
go back through User Interface and then back round to the World. This cycle is not a particularly
set in stone cycle. it's just something that we're just following for this particular section.
So. control inputs! Keyboard and mouse. as I said. and Xbox controller is what we're going
to be using for this section. You don't need to have one. If you've got one. great! An Xbox 360
controller should plug directly into the USB port of your PC and work without any troubles.
You can also use other types of controllers. if you wish. We are
going to be assuming. for this section. that we have a couple of analog triggers on the controller.
but as I said. it's not essential. you can still use and test this game without it. So. let's
look at the major tank components. There are three major components to consider in a tank. and
they all can move somewhat independently. You've got the white base. which is the tank body. Of course.
there's two tracks on that. it can move forward and backwards and rotate. Of course. it
can't strafe. Then. we've got the blue. The blue is the turret
and that is going to contain people's head and
hold onto the barrel. and then. of course the barrel there in red. which can elevate up and
down. So the turret. the blue can rotate. the tank can translate and rotate. but it
can't strafe sideways. and then the turret's up and down. So. pretty obvious stuff.
but just want to be clear on there. they're the major components we're dealing with. So. what I want to
do is start talking about the control system. Now. I'm sorry that I can't animate this table how
I would like to. on Google Slides. but I'm just going to take it from the top-left onwards.
Firstly. let's get the layout of the table. We're talking about the control intentions. the intention
of the Player or the AI or the 2nd Player. Then. we're going to talk about what
would happen in a Manual Control Paradigm. then fly by wire.
Now. fly by wire. what that means will kind of come clear at the bottom of the table. In
simple terms. its Manual Control is where you directly actuate something.
like you move a track forward or back. where fly by wire is you set an intention like
I want to rotate the tank. and then. maybe one track goes forward and the other goes back or whatever.
So. that's basically what fly by wire means. And then. we'll also be clear on what
the actuators are. the things that are actually going to be moved. So. starting with the first
movement forward. If we want to go forward. we're symmetric on the triggers. I'm assuming that the two triggers
of your controller here are... And by triggers. by the way. I mean back
here. the two little things sticking out of the top of that diagram. the actual left and
right trigger and they're analog. So. if we were symmetric with our triggers.
then we would be sending both tracks forward at the same speed. I'm assuming that the left
trigger drives the left track and the right trigger drives the right track. and the degree to which
you pull the trigger determines how fast the tracks move. because I think this is going to be quite a fun
direct control system for the tank. So. one option would be. you pull the triggers in symmetrically and
then you go straight forward. If one triggers in more than the other. of course. you'll be turning to one side.
But the fly by wire control could be the left stick
going forward. to indicate I just want to move forward. or you could use the
W key on the keyboard and then you would move forward at a constant speed. In the case of the left
stick. of course. it would be an analog stick so it's an analog speed.
So. let's think about backwards! Backwards again. we could use the bumpers. and what are the bumpers? Well. on the controller
they are these things just above. So the triggers are the little guys sticking out here. the bumpers are the ones
slightly closer to us in the foreground. They're actually digital. they are on or off. So.
what we could do with the bumpers is we could say that the bumpers put the breaks on if we're moving forward.
and then. immediately send us into a fixed speed reverse once we've stopped. That would be good
enough. So. symmetric bumpers would make us break or go backwards.
and also. we could use the left stick or the S key. so I'm going for a standard W. S. A.
D. as indicated on this picture of the keyboard over here.
OK. so that's an indication of the sort of controls. What I would like
you to do. as a challenge. is to really think through these controls. because it's a very valuable exercise
before we go diving in and actually making this happen. we want to know what control
paradigm we're ending up with. So I want you to complete the control
table. I'll flip back to the slide in a minute. but let me just brief you on it. I want you to finish
the control intention table. There is no wrong way or right way of doing this. the purpose is for you to think
through this. We want fly by wire controls
only on the keyboard and mouse. so think about how we could use the keyboard
and mouse in a less direct way. because we really don't have enough analog axes on the keyboard and mouse.
So. maybe play a tank game. World of Tanks or War Thunder or something like that.
and maybe follow the control system in those. And then. with
the controller. we want manual control and potentially fly by
wire. so we just want more of a manual control element as an option on the control.
as I started to show you. So look. really there's no right answer here. as I
said. I want you to sit down and think about how control inputs would relate
to outputs. So. we go back to this table. and I want you to just finish it
off. Add another three. four. five rows to this table. as many as you see fit.
and spend about 15 to 20 minutes researching another tank game and really just get into the
mindset of thinking about how controls might work and the consistency of it
and how it all kind of fits together. So go ahead. pause the video. and do that now.
So welcome back! Here's the challenge slide! Now. there's going to be a face full of new lines in this table
here. so we're going to work through it one at a time. and I'll use my mouse cursor to try and help you see
through this. So. boom loads of stuff! Let's go down to Strafe.
Strafe is the next thing. Well that's moving sideways. it's just not applicable to a tank. I don't know if you've
seen the new A Team Film with B. A. Baracus. when he says "You can't fly a tank fool!"?
[Laughs] Well. you can't strafe a tank fool either. so it's not going to happen. We're not going
sideways in a tank. so we can forget that. But rotating the body. how would you do that? Well. you'd use
asymmetric triggers or bumpers on the manual controller. or you'd simply use the left stick
left or right. if we're going for fly by wire control on the controller or the A
or D keys would be another way of doing that. and that would rotate
tracks. different speeds. So. that's the actuator! What we're saying here is
that the actuator is the tracks. and in order to cause a rotation. they just need to move at
different speeds. Any different speeds and it will rotate. how different the speed is determines how fast it rotates.
So let's move down to rotating the turret! Well. I'm thinking
we'll deal with these two together. rotating the turret and elevating the barrel. so
aiming is a shortcut for those two. I'm thinking we don't bother giving manual control
in the controller for that. It's too much hassle really. while you're trying to think about driving a tank as well. So we'll go for pure fly by wire
just like the controls in War Thunder. but what you do
is you look into a particular direction. the camera goes immediately
to the direction with right stick or the mouse. and then shortly afterwards the barrel
follows to that position. so both the elevation and the rotation
move to that position after some time. they're limited in their speed. And
the things you're actuating are the Turret Rotator and the Barrel Elevator. so it's
pretty simple. So hopefully that gives you an overview of what we're trying to achieve with the tank
controls here. it's pretty much as simple as that. What we're going to do next is dive in and start actually
putting a very basic block-work tank together. and then. we'll start thinking about
how we control this thing both in C++ and with a little bit of Blueprint where it makes
our life easier. So. see you there!