So. welcome to
Configuring a Tank! In this video we're going to specifically setup our
tank. we're going to make sure it sits on the ground properly. that we actually
spawn a player when we start the game. We'll
sort the camera out in a future lecture. that we can have player tanks and third
party tanks. and as I say the physics is working. We'll be simplifying the tank
blueprint a little bit. tweaking the tank track positions.
and a few other little bits. setting the game mode etc. So. let's get on with that!
OK. so before we start making this tank move. let's
fix it up a little bit. There are some issues right? It's sitting into the floor.
my tracks actually aren't positioned correctly. there's things wrong with the
blueprint in terms of the way that it's laid out. and the root
components. etc.. so we will be arranging that. The
tank is not the Default Pawn. at the moment. When we play we do not possess
the tank. we don't spawn a tank. so yeah a few things we need to
sort out. Let's take them one at a time. Let's start with adding a
mass to the tank and getting some physics going. So. if you lift the tank off the ground and
play it. you notice it just hangs in the air. because it's not simulating
physics. Well. that's a really easy fix. Over at the tank.
on the Tank component. not the Default Scene Root. because we're going to be
replacing that in a moment. In fact. let's just replace that now. We don't need a default
scene in root component. That gives us things like a transform and physics. etc.
but so does the static mesh of the tank itself. so
simpler is better. The tank static mesh does more than the DefaultSceneRoot.
so we're going to get rid of it. The way you do that is. you grab hold of the tank
and just parent it. or what looks like parenting it to the DefaultScene Root. But
you'll see that it says "Drop here to make Tank the new root. The default root will be deleted." That's
perfect. that's exactly what we want! So. let's go ahead and do that now! Now the
tank is at the root. so it's a simpler hierarchy. So. that's a thumbs up
for me. So next. we go to the tank which is now at the root
and turn on simulate physics. and let's assign a sensible mass. Well.
tanks are somewhere between 10 and 60. 70 tons. so I'm going to go for 40
metric tons. 40.000 kilos. 40 0 0 0.
OK. so that's the mass! We have some Simulate Physics on. We'll worry about the
other physics properties later. so of course. you need to compile the blueprint
and play. Let's just see! So. with your tank off the ground. let's see what happens. Ha ha!
It falls to the ground. hits the ground very nicely this time. and that's because
if we look at the tracks as
models. as static meshes. you can see that the collision mesh that
Unreal has created for us. here this purple outline. is actually pretty good and
pretty appropriate. So. that's why the tank is falling until it hits the
collision mesh of the tracks. Great! Alright. so
that's that bit done! Now. I need to fine tune the position of
these tracks. My left track is a little bit too far out. it's just sticking out here. and
my right track. if we were to rotate the tank or just line ourselves up here. you
can see is miles off. So. I'm just going to put the tank near the floor.
And not to confuse things. by the way. I'm actually going to move this tank and spin
it around. because remember there's a player start point here
and that's where we're going to spawn our tank. This tank that we've placed in the world is not going to be
our tank. this is an AI tank or will become an AI tank. Remember that we
spawn the player into the world. as per the previous section. So.
wrong axis! I'm just going to spin this tank around like that.
and then. if we play what we've got is effectively is an enemy tank and we are the
current player. Alright. so there's the tank. it's just off the ground. it falls to the
ground when we start. it's all looking good. The challenge we have right now is these track positions.
So. being very careful with Unreal's
buggy socket system. I'm going to go into the
the tank body and...
Actually. once you've renamed these sockets I think it's pretty stable now. Let's see
how it is. So. I'm going to go to the Left Track. I'm going to pick myself a preview mesh again.
and then. I'm going to
line up and just pull it in a little bit. That's good! In fact.
you probably want to use let's say a Left view is
it? Something like that in Lit? Yeah. something like that
or maybe it's a Right view. There you go! Right view and
then the Left Track. you can see there's like a notch here in the body.
We can probably want to align that notch up. something like that. Now of course. if it's snapping
wrongly. then you take your position snap. which is this
one here. and you turn the value right down.
till you can get the track in just the right position. There great! Alright. let's do the same
on the Right Track. I'm always nervous when touching the sockets. because they're buggy
or at least they are at the time of recording.
There you go! That looks fine to me! Let's try putting a new
tank in the world. because this tank that's already in the world... Oh. it has actually updated!
Sometimes it does. sometimes it doesn't. but this has! That's fantastic! So. the tank is looking
much better. and of course. any new tanks we drop in the world will have these new properties
as well. so that's cool! Great. so we've added
mass to the tank. We fine tuned the track position. We sorted out the root
component in the blueprint. so the tank is there simplifying things. We've enabled physics
and assigned a mass as I said. We now need to
set the tank to the Default Pawn. Now of course. you've done that
before. so I want you to set the tank blueprint as a Default Pawn. Create a
BattleTankGameMode blueprint. based on the BattleTankGameMode's
C++ class. There are several ways of doing that. we've done it in the previous section.
Assign the tank as the Default Pawn. and check that the correct tank spawns
on play. So. if your player start. like mine. is in the ground
you may have a little bit of trouble. You may need to move the player start. There's a hint for you. Alright.
we want to make sure that a new tank spawns. not just the one we've dropped in the world. but once we're
playing there should be two. the one we left in the world and the one that spawns on play. i.e.
us. Go ahead. pause the video. see if you can make that stuff work now.
Welcome back! So. I'm going to create the BattleTankGameMode blueprint. a slightly different way. The
previous way I think that we did it is. we went to the Game Mode here. the C++ Game Mode.
right-click. and "Create Blueprint class based on" it. You can do that. or
you can notice that you can just go to Blueprint. And you can look at
the Project Settings for the GameMode. which we're not going to change for now. but
the world override. for this particular world. we're going to use
a new GameMode here. so you want that setting. World override
let's you get to a place where you can create a new blueprint class based
on the BattleTankGameMode. It's exactly the same as right-clicking on the BattleTank
GameMode C++ on the left and creating a blueprint. I just wanted to show you this other menu.
so there it is! Let's call it BattleTankGameMode_BP.
And this tells the
GameMode. of which we'll only have one. what the Default Pawn is.
The tank blueprint. cool! So. that's down there under classes. tank blueprint.
alright. And remember. we're in the full blueprint editor here. so that's
why it's quite complex looking. Great. so
if we now play what happens? Well. we end up half way in the
floor. Let's de-possess. F8. That lets you eject from
the possessed player. So. what's going on? Where are we? If we look at the
World Outliner. we have a tank there but that's not us actually.
We have a PlayerController and a PlayerState. Something is a bit
funny. so when something is a bit funny it's a good habit to go to your Developer Tools
and make sure that you have your Output Log. Look "SpawnActor failed because
of collision at spawn location". which is that location
there. So. what is that location there? Well. it's probably the location of
Player Start. Let's have a look. Yes it is. 0. 0. 112.
So. what's happening is that our Player Start... Let me just give myself
some room here. we just go to it. ...is in the
ground. and then. the tank can't spawn there because the player starts in the ground. So. if I
move the Player Start off the ground a bit and try playing again. ah hah!
The camera's all wrong. but look what happens! The tank spawns and now we have
two tanks. if I eject with the F8 key then move around. This
is our player tank. And are we possessed in that tank? Well. click Possess.
you end up right in the middle of it. It looks like it to me! So. that's pretty
cool. right! Now. you might ask why this camera's here. sitting in the middle of the tank
like this. Well. we'll be dealing with the camera in the next
video. So. that's it! We have managed to tweak our tank. We
have AI tanks that look just like the player tanks. so we're on a level ground.
literally at the moment. [Laughs] And also
metaphorically. we want to be on an even keel. [Laughs] I like to throw out as many English
metaphors as I can. We want us and the AI tank to...
It wants to be fair right. so it's fair in terms of
our tank is the same as the AI tank. and it's going to be fair later. because we're going to force the AI
to drive like we do. using the same controls and the same physics. And
that's going to be really cool. because that make the game much more equitable. So.
let's move on and look at how we're going to deal with the camera
and various other aspect. So. see you soon!