In this video
we're going to take another major step towards being able to make a real game. which is you're going to start to
touch the User Interface System in Unreal which will be great!
What we're going to do with that is very simple actually... I don't know if you can see it even. but there's a
little tiny white dot. about a 1/3 of the way down the screen and in the middle; it's kind of
over the enemy tank right now. that's our aiming reticle. So. we're going to make
a Player UI Widget and a Tank Player Controller that's going to spawn that widget.
and then. the magic will happen! So. let's see how it's done!
So. what we want to create is a little dot
in the screen. about a 1/3 of the way down the screen and right in the middle.
So. about where the enemy tank is in our Viewport now. something like that.
and that becomes our aim point. The simplest way to do that is to
use User Interface. something called a Widget Blueprint. and we're going
to be needing that anyway to display our ammo and to create our Start Menu later. So. let's get
into Widget Blueprints and User Interface! Just before I do. I'm going
to delete my high poly model of the ground. You could proceed with high
poly modeling. it's just taking a lot more time and the focus of this section is more on
control systems. So. I'm going to delete that high poly landscape. and
I'm also just going to move the FlatLand material into the BattleGround sharedassets. just to tidy up.
It's as simple as that. Finally. I have a _Levels folder here. but I haven't
used it. underscore Levels. Why underscore? Simply because it floats to the top.
It's quite common that we want to choose our level. Later. we'll want to have a start scene in here. too.
And if you underscore levels. it floats to the top of the list. as simple as that. Alright.
so how are we going to do this? Well. we want to make ourselves
our first Widget Blueprint. So. in the Content tab you go to Add New. look for Widget.
or just scroll down for it. and User Interface.
Widget Blueprint. That's what we want! Talk about Slate. that's a more advanced
tool for User Interface. We're just going to be
messing around with the Widget Blueprint for now. Alright. let's call it
Player
UI. for example. OK. because it's going to be the player's User Interface that we're designing
here. Fantastic! So. let's go into the Widget Blueprint. A whole new
load of tools for you! Unreal's great like this. it's got so many tools hiding away!
So. I'm just going to get rid of the Animation Timeline. at the bottom. and the Animations tab. we
simply don't need those and just keep things nice and simple.
OK. so for the sake of what we're doing here. we actually just need an
image. That's all we need. just a very simple couple of white
pixels. to be honest. So. what we're going to do is just add an image.
drop it in the scene. Now. the first thing we need to get right is the anchoring.
We want to make sure it's always anchored to a position that is
1/2 way along the screen and exactly a 1/3 of the way down the screen.
And the way we're doing things at the moment. if you just drop the image in. the anchor
point is at the top-left. Let's see what happens if you change screen size. You see
how it's anchored a fixed number of pixels away from the top left? That's no use
to us. So. the first thing we want to do is change this anchor point. Now. the
simplest way to make sure that this image is always at 50% of the way
across horizontally and a 1/3 of the way down vertically is just
literally to drag the anchor point there. There you go! So. add 50% horizontally.
33.3%. exactly 1/3. vertically. So then.
this is where it's going to stay anchored to. Look what happens now. if we change the screen size. That option
is at the top-right. You see how it's always a
1/3 of the way down the screen and 1/2 way
across the screen OK. So. I'm just going to go 19" monitor. It
doesn't really matter. we're going to be focusing on a 16:9 ratio. I just wanted to show you that. that's going to
stay there regardless. OK. so next question. Where
is this block compared to that pivot point? Well. that's
these positions on the right-hand side. or not necessarily. it depends where you've got your Details
tab. But in your Details tab. under the Slot section. you can see Position.
and if you reset these positions in X and Y
and also the Size. I think maybe 5 pixels will be enough in X and Y.
Then. we've got a 5 by 5 pixel blop. but it's not
quite sitting in the middle of the anchor point. and the reason for that is the alignment needs to be
0.5 0.5. OK. you can see
that if the Alignment was 0 0. then it's the top-left of
the image that sits on the anchor point. but we want 0.5. which means half way across
horizontally and halfway up vertically. that's where we want it!
So. if we zoom all the way out now. what we've got is a little dot that regardless of
the screen size and shape is going to be a 1/3 of the way down
and 1/2 way across. Cool. nice and simple! So.
I'm just going to call this image something different. Let's call it Aim
Point. like that. and compile
the Player UI Widget and that is the start. We have a
Player UI Widget. Now. don't be disappointed that when you play your game it doesn't show.
that's because we haven't yet setup the blueprint to make that show. which is
what we need to do next. So. it's at this point we want to think about what
entity is responsible for showing the Player UI. Well. you could say it's
the tank. because it's always there when we're possessing the tank. but how about if we
de-possess the tank. i.e. our tank gets blown up. for example. What would
happen if we weren't actually possessing the tank? Should we still be showing our
UI? I think we should. Fundamentally. it's the Player Controller
that is responsible for showing the Player UI. or that's the choice we're making
in this section. And we don't have a Player Controller yet. so let's go ahead and make ourselves a new blueprint class.
So. as we're making a Player Controller. the type of the blueprint we're going to use is a
Player Controller. It's an Actor responsible for controlling a
Pawn used by the Player. That Pawn is the tank and we are the Player.
So. there you go. let's make that new blueprint! Let's call it Player
Controller or TankPlayer?
Controller I think. dot underscore BP.
Why TankPlayerController? Because we are possibly going to have Tank
AIController later. when we get to the point of having AI tanks.
Great! So. in the TankPlayerController. that is where we're going
to setup the User Interface. So. I'm going to show you how to do that. and then. I'm going to
allow you. as a challenge. to do the last little bit. So. if we go to the Event
Graph of your newly formed Tank Player Controller blueprint.
I'm going to delete the tick for the moment; it's the BeginPlay that we're interested in.
OK. so there's the BeginPlay node. So drag an execution pin
from your BeginPlay to get things going and search
for widget. One of the things we can do is under the User Interface section. which makes sense.
we create a widget. So. let's do that! Let's ditch this tab at the bottom.
So. we are going to create a widget. Now. what's the widget class? We've made it.
it's the Player UI class. We don't need
to worry about an owning player. for the moment. That's going to default
to us because we're going to be the Tank Player Controller. What we do
need to do. once we've created the widget. is we then need to add it to the Viewport. So. if
you drag off the execution node.
search for Add to Viewport. then that's what we're trying to do.
Now. it needs to know what to add to the Viewport. and that will be a reference
to the widget we just created. OK. so let
me just explain that a little bit more. The Player UI that we're working in here is.
if you look at it and you hover over it. it is a (Widget Blueprint). It is a blueprint
for making a UI Widget. What we're doing in the
Player Controller is saying. OK go ahead and create an instance of a UI Widget
from that template. which we've specified here. and once you've
got a reference to it. use that to add that widget to
the Viewport. OK. so we're nearly there! We're nearly there! If you compile
that blueprint in play. you're going to find. unfortunately. that little dot still doesn't show
up because there's one final thing we need to do. and I'm going to give you the satisfaction
of doing it. So. I want you to set the Player Controller. Find the game mode blueprint
for this level. We've already visited that in this section.
Set the Player Controller to be our new blueprint class. and then. test that the
aiming dot indeed shows up now. So go ahead. pause the video. and do that
last bit yourself.
OK. welcome
back! So. this is relatively simple. one option is the Blueprints menu. As long as we're in
this level. we'll see Edit BattleTankGameMode_BP.
We go into that and then. under here where it says Player Controller
Class we choose the TankPlayerController_BP. compile the class.
and play the game. And you see the little white dot in about the right place?
Pretty cool! There you go! So. now we have an aiming UI
widget. and we have used User Interface in Unreal. which will set us up for creating
Start Menus and all sorts of other fun! So. see you soon!