In this video we're going to talk
about Main Menu Screens, a really important part of your games, of course!
And by the end of it, you'll have a very rough and ready Main Menu, just an image but that's enough
for the first one. There's plenty to learn and I'll see you in there!
So, it's with some excitement I introduce you to how to make a start menu
for your game, because, after all, all games start here! I actually advocate
making your start menu pretty early on in the process. So, lots
of ways you can do menus in Unreal. In
our BattleGround scene, attached to our player controller, we have now
got a tiny piece of UI right, that little white dot, and later we'll have the
ammo, etc. And if you wanted a pause screen, then the pause screen
would pop up in this window, and it would do that typically
by unhiding a piece of UI that was always
there in the first place. So, what I mean by that is, if we look at
the PlayerUI, what we might do for a pause screen, for example...
Don't do this, I'm just going to give you a bit of an overview. What we might do for a
pause screen is have an image, perhaps like this, with maybe a transparent background,
and it may say some stuff on it and give us some options. And then, we might
hide that element, most of the time, so that the game just shows through,
and when we hit pause, we might unhide the element. Alright, so that's a
valid way of building up a UI. Now, we could have a single UI across the entire
game for the start menu, for the in game, and just hide elements and show
elements, but it gets really confusing in the hierarchy of the UI,
amongst other things. So, there are several reasons why it's just
simpler and easier, if we have a separate level for our
start menu. So, that's what we're going to do. We're going to setup a completely
independent level. So, let's do that now! File, New Level. I'm going to make it
completely empty, so an empty level, and I'm just going to call it
Main Menu. Now of course, the way you do that is you try and save it, and it goes well
I don't have a name. So, we give it a name, MainMenu.
Perfect! So now, in our _Levels folder, we have a MainMenu.
If it wasn't in your levels, of course, you can drag it there very easily. And while we're dragging
things, let's drag the TankPlayerController into the Tank folder, moving
not copying, and we'll leave the PlayerUI right where it is, just for now.
So, we have a main menu. I'm just going to save some changes, and it's completely blank.
So, what I want you to do is to actually setup
this UI. Don't try and make an entire main menu, I'm going to go through
that with you, but I'm going to ask you to just get it showing something. But
before you do that, we need to decide which blueprint is going to be responsible for setting this up.
In the case of the tank in the game, it's the PlayerController, because
that makes sense right? If your tank dies, you may want to de-possess the tank,
come into a spectator view, and still be able to see like your health or your
ammo or something. So, it's the PlayerController that seems
to make sense there. Now, in this level, we have nothing but a main menu,
so the logical place for me to put the code that is going to setup
the UI is in the level blueprint. So, under the Main
Menu, with that selected; make sure you are in MainMenu. Go to Blueprints
and Open Level Blueprint. There's already a level
blueprint there, we just can't see it. So, this level blueprint is
where we're going to set this up. We're going to get rid of the tick, and in BeginPlay
we're going to do exactly the same magic as we did over on the previous piece of UI,
for the aiming reticle. There's a cool name, reticle! And we're just going
to show something, just like an image or a button or something. So, that is your challenge actually.
So, really revising UI, add a widget from the level blueprint.
Open the MainMenu level blueprint, as I just did. Create a
blueprint to add the widget to the screen. So, make a widget, you haven't even
got a UI widget yet. Make a widget blueprint class, just like we did for the player,
and then, create some blueprint code to add that to the screen, same
as we just did. And test it works, by the way, with a button, an image,
or just some UI element so you can see that it's working. So, this is going to
be a great revision of a UI for you, make sure you understood what we did in the previous video.
So, pause the video. Please don't just watch my solution, please take the opportunity
to challenge yourself, that's where all the learning happens, and I'll see you in a moment!
OK, welcome back! Let's make this happen! Arguably the most sensible
thing to do first is to actually create ourselves a new piece
of UI. So, we have a PlayerUI. What we're going to want now maybe is a
folder called UI. That seems to start to make sense. Put the PlayerUI
in it, go into it, and I'm going to
make myself a new User Interface
widget blueprint, and I'm going to call it Menu... Ooh, can't
type. ...BP. And actually, while we're here, this PlayerUI, it is actually a blueprint,
so why not rename it. The great thing about anything that's blueprint related is, we
can actually rename without trouble. Of course, C++ classes aren't so
forgiving. Just to prove that, let's pop back to the battleground
and play. Make sure
that it still works. It does, good! Alright, so we're at the point now
where we want to actually make ourselves a UI main menu.
And we have two tabs, the Designer tab, which is where we're going to put the things down and the Event
Graph. We don't need anything in the graph yet, but we do need to put
something down just to prove that this is working. So ultimately, we're going to have a background image
here. So, I will take the background image,
and pop it on the background like that. That'll do, just a big white blob is pretty
obvious, and just compile that. So,
now I have a blueprint class, we need to tell something which is the
LevelBlueprint here,
to the main menu, we need to tell it to construct this widget. So,
remember what we do. We create a widget, we choose the class.
It's Main Menu blueprint. That's all you need to do there. That spits out a
reference to the actual instance of the
Widget class. The widget, you know the User Interface. Now, we
Add to Viewport. Why is it up automatically for us? And that should be it.
Let's compile it, play. Ah hah, we have the
essence of a main menu! Fantastic!
So, now let's start actually configuring up the main menu and have it do something,
like have a background image might be a start right.
Well, we're going to get you an image that you can use for the background. Now, the
way I found the image that I supply in the course I think is, I just went to
I can't remember tank firing or something?
There's Google search, I go to Search Tools, I look for...
Where did I do this? Images,
Search Tools, Usage Rights, "Labeled for reuse with modifications",
just to be fairly safe, and here's the tank image itself. So, you could just
go and get it from Wikipedia, or you can download it from against this lecture.
So, I'm going to download
this image. View Image, oops.
Just to show you. And you can go and choose any image you like, but obviously, if you're making a commercial game, just be a little
bit careful about what you do with that image. There it is! There's the image!
And let's pop into the main menu,
and let's specify this image. Now, you can't just,
by the way, pull the image directly in, because it's not yet imported into
Unreal, so it's only going to see assets that are imported. So, to import that
image we simply Import to /Game/UI. So, I'm going to
my Content Browser, in my UI folder, and you right-click in there and say
Import to Game. Then, we can go and find the relevant
image, like that, and there it is, we have the
image! Great! So now, back in the main menu
blueprint, that image I put on the background, we can then go and
specify what the actual image that we're going to be using here is.
So, I'm going to call it Background Image, for a start.
We'll worry about the anchors and stuff in just a moment. Let's just get the image in to make sure
that it is behaving itself. So, can you see in this menu system
where we set the image? It's not completely obvious, it's actually under the
Brush. We're brushing this box with the image, so you open up the Brush,
and now you can go ahead and choose, with that dropdown, the image we imported.
Great! There it is! And it's got the Image Size, etc. So, what we need to do now
is just get the properties of this image, so that it's behaving itself. We want
to think about this image staying in the screen, even if the screen is slightly
different in size. We want the image to be nicely centered
in the screen and nicely anchored.
We also need to add some buttons and to also make the mouse
available, when we're in the game, without this hackie Shift F1
that they talk about. You would find that if you actually build this game for Mac
or PC right now that the mouse won't be available. So, there's lots of other things we need
to do. Scaling the image, buttons, mouse, and others. So, let's
make those the subject of future videos, because this one is plenty long enough.