Welcome to UI
Scale Box. Buttons. & Mouse. where we'll be covering those three things. By the end of the video
you will have a much improved menu system. where we
have a mouse. for a start. which you may notice we didn't have before. We'll be able to scale the
window with our title text and our buttons sticking appropriately and
the background image scaling nicely. And that's it really. for now. the mouse
will have a default hover over effect. but it won't do anything yet. So. let's go and make that happen!
So. the first thing you may notice is. I've slightly changed my window's screen scaling.
so that when I hit the play button here. inside the Main Menu blueprint.
I actually get a preview window that doesn't overspill my screen. So everything will
be a little bit smaller for you. for the next few videos. Alright. another thing
is that once we have actually brought up this preview screen...
By the way. it's previewing an empty scene
at the moment. So if you want it to preview the actual menu. you need to go to the MainMenu
level or scene. and then. back in the blueprint. when you click play you'll find it
previews your actual menu. Now. there's no mouse. so one of the first things we need
to sort out is. how do you show the mouse when the UI is displaying? Well.
let's take a look at that now. Back in the level blueprint.
for the MainMenu. we have currently just created the menu
widget instance. from the menu blueprint class. and added it to the
Viewport. What we need to do now is to show the player's
mouse. So. we start by finding the player. So. if you do
a search. you can look for Get Player Controller. That is me. that's the human
player controlling this instance of the game.
So there's Get Player Controller! There you go! Now. from the return value. so that we
use the context sensitivity. we can then look for mouse.
and then. one of the options towards the bottom will be Set Show Mouse Cursor.
So. we get a reference to the Player Controller. we tick Set Show
Mouse Cursor. and then bring that into the execution
flow. so that once we have added the widget to the Viewport.
we then show the mouse cursor. Let's try it! Either play from the
main menu. and you can see there is a mouse there. or you can go to the main menu
blueprint there and then. you could use the play button. and you'll see that
we now have a mouse. And that has a couple of benefits. firstly. we're going to be able to click the button when
it comes up. but secondly. I can go to the bottom-right of the window and I can resize it and that will
show us how this image responds to changes in screen size. Now. I don't
like that. at the moment. Firstly. it's not filling the background. and secondly. I don't like the
way that it's cropping and leaving black areas with different screen sizes.
So. let's sort that out. I'm going to rename Background Image to just MainBG. just to make
it shorter. but that's just really me being tidy. it's not super important.
It isn't actually variable. so it's not going to have an intractable element in it. so you can
un-tick Is Variable. if you wish. and also the MainBG will no longer be bold
in the hierarchy. Now. what we need is under Panel.
you'll see there is a Scale Box. Now. if you hover over that and read it for yourself...
That's. by the way. Window. Palette. if you haven't got it. Panel section.
and then. Scale Box. If you read the stuff that comes up. it'll tell you that it's ideal
for background images. So. let's use one of them. We pop it straight onto the [Canvas Panel]. which
is our main panel for our entire User Interface. and
instead of the background image being straight on the panel. we put it on the Scale Box.
Now. let's see the effect that has. Firstly. we want this Scale Box's anchors to
be this selection at the bottom-right. so that it covers the
entire background. and then we want no offsets either.
So. let's remove those offsets. and that sets it to cover most of the screen like
that. But most of the screen is not good
enough. we want all of the screen. so select 0.0 so that all of the offsets
are 0.00 0.00 0.00. That way the Scale Box is covering
the entire UI canvas. and that is going to
be what we're looking for. So. let's see how this behaves now.
So far similarly. and that's because the scaling type isn't
what we're after. So. if you click on [Scale Box] and you look under the Stretching settings.
under details. and then. there is Scale to Fit but also
Scale to Fill. I took a while finding this recently. because they look almost identical. It's only a
couple of letters different right? So. try Scale to Fill. Let's have a look at
that now. as a preview.
Now that's nicer. look as we go up it takes a bit of the top and bottom of the image off. and left
and right. that works as well. Now. for a small array of different screen shapes.
like I'm going through now. this is working fine. And this also is important when you choose your image.
that you have what a designer would call quite zones around the left. right. top. and bottom
of the image. bits of the image that it doesn't matter too much if you lose. The screen could come in
a little bit like that. it can go out. and the image still looks OK.
Cool! So. now that we've got our scaling setup properly. let's go ahead
and show you how to add text and buttons. I'm not actually going to add them yet. I'm going to
challenge you to do that. But the things you're looking for to finish this initial version of the UI
off is number one Text. You can drag the Text into
or straight onto the [Canvas Panel]. It is not inside the [Scale Box] you need to do this. the
[Scale Box] is purely for the background image. We could call it BG
Scale. for instance. and then. you could even
collapse that down. So. we have this background scale box there.
and then. now we have a Text Block. So this could be the title. you could rename that. but the point with Text Box
is. you can move them around and under Appearance. under Font. you can change
the size of the text. Now. talking about font. please
take a little bit of time to customize the font. This default font is really boring and stinks of
somebody who's not bothered to customize it. So. somewhere like Dafont
is a good idea. Have a look through here. I'm going to use Ink Tank. So.
just searching for tank. you'll find Ink Tank here. but there's plenty of others! You could use
Boom Tank. you could use whatever.  Now. you want to have a look at
the license. it's up top here. Ink Tank is 100%
free. but Boom Tank. for example is free for personal use. If you're going to be
using this in an actual game. then you need to be thinking a little bit about what your
license is. and you need to be very careful that you either contact the author. if you're not sure.
or that you adhere to the license terms. And certainly. if you're going to be selling your game. you need to be
buying the font. But I'm going to use Ink Tank. which is free. Now. let's
get the font imported. Then. I'll show you how to make a button. then I'll leave you to
layout your UI. So. I'm going to download
the .zip file. In there I've got a .ttf. which is a True Type Font.
and the way you get that into Unreal is like the same way as you get any other asset in.
You go to your Content Browser. I'm going to go to
my UI folder. I'm going to import an asset. it's going to be Ink Tank. and
it's come in automatically as a font which is cool! So. back over here now.
in my list of fonts. I will simply be able to find Ink Tank.
There you go! So. that's how you put a text block in! The other thing I'm
going to show you is how you put a button in. You drop a button. not into the screen it won't work. but onto the
[Canvas Panel]. and then. again with a button you can resize it.
Think about the anchor. One of the first things you want to do with any UI element is think about where do you want your button
to be on the screen and where do you want it to stick to? Do you want it to stick to the bottom-right. the top-right. whatever?
And then. also you can drag text onto the button to label
it. alright. Now I want you to have a play with that. and remember to customize your fonts. So.
I'm going to delete that button for now and put you into your challenge which is to
layout your main menu. Choose a font for your title text. consider adding a
sub-title. add and style a start button. and check that the scaling
works well and that the button is visible at variety of different screen shapes.
So. go ahead. pause the video. and setup your UI now.
OK. welcome back! So.
I'm going to start by just putting some text in. as I did before. I'm going to call it Battle
Tank. Now hopefully you've found the property where you've set the text. it's here.
Let's go ahead and scale that up.
choose a font. Now. this text I want
anchored to the bottom-left of the screen. which means I want it to be a fixed offset from
the bottom-left of the screen. I'm going to justify it to the left. I think.
because I'm anchoring to the left it makes sense to justify to the left. so that we have. as I said.
the word starts in a fixed position compared to the bottom-left. Remember to go ahead and
preview these things nice and lean. i.e. nice and instantaneously. after you've put them
down. As soon as you've got your font how you want it. have a preview.
and just make sure that. for a reasonable range of screen shapes that. the
text doesn't interfere with the background and is legible. Great! That's looking OK
to me. Fine. now let's put in another button! But one
second first. I'm going to give this a name. Let's call it Title
Text. Fine! Now. let's pop a button in
onto the [Canvas Panel]. so we have the background scale box. By the way. that background
scale box aught to have a ZOrder. which is the Z depth.
It says higher numbers appear on top. so let's give it a value of -99 just to
indicate this is going to be way in the background. Anything less than 0 is fine.
and I'm just going to use -99. We just want to make sure that we explicitly tell the system that. that background
renders behind this text. which has a ZOrder of 0.
Alright. otherwise there's a chance that it won't render in the right place.
then the text will be obscured. The same with the button. I'm going to leave the button at 0. The reason I'm choosing
-99 for the background images is because. then anything else you put in comes
with this default ZOrder of 0. and then. we don't need to worry about it. it's something we don't need to change every time.
So. let's have a button down on the bottom-left here. Now. immediately when
you put that UI element in. think about where its anchors should be. The buttons are going to be anchored to
the bottom-right. There's that! OK. now
it's going to be called StartButton.
Let's just call it Start Button. It is variable.
this Variable button. if you un-tick that you won't get any events and you won't be able to deal with on
click. so leave that variable. And it's bold in the hierarchy.
it just means it's an intractable element. Now. let's add on Text and drop it on the
StartButton. I'm just going to call it StartText.
And let's change the
text to the word Start.
in capitals. I think it's nice and easy to read. Let's zoom in so we can see it.
Rescale a little bit. Start.
Just change the font to be consistent.
There you go. that's fine! Now if
you're finding that you don't like the alignment of this thing. it is possible to play around
with the padding. For instance. I could probably do with some more Top padding here.
Go to 4 or 5 pixels of Top padding or
6 even. I might just bring the word Start down a little bit and make it look a little bit more
sensible. something like that. And there you go. we now have a Start
button. Let's check the scaling. and then. we are done for this video!
So that's good! The Start button is
anchoring to the bottom-right. Battle Tank to the bottom-left. Unless we have a ridiculously narrow
screen. even at like 4:3. it's just about going to be feasible.
and on a wider screen. people have these wide monitors now. then it's all looking like
it's going to work which is great! Awesome! So. I'm going to
now commit my work. Remember to be using SourceControl yourself. I suggest every
single video. but you just want to get in the habit of committing your changes. Before you commit
anything. make sure you click Save All. of course. in Unreal so that all of your changes are saved to
disk. there are no asterisks up at the top here. And I will see you in the next video!
=======
Welcome to UI
Scale Box, Buttons, & Mouse, where we'll be covering those three things. By the end of the video
you will have a much improved menu system, where we
have a mouse, for a start, which you may notice we didn't have before. We'll be able to scale the
window with our title text and our buttons sticking appropriately and
the background image scaling nicely. And that's it really, for now, the mouse
will have a default hover over effect, but it won't do anything yet. So, let's go and make that happen!
So, the first thing you may notice is, I've slightly changed my window's screen scaling,
so that when I hit the play button here, inside the Main Menu blueprint,
I actually get a preview window that doesn't overspill my screen. So everything will
be a little bit smaller for you, for the next few videos. Alright, another thing
is that once we have actually brought up this preview screen...
By the way, it's previewing an empty scene
at the moment. So if you want it to preview the actual menu, you need to go to the MainMenu
level or scene, and then, back in the blueprint, when you click play you'll find it
previews your actual menu. Now, there's no mouse, so one of the first things we need
to sort out is, how do you show the mouse when the UI is displaying? Well,
let's take a look at that now. Back in the level blueprint,
for the MainMenu, we have currently just created the menu
widget instance, from the menu blueprint class, and added it to the
Viewport. What we need to do now is to show the player's
mouse. So, we start by finding the player. So, if you do
a search, you can look for Get Player Controller. That is me, that's the human
player controlling this instance of the game.
So there's Get Player Controller! There you go! Now, from the return value, so that we
use the context sensitivity, we can then look for mouse,
and then, one of the options towards the bottom will be Set Show Mouse Cursor.
So, we get a reference to the Player Controller, we tick Set Show
Mouse Cursor, and then bring that into the execution
flow, so that once we have added the widget to the Viewport,
we then show the mouse cursor. Let's try it! Either play from the
main menu, and you can see there is a mouse there, or you can go to the main menu
blueprint there and then, you could use the play button, and you'll see that
we now have a mouse. And that has a couple of benefits, firstly, we're going to be able to click the button when
it comes up, but secondly, I can go to the bottom-right of the window and I can resize it and that will
show us how this image responds to changes in screen size. Now, I don't
like that, at the moment. Firstly, it's not filling the background, and secondly, I don't like the
way that it's cropping and leaving black areas with different screen sizes.
So, let's sort that out. I'm going to rename Background Image to just MainBG, just to make
it shorter, but that's just really me being tidy, it's not super important.
It isn't actually variable, so it's not going to have an intractable element in it, so you can
un-tick Is Variable, if you wish, and also the MainBG will no longer be bold
in the hierarchy. Now, what we need is under Panel,
you'll see there is a Scale Box. Now, if you hover over that and read it for yourself...
That's, by the way, Window, Palette, if you haven't got it, Panel section,
and then, Scale Box. If you read the stuff that comes up, it'll tell you that it's ideal
for background images. So, let's use one of them. We pop it straight onto the [Canvas Panel], which
is our main panel for our entire User Interface, and
instead of the background image being straight on the panel, we put it on the Scale Box.
Now, let's see the effect that has. Firstly, we want this Scale Box's anchors to
be this selection at the bottom-right, so that it covers the
entire background, and then we want no offsets either.
So, let's remove those offsets, and that sets it to cover most of the screen like
that. But most of the screen is not good
enough, we want all of the screen, so select 0.0 so that all of the offsets
are 0.00 0.00 0.00. That way the Scale Box is covering
the entire UI canvas, and that is going to
be what we're looking for. So, let's see how this behaves now.
So far similarly, and that's because the scaling type isn't
what we're after. So, if you click on [Scale Box] and you look under the Stretching settings,
under details, and then, there is Scale to Fit but also
Scale to Fill. I took a while finding this recently, because they look almost identical. It's only a
couple of letters different right? So, try Scale to Fill. Let's have a look at
that now, as a preview.
Now that's nicer, look as we go up it takes a bit of the top and bottom of the image off, and left
and right, that works as well. Now, for a small array of different screen shapes,
like I'm going through now, this is working fine. And this also is important when you choose your image,
that you have what a designer would call quite zones around the left, right, top, and bottom
of the image, bits of the image that it doesn't matter too much if you lose. The screen could come in
a little bit like that, it can go out, and the image still looks OK.
Cool! So, now that we've got our scaling setup properly, let's go ahead
and show you how to add text and buttons. I'm not actually going to add them yet, I'm going to
challenge you to do that. But the things you're looking for to finish this initial version of the UI
off is number one Text. You can drag the Text into
or straight onto the [Canvas Panel]. It is not inside the [Scale Box] you need to do this, the
[Scale Box] is purely for the background image. We could call it BG
Scale, for instance, and then, you could even
collapse that down. So, we have this background scale box there,
and then, now we have a Text Block. So this could be the title, you could rename that, but the point with Text Box
is, you can move them around and under Appearance, under Font, you can change
the size of the text. Now, talking about font, please
take a little bit of time to customize the font. This default font is really boring and stinks of
somebody who's not bothered to customize it. So, somewhere like Dafont
is a good idea. Have a look through here. I'm going to use Ink Tank. So,
just searching for tank, you'll find Ink Tank here, but there's plenty of others! You could use
Boom Tank, you could use whatever.  Now, you want to have a look at
the license, it's up top here. Ink Tank is 100%
free, but Boom Tank, for example is free for personal use. If you're going to be
using this in an actual game, then you need to be thinking a little bit about what your
license is, and you need to be very careful that you either contact the author, if you're not sure,
or that you adhere to the license terms. And certainly, if you're going to be selling your game, you need to be
buying the font. But I'm going to use Ink Tank, which is free. Now, let's
get the font imported. Then, I'll show you how to make a button, then I'll leave you to
layout your UI. So, I'm going to download
the .zip file. In there I've got a .ttf, which is a True Type Font,
and the way you get that into Unreal is like the same way as you get any other asset in.
You go to your Content Browser. I'm going to go to
my UI folder. I'm going to import an asset, it's going to be Ink Tank, and
it's come in automatically as a font which is cool! So, back over here now,
in my list of fonts, I will simply be able to find Ink Tank.
There you go! So, that's how you put a text block in! The other thing I'm
going to show you is how you put a button in. You drop a button, not into the screen it won't work, but onto the
[Canvas Panel], and then, again with a button you can resize it.
Think about the anchor. One of the first things you want to do with any UI element is think about where do you want your button
to be on the screen and where do you want it to stick to? Do you want it to stick to the bottom-right, the top-right, whatever?
And then, also you can drag text onto the button to label
it, alright. Now I want you to have a play with that, and remember to customize your fonts. So,
I'm going to delete that button for now and put you into your challenge which is to
layout your main menu. Choose a font for your title text, consider adding a
sub-title, add and style a start button, and check that the scaling
works well and that the button is visible at variety of different screen shapes.
So, go ahead, pause the video, and setup your UI now.
OK, welcome back! So,
I'm going to start by just putting some text in, as I did before. I'm going to call it Battle
Tank. Now hopefully you've found the property where you've set the text, it's here.
Let's go ahead and scale that up,
choose a font. Now, this text I want
anchored to the bottom-left of the screen, which means I want it to be a fixed offset from
the bottom-left of the screen. I'm going to justify it to the left, I think,
because I'm anchoring to the left it makes sense to justify to the left, so that we have, as I said,
the word starts in a fixed position compared to the bottom-left. Remember to go ahead and
preview these things nice and lean, i.e. nice and instantaneously, after you've put them
down. As soon as you've got your font how you want it, have a preview,
and just make sure that, for a reasonable range of screen shapes that, the
text doesn't interfere with the background and is legible. Great! That's looking OK
to me. Fine, now let's put in another button! But one
second first, I'm going to give this a name. Let's call it Title
Text. Fine! Now, let's pop a button in
onto the [Canvas Panel], so we have the background scale box. By the way, that background
scale box aught to have a ZOrder, which is the Z depth.
It says higher numbers appear on top, so let's give it a value of -99 just to
indicate this is going to be way in the background. Anything less than 0 is fine,
and I'm just going to use -99. We just want to make sure that we explicitly tell the system that, that background
renders behind this text, which has a ZOrder of 0.
Alright, otherwise there's a chance that it won't render in the right place,
then the text will be obscured. The same with the button, I'm going to leave the button at 0. The reason I'm choosing
-99 for the background images is because, then anything else you put in comes
with this default ZOrder of 0, and then, we don't need to worry about it, it's something we don't need to change every time.
So, let's have a button down on the bottom-left here. Now, immediately when
you put that UI element in, think about where its anchors should be. The buttons are going to be anchored to
the bottom-right. There's that! OK, now
it's going to be called StartButton.
Let's just call it Start Button. It is variable,
this Variable button, if you un-tick that you won't get any events and you won't be able to deal with on
click, so leave that variable. And it's bold in the hierarchy,
it just means it's an intractable element. Now, let's add on Text and drop it on the
StartButton. I'm just going to call it StartText.
And let's change the
text to the word Start,
in capitals. I think it's nice and easy to read. Let's zoom in so we can see it.
Rescale a little bit, Start.
Just change the font to be consistent.
There you go, that's fine! Now if
you're finding that you don't like the alignment of this thing, it is possible to play around
with the padding. For instance, I could probably do with some more Top padding here.
Go to 4 or 5 pixels of Top padding or
6 even. I might just bring the word Start down a little bit and make it look a little bit more
sensible, something like that. And there you go, we now have a Start
button. Let's check the scaling, and then, we are done for this video!
So that's good! The Start button is
anchoring to the bottom-right, Battle Tank to the bottom-left. Unless we have a ridiculously narrow
screen, even at like 4:3, it's just about going to be feasible,
and on a wider screen, people have these wide monitors now, then it's all looking like
it's going to work which is great! Awesome! So, I'm going to
now commit my work. Remember to be using SourceControl yourself. I suggest every
single video, but you just want to get in the habit of committing your changes. Before you commit
anything, make sure you click Save All, of course, in Unreal so that all of your changes are saved to
disk, there are no asterisks up at the top here. And I will see you in the next video!
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1:Unreal/Section4/BT18 UI Scale Box, Buttons & Mouse.srt