Hi and welcome to Trial
Packaging Your Game! What we're going to be doing this video is actually making a Windows executable
here. which is going to run independent of the Editor altogether. and you'll have an
actual app here that you can rescale and move around. And crucially you'll
be able to start it. this was me hitting on the control pad. move the camera around.
and then. quit. all just from the control pad. which is
great! Or keyboard and mouse if you want. but the point is. there's a complete game loop available. Let's dive in and see how that works!
OK. so the first place to start is to make sure that in our Settings and
Project Settings. that we actually under Maps and Modes. have the
Game Default Map set correctly to the main menu. because that's where we want to start.
I think I'm going to set my Editor Startup Map to the
BattleGround. actually. just to show the difference. So. the
Editor Default Map is the following. If I close Unreal altogether and then
reopen it. then what's going to happen is. because I set the Editor Default Map
to the BattleGround that's where we're going to end up. which is fine for building this game. Most of the action happens
here. When we play. we'll also be playing straight from the battleground. but
when we build the game. and that's what I'm going to want you to do in this video. you can either do
it with me or you can wait until the challenge in a minute and do it for yourself. What we're doing to do is.
we're going to package the project rather for. in this case. a Windows
for me. a 64-bit Windows. and I'm going to pop it in my Downloads
folder and just let Unreal go ahead and package this. So. we're actually going to be making
a stand alone game here that we can run. so almost a shippable
game. not quite. Quit a lot more to do. So. if we just watch in Downloads
what comes in. let's see what actually happens because it's quite interesting
to see what it actually produces. It's not currently
appearing in Downloads. for some reason. Maybe it hasn't refreshed? Here you go! So. you'll find
yourself a folder called a WindowsNoEditor. It's still building but there's a folder called WindowsNoEditor.
And what have you go in there? Well. let's look at the size of these things. Actually. let's use
TreeSize. a useful little utility I have installed. TreeSize Free.
there we go! So. most of it goes in this BattleTank folder 655
megabytes. In the Content and then in a Pak. it makes this Content Pak.
which contains all the assets basically. There are the Binaries
as well. which there has an .exe in it. and then. you've also got
an Engine folder which includes the parts of the engine that you need for this game
to run. So. all in all you end up with this lot. and what
you want to run is this top-level BattleTank.exe. And
with any luck it'll go to the start menu. or the main menu as we call it.
because that is where we decided to go. If you check the scaling. then this is all
working. Then. we start the game. Now. the scaling. by the way. in the game we haven't
really thought about. but so far it's working fine because it's just rendering a 3D scene.
so the scaling will work. And that's it. so you can close the app
by either hitting the Escape key...
Is that working? Let me try again. let me run it.
start. and then. I'm going to try the Escape key. No. the back key on the
gamepad is also not working. OK. so we need to sort that out. because I did
want a way of getting out of the game. Let me make sure. before I go and sort that out. that we can get into
the game. so I'm going to push A on the gamepad now. Yeah. so A is working
but the back button isn't. So. let's go see what's wrong. There's something simple
in the Project Settings. Let's start at the beginning. Input. Quit.
It's either the Escape key or the Gamepad Special Left. Great! So.
now what we need to do is make sure that in the level blueprint for this.
we actually have an InputAction on
Quit. Yeah. InputAction Quit. we Quit the Game.
Yeah. the Quit Preference is Quit. so that should be working. Let's
try it from here. from the preview. I'm going to hit Escape and it does stop.
I'm also going to hit the back button on the controller and it does stop. so I'm not sure
now why it's not stopping when we packaged for the
windows. Let's just try repackaging. Sometimes it can be
a little bit quirky like this. We just want to make sure that we have a fully
playable standalone game for this video. that's the purpose. I just want you
to get used to packaging really early for testing. because even though the Editor is supposed
to preview precisely what the game would be like. when it's running on the target machine. you
can't be sure that it's doing that perfectly all the time. It's a very good practice to
regularly package and check. and this just seems like a good time to do it. especially
because we're dealing with esoteric things like. you know. bindings
of these controls and exit conditions. So. let's try running again!
I'm picking up my gamepad. I'm pushing the A button. we're going into the game.
I'm going to push the back button now. and it's still not quitting.
Nope OK. so we still need to do some work!
Now. this is a slightly strange error. and I believe the reason for it is as
follows. Let's try! If we start in the MainMenu here
and we run the game and I hit A and then
I check that I can move. Ah you see I can't control the tank. whereas
if I start playing directly from the battleground. then I can control
the tank. and that's because the input mode has defaulted to game only.
The problem is this. in the MainMenu blueprint when
we setup. in the beginning once the widget is ready. we set the Input Mode to UI only.
but when we hit the start menu and go ahead and open BattleGround. we
still have the Input Mode in UI only. so it's persisting through.
So there's lots of places we could change this. but I think here is a good place to do it. because it's right
next to where we set it. So. if you go to your Main Menu blueprint.
in the Event Graph. and there's a Set Input Mode
to Game Only node. Let's set that. So. what we're
saying is. if we hit the start button.
then what we want to do is we want to open the BattleGround level. and then set the
Input Mode to Game Only. for the Player Controller. It's a bit ugly
this but it's fine. In fact. if we move things around a little bit. we can prevent
crossing. which always makes things a little bit clearer. OK. so we're saying that
once we've opened the BattleGround level. set the Input Mode to Game Only. Let's see what
that does. It'll only take effect if you start the game from the main menu.
Play the game. we hit A on the controller. we test that we have
control. which we do. We may want to give the player an inverted Y axis later option later. but
for now. that's fine. and then. I hit the back button on the controller and the game quits. That's
great! So the final check is to make sure this actually works in a Windows 64
build. so I'll just go ahead and just do the build. And that's
that! So the problem was that the Input Mode propagated from the menu outwards.
so we fixed that right at the source by saying. well as soon as you leave go ahead and change
the Input Mode back. Alright. so let's just wait for the package to finish.
test it out. and then we'll be taking it from there. So. let's go ahead
and run and have a final test. Start.
control works. back button works. and that's all without
touching the keyboard or mouse! Fantastic! So. if you haven't done it already. I want you to
package for your operating system. set the Editor and Game startup maps. build for your
platform. and test that it runs well. Try rescaling the menu. try the gamepad
only. see if you can get in and out of the game with just the gamepad. Of course. you'll have to double-
click it to launch it in the first place. and I'll see you in the next video.
=======
Hi and welcome to Trial
Packaging Your Game! What we're going to be doing this video is actually making a Windows executable
here, which is going to run independent of the Editor altogether, and you'll have an
actual app here that you can rescale and move around. And crucially you'll
be able to start it, this was me hitting on the control pad, move the camera around,
and then, quit, all just from the control pad, which is
great! Or keyboard and mouse if you want, but the point is, there's a complete game loop available. Let's dive in and see how that works!
OK, so the first place to start is to make sure that in our Settings and
Project Settings, that we actually under Maps and Modes. have the
Game Default Map set correctly to the main menu, because that's where we want to start.
I think I'm going to set my Editor Startup Map to the
BattleGround, actually, just to show the difference. So, the
Editor Default Map is the following. If I close Unreal altogether and then
reopen it, then what's going to happen is, because I set the Editor Default Map
to the BattleGround that's where we're going to end up, which is fine for building this game. Most of the action happens
here. When we play, we'll also be playing straight from the battleground, but
when we build the game, and that's what I'm going to want you to do in this video, you can either do
it with me or you can wait until the challenge in a minute and do it for yourself. What we're doing to do is,
we're going to package the project rather for, in this case, a Windows
for me, a 64-bit Windows, and I'm going to pop it in my Downloads
folder and just let Unreal go ahead and package this. So, we're actually going to be making
a stand alone game here that we can run, so almost a shippable
game, not quite. Quit a lot more to do. So, if we just watch in Downloads
what comes in, let's see what actually happens because it's quite interesting
to see what it actually produces. It's not currently
appearing in Downloads, for some reason. Maybe it hasn't refreshed? Here you go! So, you'll find
yourself a folder called a WindowsNoEditor. It's still building but there's a folder called WindowsNoEditor.
And what have you go in there? Well, let's look at the size of these things. Actually, let's use
TreeSize, a useful little utility I have installed. TreeSize Free,
there we go! So, most of it goes in this BattleTank folder 655
megabytes. In the Content and then in a Pak, it makes this Content Pak,
which contains all the assets basically. There are the Binaries
as well, which there has an .exe in it, and then, you've also got
an Engine folder which includes the parts of the engine that you need for this game
to run. So, all in all you end up with this lot, and what
you want to run is this top-level BattleTank.exe. And
with any luck it'll go to the start menu, or the main menu as we call it,
because that is where we decided to go. If you check the scaling, then this is all
working. Then, we start the game. Now, the scaling, by the way, in the game we haven't
really thought about, but so far it's working fine because it's just rendering a 3D scene,
so the scaling will work. And that's it, so you can close the app
by either hitting the Escape key...
Is that working? Let me try again, let me run it,
start, and then, I'm going to try the Escape key. No, the back key on the
gamepad is also not working. OK, so we need to sort that out, because I did
want a way of getting out of the game. Let me make sure, before I go and sort that out, that we can get into
the game, so I'm going to push A on the gamepad now. Yeah, so A is working
but the back button isn't. So, let's go see what's wrong. There's something simple
in the Project Settings. Let's start at the beginning, Input, Quit.
It's either the Escape key or the Gamepad Special Left. Great! So,
now what we need to do is make sure that in the level blueprint for this,
we actually have an InputAction on
Quit. Yeah, InputAction Quit, we Quit the Game.
Yeah, the Quit Preference is Quit, so that should be working. Let's
try it from here, from the preview. I'm going to hit Escape and it does stop.
I'm also going to hit the back button on the controller and it does stop, so I'm not sure
now why it's not stopping when we packaged for the
windows. Let's just try repackaging. Sometimes it can be
a little bit quirky like this. We just want to make sure that we have a fully
playable standalone game for this video, that's the purpose. I just want you
to get used to packaging really early for testing, because even though the Editor is supposed
to preview precisely what the game would be like, when it's running on the target machine, you
can't be sure that it's doing that perfectly all the time. It's a very good practice to
regularly package and check, and this just seems like a good time to do it, especially
because we're dealing with esoteric things like, you know, bindings
of these controls and exit conditions. So, let's try running again!
I'm picking up my gamepad, I'm pushing the A button, we're going into the game,
I'm going to push the back button now, and it's still not quitting.
Nope OK, so we still need to do some work!
Now, this is a slightly strange error, and I believe the reason for it is as
follows. Let's try! If we start in the MainMenu here
and we run the game and I hit A and then
I check that I can move. Ah you see I can't control the tank, whereas
if I start playing directly from the battleground, then I can control
the tank, and that's because the input mode has defaulted to game only.
The problem is this, in the MainMenu blueprint when
we setup, in the beginning once the widget is ready, we set the Input Mode to UI only,
but when we hit the start menu and go ahead and open BattleGround, we
still have the Input Mode in UI only, so it's persisting through.
So there's lots of places we could change this, but I think here is a good place to do it, because it's right
next to where we set it. So, if you go to your Main Menu blueprint,
in the Event Graph, and there's a Set Input Mode
to Game Only node. Let's set that. So, what we're
saying is, if we hit the start button,
then what we want to do is we want to open the BattleGround level, and then set the
Input Mode to Game Only, for the Player Controller. It's a bit ugly
this but it's fine. In fact, if we move things around a little bit, we can prevent
crossing, which always makes things a little bit clearer. OK, so we're saying that
once we've opened the BattleGround level, set the Input Mode to Game Only. Let's see what
that does. It'll only take effect if you start the game from the main menu.
Play the game, we hit A on the controller, we test that we have
control, which we do. We may want to give the player an inverted Y axis later option later, but
for now, that's fine, and then, I hit the back button on the controller and the game quits. That's
great! So the final check is to make sure this actually works in a Windows 64
build, so I'll just go ahead and just do the build. And that's
that! So the problem was that the Input Mode propagated from the menu outwards,
so we fixed that right at the source by saying, well as soon as you leave go ahead and change
the Input Mode back. Alright, so let's just wait for the package to finish,
test it out, and then we'll be taking it from there. So, let's go ahead
and run and have a final test. Start,
control works, back button works, and that's all without
touching the keyboard or mouse! Fantastic! So, if you haven't done it already, I want you to
package for your operating system, set the Editor and Game startup maps, build for your
platform, and test that it runs well. Try rescaling the menu, try the gamepad
only, see if you can get in and out of the game with just the gamepad. Of course, you'll have to double-
click it to launch it in the first place, and I'll see you in the next video.
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1:Unreal/Section4/BT20 Trial Packaging Your Game.srt