Welcome to
Delegating to Components. In this video. we're going to start fleshing out the architecture
of our tank game and really setting ourselves up to win. So. I'll see you in there!
OK. so let's talk about our Iterative
Cycle. just to get a handle on where we are. We've kind of been around this once. and we're going to have another
look at the tank now. in a bit more detail. So.
this is our Aiming Architecture. I'm sorry I can't build this up bit by bit. but it's a limitation
of Google Slides. So. how are we going to do this? Well. let's start at the
top. The Tank is going to be possessed by one of two things.
either a Tank AI Controller or a Tank Player Controller. i.e. us
at the keyboard or trackpad. And either of those controllers. depending
on which one is possessing the tank. is going to send messages to the tank. So.
in the case of the AI Controller it's going to send a message that's going to say something like AimAt
the Player. And in the case of the Tank Player. it's going to Aim At the
(Crosshair). although there's a bit of a subtlety there. because the crosshair's in 2D
space. and if you project from the camera through the crosshair to
the world. then you're talking about a 3D space. So. we'll deal with that when we get to it. but
we're basically saying aim it where this crosshair's pointing at in the world.
And then. the Tank is going to receive that and say. well OK that's fine. but I'm going to deligate
that functionality down to my Tank Aiming Component. Why bother with that?
Well. it's simple information hiding. The Tank Player Controller. the Tank AI Controller.
anything outside of the Tank don't care how the Tank aims. they're just
saying to it. please aim at something. And the Tank. we're saying is
complicated enough to need to break it's functionality into components. It's going to have a
Tank Aiming Component. It's also going to have a Tank Movement Component. So. it's
going to simply pass that method straight through to the Tank Aiming Component. which is going to do some processing
on it. including ballistic calculations. etc.
By the way. by ballistic calculations I mean a reverse calculation of
where it needs to aim right now. in order to hit the desired target.
or more specifically how fast it needs to fire in order to hit that
target. the projectile velocity. Once it's worked all that out. it's going to then
raise an event in Blueprint. Why in Blueprint? Well. because
what's actually finally going to happen is. we're going to rotate the turret and we're going to elevate the barrel.
and those two things. the turret and the barrel are
assets and they want to be soft-referenced in Blueprint. so that should we want
to make a change to those assets. well they're not hard coded by path. by
file name. in the C++. So. we make all our asset references in Blueprint. So. finally
this long line of code will emerge in the blueprint. and that will
do the final bit of work. Alright. so for any of this to work. we're going to
go through it bit by bit nice and slowly. The first thing we're going to need is a Tank Player Controller
in C++. So if you remember. in our project. we already have.
of course. in the Tank folder a TankPlayerController blueprint.
and it does very little at the moment. It just sets up the User
Interface. the Player User Interface. but it's currently based on
the Player Controller class. What we want to do is. we want to
specialize this ourselves and make ourselves our own Tank Player Controller.
So. that's going to be your challenge. is just to make sure that you know how
to make your own classes. So. before I put you into a challenge.
I want to remind you how to reparent a class. You click on Class Settings and then
you can choose your parent class here. So. here's the challenge for you. relatively
simple. I want you to create a Tank Player Controller C++ class.
You'll need to compile that class first. then you can reparent the TankPlayer
Controller blueprint onto your new class. By the way. the TankPlayer
Controller is going to inherit from Player Controller. So. that's what you're going
to be inheriting from. when you create it. You're going to have to find your way around the menus to do this. We've done this before.
so it should be a good bit of revision for you. And basically good luck!
So. see if you can do that. The class doesn't need to do anything yet. we just want you to create it
and reparent the blueprint.
OK. welcome back! So. here we are in
Unreal. I am going to go to my C++ classes. We're going to add a new C++ class.
and we're going to have to ask ourselves what type of
class this is. Well. here you have a PlayerController option.
so the reason for choosing these things is. it prevents you from having to write all of the
header code in the header file yourself. By doing this. it's basically writing a bunch of
that for you. So. we choose the Player Controller style.
We're going to call it TankPlayerController. as we're specializing a
PlayerController for a tank.There's also the concept here. by the way.
of public and private. in terms of
where it stores these things. in terms of directories. Click the buttons and
see what it does. If you click Private. then both of these methods go into
a private folder. Both the header file rather and the C++ file go into
a Private subfolder of BattleTank. If you click Public. then the header file is
left out in a Public folder. so you're really asking yourself the question.
is this thing going to be called from the outside? But there is no outside
here. You know. we're just a tank game. we're not multi-module
here. this is just a single game. So. some projects
decide to separate their files into public and private. for simplicity.
I'm just going to do this. just so we can get used to it. What we're going to do for the whole project is just always
click Public. and then. all that's going to do is mean that all our header files will be in a folder
called Public and all our C++ folders will be in a subfolder called Private.
So. let's go ahead and create that TankPlayerController class
now. It doesn't matter. by the way. if you didn't choose public or private. I've never brought it up before.
I didn't expect you to. We can move our classes into these required sub-directories
in a little bit. But for now. let's just let this
happen and we'll check our header file. and then. we
will carry on. because one of the first things we're going to need to do. once this
class exists is make ourselves a getter. which can get the controlled tank. So. that'll be the
first method I'll be writing. Let's go and
have a look at the disk. while we wait for this. for a second by the way. Let's have a look
at Source. BattleTank. and now you can see we have these
the Build. the GameMode. etc. These have all come as default. And then. you've got this concept
of private. which now has our TankPlayerController.cpp in it
and Public which has the header file. So. all that Public button has done has said that
I want it separated into this type of subfolder. Great! OK. so
now we have what? TankPlayerController.h I'm looking for. What
has it written for us? It's included "GameFramework/PlayerController.
h" and "TankPlayerController.generated.h". That's always there.
That's all fine! And it's created us a new class called ATankPlayerController
based on APlayerController. That's all fine! So
let's make ourselves a public getter. as a start. So. public and it's
going to be GetControlledTank. So. we're going to return a
pointer to a tank. Now of course. it doesn't know what a tank it. so we're going to need to
#include the tank. It needs to go above the generated .h. The
generated .h must be the last
include. Alright. so just remember that. it's just a quirk of the Unreal Header
Tool. So. we're going to #include
"Tank.h". otherwise this ATank* pointer will not
be a recognized type. The method's going to be
GetControlledTank(). and it's going to be const; It's not going to change any
future member variables of this class right. Being a getter that
makes sense. So. let's try and see... Oh. hang on. am I missing
something here? ATank*. no I think that's good! Let's see if we can implement this
using the VisualStudio Create Definition
method. Ah. you see it's failed. so don't worry. I'm going
to just go and do it manually. as you would have to do it if you're in Xcode. So. in Xcode
or VisualStudio. you're over in the .cpp. You have to. of course. paste that in. but there's
some syntactic noise we need to add. of course. over in the C++ file.
We need to get the name of the class and put a colon colon in.
to fully qualify the class name. So. what we
have is ATank* pointer. ATankPlayerController::GetControlled
Tank() const; We keep the same
signature. and then. we need our curly braces to give us the
implementation. So. what do we do? How do we get the
ControlledTank? Why are we getting the ControlledTank. in the first place? Let's go back to our architecture.
The TankPlayerController is going to need to know what tank it is controlling.
So. we're going to ask the TankPlayerController. what tank are you controlling?
Alright. so GetControlTank is going to work like this. We get Pawn.
from the TankPlayerController's
perspective. and what that should do is return the Pawn that
the PlayerController is currently possessing. That's all happening because our
PlayerController class is based on this APlayerController here. So. GetPawn() should return
the Pawn. The tank is a specialization of the Pawn. so what we're going to do is we're
going to cast to type ATank
that Pawn. OK. like so
and then. that's the value we're going to be
returning. So. that's what GetControlledTank() should be doing for us.
Alright. we'd better check it works. so we'd better have a BeginPlay. I think.
Well. let's just check it compiles to start with. before we check it works. In fact. we
could make it a blueprint event and check it works. by printing to the screen from
blueprint. That's something we haven't done before. I think we'll do that to finish off the video. So.
bear with me a second. the compiler has failed.
Now. the reason it's failed is because we don't have a Tank.h.
and that's because we don't yet have a Tank dot C++. That's fine.
remember that our Tank blueprint is currently based on Pawn. So.
let's go ahead and quickly make ourselves a Tank C++ file. It's going to
be almost the same process we just did a moment ago. so I won't challenge
you to do it. but you're welcome to pause and do it yourself. if you want. We're going to make a class based
on a Pawn. we're going to call it Tank. we're going to leave it selected as Public.
which will stay the default now. by the way. And again. let me show you
what that does. It means that we now have a Tank.h in the Public folder and
a Tank.cpp in the Private folder.
OK. so we now have a Tank C++ class. I'm going to reparent
the Pawn. by going to Class Settings and set
this to Tank. And while we're here. we're also going to reparent the
TankPlayerController onto TankPlayerController.
which we missed previously. Let's compile both of these
blueprints. and now. let's go ahead and compile the C++.
So. I think now that it's compiled. rather than proving this works right now and making
this video too long. I'm just going to leave things as they are. recap what we've done for you briefly.
and then. in the next video. we'll start logging out and looking and making sure we understand what's
going on. So. what we've done is. we've made a TankPlayerController C++ class.
we have given ourselves a GetControlledTank
method. which should return the tank that is
being possessed. when we call it. So. we're going to need a way of
calling it. which we will do in the next video. So. congratulations getting this far!
I'm just going to leave my code on the screen for you. the relevant code. which
is mainly the TankPlayerController.h. which you need to know is
just that. And then. the TankPlayerController.cpp
is just that. OK fantastic!
I'll see you soon!