In this video we're going to be
getting the Player Controller using C++. By the end of it
we'll have the simple but important result that, when we play the game we have say three AI
tanks in the world, and if we look at the logs, we'll see that all three of them are finding us
as a PlayerController. And we'll understand that from the context of this
diagram which I will build up for you, which explains how Levels, World Actors
PlayerController instances, Game Modes, and stuff all relate together. [Laughs]
So, I will see you in the video!
So guys, what we want to do now is to implement this bit, on
the left. We have both the Tank AI Controller
and the Tank Player Controller, finding the Tank and reporting that their
possessing the relevant tank. Now we want to get to the bit where we can actually send a message
through to the tank to aim at the player. So, let's take a look
at what that involves. Firstly, we need to understand how we're going to find the PlayerController,
that is the Tank on this diagram on the
left at the top, needs an AI tank, so it needs to find
the Player Tank. In this case, there's only one Player Tank, but there could be more than one, so
let's work it through. A World or Level, which aren't exactly the same thing, but for now,
let's consider them to be the same thing, has one or more Actors in it like that.
And those Actors may be tanks, they may be, I don't know,
lights anything. They could be anything inside the
world, a barrel, it could be a chest, it could be anything.
Alright, but some of those Actors are actually a PlayerControllers
as well, are also Actors, and of course, the tanks are Actors.
So what we've got is, this world that's got a lot of Actors in it, for now that's
just three tanks, all of which are Pawns, all of which are specialized
to be tanks, and we have one PlayerController instance. We
could have many, which is why I've drawn it like that with a stack, though it's at the moment , we only
have one PlayerController. It's not a multiplayer game, it's a single human player multi
AI player game. OK, so there are going to be
multiple AI Controllers but only one PlayerController. So that's
the instance we're in, we have one PlayerController, which is possessing one of the
Actors, tanks, and then, the other tanks are possessed by something else which we're not concerned
about here, which is the AI Controller. So, how do they end up? How do these PlayerControllers
end up in the World? What happens, on construction, is that the
World or Level specifies a Game Mode, which we've done, I think we've done it in
Blueprint, and then that Game Mode specifies either a PlayerController C++
class or a PlayerController blueprint class. And in our case, we
will end up with both, one parented on the other, which in turn
instantiates the PlayerController instances as necessary. So it's important to
remember that's the kind of sequence of events that goes on, so that we know how to find
our PlayerController. And if we couldn't find our PlayerController, for some reason, you'd know to come back to this
slide and look at and work it through methodically to work out why.
Alright cool! So, now we've got this far, let's go ahead and open our
TankAIController C++ class, and we're going to write another
method, which is GetPlayerTank(). So
we got GetControlledTank() and BeginPlay(). By the way, by default these things are private.
Despite what I said in a previous video, they're private: by default, and
so we may as well explicitly say that. And let's write a new method which is ATank* pointer
GetPlayerTank();
And it's going to return its constant, because it's not going to change anything. It's going to return a
pointer to the player tank. So that's what we want to go and implement! Let's go ahead and
write the implementation of that now! So,
use basically the same signature with, of course, the class name.
Perfect! OK, so how are we going to get the player
tank? Well, there's a couple of different methods you can actually use for this,
and I want you to have a look on the web and see if you can work out how to do it.
I'm going to suggest that there'll be two things you'll find. You'll see a game play statics,
when you do a Google Search; you'll also see this method here, so if you haven't got an Internet connection or you don't
want to look it up yourself that's the method we need. Once you've got the First Player Controller
like that, I want you to protect your pointer because maybe it'll fail, and then, maybe cast it
to a Tank and then log out on BeginPlay() to check it worked.
So, you actually can replace the code that currently says, I'm possessing
a tank, and you could say, instead of that, using the same if structure in the BeginPlay()
we could say either I have or I haven't found a Player Tank.
So, rather than this AI Controller reporting what tank it's possessing, it's going to report
something very different, which is which is the Player Tank, Player 0 as a hint for you,
which is Player 0 in the game, the first Player Controller. Alright, so
good luck and I'll see you in a minute! See if you can get that done.
If you're struggling, as a recap
we're just trying to get the AI Tanks to find and report
which tank is the Player Tank.
OK cool, so welcome back! How are we going to get this Player Tank then? So, well
let's start off with auto PlayerTank = and
we'll go for this GetWorld() method, and then it's a pointer
so we need to use the arrow operator -> GetFirstPlayer
Controller(); Now, inteli-sense has not caught up with me yet but that should
be fine. So that gets us the PlayerController, and from the Player
Controller we want to get the Pawn,
i.e. we know that we are Player 0, we are controlling that tank that's in the foreground,
we want to get the Pawn of that. Now, if not
(PlayerPawn). We should call it (PlayerPawn), not PlayerTank, because that's what it is.
Then, what do we want to do? We want
to get out of here, before we try and cast it.
We get out of here by returning null pointer, because this method that we're in returns a pointer,
it expects a pointer coming back to a tank, but if it succeeds we'll get
this far. Then we'll return a Cast, if you remember that, to a type of
and it's the (PlayerPawn)
that we are casting. OK, so that should,
if we have properly declared this. Why TankAIController?
ATankAIController, that's the problem! It should all fall into place now! Great!
Then, what I'm saying up here, instead of getting controlled tank, we're going to get
PlayerTank. So, PlayerTank
and then we'll just replace this stuff GetPlayerTank(); if
not player tank, report ( "AIController
can't find player tank")); AI controller can't find player tank
But if we do manage to find the player tank, then we say the
player tank is ("AIController
found player: %s") that'll do, and instead of
ControlledTank it's PlayerTank name. You see what we're doing there? So, we're going and getting the PlayerTank
and then reporting out what's going on. Let's try this! Before we do, before we
even try and run it, let's check all this is setup right! So, is the World or Level
has it got the right Game Mode set? So, you go to Blueprints,
BattleTankGameMode blueprint for this world,
and what does it specify as a PlayerController? The PlayerController blueprint great.
So from our diagram, that's this specifying a blueprint class
which actually is in itself, if we look at the class...
Do we have a blueprint? Let me have a look. Yeah, the blueprint class
is based on our TankPlayerController C++ class, which is flashing away over here.
So, we've got exactly this situation, it's that that should be spawning the PlayerController instance.
So hopefully this'll work! Let's play the game and see if we get what we're looking for!
So, we seem to have the AIController, can't find the
PlayerTank. Well why not? I don't know if you're getting this problem,
you may not be. I'm not sure why I'm getting it, so let's follow the logic through. Let's
go look at our code and see what may or may not be happening over there.
So, ("AIController can't find player tank"). We're getting to here, which means that we're seeing a not PlayerTank. So, if
ah look! I've missed the exclamation mark in front of (PlayerPawn). I was not saying if not PlayerTank, I was just
I was just saying if PlayerTank returned null pointer, so this was succeeding, and then, we're
returning a null pointer which was coming up here and dropping through to here.
I think that's what's happened. Let's see if that's what's happened![Laughs] What a pain!
Let's just take a look. So, those semicolons are subtle and they're small, but
they can totally invert the behavior of your game. Ah, cool! Look!
The AIControllers, both of the AIControllers for the AITanks found player
BP_C_38. Let's just de-possess the tank, go to the
World Outliner, and check that that is indeed this tank. It is! Success! So
The tanks can actually find the player now, and that's great news!
And if we were to drop a third tank into the world, just for laughs,
and play, then we would have three of them all finding the same player! So that's pretty
cool! Congratulations on getting that far! I'm just going to leave you with this diagram
to remind you of the architecture. Take a little look at that, make sure it makes sense and that you know where the
checkboxes and buttons are inside the engine, and remember to commit your work,
over in the source control, as I have been for every single video. And
I will see you soon!