So, in this video we're going to
Add Tick() to a PlayerController. A simple code change and, by the end of it, we'll
have something like this, where we've added a Tick() method in and we'll be requesting
an aim towards the crosshair every frame, and then, we've got a little bit of pseudocode
for what that'll do. We won't quite get to it in this video, and the idea is we're
setting up for, in our game, the ability for that little white dot to
send a bit of information about where that hits in the world,
to the aiming system so that we can start moving the barrel and the turret
to point in that direction and fire the projectile. OK, so see you in there!
OK guys, so we have basically found a
couple of things! We've got the AIController finding the player, and the PlayerController's
possessing the tank, the AIController's possessing their tanks. So, we kind of have
the top layer of this nearly ready to go, we have these things. What we
want to do now is focus, for a moment, on aiming at the crosshair,
because that's the hardest thing to do next. Aiming at the player is going to be really
simple, because we've got the tank finding the player, and actually finding the
player's location from that is pretty simple. I think it's dot get actor location
or something. So, we'll come back to that, but the bit that worries me more is
how do we aim at the crosshair? We're going to have to do something like line trace
through the crosshair on the screen and hit the world and check we're hitting the world and yada yada.
So, because it's a more challenging problem, to me I like to
tackle those first, because it's the most risky part of the project, so that's what we're
going to look at next. So, we're going to go back to the TankPlayer
Controller class. Let's get that up on the screen; Visual
Studio needs to load. And we're going to start thinking about how to aim
towards the crosshair that's on the screen, you know the little white dot that we put in
UI a few videos ago. So, we got the Tank
PlayerController C++. I'll get the header file next to it as well, and let's start thinking
about what we're doing. Well, one of the things we're going to need is a tick, isn't it? We're going to need to have the
TankPlayerController actually ticking, which it isn't doing at the moment,
because there's not tick method in here. And
we're going to use the tick to update the aim every frame.
So, let me just pseudocode it, then I'll get you to implement this tick to
revise the idea of fine adding a method that's not there, like we did a few
videos ago. So, we're going to basically go "// Tick", and then on Tick we're
going to do something like "// Super" i.e. do what the super class does in its tick,
and then, we're going to have a method that's something like... In fact,
let's call it this "// AimTowardsCrosshair()".
A very thin simple Tick function. I always like the Ticks to be very clear
about exactly what they're doing. It doesn't mean that "// AimTowardsCrosshair()" could be quite
expensive and we need to be very careful about how long that takes to run, but I do
like the Tick to be very simple and clear. So, that's what I want you to do now,
not right aim towards crosshair, leave that in as a comment, but I do want you to write what's necessary
for this PlayerController to actually Tick.
So, you might need to revise what we did a couple of videos ago with BeginPlay(), but it's not rocket
science. In fact, if you were to look in the Tank.cpp, that would give you a pretty good
idea to be honest, or any other actor class.
But let's do that! So, make the PlayerController Tick. I want you
to declare and define the Tick() method inside the PlayerController, and then, check that it
works with a simple log message. So, go ahead, pause the video, and do that now.
Welcome back! So, let's take a look at how we're going to do that! I'm
going to look at Tank.cpp for inspiration and remind myself
that Tick tends to take ( float DeltaTime ). Now this is risky
by the way, because the TankPlayerController is based on the APlayer
Controller class and the Tank is based on the APawn class, and it
may be that the way that PlayerController and in turn controller
implements Tick might be different but I don't think it is. So as a first
port of call, let's go ahead and just assume that we have
exactly the same thing, Tick ( float DeltaTime ) like that. So that's the
end of it, and then, what we're going to want to do is have a
void on the front. void Tick(float DeltaTime), so it
passes in every time it ticks this DeltaTime. Then, we'd say Super, to call this
Super class's Tick method, colon colon because it's a static accessor,
and then, we go Tick() with the same signature but we need the
(DeltaTime) in there. Now again, if this all looks bamboozling, what
on earth am I doing? I'm just recreating exactly what you see in say the Tank.cpp
file. This code here, all I've done is switched out ATank
for APlayerController, or I haven't yet but I'm about
to. Comsa OK!
So, that should be the definition of the Tick() that we need, and
what we want to do in that Tick is AimTowardsCrosshair() but we don't have that method yet.
I think that I won't bother with the method just yet, I'm just going to put in a
temporary log. UE_LOG(LogTemp,
Warning, TEXT()) and we're going to say
("Player controller ticking')); Put a semicolon just
for consistency, although we know that it doesn't need it. Going to check the matching of my
brackets, because we've got a lot of brackets here. That looks good! That bracket matches that bracket!
I'm also going to declare this method. Now, the declaration
remember, as before, it's a virtual void tick
with at least the float override, so let's go do that in the Player
Controller. So, let's think about what we're doing. We don't need
the class name. Virtual, virtual's just a
good habit, it's completely optional here. We're just saying that if we were to make
a child of this PlayerController class, then it's children
would be allowed to override and extend the behavior of the Tick() method. Fine,
so then what? virtual void Tick. Now, (float DeltaTime); we don't have to
put a parameter name there, but we may as well do exactly what it does in Tank.h.
You see that? And then, the other
final thing we need on the end is the override. Just as a recap, what that means
is it makes the compiler check that there is indeed a method with
exactly the signature I've highlighted on the screen, in the parent class or one of the parent's
parent classes. OK, so that's why we do it that way! Let's just
make sure this puppy is ticking. I'm going to compile it up and see
if we get the relevant log messages, and if we do, we can progress a little bit.
It's going to take a few videos to get this aiming working fully, if I'm going to do it at a
reasonable pace and not bamboozle everybody. It's going to take a few, but it's going to be worth it! It's a really
powerful reusable thing to know, how do you look through
the screen position. So, I've done a booboo, Delta time
is an undeclared identifier. What have I done there? DeltaTime, it's a
simple capitalization issue there. And also, what do they do about
spacing? Did they put, yeah, they put some spaces. So, let's write code like
the engine code. OK, now that DeltaTime and that DeltaTime match!
And let's recompile! So,
then what we're going to do, just as a recap, is we're going to, that white dot, we're going to be
ray casting through that white dot and seeing where it hits the
the world. Now look, you'll notice the compile finished while I was yabbering on,
and if you look in the output log, the PlayerController ticking has come in and
that's called hot reloading. It's a fantastic feature of using either Xcode or Visual Studio
with Unreal, and it actually recompiles the code and pushes
it into the running game, so you can live see your changes, which is pretty cool!
By the way, Unreal 4.12... uh sorry, that's right
Unreal 4.12 has just shipped, and we're
not quite yet going to include it in the course, just going to
probably wait until 4.12.1, when it's going to hopefully be
a little more stable. There's a load of stuff on the web abut it, VR editing and the like.
One of the things about it is that it actually requires, on a PC, you to use Visual Studio
as your IDE, so be aware of that if you're going to go to 4.12. But I do
recommend you use Visual Studio if you're on the PC. Pretty much any version of it will do, any of the
modern versions, and it's a good and free IDE. So, another thing I want to thank
Andrew Hunt from the Facebook group for is, there is actually a very cool
plugin called "visual assist" for Visual Studio.
Now, it's not free but you know how Visual Studio takes absolutely
ages to autofill or to do anything with such a large code base, because
all of the engine code is sitting here in our solution as a separate project.
It takes ages, you keep seeing it take ages to do anything. This Visual Assist turns
that into an instant process. Now, it's $100 for personal
use or $200, $250 I think, for
business use, but I just recommend you take a look at it. It's at WholeTomato.com, not
rotten tomato(laughs), and it's worth your time.  Anyway, I will be
assessing that, maybe including it in the course if I can get a deal for you guys. So that's it, we
have now just simply revised that ability to tick. I'm just going to write
the AimTowardsCrosshair() method, so that it's there for completeness,
and then, we will start fleshing out AimTowardsCrosshair() in the next video.
So, I like to have my BeginPlay() above my Tick(), because to me the order
of things is BeginPlay(), Tick(), and then my methods. I've got a getter,
so the getter will go next, and then, I'm going to implement this
thing, which is simply what do we call it? Aim
TowardsCrosshair(); So, it's going to be void, it's going to return nothing.
It's going to be called AimTowardsCrosshair(); The question is, is it const? No, it's not const
because aiming towards the crosshair is going to change something about the TankPlayerController
state, so we don't need a const on it. So, there's your
AimTowardsCrosshair() definition! Now, it's worth declaring this straightaway, because all the time there's
a Visual Studio error like this, we're not going to get much help inside the method with
our composition of our code. So, I'm just going to go and declare it now, it's
private. It's a private method and it's just going to return nothing,
and it's simply going to... Well, let's write what it's going to do, in a comment in the
header file. This is going to "// Start the tank
moving the barrel towards
so that
a shot would hit where
//  the crosshair intersects
the world". OK, worth putting in a bit of a
comment there! "// Start the tank moving the barrel so that a shot would
hit", not it, "where // the crosshair intersects the world".
OK, that's what it's going to do, and we come in here,
one of the first thing's we're going to want to do is, we're going to say if we don't have a Controlled
Tank, then we need to get out of here. So, if not (!GetControlled
Tank()), remember your not, if you don't do that then this method will always exit of
course. Then, we just exit, and then I'm just going to pseudocode
the rest of it. So, what we need to do is, we need to
"// Get world location
through crosshair", or if you line trace.
If you "linetrace through the crosshair",
and then, if it hits something,
i.e. "// If it hits the landscape", then
we're going to want the "controlled tank
to aim at
this point". That's the pseudocode. Alright, so that's what we're aiming for
with this AimTowardsCrosshair(). [Laughs] See what I did there?! OK, so let's just
compile this, and then, we'll split this here and start again in the next video!
Of course, there's no brand new functionality here, apart from this
ticking log. By the way, the ticking log, we should probably get rid of, in the Tick()
method of the TankController.cpp. We don't need it now, it was just to prove that we got
Ticking() working. So if we play, there you go! The ticking's still there because I haven't
recompiled but I'll leave it recompiling, and then, I'll go off when that's finished and
commit my work, as I'm hoping you're doing. I hope you're getting on well with the source control, and I'll
see you in the next video!