So. Finding
Screen Pixel Coordinates is what we're up to in this video! By
the end of it. you will have the wonderful result that when we play the game it will
start logging out the number of pixels along the screen that white dot. aiming dot
is. and the number of pixels down the screen or the Viewport more specifically
that is. And we'll even tackle windows scaling issues and all sorts. so let's
go and get it done!
So. the next step in doing this job is going to be to.
what we call. de-project the position of a little dot on the screen into
world coordinates. and we want to know what direction we're looking in
when we look through that dot on the screen. So.
let's take a look at how we're going to do that! Start off in pseudocode. So in
the GetSightRayHitLocation(). this HitLocation = FVector(1.0);
That was purely for testing and so that we are
proving that we were changing the value. Remember we set a value here?
We pass a reference to it as an out parameter. it gets
changed inside this method. and then we print it out. OK. but now
what we want to do is. we want to know what actual direction we
are looking in. so we want to get to the point where we can put the  ("Look direction:
logged out here as the least to next step.
So. what are the steps for doing that? Well. the first thing we need to do is "// Find the
crosshair position" or
at least set the crosshair position. What else are we going to need to do? We're going to need to
"// De-project" is the term they use
the "screen position
of the cursor or crosshair
to a world direction" It's what they call a deep
projection. And then. we're going to "// Line-trace
through. along that" direction. which
we would call a "look direction.
and see what we hit" up to some
maximum range. Wow! OK. it's definitely worth thinking about
what the recipe is. Something like that! We're going to find out
what the crosshair's position is. de-project that position into world direction. and then line trace
along that and see what we end up hitting. So. it's going to take more than just this method. we're going to need
a couple more helper methods below but let's get started on it. and I
think I'll challenge you to do part of this. as part of this video of course.
So. let's just get you off the ground! We're going to have an int32.
a couple of int32's. so you can actually declare them on the same line. We're going to call it
sizeX. and SizeY. In fact.
we ought to be more explicit and call it Viewport
SizeX. and Viewport
SizeY. OK.
so what are they? Well. they are just going to be the size of the current Viewport.
i.e. when we're playing the game the Viewport that the game is running
in. the whole thing that's moving around as I move my mouse cursor. that is the
Viewport. OK. so how do we get that? Well. we have a method called GetViewportSize().
and there it is. It's just
immediately available to us and it's going to use out parameters. Look you can see that
in the clue of the signature there. int32 &SizeX.
int32 &SizeY. I would prefer to see the ampersand bound
to the int32. to give us an idea that it's a reference to an
int32. but it's basically how
Unreal does it. so we'll just have no control over that. We'll just live with it. get used to the
ampersand being either side of the space. So. we're going to
pass in ViewportSizeX and ViewportSizeY and these are out parameters.
which is why I really want you to get used to them. because we have to use them because a lot of the engine
calls use out parameters. So. next we want a
way of the designer ideally specifying on the TankPlayer
Controller blueprint. where this reticle
or crosshair is. Now. we don't. I think. need to go as
far as actually reading the position of that dot from
the user interface. I think that that gets changed so little
that it doesn't matter if we have to change it into places. i.e. if we have to
actually go to the widget. move the dot around. then
come into the TankPlayerController blueprint and set some
sort of parameter for the position. the relative position
on the screen. I think that's OK. I'm generally against things being in two places. but two places are
OK. three isn't. Two is OK. especially when things don't change very often. it
will reduce the complexity of reading from the UI. So I think this would be
a great challenge. actually for you at this stage. is for you to
work out what the screen location is
based on the Viewport size and a
couple of parameters that you will make. so let me formalize that in a challenge
slide for you.
So. here goes your challenge. I hope it makes sense to you. I want you to create
a couple of private member variables. CrossHairXLocation
and set that to 0.5. That is to represent the fact that in our game the Crosshair
is halfway across the screen. it's the same convention as the UI anchors and the like.
so it's 50% of the way across the screen. I want you to create another
private member variable called CrossHairYLocation and set that to
0.33333. Now that's horrible but it's also fine because
we are accurate there to within 1 part in 100.000 or whatever.
and that is far less than the number of pixels you're going to have horizontally. so we're plenty accurate
enough. And this is exactly how things work when you set relative
numbers in the User Interface System. so it's consistent with that and
it's fine. So. have a CrossHairYLocation. and it's the distance down the screen so you can
see that we're starting from the top-left and that that dot is 0.33333. OK.
it goes on forever but that many decimal places is plenty of the way down the
screen. Alright. make them both EditAnywhere for Blueprint. so that
the designer can. if he decides to move his little white dot. him or her can
also change the position in code
or in at least a parameter. I want you to then calculate an FVector2D called Screen
Location. Now. it's actually very simple. it just involves a couple of multiplications.
but tying it all together is the bit that counts. so you're going to work out what the screen
location is in pixels. It'll be a pair of floats specifying the pixel
coordinates that we'll want to de-project later. and it will change as the
Viewport size changes. Not that that's likely to change. while there playing the game.
but you get the idea. it's flexible. So go ahead. pause the video and see if you can
make that work now.
So welcome back! Let's take a look at the code!
Make these member variables first. So. what did I say they were going to be called?
I have to look at the challenge slide. CrossHairXLocation was the first one. so it's
private so... Ooh. you know what I've done?! I've made all these puppies here public.
when actually they all need to be private. so there's a mistake I can correct.
Alright. so here we want a UPROPERTY ( Edit
Anywhere ). Spaces. no spaces.
don't really mind. I'm going to leave it without. And then it's going to be a float because
it's a fraction of a number. and it's going to be called Crosshair
XPosition I think. I keep forgetting what I asked you to call it
Location whatever. Location. OK
now make the 0.5 fine.
Indentation goes wrong because Visual Studio doesn't understand this macro.
OK. let's paste in for the Y location.
because it's almost identical. and give it about four decimal places
worth of 3's. Alright cool. I'm going to copy CrosshairXLocation
because we're about to use it. It'll save me retyping it and forgetting whether its location or
position once again. And let's think about what it's going to be. Well. we may as well use auto
because it'll come out in the wash. so ScreenLocation is what I asked you to create
and it's an FVector2D(). so hopefully you realize that you can
do this calculation directly in the constructor of the FVector2D.
So what do we start with? Well. we're going to start with ViewportSizeX.
if I can type.
and we're going to multiply that by the CrosshairXLocation. So.
whatever the X Viewport size is in pixels. let's call it 1.000 pixels wide. If the
CrosshairXLocation is 0.5. then we get a value here of 500
being returned for the X part of the FVector
2D. So. at pixel 500 is where the screen location is
in X. and then. we do exactly the same thing in Y. In fact. it's so exactly
I would recommend copying and pasting and then changing X's for
Y's to minimize the chance of boo boos. OK.
that's fine! Now. if you wish you can log this out. as long as we are actually
getting SightRayHitLocation every frame. Are we calling it? Yes.
GetSightRayHitLocation. Good! So. I think it would be good practice here to do a UE_LOG()
of what this is. so (LogTemp). otherwise we don't know we've done it right.
Warning and then we're going to have a TEXT macro. because we love them.
and I'm going to put some string in so that we don't get some horrible you shouldn't have
for parameters warning and also tells us what this is talking
about. So. ("ScreenLocation:  ")).
may as well use the exact variable name with a %s to say. expect to
find something that I can make into a string or display as a string. coming afterwards
and then comma and then we're just going to go ScreenLocation).
And of course. the type of this screen location is an FVector2D.
it must be because that's what we've constructed on the right-hand side. Alright. let's
have a look and see what we get. Oh. before I do it let's just
press this ("Look direction:  %s") log up here. so that we only get one thing
coming out. Now with a log that's down and deep in a function like this. rather than
near the top of your class and at a high level. you want to
get rid of that log pretty quickly. because we don't want deeply nested
sub-methods logging. because it just gets really confusing trying to get rid of logs
then. So. let's just wait for this to compile. see if it works. We should be
getting. well it depends on our Viewport size. What is my Viewport size here?
Well let's have a look. I could veri. You could verify it using something
like Snagit. you could take a screen-capture but it's probably you know 600 pixels. that sort of thing.
It will see if it's right. It'll be obvious if it's right. So
"note: see reference to function template instantiation" in TankPlayerController 52.
there's something wrong. So. maybe the first thing to do is just have a look and see
if you can see what's wrong with it. What is wrong with it is ScreenLocation
of course is an FVector2D. and what we need to do is something like a
ToString() on that. So. we do a ToString() method. and then. we
need to do a star in order to turn this string back into a
TChar*. that old chestnut. Let's try again!
Quite cryptic errors. I would say. That's not an error that. unless you've got some experience
which is why I'm showing you these types of errors. is too easy to
deal with. but don't get too caught up in those massive long complicated
errors. Just go back to your code. take a look at it. and say well you know.
the first look at it. what was wrong with it? Is there something
obviously wrong with it? And to me there was something obviously wrong with it. You don't need to go through and read every nuance
of that error message until your first couple of gut feels don't work; I
would suggest. otherwise the sheer time it takes to read the full width of the error message
makes it not worth it. But of course. don't leave it too long before you do read that error
message carefully. if you're still stuck. So let's play! Ah. here we go look!
402 by 179.4 blah blah blah. That sound very
feasible. I'm going to just load up Snagit so you know what I was talking about when I
mentioned Snagit earlier. I think I've got a keyboard shortcut setup for it. I have. I'm going to
screen-capture the middle portion of my screen there. which is the Viewport. This will
also highlight to you what the Viewport actually is. I'm going to look at the size
of that. if I can find where it stored it. Bless it.
And then. we can see here that this is roughly 1.000 by 677
pixels. this bit. I've got the pixels a little bit wrong.
I didn't cut it that carefully. so let's just see if we're getting roughly 500 and something by
350 something. So. we're not getting that. we're getting 400 by
179. So. the likely reason is because if I look at my
display settings. I've got 125% scaling
on my windows Display scaling. just to confuse things. So.
if we take this 402 in a calculator
and go 402
times 1.25. we get 502 pixels. almost exactly
what we'd expect. Let's try the same in the Y. 180 is good enough for
179 times 1.25. It gives us 225
in the Y. as if the total height of this thing was...
I've got to think about this a bit more carefully. 225 is the number of pixels.
Once we've changed. because of my strange screen scaling. from the top
of the screen to the dot which is a third of the way down. So. we need to multiply the 225
by 3. which gives you the 675 (laughs). Wow!
At last! And then. if we go back here and look. well it was 677. Sue me. it's only
2 pixels out. So. after a lot of combobulating. I think that's
the word I'll use. we have actually have got the right place. As I say. let me
reiterate. the reason it didn't come out exactly is because I have display
scaling going on. on my screen. to keep things visible for you guys. So.
the pixels ain't pixels. they don't map 1 to 1. Ahh. that
was all good fun! So. hopefully that makes sense. I'm just going to go in and remove
this log message. as I said we should do. and we actually have
done the first bit. which is "// Find the crosshair position in
pixel coordinates". And that's what
all this stuff here does. and that's what we've done by doing our
intermediate variable and compose an FVector etc. So. relatively simple
revisiony stuff for you. and I'll see you in the next lecture!
=======
So, Finding
Screen Pixel Coordinates is what we're up to in this video! By
the end of it, you will have the wonderful result that when we play the game it will
start logging out the number of pixels along the screen that white dot, aiming dot
is, and the number of pixels down the screen or the Viewport more specifically
that is. And we'll even tackle windows scaling issues and all sorts, so let's
go and get it done!
So, the next step in doing this job is going to be to,
what we call, de-project the position of a little dot on the screen into
world coordinates, and we want to know what direction we're looking in
when we look through that dot on the screen. So,
let's take a look at how we're going to do that! Start off in pseudocode. So in
the GetSightRayHitLocation(), this HitLocation = FVector(1.0);
That was purely for testing and so that we are
proving that we were changing the value. Remember we set a value here?
We pass a reference to it as an out parameter, it gets
changed inside this method, and then we print it out. OK, but now
what we want to do is, we want to know what actual direction we
are looking in, so we want to get to the point where we can put the  ("Look direction:
logged out here as the least to next step.
So, what are the steps for doing that? Well, the first thing we need to do is "// Find the
crosshair position" or
at least set the crosshair position. What else are we going to need to do? We're going to need to
"// De-project" is the term they use
the "screen position
of the cursor or crosshair
to a world direction" It's what they call a deep
projection. And then, we're going to "// Line-trace
through, along that" direction, which
we would call a "look direction,
and see what we hit" up to some
maximum range. Wow! OK, it's definitely worth thinking about
what the recipe is. Something like that! We're going to find out
what the crosshair's position is, de-project that position into world direction, and then line trace
along that and see what we end up hitting. So, it's going to take more than just this method, we're going to need
a couple more helper methods below but let's get started on it, and I
think I'll challenge you to do part of this, as part of this video of course.
So, let's just get you off the ground! We're going to have an int32,
a couple of int32's, so you can actually declare them on the same line. We're going to call it
sizeX, and SizeY. In fact,
we ought to be more explicit and call it Viewport
SizeX, and Viewport
SizeY. OK,
so what are they? Well, they are just going to be the size of the current Viewport,
i.e. when we're playing the game the Viewport that the game is running
in, the whole thing that's moving around as I move my mouse cursor, that is the
Viewport. OK, so how do we get that? Well, we have a method called GetViewportSize(),
and there it is. It's just
immediately available to us and it's going to use out parameters. Look you can see that
in the clue of the signature there, int32 &SizeX,
int32 &SizeY. I would prefer to see the ampersand bound
to the int32, to give us an idea that it's a reference to an
int32, but it's basically how
Unreal does it, so we'll just have no control over that. We'll just live with it, get used to the
ampersand being either side of the space. So, we're going to
pass in ViewportSizeX and ViewportSizeY and these are out parameters,
which is why I really want you to get used to them, because we have to use them because a lot of the engine
calls use out parameters. So, next we want a
way of the designer ideally specifying on the TankPlayer
Controller blueprint, where this reticle
or crosshair is. Now, we don't, I think, need to go as
far as actually reading the position of that dot from
the user interface. I think that that gets changed so little
that it doesn't matter if we have to change it into places, i.e. if we have to
actually go to the widget, move the dot around, then
come into the TankPlayerController blueprint and set some
sort of parameter for the position, the relative position
on the screen. I think that's OK, I'm generally against things being in two places, but two places are
OK, three isn't. Two is OK, especially when things don't change very often, it
will reduce the complexity of reading from the UI. So I think this would be
a great challenge, actually for you at this stage, is for you to
work out what the screen location is
based on the Viewport size and a
couple of parameters that you will make, so let me formalize that in a challenge
slide for you.
So, here goes your challenge, I hope it makes sense to you. I want you to create
a couple of private member variables, CrossHairXLocation
and set that to 0.5. That is to represent the fact that in our game the Crosshair
is halfway across the screen, it's the same convention as the UI anchors and the like,
so it's 50% of the way across the screen. I want you to create another
private member variable called CrossHairYLocation and set that to
0.33333. Now that's horrible but it's also fine because
we are accurate there to within 1 part in 100,000 or whatever,
and that is far less than the number of pixels you're going to have horizontally, so we're plenty accurate
enough. And this is exactly how things work when you set relative
numbers in the User Interface System, so it's consistent with that and
it's fine. So, have a CrossHairYLocation, and it's the distance down the screen so you can
see that we're starting from the top-left and that that dot is 0.33333. OK,
it goes on forever but that many decimal places is plenty of the way down the
screen. Alright, make them both EditAnywhere for Blueprint, so that
the designer can, if he decides to move his little white dot, him or her can
also change the position in code
or in at least a parameter. I want you to then calculate an FVector2D called Screen
Location. Now, it's actually very simple, it just involves a couple of multiplications,
but tying it all together is the bit that counts, so you're going to work out what the screen
location is in pixels. It'll be a pair of floats specifying the pixel
coordinates that we'll want to de-project later, and it will change as the
Viewport size changes. Not that that's likely to change, while there playing the game,
but you get the idea, it's flexible. So go ahead, pause the video and see if you can
make that work now.
So welcome back! Let's take a look at the code!
Make these member variables first. So, what did I say they were going to be called?
I have to look at the challenge slide. CrossHairXLocation was the first one, so it's
private so... Ooh, you know what I've done?! I've made all these puppies here public,
when actually they all need to be private, so there's a mistake I can correct.
Alright, so here we want a UPROPERTY ( Edit
Anywhere ). Spaces, no spaces,
don't really mind, I'm going to leave it without. And then it's going to be a float because
it's a fraction of a number, and it's going to be called Crosshair
XPosition I think. I keep forgetting what I asked you to call it
Location whatever. Location, OK
now make the 0.5 fine.
Indentation goes wrong because Visual Studio doesn't understand this macro.
OK, let's paste in for the Y location,
because it's almost identical, and give it about four decimal places
worth of 3's. Alright cool, I'm going to copy CrosshairXLocation
because we're about to use it. It'll save me retyping it and forgetting whether its location or
position once again. And let's think about what it's going to be. Well, we may as well use auto
because it'll come out in the wash, so ScreenLocation is what I asked you to create
and it's an FVector2D(), so hopefully you realize that you can
do this calculation directly in the constructor of the FVector2D.
So what do we start with? Well, we're going to start with ViewportSizeX,
if I can type,
and we're going to multiply that by the CrosshairXLocation. So,
whatever the X Viewport size is in pixels, let's call it 1,000 pixels wide. If the
CrosshairXLocation is 0.5, then we get a value here of 500
being returned for the X part of the FVector
2D. So, at pixel 500 is where the screen location is
in X, and then, we do exactly the same thing in Y. In fact, it's so exactly
I would recommend copying and pasting and then changing X's for
Y's to minimize the chance of boo boos. OK,
that's fine! Now, if you wish you can log this out, as long as we are actually
getting SightRayHitLocation every frame. Are we calling it? Yes,
GetSightRayHitLocation. Good! So, I think it would be good practice here to do a UE_LOG()
of what this is, so (LogTemp), otherwise we don't know we've done it right.
Warning and then we're going to have a TEXT macro, because we love them,
and I'm going to put some string in so that we don't get some horrible you shouldn't have
for parameters warning and also tells us what this is talking
about. So, ("ScreenLocation:  ")),
may as well use the exact variable name with a %s to say, expect to
find something that I can make into a string or display as a string, coming afterwards
and then comma and then we're just going to go ScreenLocation).
And of course, the type of this screen location is an FVector2D,
it must be because that's what we've constructed on the right-hand side. Alright, let's
have a look and see what we get. Oh, before I do it let's just
press this ("Look direction:  %s") log up here, so that we only get one thing
coming out. Now with a log that's down and deep in a function like this, rather than
near the top of your class and at a high level, you want to
get rid of that log pretty quickly, because we don't want deeply nested
sub-methods logging, because it just gets really confusing trying to get rid of logs
then. So, let's just wait for this to compile, see if it works. We should be
getting, well it depends on our Viewport size. What is my Viewport size here?
Well let's have a look. I could veri, You could verify it using something
like Snagit, you could take a screen-capture but it's probably you know 600 pixels, that sort of thing.
It will see if it's right. It'll be obvious if it's right. So
"note: see reference to function template instantiation" in TankPlayerController 52,
there's something wrong. So, maybe the first thing to do is just have a look and see
if you can see what's wrong with it. What is wrong with it is ScreenLocation
of course is an FVector2D, and what we need to do is something like a
ToString() on that. So, we do a ToString() method, and then, we
need to do a star in order to turn this string back into a
TChar*, that old chestnut. Let's try again!
Quite cryptic errors, I would say. That's not an error that, unless you've got some experience
which is why I'm showing you these types of errors, is too easy to
deal with, but don't get too caught up in those massive long complicated
errors. Just go back to your code, take a look at it, and say well you know,
the first look at it, what was wrong with it? Is there something
obviously wrong with it? And to me there was something obviously wrong with it. You don't need to go through and read every nuance
of that error message until your first couple of gut feels don't work; I
would suggest, otherwise the sheer time it takes to read the full width of the error message
makes it not worth it. But of course, don't leave it too long before you do read that error
message carefully, if you're still stuck. So let's play! Ah, here we go look!
402 by 179.4 blah blah blah. That sound very
feasible. I'm going to just load up Snagit so you know what I was talking about when I
mentioned Snagit earlier. I think I've got a keyboard shortcut setup for it. I have, I'm going to
screen-capture the middle portion of my screen there, which is the Viewport. This will
also highlight to you what the Viewport actually is. I'm going to look at the size
of that, if I can find where it stored it. Bless it.
And then, we can see here that this is roughly 1,000 by 677
pixels, this bit. I've got the pixels a little bit wrong,
I didn't cut it that carefully, so let's just see if we're getting roughly 500 and something by
350 something. So, we're not getting that, we're getting 400 by
179. So, the likely reason is because if I look at my
display settings, I've got 125% scaling
on my windows Display scaling, just to confuse things. So,
if we take this 402 in a calculator
and go 402
times 1.25, we get 502 pixels, almost exactly
what we'd expect. Let's try the same in the Y. 180 is good enough for
179 times 1.25. It gives us 225
in the Y, as if the total height of this thing was...
I've got to think about this a bit more carefully. 225 is the number of pixels.
Once we've changed, because of my strange screen scaling, from the top
of the screen to the dot which is a third of the way down. So, we need to multiply the 225
by 3, which gives you the 675 (laughs). Wow!
At last! And then, if we go back here and look, well it was 677. Sue me, it's only
2 pixels out. So, after a lot of combobulating, I think that's
the word I'll use, we have actually have got the right place. As I say, let me
reiterate, the reason it didn't come out exactly is because I have display
scaling going on, on my screen, to keep things visible for you guys. So,
the pixels ain't pixels, they don't map 1 to 1. Ahh, that
was all good fun! So, hopefully that makes sense. I'm just going to go in and remove
this log message, as I said we should do, and we actually have
done the first bit, which is "// Find the crosshair position in
pixel coordinates". And that's what
all this stuff here does, and that's what we've done by doing our
intermediate variable and compose an FVector etc. So, relatively simple
revisiony stuff for you, and I'll see you in the next lecture!
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1:Unreal/Section4/BT27 Finding Screen Pixel Coordinates.srt