Welcome to
DeprojectScreenToWorld. In this video what we're going to do
is, we're actually now going to find out, as we look around with the camera,
what the world space direction we are looking in as a
unit vector is. You can see that logged out to the console, so let's do it!
So, it's time to do this deprojection thing. We're going to work out what the
screen position, that our crosshair is effectively pointing at, is which
will be fun. So, the method that you need for this is on the
APlayerController. We've got something called DeprojectScreenPositionToWorld on the APlayerController.
So there it is and there is its signature. Now, it doesn't
tell you what this WorldLocation is, it's actually the camera
world location. We don't need that but we need to provide a variable so
that it can spit the camera world location into it. So, that's what's
going on there. ScreenX is the ScreenX position, ScreenY is the ScreenY position,
which we've just calculated both of these here, and they're all wrapped up in this screen
location. But of course, we can do a dot X dot Y to get those out,
and then, the WorldDirection is the thing we're looking for. We're looking for the direction
that we're looking in, so that we can line trace down that. So, that's what I
want you to do actually. I want you to do the deprojection yourself.
Lookup that method, DeprojectScreenPositionToWorld. Make sure you've got the one
that I just showed you, that's here on the APlayerController, because there is another method that sounds similar.
In fact, there are two others; one's in game play statics and I've forgotten where the other
one is but this is the one you want anyway. That's the method, look up the method
signature online, or just go back in the video a second to where I just had it and spoke about
it. Log the WorldDirection it returns. So, use the method and
log out the WorldDirection to see if it makes sense, and ignore WorldLocation
it. It's actually the camera's World Location. Camera World Location may be a
good name for the variable but we'll just discard it. So go ahead, pause the video, and see
if you can get that working now please. I say please,
it's please for your sake more than mine. Really all the learning happens when you do these
challenges, so please go ahead, pause the video, and give it a crack.
Welcome back! OK, let's get this thing done! So we need an
FVector, or it could be an auto, but let's just be explicit this time for fun.
Let's go FVector CameraWorld
Location. I said we're going to have to throw that away, so there it is.
Now, we're going to do the actual deproject, so how do we do that?
Well, it's DeprojectScreenPositionTo
World(). There you go, that's the one! Now, what does it take in? Well it wants a
ScreenX position, so that is viewport...no no it's not
It's (ScreenLocation.X).
Lowercase X won't work. ScreenLocation oop hello!
Dot capital Y, so that's
giving it that. Now, it wants a WorldLocation. That is this Camera
WorldLocation thing that we talked about, so let's give it what it asked for, and
then, finally it wants to give us a WorldDirection.
So, let's just use something called WorldDirection,
and then, let's make ourselves another FVector temporarily
for the WorldDirection. Ultimately this is probably going to be refactored
into another method, but so that we can see that this is working, let's just make another
FVector. I won't put it on the same line as the one above, because we're going to remove this one, probably.
FVector WorldDirection OK, and then that gives
us something to pass into the Deproject position to world. Now, that's
a boolean type that comes back from us, remember. So, we can actually say if
DeprojectScreenPositionToWorld, i.e. if that works do something.
What are we going to do? Well we're going to do a famous log to make sure it works. So, here
is the log entry above, which I can just copy,
and we're going to come in and say... Now is it
Look direction? I think it actually is the Look direction! Yeah, so that's
good! The reason I'm not
returning this value yet, by the way, is because we haven't actually go the hit location yet, so I'm just
debugging that we are looking at the value of the WorldDirection. We need to do a little bit more work.
We need to actually do the line trace here, as per the comment, before we end up with a hit location.
That's why I'm suppressing this logging at the top here, because
we're still working through step by step. So, we're saying if that, and in doing so
you're actually doing this deproject, then tell me what the direction you
found was, otherwise don't tell me anything. So that's what we're doing, let's have a go!
I'll leave my code on the
screen, while it compiles. I think that's probably more helpful for you. I hope you didn't get too tripped up by the
fact you need a capital X and a capital Y and the dot's there, or even indeed I'm just
accessing those members in general. And I hope you didn't get too thrown off by the CameraWorldLocation
thing. How are we doing? I think that worked!
There you go, "Look direction"! Now, let's ask if it makes sense! So, just before I even
start let's see what we'd expect. The tank is pointing down positive X, Z is
above, Y is to the right. So, if we face forward
we get an X value of 1, if we face to the right we get an X value of 0,
and if we face behind we get an X value of -1. OK, that sounds
feasible. Let's have a look at the Y's now, independently. Y is 0
facing that way, it is 1 facing to the right. I said Y was to the right, that sounds good.
0 and -1 yep and then the Z! If we look straight down, Z is
-1ish horizontally, Z is 0ish,
and when we look up Z is 1ish. Great! So, we have the components of
these vectors. Look at this little guy down at the bottom of the screen, the actual axis indicator
down here. But basically, it's telling us what proportions
of this we have in each "Look direction". So if we're looking straight down X, we have a vector that
is 1 0 0 for all the way down X. If we're looking
equally in X and Y, we end up with something that is not
1 1 0. So, the reason we're getting 0.7 something
by 0.7 something here... Or where does it even out? Point
707, there you go! Is because...
If we have a look at a calculator, if we take 0.707 and we square
it, we get 0.5. So, I'd have to draw
you a diagram, but it's simple trigonometry that if you want the vector
to be a total length of 1, then it needs to be 0.707
down either side, because 0.707 squared which is 0.5
+ 0.707 squared gives you 1, and the square
root of 1 is 1. Remember the square on the hippopotamus is the sum of the square on the two opposite squirrels
or whatever the thing is. So basically it's Pythagorus, that's why
this happens. You're always getting a unit vector, is the bottom line. The vector that you get out of it
this is always of length 1, so if you start giving it some Z component,
the other vectors will also shorten appropriately. Alright, so that's what we're getting back!
A unit vector in the direction that we are looking. I think I'll leave it there for
this video. That was short and sweet and simple, but it's pretty good that we
now actually have that direction. So, what we'll go on to do in the next video
is... Actually I'll tell you what, just before I dive out I think I'm going to just refactor
this out, because this method's getting a bit chunky in my opinion. So, let's just
quickly factor out this whole DeprojectScreeToWorld position into
a different method. I think that would be a lot neater. And I think what we're doing in
this method is, we're getting the Look direction. So, it's going to be
bool because we again want to know if it worked. ATankPlayer
a controller and then GetLook
Direction(). And then, what do we need to take in? Well we're going to need
the screen location for this guy to work, so it's going to be an (FVector
2D ScreenLocation) and it's
going to be an FVector. We're going to make ourselves an out parameter, ampersand
because we need a reference for this out parameter, World
Direction. Or to be honest we ought to call that Look
Direction. Let's have a name change here, to be consistent with a name of
the method. OK, so that's what we want! Now, it's complaining because we
haven't yet declared this method in the header file. So, let's go over to the
header file, make a quick declaration, and in our declaration
we probably realized that it should be const. Getting the LookDirection should not change
any of the member variables of this class. So const,
back to the implementation, make it const. I'm simply doing a refactor here,
I'm doing it manually because I too often use Visual Studio tools,
and you poor guys on Xcode don't get the same deal, so I'm going
to do it this way. Alright, so when we actually call this method, what do we do? Well, we set
up a camera location and a WorldDirection, so let's just take all
this code, pop it in here. Now, we don't need WorldDirection.
Indeed it's not WorldDirection anymore, we're calling it Look Direction. That was the name change, so I'll
replace that. This is for discarding,
"// To be discarded",
but it must be passed in, so CameraWorldLocation must go in there. LookDirection
comes in as a reference, as an out parameter. Then, we need to actually do
the deproject, which we do, so take the if off
like so,
and then, I may as well just log to test.
So very simple thin method, it just does the deproject, it gets the Look
Direction. If you want, by the way, with these types of methods, to make life
easier and to make it easier to read with these multi-parameter methods you can
of course do what we've done many times before, which is just space things out into
multiple lines. That, of course, makes everything just that much easier to read.
OK, so that's
done like that! So, DeprojectScreenPosition. Now, we can
go back in and say, well instead of if and then the whole thing, we can just say if
(GetLookDirection()) and then, of course, we pass it
the things that we needed, which is the (ScreenLocation,
and this LookDirection)) like
so. So, if that succeeds then go ahead
and just logout where we saw it. So it's a simple refactor out
here. You could argue that's hardly worth doing, but I think it just makes it a little bit more
what's self documenting, and it helps us practice how you've refactored these slightly trickier things
that need out parameters. Of course, the final thing we need here is an FVector
LookDirection because it's about to be
used as an out parameter here. We're not yet doing anything
with taht LookDirection, but we will do something with that LookDirection. Shortly
we're going to use it here. I'll just make it look
exactly the same along that LookDirection. OK, now let's see if this compiles.
Just getting a couple of complaints, but I think they're just IntelliSense errors. If not, the compiler will
give me a much more useful error. I'll leave the
code on the screen so you can see the refactor that I've done.
I can't see anything wrong but I'm sure
there is something. OK, " 'LookDirection': undeclared identifier"
on line 55.
Ah hah, spelling
error. OK let's try again!
We always get an error on UE_LOGs, of course, as I've mentioned before
or because Visual Studio doesn't understand these macros, so we have to
live with that. I'm not quite sure why I've got an error down here. It's probably glaringly obvious to
somebody out there but I can't see it, and it should be LookDirection
not WorldDirection. That will teach me for renaming variables, but on the other hand, it is
worth renaming things because we want to make sure that things
stay very meaningful, so don't be shy to rename things.
And on line 72 I'm missing a closing brace,
and that is just because I've got too many of them. That's what the complaint
has been, I have too many closing braces. Finally, I think this will compile
and hopefully work. So, you can see how long it can take to refactor things out.
But, at the end of the day I think it makes it easier to read and it
will make sure that our GetSiteRayHitLocation method here doesn't blow up
too large. It's already that big before we start doing the line tracing,
and this makes sure that it kind of stays on a screen.
And finally, Get
LookDirection must return a value. Of course it must and
that's because I haven't returned here. OK, so lots of
errors on my behalf there, but you get to see what a just
eaten a big carbohydrate coder behaves like compared to
the normal sharp self. So, you can excuse yourself if it takes you
this many compiles to get something working, because occasionally it takes me that long too.
Let's take a look and see if it looks feasible! It does, the vectors are coming out OK,
and the code I shall leave on the screen there for you.
And that's it, we've refactored, we've got it working, and in the next video we'll actually do the line trace.