So in this video we will Unify Player & AI
Aiming! What that means is that we will end up with the top section of this diagram
finished so that. regardless of whether it's the player or the AI possessing the
tank. they will call the same AimAt method. And then. what that will mean is that we can
actually log out these three AI tanks are aiming at me. my player.
the player position. and we are aiming at. well whatever we fancy really. So.
let's dive in and get it going!
Okie cokie! So. we are ready to get
this whole top section working. We have a Tank AI Controller. it's going to be pretty
easy to organize. excuse me. to aim at the player. We have a Tank Player
Controller and we have just spent loads of effort making sure we know what this
world-space is here. So. in either case we're going to aim at a particular
world-space. whether it's the player's world-space or whether it's the world-space that the crosshair
is pointing at. And we're going to send that to the tank. and there's going to be an
AimAt method. as we can see here on the tank. So. the first thing to do
is to make that AimAt method on the tank. That's pretty simple. if you want a mini challenge for yourself.
go ahead and do it now. I'm going to just do it anyway.
By the way. all these things should have been private in here. because they don't need to be public.
So. for the first time now. I'm going to make a public section. and ask
myself the question. is it reasonable for a tank to have a public
method called AimAt? I think it is! The public part
of these classes is the most important thing. it's the contract. it's the external
view of the tank. But I think it's perfectly reasonable to have a void AimAt
(FVector HitLocation).
In this case. we kind of mean the location of the thing we want to hit. but it is also
the HitLocation. formally from the line trace that we did
in the TankPlayerController. because we are wanting to hit the
thing that our line trace hits. So. AimAt (FVector HitLocation);
Cool! Let's go ahead and implement that inside the tank.
I think I'll do it down here. We need an
ATank:: qualify the class.
and then. we come in here. Now. we're not actually going to do the aiming
now. so what I'm going to do is I'm just going to take the log entry from
here and from the TankPlayerController.cpp.
and I'm going to replace... Well. let me put it in where it wants to go. so I don't
lose my copy buffer. So I'm going to pop it in there. I'm going to make the call here though
from the TankPlayerCo?ntroller. So. instead of the TODO that
tells ControlledTank to aim at this point. we want to GetControlledTank
and we have protected that access
here. And then. we want to say AimAt
and then we want to say (HitLocation). OK. so we're just going to
pass it from the TankPlayerController through to the tank. So. in terms of our
fancy diagram. that is this right-hand side here. We're aiming at the thing
the crosshair is pointing at. and this is where it finally gets called. So. over on the tank we're
going to want to log this out. Now. I'm going to want to log a little bit more than this. I'm going to want to know
which tank is aiming at what. so I'm going to say something like this.
("%s aiming at %s") OK. And
then. we're going to insert into here the tank name. So. auto
TankName =... Now. what
is TankName? So. let's be clear on this. OurTank
Name. So this is the current name of the current tank. which is
just GetName(); Now. if we look at GetName(). we can tell the type by looking;
auto comes out as an FString already. so we just need to say
. *OurTankName. *HitLocation. So it's
going to say the tank name is aiming at whatever the HitLocation that's been passed in at. So.
we're just reporting. at this layer down here the Tank. what
I'm receiving. And we're going to do this both for the Tank Player Controller. which we've just done. and
for the Tank AI Controller. which you've guessed it. you're going to be [laughs] doing. So.
we want you to get the Tank AI reporting the aim. Just before we go into that though.
I want to just check that it works. that what I've setup for you
works for the PlayerController. and also. that'll give you an idea as to what the
correct output is. if you get this challenge right. So. just compile what
I just did up. And what did I just do. in case it all flicked by your eyes too quickly?
I made an AimAt event inside the Tank.cpp. and inside the
TankPlayerController we did this. GetControlledTank() ->AimAt(HitLocation). So that's what
we did. Now. did we compile? I think we did! Play!
Cool look! So that's that same Amap. but it's fully qualifying a tank
name. If I de-possess or Shift F1 to get the mouse out. I can
see that we are. if I click on us. Tank_BP_C_32.
So it's just fully qualifying what we are aiming at. and then. it's giving us a world-space location.
What I want to happen in your challenge is. I want every frame. I want 3 logs or 4 logs.
you know however many AI tanks you have plus 1; i.e. each of these
AI Tanks is going to say me. i.e. Tank_BP2_183
aiming at and then my location. i.e. the player location.
And so. all three of my tanks will report the same aim location; so
every frame we'll get 4 logs. the 3 AI tanks aiming at the same place. and then.
1 other. which is this tank aiming at whatever the mouse is pointing at or the
cursor is pointing at. So hopefully that makes sense. I shall formalize it in a challenge slide.
Add a Tick() method into the TankAIController class.
you should be able to do that by now. Call Tank -> AimAT() every single frame.
You're going to need to get the Player Tank as
well. and make sure you protect that access. protect the pointer.
And you should get 3 logs per frame. Actually you should get 4 logs per frame. 3 from the
AI and 1 from the Player. So go ahead. pause the video. and see
if you can get that done now. by the way. By the way. why did I say that? I didn't
need to say that. Anyway you can't hear this because the video is paused! Wait. you probably can.
because you probably just un-paused it. Anyway. did you do the challenge? This is the important thing. All the learning happens
when you do the challenge. so please really give it a go.
If you can't do it. it's the trying that's going to help as well.
OK wicked! Let's go and show you how I would tackle
this! So. the issue here is over on
the TankPlayerAIController. the Tank
AIController. We need to get a tick into the tank. AI controller is the first thing. I think
I'll start in the header file actually. So private. yep that's right! BeginPlay(). so
virtual void Tick
(float DeltaTime) and now again you could see this from the Tank.h
if you wanted to. or DeltaSeconds.
Actually. it doesn't matter what you name the parameter here in the header file.
override; because we want to make sure that we're definitely overriding a super class
method. And then. let's copy all that. or I could be bold
and copy it from the Tank.cpp. There it is!
"// Called every frame". Pop that into the TankAI
Controller. It's the AI Controller that we now want to tick. If you're going to copy
from another class. remember to change the class name here.
Remember to call Super. which we have done now. Then.
we want to think about what we're doing. Well. the first thing we want to do is say. do we have a
Player Tank. so we need to say if (GetPlayerTank))
If we don't have a Player Tank. then we don't want to do anything this frame. It makes no sense to do
anything without a Player Tank for the AI Controller. It's kind of a lemon. unless there's
a tank to aim at. So in general. in pseudocode. what are we going to do every single
tick? There's an important important bit of code here. What are we going to "//Move towards
the player". We can't do that yet. so we leave it as a comment. We could do it as a TODO though.
because it's something we're going to actually add later. We're then going to
aim at the player. Well. let's just write it as pseudocode for the moment. "// Aim
at the player". or "// Aim towards the player".
Start aiming towards the player. And the third thing we would do is "//Fire
if ready". What we're interested in is this "// Aim towards
the player" bit. So. how do we do that? Well.
we're going to GetControlledTank. Remember it's the ControlledTank . not the PlayerTank.
because. if we look at the architecture. the AI
Controller is possessing this Tank here. So. we're inside this AI
Controller saying get me the ControlledTank. So. it's the Tank that the AI Controller is possessing
we're interested in. Get the ControlledTank. and once you've got the ControlledTank. it will now
have an ->AimAt() method on it. won't it. regardless of whether it's a player's tank or not. And then. what
are we going to aim at? Well. we need to Get the PlayerTank
and then. we need to just get the location.
Get
ActorLocation should do it. There you go! Does that make
sense? We tell the ControlledTank to AimAt the player's location.
in English. Cool! Let's try it. let's see what happens!
Compile complete! Ooh. look at that. lots of stuff in the log! Let's pause it. take a look
and make sure this log stuff makes sense. So. Tank_BP_569. I can
see that here. it's aiming at 0. 0. 107. Is that where we are?
Yeah! It's going to be where our tank is. I believe.
Um. which tank are we? We're none of them. because we're not playing anymore.
but it is where we would have been. It's pretty much exactly where we started. at roughly
the origin. OK. the PlayerStart point is at  240.
and the actual origin of our tank. when it spawns. if we de-possess is
probably slightly different. Which one are we? We're this one here. 0-ish 0-ish
107. It's good enough! There's a little bit of collision physics or the way this land
is moving it. So. this tank. this AI tank
is aiming at us. In fact. all of the AI tanks are aiming at
us. and the only anomaly is this Tank_BP_C_35.
which was the player tank and that value will keep changing. So. if we look at this.
most of those values should be stable. You can just about see it as they flick past. and then. as we
move the viewpoint around. the player is reporting a different position. Great!
So that means that everything is working through a unified interface.
The Tank. regardless of whether it's controlled by. who it's possessed by.
an AI or a Player. is on equal grounds. They're both calling the same AimAt
method. and everything that happens from there on in will be the same for the Player's
tank and the AI tank. meaning that the AI cannot cheat and cannot get an advantage.
And we don't have to duplicate any code. we don't have to play-test or
balance the tank's behavior against the player's behavior. anything like that.
It's really equitable. the tank and the player's tanks will
move and aim in the same way. because they're using the same API. the same AimAt
call. So that's it. that's pretty cool! I think I'll just leave a bit of code on the screen for you. just
for fun. and anything else you need to do. just rewind and take a look
at it. So. see you soon. and well done!
=======
So in this video we will Unify Player & AI
Aiming! What that means is that we will end up with the top section of this diagram
finished so that, regardless of whether it's the player or the AI possessing the
tank, they will call the same AimAt method. And then, what that will mean is that we can
actually log out these three AI tanks are aiming at me, my player,
the player position, and we are aiming at, well whatever we fancy really. So,
let's dive in and get it going!
Okie cokie! So, we are ready to get
this whole top section working. We have a Tank AI Controller, it's going to be pretty
easy to organize, excuse me, to aim at the player. We have a Tank Player
Controller and we have just spent loads of effort making sure we know what this
world-space is here. So, in either case we're going to aim at a particular
world-space, whether it's the player's world-space or whether it's the world-space that the crosshair
is pointing at. And we're going to send that to the tank, and there's going to be an
AimAt method, as we can see here on the tank. So, the first thing to do
is to make that AimAt method on the tank. That's pretty simple, if you want a mini challenge for yourself,
go ahead and do it now. I'm going to just do it anyway.
By the way, all these things should have been private in here, because they don't need to be public.
So, for the first time now, I'm going to make a public section, and ask
myself the question, is it reasonable for a tank to have a public
method called AimAt? I think it is! The public part
of these classes is the most important thing, it's the contract, it's the external
view of the tank. But I think it's perfectly reasonable to have a void AimAt
(FVector HitLocation).
In this case, we kind of mean the location of the thing we want to hit, but it is also
the HitLocation, formally from the line trace that we did
in the TankPlayerController, because we are wanting to hit the
thing that our line trace hits. So, AimAt (FVector HitLocation);
Cool! Let's go ahead and implement that inside the tank.
I think I'll do it down here. We need an
ATank:: qualify the class,
and then, we come in here. Now, we're not actually going to do the aiming
now, so what I'm going to do is I'm just going to take the log entry from
here and from the TankPlayerController.cpp,
and I'm going to replace... Well, let me put it in where it wants to go, so I don't
lose my copy buffer. So I'm going to pop it in there. I'm going to make the call here though
from the TankPlayerCo?ntroller. So, instead of the TODO that
tells ControlledTank to aim at this point, we want to GetControlledTank
and we have protected that access
here. And then, we want to say AimAt
and then we want to say (HitLocation). OK, so we're just going to
pass it from the TankPlayerController through to the tank. So, in terms of our
fancy diagram, that is this right-hand side here. We're aiming at the thing
the crosshair is pointing at, and this is where it finally gets called. So, over on the tank we're
going to want to log this out. Now, I'm going to want to log a little bit more than this. I'm going to want to know
which tank is aiming at what, so I'm going to say something like this.
("%s aiming at %s") OK. And
then, we're going to insert into here the tank name. So, auto
TankName =... Now, what
is TankName? So, let's be clear on this, OurTank
Name. So this is the current name of the current tank, which is
just GetName(); Now, if we look at GetName(), we can tell the type by looking;
auto comes out as an FString already, so we just need to say
, *OurTankName, *HitLocation. So it's
going to say the tank name is aiming at whatever the HitLocation that's been passed in at. So,
we're just reporting, at this layer down here the Tank, what
I'm receiving. And we're going to do this both for the Tank Player Controller, which we've just done, and
for the Tank AI Controller, which you've guessed it, you're going to be [laughs] doing. So,
we want you to get the Tank AI reporting the aim. Just before we go into that though,
I want to just check that it works, that what I've setup for you
works for the PlayerController, and also, that'll give you an idea as to what the
correct output is, if you get this challenge right. So, just compile what
I just did up. And what did I just do, in case it all flicked by your eyes too quickly?
I made an AimAt event inside the Tank.cpp, and inside the
TankPlayerController we did this, GetControlledTank() ->AimAt(HitLocation). So that's what
we did. Now, did we compile? I think we did! Play!
Cool look! So that's that same Amap, but it's fully qualifying a tank
name. If I de-possess or Shift F1 to get the mouse out, I can
see that we are, if I click on us, Tank_BP_C_32.
So it's just fully qualifying what we are aiming at, and then, it's giving us a world-space location.
What I want to happen in your challenge is, I want every frame, I want 3 logs or 4 logs,
you know however many AI tanks you have plus 1; i.e. each of these
AI Tanks is going to say me, i.e. Tank_BP2_183
aiming at and then my location, i.e. the player location.
And so, all three of my tanks will report the same aim location; so
every frame we'll get 4 logs, the 3 AI tanks aiming at the same place, and then,
1 other, which is this tank aiming at whatever the mouse is pointing at or the
cursor is pointing at. So hopefully that makes sense. I shall formalize it in a challenge slide.
Add a Tick() method into the TankAIController class,
you should be able to do that by now. Call Tank -> AimAT() every single frame.
You're going to need to get the Player Tank as
well, and make sure you protect that access, protect the pointer.
And you should get 3 logs per frame. Actually you should get 4 logs per frame, 3 from the
AI and 1 from the Player. So go ahead, pause the video, and see
if you can get that done now, by the way. By the way, why did I say that? I didn't
need to say that. Anyway you can't hear this because the video is paused! Wait, you probably can,
because you probably just un-paused it. Anyway, did you do the challenge? This is the important thing. All the learning happens
when you do the challenge, so please really give it a go.
If you can't do it, it's the trying that's going to help as well.
OK wicked! Let's go and show you how I would tackle
this! So, the issue here is over on
the TankPlayerAIController, the Tank
AIController. We need to get a tick into the tank, AI controller is the first thing. I think
I'll start in the header file actually. So private, yep that's right! BeginPlay(), so
virtual void Tick
(float DeltaTime) and now again you could see this from the Tank.h
if you wanted to, or DeltaSeconds.
Actually, it doesn't matter what you name the parameter here in the header file.
override; because we want to make sure that we're definitely overriding a super class
method. And then, let's copy all that, or I could be bold
and copy it from the Tank.cpp. There it is!
"// Called every frame". Pop that into the TankAI
Controller. It's the AI Controller that we now want to tick. If you're going to copy
from another class, remember to change the class name here.
Remember to call Super, which we have done now. Then,
we want to think about what we're doing. Well, the first thing we want to do is say, do we have a
Player Tank, so we need to say if (GetPlayerTank))
If we don't have a Player Tank, then we don't want to do anything this frame. It makes no sense to do
anything without a Player Tank for the AI Controller. It's kind of a lemon, unless there's
a tank to aim at. So in general, in pseudocode, what are we going to do every single
tick? There's an important important bit of code here. What are we going to "//Move towards
the player". We can't do that yet, so we leave it as a comment. We could do it as a TODO though,
because it's something we're going to actually add later. We're then going to
aim at the player. Well, let's just write it as pseudocode for the moment. "// Aim
at the player", or "// Aim towards the player".
Start aiming towards the player. And the third thing we would do is "//Fire
if ready". What we're interested in is this "// Aim towards
the player" bit. So, how do we do that? Well,
we're going to GetControlledTank. Remember it's the ControlledTank , not the PlayerTank,
because, if we look at the architecture, the AI
Controller is possessing this Tank here. So, we're inside this AI
Controller saying get me the ControlledTank. So, it's the Tank that the AI Controller is possessing
we're interested in. Get the ControlledTank, and once you've got the ControlledTank, it will now
have an ->AimAt() method on it, won't it, regardless of whether it's a player's tank or not. And then, what
are we going to aim at? Well, we need to Get the PlayerTank
and then, we need to just get the location.
Get
ActorLocation should do it. There you go! Does that make
sense? We tell the ControlledTank to AimAt the player's location,
in English. Cool! Let's try it, let's see what happens!
Compile complete! Ooh, look at that, lots of stuff in the log! Let's pause it, take a look
and make sure this log stuff makes sense. So, Tank_BP_569. I can
see that here, it's aiming at 0, 0, 107. Is that where we are?
Yeah! It's going to be where our tank is, I believe.
Um, which tank are we? We're none of them, because we're not playing anymore,
but it is where we would have been. It's pretty much exactly where we started, at roughly
the origin. OK, the PlayerStart point is at  240,
and the actual origin of our tank, when it spawns, if we de-possess is
probably slightly different. Which one are we? We're this one here, 0-ish 0-ish
107. It's good enough! There's a little bit of collision physics or the way this land
is moving it. So, this tank, this AI tank
is aiming at us. In fact, all of the AI tanks are aiming at
us, and the only anomaly is this Tank_BP_C_35,
which was the player tank and that value will keep changing. So, if we look at this,
most of those values should be stable. You can just about see it as they flick past, and then, as we
move the viewpoint around, the player is reporting a different position. Great!
So that means that everything is working through a unified interface.
The Tank, regardless of whether it's controlled by, who it's possessed by,
an AI or a Player, is on equal grounds. They're both calling the same AimAt
method, and everything that happens from there on in will be the same for the Player's
tank and the AI tank, meaning that the AI cannot cheat and cannot get an advantage.
And we don't have to duplicate any code, we don't have to play-test or
balance the tank's behavior against the player's behavior, anything like that.
It's really equitable, the tank and the player's tanks will
move and aim in the same way, because they're using the same API, the same AimAt
call. So that's it, that's pretty cool! I think I'll just leave a bit of code on the screen for you, just
for fun, and anything else you need to do, just rewind and take a look
at it. So, see you soon, and well done!
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1:Unreal/Section4/BT30 Unify Player & AI Aiming.srt