So, welcome to Creating Default Sub Objects! What we're going to do in this video
is, we're going to add an aiming component to our tank blueprint, but we're going to add it
in C++ code; so it comes up here, whether you kind of like it or not. You won't even
be able to remove it or the designer won't. Then, we're going to delegate down our
behavior, our aiming behavior to this component. So let's see how that's done!
So, let's talk about the architecture of this puppy! We have
already done the whole top of this now, the top up to the Tank.
We have both of the Controllers reporting where they're aiming at, and the Tank's
receiving those. What we're going to do, mainly as an option to show you
other ways of doing thing, for the moment, is we're going to delegate that behavior straight
out to a Tank Aiming Component, rather than dealing with it in the Tank. In reality,
as you're building up a project, you may well just bungle this in the Tank and then later decide, well
actually some of this could be easily moved out into a separate class,
especially if you were going to reuse that aiming component. Perhaps as a more general Aiming
Component, like a mortar or something like that. But I'm going to go straight to
separation into an Aiming Component, because I'm going to show you the delegation process. You'll see that
in the engine, you'll see it all over the place, and it
works here. It works much better, when we talk about the movement, which you'll see later on when we do all the
tank movement, but we'll be ending up doing movement and aiming in exactly the same way. We'll have an Aiming Component
and a Movement Component, and it'll all be on level ground in that respect. So, it's an architectural
decision. There are lots of ways of approaching this but we're going to stick with this, for this section.
And what it means is that we're going to have on the tank here, we're going to add a component,
but rather than adding a Blueprint Component and then
perhaps choosing Actor Component... Don't do this, by the way. We're not even going to do that, we're
not even going to do it by adding a C++ component. We're actually going to do this directly
in script. We're actually going to add the component in the constructor of the
tank, because the tank is going to require the
Tank Aiming Component. It does require the Tank Aiming Component, if it's going to delegate aiming to it.
And we're going to show you how to add these things in code, so that means that your designer basically
can't break the requirement by
removing the Tank Aiming Component, for example. Alright, and that'll make sure all your code runs
together, so it's a pretty cool technique. So, the first thing we're going to need to do in our
Tank.h then, is to actually make ourselves a space for these
aiming components. Now, I'm going to put this in the protected section. Why protected? Well, it can't
be private, because we are going to need to
access it using a uproperty later, and it's not going to be
allowed to be private, we'll get a compiler error. And it doesn't need to be public because
who needs access to this component from the outside. This is the tank's business
that it is using a separate Aiming and Movement Component. So, we're going to start
in protected: so we create ourselves a
protected section, and then, we're going to make ourself a Tank Movement Component
pointer. But of course, the Tank Movement Component does not exist yet as a class,
so let's start by making that class. Over in your
Content Browser, C++ Classes, you can
Add a New C++ Class. Now, the question is, what's it going to be? Well,
which of these things, that are on my screen now, do you think it's going to be, before I tell you; the ones
that are highlighted: Character, Pawn, Actor, Actor Component, or Scene Component,
if we're making a Tank Aiming Component? Hopefully you guessed that it should
be Actor Component, because it's a component on an Actor. So remembering
that a Pawn is also an Actor and that a tank is a type of Pawn, which is a type of Actor. You've got to love
inheritance. So, we're going to make an Actor Component, and it's going to be called Tank
Aiming, with a g,
Component, without an eye! [Laughs] OK, so we create
the class TankAimingComponent. Just let that
happen. And then, we can go back to the Tank
and we can start talking about include, do the #include that we need to do,
and then we can create ourselves a pointer to a TankAimingComponent, because, of course, without the class
none of that is possible. But let's just get the boiler plate code.
Have a look and see what the boiler plate code looks like! Here it is, TankAimingComponent.h.
It's done all this for us, and TankAiming
Component.cpp. Cool! So importantly, we need to
we're going to need to #include the "TankAimingComponent.h", just like we do in the .cpp.
For the TankAimingComponent, we're going to need to do this in the Tank
aren't we? And we're going to need to do it in the Tank.h,
because we're going to want to reference it in the Tank.h. Now,
remember that you can't be below the Tank generated .h. It's just a rule, you must place
new classes above this. I'll make a note here.
Paste put...
Put probably better, because you're not always pasting, but in this case I'm going to do a paste,
with some quotes... Oops, I didn't need that did I?
Took the whole thing. There you go! "#include "TankAimingComponent.h"" So that means
that the tank now has a concept of this TankAimingComponent.h. This means that in
the protected section we can say UTankAiming
Component. Remember it's named it like that for us
here. UTankAimingComponent pointer.
So we want to store a pointer to it, and we can call it Tank
AimingComponent = and that should be the null
pointer to start with, just to initialize it to something sensible and predictable
if not desirable. OK cool! So we have now, the Tank
has the ability to have a reference to a TankAimingComponent now. So, over in the Tank.cpp
up in it's constructor then, we're going to look about adding this
from code. Now, we don't need to protect the pointers, because
it's adding in the constructor, and it's very likely to
fail, so "// No need to protect pointers
as added at construction".
Make a note about that before I do it. So, we want the Tank
AimingComponent... so AimingComponent
Where has my variable gone?
TankAimingComponent, it just hasn't popped through yet. The IntelliSense,
as usual, is being very slow. So, TankAimingComponent =...
Now, this is the new method for you. It's called CreateDefaultSubObject,
so let's use that. CreateDefault
SubObject, and then, you give it a
type. It's a generic type, so in the brackets here we're going to put the type, and then, we're going to give it
an FName in the circular brackets. So the type is <UTank
AimingComponent>. There you go, something that the IntelliSense is working on!
And then, the argument we need to pass is an (FName
and we give it a name, and we can call it the AimComponent or ("AimingComponent"))
like that. Now, you'll see what that FName does in a moment; you'll see how it
appears in the hierarchy. Let's go ahead and see if this will compile. I've got a lot of VisualStudio warnings,
but I'm thinking they're probably all just um, all just VisualStudio
having a hissy fit about nothing in particular. So, let me see if I can get to the Compile
button.
Hmm, my Compile button has completely disappeared in Unreal, so I'm
just going to close and reopen Unreal. I have seen that happen before. If it ever happens to you, the first port of
call is just to close and reopen your Unreal Editor.
OK, there it is back, the Compile button! Unless I didn't
see it before but I think I didn't. Alright, so that's now
triggering VisualStudio to compile this code, which might force into submission in terms
of these errors. Either that or there is some error here, but I can't see it, so
OK, there is some error, let's take a look and see what it is! CreateDefaultSubObject
is undeclared! So the question is, have I spelled that wrong?
Yep, it's
a small o on the SubObject, I believe that's my problem. Let's
recompile! So,
the code you want is this, Create DefaultSubobject, like that, with a small
o. Let it compile, see if there are any more errors.
Compile Complete! Now, if we go look at the tank now. Let's
go have a look at the tank blueprint, see how it's looking. Ah, look at
that! At the top of the tank blueprint, we have AimingComponent (Inherited).
We can't currently see any details on it and we can change that if we wish to,
but you have the component added there at construction time, so it's
already there before we even play the game. Now, talking about playing the game, we probably should play the game just to
make sure that it's not broken. It seems to be fine. Everything that was happening before is happening now,
but the tank has a pure C++ Aiming Component that it calls there
(Inherited), which is exactly what we want.
So it's challenge time! I want you to move the aiming logs, the things that are
giving us our logs about where we're pointing to the new component. Move
them, don't copy them so that they're in one new place and we can be sure it's working.
Obviously recompile your code, and make sure that the message still gets through to
the log. And when you've done that, just take a step
back and ensure that you're comfortable with what's happening overall, and then, I'll
show you quickly how I do that and then we'll end the video. So,
see you in a moment! So welcome
back! Let's take a look and see what's happening here. So previously,
in the Tank C++ we have got some
logs. Here you go! AimAt and the AimAt
is just logging out directly. It's getting the tank name and it's
logging out. So, let's take that code, so it's no longer there, and
let's add it into the TankAimingComponent. And then, we need to make
ourselves a new AimAt method,
in this subcomponent. So, before I do that I'm just going to paste that
code back. If you ever cut code and then think you're going to do something and then realize that
you're not quite ready to use it, and it's left in the paste buffer, put it back where you left it for a moment, because
otherwise you can end up with it, you'll reuse your copy buffer and lose
your code right. So it's pretty obvious computer use stuff that, but definitely worth mentioning.
OK, so over in the TankAimingComponent... And I'm going to get rid of the AIController,
for a minute. Over in the AimingComponent, we're going to need a new method, so this is going to
be a public method. Telling the AimingComponent to aim is a
candidate for being a public method. So, void AimAt and then
we're going to say, well we're going to aim at some (FVector), and let's
give it a variable name for now, just kind of for commenting purposes. You don't need it here in
the .h file, but WorldSpaceAim). And this thing is going to tell the tank
to start aiming at a particular WorldSpace. Aim, pretty self explanatory.
So let's make that method over here in the implementation.
Just grab the class name and decorate it with that,
and then, just pop in and implement. Now,
that's fine! So, we now have an AimAt in there, which means that from the tank, instead of
doing this logging we can do the following. We can say... We can get the TankAimingComponent, which
we should have now down here as TankAimingComponent. So,
let's say TankAimingComnponent. Now that's a pointer.
And then, we should be able to go AimAt and then this (HitLocation),
which means that the log
can come from here down to the TankAimingComponent
there. The only problem is, we're not just going to be able to get the name of the component;
we need to GetOwner()-> GetName(); which means
from a hierarchy point of view, we're in the AimingComponent, we're going to come up to the tank itself and get
it its name. OK, so that's what I'm proposing we do.
The only thing is that we've got WorldSpaceAim as a name coming in here
and then HitLocation there. Let's change it all to HitLocation. So, I'm going to
change the signature to HitLocation and the same here. So, we're going to
aim at a particular HitLocation, that makes just as much sense. And
there it is! Alright now, let's compile and see if this makes
it all the way down to the new component, that's automatically added in code
and if it does that's great! We can focus on tanky stuff at the tank and we can focus on
aiming specific stuff in the AimingComponent.
While this recompiles... Oops, what I missed...
Done! I'll just carry on! Here we go! Ooh look, that works! Now, just to
convince ourselves that that's definitely working here, let's just double check that
the tank is saved, there are no stars, there's no logs in the tank,
the only logs are here, so it is being logged from the AimingComponent. That's it, congratulations! We've got that
done!