Welcome to Predict
Projectile Landing Point! What we're going to do in this video is actually implement
our method call. Don't look at that too long. because it's the solution to your challenge. and find
that the logs will actually tell us where we should be aiming our barrel
as unit vectors. which is pretty cool!
Can't we just work out where to point this barrel already.
I hear you cry! Well I'm glad you asked. because yes it is time to actually
implement this method. So. let's take a
quick look at this. You've look at this. as your homework. It's time to
actually implement this code now. I think I'm actually going to keep it on the screen on the
left here and see if I can find some room for Visual Studio.
on the right-hand side. I'll close my Solution Explorer. customize my workspace
so that it works for me. OK cool! I don't even need these
line numbers. but I think I'll try and do this squeezing them in. Can I just
change the dividing point here? I can. good old Windows is helping me
out a little bit there. So. I'll just get you setup with what we need at the beginning and the end.
and then. you can actually make the method call yourself as the challenge. Go ahead. do the whole lot if you
think you know what I'm going to do. but for everybody else. we're going to firstly protect our barrel pointer
member. So. if we don't have a barrel. then what do we want to do? We want to get out of here!
We return. Return what? Well void. so nothing.
Fantastic! So that's protecting that barrel reference. What else
do we need? Well. we're going to need a start location. In fact. let's just go through this in order.
We're going to need a world context object. Well this
will do. Literally the word "this" will do. because our TankAimingComponent
is sufficient as that WorldContext. So there's a hint there for you. for the challenge. Now the
TossVelocity! Do we have the TossVelocity yet?
Well. it's an out parameter. it's actually the TossVelocity we're going to get out of this thing.
so you're going to need to make room for an out parameter. I'm going to call that out
parameter LaunchVelocity. So let me do that bit for you.
FVector out. I'm going to call it OutLaunchVelocity.
just to mark it as an out parameter. a different way Unreal does this inside the engine.
OK. what else are we going to need? We're going to need the start location. so let me just
help you a little bit with the start location. which is this guy
here. That's going to be an FVector. of course.
and it's going to be called StartLocation. just to keep things simple.
Now. we're going to start where the
barrel is but what part of the barrel? If we go to the barrel and use an
arrow operator because it's a pointer. then we can ask ourselves. well what
can we do? We could try and get location. and my autofill gives
me the following. GetComponentLocation. Well it's not a component. it's a...
Well it is a component but we can do better than that.
We don't want to get a custom location. but we can do even better and get a socket location
if we want to. So. either GetComponentLocation or GetSocketLocation.
I'm going to roll with GetSocketLocation. and we're going to make a socket first.
over on the barrel. So. you go to the tank_fbx_
barrel. static mesh. open it up. add yourself a socket. Because of the bug.
we move the socket to where we want the projectile to launch from first. say here
Then. we give it a rename to Projectile.
Because it's referenced by string. let's copy that into the paste
buffer so that we've got it ready. So now we have a place that we can adjust on the barrel.
As long as we save that barrel. then we're going to be able to find that
socket from code. and the way we do that is we use the GetSocket
Location method. What does it take as a parameter?
It takes an FName for the socket in question. so we can construct
that (FName() open brackets and then as a
string the word ("Projectile"). And if you read the documentation
of that method. it'll tell you that it'll go and try and find a socket called Projectile.
and if it can't find one. it'll just return the location of the barrel. So it fails over
nicely I like that! That's always good! So then. we're going to
make our function call. So make...
"// Calculate the Out
LaunchVelocity" and
you're going to do that bit. given that I've set you up properly. And then. what we're
going to do at the end. after that. is we're going to
turn that into a unit vector using the dot
GetSafeNormal. So I want you to create
a auto
AimDirection. let's call it. and that's going to be = to
whatever this OurLaunchVelocity is.
which remember from the previous slides. if I go back. will be
this guy here. the big green arrow. I want you to convert it into that little white arrow. and
the way that we do that is using the .GetSafeNormal method.
which you can go read about if you like. but that's just going to turn it into a
unit vector. Alright. so now you have an AimDirection. and
we can say "Aiming at...
You can see what I'm doing here. I'm setting up the outside of this thing for you.
Let's just maximize this window for now. Aiming at...
AimDirection is coming out as a vector. so I'm going
to say
star AimDirection.ToString()); and then
if the AimDirection is actually a FVector. like we hope it would be
after this... It will right now. by the way. be an empty FVector. In fact. let's just test it compiles
before I even put you into the challenge. While it's compiling. I'll show you the code I've written. it's just
here. Nothing is going on because we set
a LaunchVelocity. We don't bother to initialize it. because we're about to use it as an out parameter.
Because it'll initialize by default to 0. we should
end up getting aiming at 0 0 0. "Aiming at" 0
0 0. Perfect! So you are now ready for your challenge! What I want you to do
is make the method call. Sounds easy enough but you need to make sure you read the docs properly.
So fast forward to it
and here we go! Use SuggestProjectileVelocity(). that's the method to use.
We've talked about that. Use OutLaunchVelocity.GetSafeNormal(). I've done that bit for you.
And then. log out the required AimDirection. I've even setup the logging. so all I need you to do
is write the method call for SuggestProjectile
Velocity() properly and see if you can get it working. Go ahead pause the video. Give it 5 to 10 minutes if you need to.
and I'll see you in a moment.
OK. welcome back! So this is where I'm going to split my screen again. because I do think it's
helpful to have the method details on the left-hand side here. And
let's see if we can make this method call! So
firstly. I want to pattern where I say if
we successfully calculate the LaunchVelocity. so
if we calculate the LaunchVelocity. then I want to go
ahead and print this stuff out here. so
just tab these in. otherwise we're going to do nothing.
So "// If no solution found
do nothing". and that's because this thing.
this SuggestProjectileVelocity returns a boolean. and if it can't
succeed it says false. OK. so this pattern here is going to allow us to only
log if we get a result. So then. if you're going to
do that all in one. how do we lay it out? Well we've done this very recently. so let's just
go ahead and get on with it. and it's just a bit of weird indentation. which I think probably
ends up with the cleanest code that we can get. So. I've taken too much
stuff. If UGameplayStatics suggests projectile
velocity. like so. Ah. I'm going to get rid of
the comments. So there is the beginning of our function call right.
at the end of that. So what we're going to do is open the brackets.
let's say here or on this line. and then. we're going to close
the brackets somewhere down at the bottom. So it's in here now that we're going to
make the method call and pass in all of the parameters. So. I said that this was going to be the
context from the left screen. The WorldContext is just going to be a
reference to the actual TankAimingComponent. The TossVelocity. what
was that going to be? Well that's going to be the out parameter. this OutLaunchVelocity.
That's what we're going to get out of this thing. So there's the Toss Velocity. Let me
just tighten this stuff up a little bit. Hopefully you can see what I'm doing with the
indentation here. Now have I mismatched my brackets? I have!
I need another closing bracket. and I'm going to push all these parameters in
by one indentation.There you go. It's a bit weird. may be a bit clearer like that.
So yeah. I think that's working. So. Out
LaunchVelocity StartLocation. So what is the Start
Location? Well. we've defined it above. Then. what comes next? The
EndLocation. Well. the EndLocation is the hit location. That's where we
want it to end up. Toss Speed. well that's the LaunchSpeed that
we've already given ourselves. Fantastic! The HighArc.
we don't want to go by the HighArc so we say false. Then the Collision
Radius. How much variability do we want on it? 0. I'm going to
choose because we want to aim precisely. The OverrideGravity. no we're not going to do
that. and the final thing. which is a little trickier. is that you need to decide whether we're going to trace
or not. whether we're going to debug trace. So. I'm not going to bother.
but I am just going to find the name of this enumerator.
by copying it without clicking on it which is harder than it sounds.
There and then I'm going to go colon colon to get the things and I'm going to say do not trace.
And that should be it! I think. yeah. the bracket matching is working now.
and that is my code! If this succeeds
print this. otherwise do nothing. I hope that makes sense. Now.
let's go ahead and see if it compiles. All very well at the code making sense. I'll leave it on the screen while it
compiles. I think that's a helpful general habit for you guys to follow. please tell me in
our forums or on the Facebook group if you find that helpful.
or even in the Q & A on Udemy. wherever you like.
OK. how are we doing? That worked! Ah hah. "Aiming at"!
And now. it's telling us if I wanted to hit this world space location.
where would I need to aim? Three of them are staying consistent but look at this guy. this looks feasible.
It's saying that in order to hit that mountain I would need to aim at Y = 1-ish.
which is to the right. X = not very
far forward. In fact. you'll see as I go forward and backwards
of the exactly right-hand direction.
the exactly positive Y direction. that that X goes either side
of 0. I'm looking at the line that's changing here. of course. in the logs.
And then. the Z is depending on how high I'm aiming. so let's just try aiming at the sky.
What happens? Well. we don't know for sure because we're not logging the tank
name. so we'd better just pop in here the tank name as well. So we're just
going to go auto TankName =
GetOwner()->GetName
(). We may as well do all of this. ToString();
OK and then I can just put the tank name in
and just
pop it right on here. *TankName comma.
That's great! Let's just recompile that
because the information I'm getting right now is. I don't know which tank
my tank. when I'm aiming at the sky. is failing to find a solution. I'd be guessing
if I tried to look at those numbers. So. I've done a boo boo! " 'To
String' is not a member of
'FString' ". Oh. of course. the name is already a
string. Silly me! OK. easy to do though!
So this is the code I'm ending up with. I'm just getting a tank name here and just passing it
in as a second parameter. so that when I do my check here I
can be sure that my tank... Now before we do that. let's see what my tank is. Let's
depossess. go to the World Outliner. Which one is my tank? It is
BP_C_38. OK. so let's repossess! So. we don't really know
for sure that that's working perfectly. but I think we can move on and start actually
firing a projectile. That's going to give us a much better bit of visual feedback than trying to stare at these numbers
and work out if they're giving us what we want. So. well done on getting this far!
I'll leave the code on the screen for you. Hopefully it makes sense how we made this method call and what it's
doing. and now. we actually have something that we can use
to this AimDirection here to actually point the barrel.