Welcome to
Using Forward Declarations! In this video we're going to make a Barrel
Elevate method. but that includes the need to create a barrel
class. which we will do. And we need to include that barrel class in
the TankAimingComponent. but we're not going to use a #include this time. we're going to use a forward
declaration just so that we can actually change this
thing that we hold. this private member for the barrel. from a StaticMeshComponent
to a barrel but without doing a #include. You'll see why in the video. And then.
in the .cpp we will do the normal #include. and we'll
be logging out to make sure that the TankAimingComponent can call into the barrel
and that the barrel can log to the console like so. So see you in there!
OK. let's have some fun with a barrel class then. I'm going to make a
new C++ class. and I'm going to ask myself. what's it going to be based on? Well.
as we recently dealt with StaticMeshComponents. if you remember...
Let's just take a look inside the TankAimingComponent. Where did we do that?
Here you go. the SetBarrelReference was using the StaticMesh
Component class. And if you remember that the barrel
itself is indeed a static mesh. That's the class we're going to base
our Barrel.cpp off. It's the most basic class that we can use
and it's very relevant to the barrel. So. we're going to add a new C++ class
and it's not going to be in the list.  So. we're going to need to show all classes and then
look for it. There you go. StaticMesh
Component there! So. let's go ahead! And what do we call this thing? Well. I think
it's specifically a TankBarrel. Now. Unreal
is going to prefix this for us with something. Do you know what it's going to prefix it for us with?
Is it going to be U or A? If you're not sure. then it's maybe worth having a quick look at
the Class Viewer and trying to remind yourself what the coding convention is. but
anyway it's going to do one of those two and it's going to be U. because it's ultimately based off of Component
rather than Actor. I should be able to show you that. but I think I need to wait until the
class has finished compiling. before I can do anything with the Editor right now.
So meanwhile. I noticed I've got two VisualStudio windows open.
so I'm going to just close one of those. And here we go. Tank
Barrel.cpp and TankBarrel.h. UTank
Barrel based off UStaticMeshComponent. That's why it's U. because
we're coming off a Component based class in the first place.
Fantastic! So. that is the beginnings of this! So we said
we need some properties for the barrel. but I'm tempted. before we put the properties in.
to think about what the public method is. So. the public interface to this barrel is simply
that we can. without a return value.
Elevate() the barrel at some floating
point DegreesPerSecond.
OK. so that's the public interface. [Laughs] Whoah. if I could spell Elevate
correctly! And of course. you're going to write that method. I think it would make
sense for me to immediately pop that into the C++ file. Now. look
at the C++ file. Has it got everything we need? I think it does! It looks very
sparse but it actually has everything we need. I think it's
only going to need to do these includes. so that's fine.
void Elevate DegreesPerSecond! Of course. we are going to need to pop
the class name in here. OK great! So now.
we have an outline for elevating that barrel. Now some of the code is over here in the
TankAimingComponent. "// Move the barrel a right amount this frame" and "// Give a max elevation
speed. and the frame time". So. I'm going to take those comments. pop it in here.
and then. I'm just going to call this method. this Barrel.
Elevate that Barrel.
which IntelliSense hasn't caught up with yet. And I'm going to
pass it in a value for testing. which is going to be the end of your challenge
anyway. of say 5 degrees per second. That should be
easy to see. So. "// TODO remove
magic number". because we have a magic number of
degrees per second here. So. we're going to call Barrel->Elevate at (5) degrees per second.
and the rest of our work for this video is going to be over here in
the TankBarrel. But before we go any further and actually write
Elevate. look the "class "UStaticMeshComponent" has no member
"Elevate" ". What's this talking about? Well. remember that the barrel when we declared it in the
AimingComponent. which is here. was a UStatic
MeshComponent. but we are now saying that we are going to use. rather
than a UStaticMeshComponent type of barrel. we're actually going to use a barrel
class. So. we need to make a change here. this needs to be UTankBarrel
in the TankAimingComponent.h.
UTankBarrel* like that! Now. the system doesn't know
about tank barrels at this stage. The TankAimingComponent doesn't know anything about
tank barrels. So. we need to find a way of telling the AimingComponent that tank
barrels exist. so what we can do is something we haven't done before. which is something called a forward declaration.
We can just say class UTankBarrel;
Now. if you look at that. that's the same as saying class and then all this stuff here.
but it's really stripped down. it's something called a forward declaration.
And that just allows us
to reference the type UTankBarrel here in the header file. It also makes all of
our dependencies very explicit. without creating a chain of dependencies.
OK. so we'll start using forward declarations like that more. And this shows
that in a given header file. you can actually define more than one C++ class. it doesn't
always have to correspond. Usually the name of the class is the same as the name of the file
with a prefix. but with this forward declaration. that breaks that pattern
and it's just a feature of C++. Cool! So we now have
a UTankBarrel. pointer Barrel. and it starts off as null pointer. which
is safe. So. now we can actually call Barrel
Elevate on there. which is wonderful. but let's
try compiling our code now and see if we actually get as far as this
tank barrel code being called. Let's do a UE_LOG. Have I got a UE_LOG waiting over here that
I could use? Ah yeah. let's take this log away
from the MoveBarrelTowards. Try and only keep one log at a time. if you can help it. unless you're right in the
middle of a problem. and then. let's just say
("Barrel-Elevate() called")
OK. and we don't need any qualification of that.
We could say with speed if we wanted to. um at speed
%f") and then you could just pass in Degrees
PerSecond); there you go! Why not do that! Fantastic! Let's see
if this compiles. and if the information actually gets passed through.
given that we've made these structural changes and that the
TankAimingComponent's barrel is now a barrel type
rather than a StaticMeshComponent type. So. let's see what the problem is!
So. in TankAimingComponent. on line 20.
it can't convert from a StaticMesh to a barrel. so let's have a look and see what we need to do there.
OK. now that's because here in the TankAiming
Component we need to be talking about. rather than a new StaticMeshComponent. we need to be talking
about a UTankBarrel* OK. which makes sense because
all of the instance where we were using a plain UStaticMeshComponent. we're
now using a barrel which is a derivation of a child of the Static
MeshComponent. but that means that. of course. we've got to do a bit of work in the TankAiming
Component. Let me just do a search in the current project
for UStaticMeshComponent. without rejects and
without case sensitivity.
Now it can't find any
references to that. Just in case you wonder whether I spelled it right. I can cut and paste there.
and you can see that
the only place it exists is in this SetBarrelReference OK.
So. it's just here that we need to change it. so UTankBarrel*
in the Tank.cpp. And
then. let's go and see where else it was. and that'll also be in the Tank.h
of course.
UTankBarrel* right! Now. in the Tank.h. again it has no
concept of a TankBarrel type. OK. in a moment. when IntelliSense
catches up. it'll complain about that. So. what I want you to do is a micro challenge is.
pause the video and make a forward declaration here in the Tank.h for the TankBarrel
type. So go ahead. pause the video. and do that now.
OK. so it's
simply a question of saying class UTankBarrel;
in here. and that will work fine. So now. it understands what this
type is. How about in the Tank C++. when we call UTank
Barrel* like this. Is this going to be OK? Well. let's do a compile and see what it complains about.
So. the basic point is that in the header file. if you need access to a type.
then you just use a class. a forward declaration. By the way. you can
put that word class somewhere else. You can actually put it on the line in
question. but I'm not going to confuse you with that at the moment. it's better that we do our
classes at the very top. for the moment. just to keep things simple. So. we should get another
complaint. I think. from the compiler now. As it says that on TankAiming
Component 20. it can't make a conversion. So. that's just because I didn't
change it to UTankBarrel. Let's go recompile!
So. it's a bit of a hassle refactoring it like this. but it wouldn't have made much sense
for me to show you this as a tank barrel type. because that would mean I
meant to. needed to setup the tank barrel far too early. It's only at this very
stage now that we even need a tank barrel. so this is a good time to
be doing it. Now. what do we get. when we compile this time? Let's try and
see what happens! It's interesting to see the compiler errors. because
when you start doing forward declarations for the first time you're going to get these. OK. so in TankAimingComponent
19 it is not liking. it thinks something is
overloaded.
Well let's check the TankAimingComponent.h. and
we need to change the type there. So. these are the sort of things that
happen if you don't carefully refactor and change all of
your references. and part of this is the syntactic noise in C++.
of having to change things both in the header file and the C++
file. So. we're still got an IntelliSense error here. I think that'll lead to a compilation error.
Let's take a look and see what it says! So now. we get to the point
I wanted to make. which is that in the TankAimingComponent C++ now it doesn't
understand the type. Now. we can't just do a forward declaration here.
because we actually are going to be
calling a method on the barrel. which is
here Barrel->GetSocketLocation. If we need to call a method. then you actually need to include
it. So it's at this point we do need to do a full #include in the C++ file
of Tank... What's it actually called?
TankBarrel.h. Alright.
now let's try and see if that'll compile! So. I hope you get the difference here.
Basically. in a header file. all it needs to do is know
that that type exists. and by going class and putting in a empty
type definition. then that keeps the compiler happy as far as the header file is concerned without
creating a chain of includes. Whereas in the C++ file. to of course. to
actually use a class you need all of that classes code available;
when we get down here and actually call methods. Barrel->GetSocketLocation. and that's where we need to
do the full #include. So this is just some good practice for you. I'm going to close that window so that I don't keep
clicking on the wrong one. and I think that hot reload worked! Here you go! "Barrel-
Elevate() called at speed 5.000000! Great! So. a little
bit of thinking for you there. a little bit of new stuff about forward declarations and
classes. But we have the outline now of a barrel.
and we can now start filling in the private properties that we're going to need in
a barrel. which we'll do in the next video. And we have ourselves
a new type in the TankAimingComponent. the UTank
Barrel. So. we've moved away from the StaticMesh. and we'll use the same sort of thing
for the turret. of course. We'll be having a UTankTurret type.
And we are now ready to go ahead and code out that TankBarrel method!
So I shall see you in the next video!