So. welcome to
The C++ Compilation Process! In this video we're going to set the stage
for the next video where we talk about forward declaration. And during the video. I'm going to be
building up this diagram for you to help you understand how compilation works in
C++. So let's dive in and take a look at it. step by step!
So. before I even start this video. I want to thank Daniel Marshall for
pointing out the shortcomings in the next video actually. which is the
one about forward declarations. I have now come to retrospectively insert this
declaration. this video rather. because it's going to help make things clearer as to
how compilation works. So thanks. Daniel! Here we go! How
does compilation work in Unreal? It's about time we knew. so
when you have a header file and you #include it into a .cpp file.
then the pre-processes... now I say pre-processors because
in Unreal there are various things going on before compilation. One is that
header files get included into .cpp files. One is that the
Unreal header tool has an involvement and the other is that macros have an involvement. things like UE_LOG
get expanded out to different C++ code. All of that. we're just going to for the moment lump
together into the concept of pre-processing. But you'll remember from section 1 that
.h files literally get cut and paste into the top of a .cpp file.
at the Pre-Processors stage. Alright. so just remember that for now.
So. if we #include Tank.h into the Controller
C++ file. then at the top of the Controller C++ just before
compilation you'll have all of the text of the Controller.h and all of the text of the Tank.h
but none of the Tank's actual code. none of the Tank.cpp
code. So at this stage. the compiler can turn this new .cpp file.
that we never get to see but is a combination. as I say. of those two header files
plus some macros that have been expanded plus possibly some other stuff
the Unreal header tool has put in. and that gets compiled
into a Controller.obj file. an object file. Now you can find these
object files. by the way. in your project directory under Intermediate. Build.
Win64. UE4Editor. Development.
BattleTank. and you'll find it in a similar place in. on a Mac. and you'll
have these .obj files. So there's the Tank Object and there's the Tank AI
Controller Object. they're the ones we're talking about. I'm calling it Controller
just because I want to group together the PlayerController and the AI Controller
conceptually. just to keep this diagram simple. OK. so there are these object
files. Now. they can't be run directly but they are there. so let's continue the story.
In a very similar way the Tank.h gets pasted into
the top of the .cpp. possibly including some other class
let's say TankBarrel.h. That new .cpp file with all its
nuances and changes gets compiled into an object file. Tank.obj.
there it is right here. And then. what happens
is something called linking. Well actually. this happens after all of the classes have been
compiled but let me just tell you a bit early for the sake of argument. So.
what this means is the Controller Object is expecting to be able to make
some injections directly into the Tank Object. because it knows
about the types of all of the public members of the Tank. the
variables and the methods. Alright. so it's expecting that to be
conforming to some sort of contract. but once all the linking has happened for all of the classes.
that includes now on the right-hand side the Barrel. then you've actually got a workable
.exe (Executable) file. The reason. by the way. you get linker errors some of the time is if.
for example. you use a Tank.h and you declare a class.
and then you import it into the Controller and talk about a Tank.
Then. it will get this far it'll compile. but it won't link if you don't
implement the Tank properly. because what'll happen
is it'll go I'm trying to find a hook into the Tank here and I can't find it. So. when you get linker errors. it
is normally a discrepancy between your header file and your .cpp file. Check your definitions
with linker errors. and make sure you have the same signature between your header file and your C++.
That's the typical cause of the problem there. So. I don't want you to change any
code right now. I just want to show you something. and then. I've got your step by step process
for you to show you how I want you to explore for yourself. And by
the end of the video we won't have changed any code. we're going to put it all back to how it is now.
because this video has been retrospectively inserted into the course. and I don't want to change the state of the next
couple of videos. Alright. so here we go. I just want to show you a couple of things!
Here's the TankPlayerController. we currently #include the header file.
OK. we don't want to do that! I'll show you back on the diagram. What we don't want to
do is this. #include header files. in header files like this. because if you do it once.
the Tank into the Controller. then you may want to do it again the Barrel into
the Tank. And that means that all of the Barrel's code and all of the Tank's code is
included in the Controller. which is in turn pasted into the top of the C++
of the Controller. which slows down compilation and also confuses
things. you get these weird strings of dependancies. So. we don't want to do it like that.
we want to do it like this. header files into C++ files only. Unless the only
time you need to do a header file into a header file is when you're actually inheriting. So.
a TankPlayerController is APlayerController. inherits right
there. so therefore we do need to include the TankPlayerController there
because it's inheriting. But the rest of the time. in general. you wouldn't do a
#include. like I've already done. here in a header file. So if we took it out
of a header file and we stick it in the PlayerController
file. say here above the TankPlayerController. it will actually
build right now. and the reason is. because when
the pre-processing happens it's putting the tank header file
content above the TankPlayerController content. which means that
when we get to this bit here where it says ATank.
in the header controller. it already knows what a tank is. Now go about
into this in a bit more detail in the next video. but the problem with this
is that if you were to put the tank somewhere else. which is below the PlayerController.
it now won't compile. Let me just show you it not
compiling. OK. and that's
because when it gets to the bit in the Tank
PlayerController that says ATank here. it doesn't know anything about the tank yet. Now. we don't want these
type of dependencies. The only dependencies we want in our #includes. in terms of the
order we write them. is this horrible Unreal thing that the generated .h has
to go last. Alright. but we've got no control over that. we do have control over what
we do here. So. what I'm going to be showing you in the next video is actually
what to do so that this #include
can still stay in the .cpp file but it can stay in here anywhere.
And for now. I'm just going to put my code back exactly where it was. so I leave things
exactly where they were. In fact. I'll use version control to do that. I'll close down
my file. and there are no changes made now to my code. whatsoever.
in this video. So. what I want you to do now.
as a challenge. is to go ahead and try it for yourself. it'll make a lot more sense. Open your TankPlayer
Controller.h. Move the #include "Tank.h" to the C++ file.
Try it both above and below the TankPlayerController import
and see what works and what doesn't for yourself. And then. when you're finished. put your code
back to the original state. and that's it!
I'm just going to leave you to do that. and I'm going to leave on the screen this slide here. because
it explains how the compilation works and how we want to do our #include. So. have a good think about
this. Have a quick play with it. see if it makes sense to you. Maybe go and share
with us on Facebook or wherever you wish about
your thoughts and confusions and clarity over this. and I will see you in the
next video!
=======
So, welcome to
The C++ Compilation Process! In this video we're going to set the stage
for the next video where we talk about forward declaration. And during the video, I'm going to be
building up this diagram for you to help you understand how compilation works in
C++. So let's dive in and take a look at it, step by step!
So, before I even start this video, I want to thank Daniel Marshall for
pointing out the shortcomings in the next video actually, which is the
one about forward declarations. I have now come to retrospectively insert this
declaration, this video rather, because it's going to help make things clearer as to
how compilation works. So thanks, Daniel! Here we go! How
does compilation work in Unreal? It's about time we knew, so
when you have a header file and you #include it into a .cpp file,
then the pre-processes... now I say pre-processors because
in Unreal there are various things going on before compilation. One is that
header files get included into .cpp files. One is that the
Unreal header tool has an involvement and the other is that macros have an involvement, things like UE_LOG
get expanded out to different C++ code. All of that, we're just going to for the moment lump
together into the concept of pre-processing. But you'll remember from section 1 that
.h files literally get cut and paste into the top of a .cpp file,
at the Pre-Processors stage. Alright, so just remember that for now.
So, if we #include Tank.h into the Controller
C++ file, then at the top of the Controller C++ just before
compilation you'll have all of the text of the Controller.h and all of the text of the Tank.h
but none of the Tank's actual code, none of the Tank.cpp
code. So at this stage, the compiler can turn this new .cpp file,
that we never get to see but is a combination, as I say, of those two header files
plus some macros that have been expanded plus possibly some other stuff
the Unreal header tool has put in, and that gets compiled
into a Controller.obj file, an object file. Now you can find these
object files, by the way, in your project directory under Intermediate, Build,
Win64, UE4Editor, Development,
BattleTank, and you'll find it in a similar place in, on a Mac, and you'll
have these .obj files. So there's the Tank Object and there's the Tank AI
Controller Object, they're the ones we're talking about. I'm calling it Controller
just because I want to group together the PlayerController and the AI Controller
conceptually, just to keep this diagram simple. OK, so there are these object
files. Now, they can't be run directly but they are there, so let's continue the story.
In a very similar way the Tank.h gets pasted into
the top of the .cpp, possibly including some other class
let's say TankBarrel.h. That new .cpp file with all its
nuances and changes gets compiled into an object file, Tank.obj,
there it is right here. And then, what happens
is something called linking. Well actually, this happens after all of the classes have been
compiled but let me just tell you a bit early for the sake of argument. So,
what this means is the Controller Object is expecting to be able to make
some injections directly into the Tank Object, because it knows
about the types of all of the public members of the Tank, the
variables and the methods. Alright, so it's expecting that to be
conforming to some sort of contract, but once all the linking has happened for all of the classes,
that includes now on the right-hand side the Barrel, then you've actually got a workable
.exe (Executable) file. The reason, by the way, you get linker errors some of the time is if,
for example, you use a Tank.h and you declare a class,
and then you import it into the Controller and talk about a Tank.
Then, it will get this far it'll compile, but it won't link if you don't
implement the Tank properly, because what'll happen
is it'll go I'm trying to find a hook into the Tank here and I can't find it. So, when you get linker errors, it
is normally a discrepancy between your header file and your .cpp file. Check your definitions
with linker errors, and make sure you have the same signature between your header file and your C++.
That's the typical cause of the problem there. So, I don't want you to change any
code right now, I just want to show you something, and then, I've got your step by step process
for you to show you how I want you to explore for yourself. And by
the end of the video we won't have changed any code, we're going to put it all back to how it is now,
because this video has been retrospectively inserted into the course, and I don't want to change the state of the next
couple of videos. Alright, so here we go, I just want to show you a couple of things!
Here's the TankPlayerController, we currently #include the header file.
OK, we don't want to do that! I'll show you back on the diagram. What we don't want to
do is this, #include header files, in header files like this, because if you do it once,
the Tank into the Controller, then you may want to do it again the Barrel into
the Tank. And that means that all of the Barrel's code and all of the Tank's code is
included in the Controller, which is in turn pasted into the top of the C++
of the Controller, which slows down compilation and also confuses
things, you get these weird strings of dependancies. So, we don't want to do it like that,
we want to do it like this, header files into C++ files only. Unless the only
time you need to do a header file into a header file is when you're actually inheriting. So,
a TankPlayerController is APlayerController, inherits right
there, so therefore we do need to include the TankPlayerController there
because it's inheriting. But the rest of the time, in general, you wouldn't do a
#include, like I've already done, here in a header file. So if we took it out
of a header file and we stick it in the PlayerController
file, say here above the TankPlayerController, it will actually
build right now, and the reason is, because when
the pre-processing happens it's putting the tank header file
content above the TankPlayerController content, which means that
when we get to this bit here where it says ATank,
in the header controller, it already knows what a tank is. Now go about
into this in a bit more detail in the next video, but the problem with this
is that if you were to put the tank somewhere else, which is below the PlayerController,
it now won't compile. Let me just show you it not
compiling. OK, and that's
because when it gets to the bit in the Tank
PlayerController that says ATank here, it doesn't know anything about the tank yet. Now, we don't want these
type of dependencies. The only dependencies we want in our #includes, in terms of the
order we write them, is this horrible Unreal thing that the generated .h has
to go last. Alright, but we've got no control over that, we do have control over what
we do here. So, what I'm going to be showing you in the next video is actually
what to do so that this #include
can still stay in the .cpp file but it can stay in here anywhere.
And for now, I'm just going to put my code back exactly where it was, so I leave things
exactly where they were. In fact, I'll use version control to do that. I'll close down
my file, and there are no changes made now to my code, whatsoever,
in this video. So, what I want you to do now,
as a challenge, is to go ahead and try it for yourself, it'll make a lot more sense. Open your TankPlayer
Controller.h. Move the #include "Tank.h" to the C++ file.
Try it both above and below the TankPlayerController import
and see what works and what doesn't for yourself. And then, when you're finished, put your code
back to the original state, and that's it!
I'm just going to leave you to do that, and I'm going to leave on the screen this slide here, because
it explains how the compilation works and how we want to do our #include. So, have a good think about
this. Have a quick play with it, see if it makes sense to you. Maybe go and share
with us on Facebook or wherever you wish about
your thoughts and confusions and clarity over this, and I will see you in the
next video!
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1:Unreal/Section4/BT38 The C++ Compilation Process.srt