So. welcome to Code Architecture Storing State! In this video
we're going to reorganize a little bit. so that we have a slightly different
method over on our TankBarrle.h. We're going to call it MoveToPitch.
rather than elevate at a particular speed. And by the
end of it. we'll be in a similar position but with better architecture. and we will
have a log here saying exactly what target pitch the barrel needs
to be going to. So. see you in the next video!
So. before we go any further. let's make sure we understand how all this works. And we're going to make a
small change to a method inside the barrel. So. this is how things
happen. The TankPlayerController or Tank AI Controller here call an
AimAt method. with a world space Hit Location on the Tank. So. you're just saying
to the Tank. hey aim over here buddy. The Tank then looks at its own
LaunchSpeed. which is a property of the tank. It doesn't need to be known by the Player or the AI
really. because we aim at a particular world
point. and it's up to the Tank to know its current launch speed. That may even vary if we
upgraded the Tank. So it just takes that LaunchSpeed and passes
it along with the HitLocation to the TankAimingComponent. So. it's
nearly delegation but it's not quite. because we're actually adding some value here. we're adding the
LaunchSpeed. The TankAimingComponent. I'm going to suggest. then uses a
move to a particular pitch method. rather than the
current thing that we started to build. which is Elevate at a particular
speed. And the reason is that we don't need to be telling the Barrel how
fast to Elevate. The Player and the AI both
want the Barrel to move up and down as fast as possible and left and right. they just want it
to go to the aiming point. So rather than calculating a speed
to move at and then having to worry about clamping that speed and
making sure that its a reasonable speed. t's not really up to the AimingComponent how
fast the Barrel moves. it's up to the Barrel how fast the Barrel moves. So we're going to say to the Barrel in the future.
just move to a particular pitch. a particular number of degrees
above or below the horizon. Alright. so there's a bit of an architectural
change we're going to make there. And this architecture is nice and simple and it means
that we're only storing state. either at the PlayerController or down in the Barrel.
So the rotation. or the Pitch of the Barrel should I say. is
only stored in the Barrel mesh and then when you tell it to move to a pitch.
the job of the Barrel is to start moving towards that target pitch.
and the Barrel's pitch is not stored in the TankAimingComponent or in the Tank
or in the Player Controller. The desired aim direction is
up at the Player Controller. and the actual current aim direction is right down
in the Barrel. So we're keeping our state at the top and the bottom of the stack.
which is generally more healthy than trying to consider what's going on in between.
OK. so let's just challenge you now to make that minor
change. By the way. the Barrel also has a concept of the Max and
MinDegreesPerSecond. A Max and Min Elevation rather and the
MaxDegreesPerSecond. So you say to the Barrel. hey. Barrel. go move to a particular pitch.
You decide how fast to move there. You decide
how high you can go and how low you can go and hence whether you can even get there. The Tank
AimingComponent's just going to instruct it to try and get to that pitch as quickly as possible.
Alright. so given that. let's just make that minor
API change. and I'm going to let you do that. re-architect  your code. Apply that simple new architecture.
You're just renaming a method there on the Barrel. And
no need to actually implement anything new at this stage. just go ahead and make the
basic renaming. and make sure that you are completely comfortable with the architecture
and how the calling occurs. So go ahead. pause the video. take a good look at the code. make sure it
makes sense to you and do that now.
So welcome back! Alright. so it's literally
pretty simple. we just want to Elevate to... Well. I said I was going to rename the
method didn't I? So. let's rename it! Rather than Elevate. let's just say MoveTo.
and it's a good idea to change names if you change the function. so you don't confuse yourself.
It's a clean break. if you like. changing that name. So MoveTo
(float... And what did I say it was going to be called? ...Pitch).
OK. so we're going to move
to a particular Pitch. That's fine! So.
now we need to change this log.
("Moving towards pitch: and then we're going to
take in the Pitch. rather than degrees per second. Now let's go look and see
where this is called from. Well it's called from the TankAimingComponent.
And rather than Barrel->Elevate
(5). what we're going to do is we're going to Barrel...
I'll tell you what I better do. I'd better edit the header file.
Let's go get the signature from here.
pop it in the header file without the class
name. MoveTo Pitch. OK fantastic! Now. in the Aiming
Component. we're going to Barrle->Move
To(). Now we're going to pass at a pitch. Now. what is that pitch? Well.
we no longer need to the DeltaRotator do we? We just need to know
what we want to be aiming towards. In fact. we don't even care
what the Barrel's current rotation
is. In fact. we don't even need to the MoveBarrelTowards method. because we
can just. straight in here. just say Barrel->
MoveTo(). So it's (AimDirection dot. Now what
is the AimDirection? Well. it's an FVector. so we need to
turn that into a rotation. OK
fantastic! And then we ask for its Pitch.
Your remembering
that Rotation is a method like that. Fantastic! So what we're going
to do is. we're going to tell the Barrel to move to a particular pitch. We don't
need the MoveBarrelTowards method. that's a great simplification. So. let's take that out of the TankAiming
Component's header file. Well done if you've spotted this bit. by the way.
So that's very simple and hopefully
that's all we need to do. And then. by the way. I'm also going to
make sure that none of my header files have any
#includes of other unnecessary header files. per the forward declarations
and compiler video we talked about. So the tank includes
the TankAimingComponent. Well. why does it include the TankAimingComponent? It
doesn't need to. The Tank.cpp will need to. but the Tank.h
doesn't need to. So. let's take the TankAimingComponent out of the Tank.h. into the Tank.cpp.
and then. back at the Tank.h
so that TankAimingComponent here is available. We're
also going to write class TankAimingComponent; with
a U. so that's your forward declaration. So. I'm just going through and popping forward declarations
in everywhere that we need them. The AIController. that's including the Tank. it shouldn't be.
Let's cut that out. put it in the Tank.cpp.
which it already is. and then. back at the
TankAIController let's. if we need it. do a
forward declaration of the Tank. which we do
because we use ATank here. So. let's just go class ATank;
That's great! And just tighten this up a little bit. Let's
move to the next header file. The TankAimingComponent. that doesn't include anything unnecessary.
The TankBarrel doesn't include anything unnecessary. and the TankPlayerController
does. it includes the Tank. Naughty naughty! Let's take it out of the PlayerController.h.
into the PlayerController.cpp
and in the Player.Controller.h. because we need access to a tank.
Do we need access to a a tank anywhere? Maybe we don't? Yes we do. ATank*
star. so therefore we're going to need to go class ATank.
Cool! Alright. so we sorted a couple of things out there in one go! Let's make sure this compiles.
It was just a relatively simple API change there.
To make sure that aiming is simpler and that we've
removed code. Removing code is always a good thing. I'll be surprised if I don't get at least one
compilation error in all of those changes. because well I made a lot of changes.
There it is. "use of undefined type 'ATank' " in TankAIController.
line 18. So. and that's because I
do need to #include the tank in the TankAIController.
I just forgot to do that.
OK. let's just try compiling again.
Now. if you had a bigger project. it'd probably be quicker to read through
all the error messages and make sure you had got to all of them
that weren't cascades. But it's difficult to know when one error's
caused by a whole bunch of others. without reading really carefully. so in our case. it's quicker just to recompile.
So if we play now. look you can see that it's aiming towards pitch. and if I go down here. -30
degree. -3 degrees... Let me just switch
back to VisualStudio because it's popped over the top. If I aim at
that hill. it may be the most obstructive. it's probably going at the high arc there at 80 degrees. that
tank 8 degrees. It looks feasible! So. much better looking architecture
for us there. so I hope that all makes sense to you. I'm going to pop up on the screen
that. How The Barrel Elevates. the new API.
Remember that we also went through... I went through it pretty quickly. so I went through
and switched out all the forward declarations. well all of the #includes
of unnecessary header files in header files and moved to forward declarations.
So. make sure you've done that and that makes sense. Gather yourself
mentally and I'll see you in the next video!