So welcome to
Review Our Execution Flow! What we're going to do in this video is take a look at the diagram of the whole
elevation execution flow. so that we can just get the big picture. I feel like
we're really stuck in the details. We need to zoom out a little bit and make sure we understand what's
calling what and what eventually is leading to the request for the barrel to
elevate or go downwards. So. let's take a look at that!
OK guys. before we go any further than this. let's just take a
recap of how this barrel is elevating. because there's quite a long call stack. So.
the Player or AI Controller makes a call to a method called AimAt.
passing in a HitLocation which is a World Space Location right. and it sends that to the
Tank. So it says. Tank aim over here in the world. The Tank goes
fine. I'll use my knowledge of the LaunchSpeed. of the projectile. to then
pass that method on to my TankAimingComponent. I'm not going to deal with it myself. I'm going to delegate it down
to the TankAimingComponent. but given my LaunchSpeed. The Tank
AimingComponent then calls Elevate. with some RelativeSpeed. Now.
I know that right now the TankAimingComponent's method is... Sorry!
The Barrel's method is Elevate. and let's
just take a look at the signature. We have DegreesPerSecond. That's actually wrong.
so I will change that. I'll just change it right
now. actually. What it should be is relative speed and let's see why. So.
if we look in the TankBarrel implementation
now...If we look at. Well. you can't really tell from the implementation
yet. but the point is. you can tell from the header
file. because the TankBarrel has a concept of a
maximum number of degrees per second. So. you could pass in a
number of degrees per second. that would be OK. and you could clamp it to this
maximum. Or. in my mind. it's more meaningful to just pass in a relative
speed. where -1... In fact. let's comment this as we go!
So. "// -1 is max
downward" movement. and
"and +1 is max up movement".
OK. that's the idea! So that's what I mean by relative speed. it's between -1 and +1.
If we give it a value outside that range. it'll just treat 2. 3. 4. as 1.
it'll clamp it down. Alright. so that's what I want to do is call it
RelativeSpeed. OK. let's go back to the overview! So. the AimingComponent
calls the Barrel with a RelativeSpeed. The Barrel uses its knowledge of the maximum
number of degrees per second it can move at. it's maximum elevation in degrees.
I think we set it to 40. and the minimum elevation in degrees. Now remember
we set sensible defaults on those here in the C++.
and then. we also. if you recall. in the Tank blueprint made it
possible for the designer. at the Barrel here. to come in and tweak those values.
Fantastic! So. if I just go back to the slide. that's an overview.
The other thing to note is that the Tank AI. sorry
Player or AIController. they both tick. They both have a Tick
method. and what they do is. they just update the aim every frame.
The Tank actually doesn't need a Tick. and we'll go through and take a look at that in a moment.
And the TankAimingComponent does need a Tick. Now. you might say why
does the TankAimingComponent need a Tick. why couldn't it just tell the Barrel where to aim? Well.
think about the situation where an AI tank is aiming at me.
I'm the player. I'm sitting at the origin. for example I'm not moving. but the AI tank
is moving. And as that AI tank moves. it's HitLocation
value. up here. will not change. because my world space location is not
changing. But the Barrel and the Turret will need to move. as the
AI tank moves. in order to constantly adjust its aim to be able to hit me. The Tank.
it could be in a different position. it could be on a hill. etc. So. the TankAimingComponent
does need to tick. it does need to calculate things every frame.
alright. to re re-um instruct the Barrel and the Turret where to
move. So. let's go through and just make sure this is the case. before we do anything else. that the PlayerController ticks.
So let's go take a look at that code. And the TankPlayer
Controller.h. does it tick? There is a tick?
declaration there. but that doesn't mean that it's actually ticking. And if we look in the
method. here you go. Tick. and every Tick it AimsTowards the Crosshair.
Fine. so that's what it does! Let's move down the stack to the Tank! Well.
what does AimTowardsCrosshair do? It does some things and then
Gets the ControlledTank and says. hey tank. aim at this! So. we go to the Tank!
Now. does the Tank have a Tick? Well.
the Tank Tick is declared here in the private section of its header file. but
if we actually go to the Tank implementation
and we look at the Tick. you'll find that it's empty. Here we go! So. let's remove Tick
from the Tank. Let's do that by removing the Tick() method from this Tank.cpp.
In the constructor of the tank. we can explicitly say
don't tick. We can say. CanEverTick = false.
It says you can improve efficiency if you don't need it. so let's
stop the tank ticking. and then. in the Tank.h file. we don't even need to declare
this Tick method. Now. because I've made these changes. let's go ahead
and compile the code and make sure that we haven't busted it.
Just give it a second to compile. And then. we will continue down this stack.
looking at the TankAimingComponent. making sure that does have a Tick structure and then just double checking
the Barrel doesn't. And that way we're Ooh. I've got a compile
failure! " 'DegreesPerSecond': undeclared identifier". So. I love
C++. it's my favorite language! And one of the reasons it's my favorite
language is. because you have to do things like this. You have to go and change things in two places.
And where is this other place? So. somewhere I'm calling
Elevate. Well. I don't need to guess where that somewhere is. I'll be calling it from the TankAimingComponent.
won't I. because we know our architecture. So. in the TankAimingComponent.
where are I calling that? OK I've given up. I'm going to read the error message.
It's in TankBarrel. line 11. There we go!
And it's here!
This DegreesPerSecond. it's just our log entry. Simples! OK.
let's go ahead and compile and see how we're getting on!
So. as I was saying. we are now just making sure that the changes we made to the AI
Controller and the Tank are actually working and that the game still works
as well as it did before. without that tank ticking. Seems to. it still keeps
calling out the BarrelElevate. Now. how do we know. by the way.  that it's
continually calling that? Is it continually calling that? Well. we'll
look at that in a moment. possibly in the next video. There is actually a bug with one of the methods in here.
But the way to find if something is actually being called
is. it's very useful to know about this. You go auto and then you say...
You go Get the World(). and then you go get from the world.
There's a time. Now. autocomplete on here. of course. is not
behaving for me. I think it's GetTime
but I'm not sure. so I'm just going to check my stash here. I've got a note in
here. and if I can find it...
GetTimeSeconds. it is! OK. I'm not sure
why autocomplete's not behaving. So. if we GetTimeSeconds from the world. now we
have a floating point. Ah. I need to give it a name. that's my problem!
Time = GetWorld()->GetTimeSeconds(); perfect! Now. Time is a float.
so it's very easy for me to just come in here and go %f colon.
and then put in Time as the first
formatting parameter. So. this %f matches with the Time. and this one
matches with the RelativeSpeed. Now when I play the game. my logs will be
beautifully endorsed or annotated or decorated. I think is the word I'm
looking for. certainly not endorsed. with a prefix which tells me the time
which that log entry was made. And that's much more encouraging cause we can see now that the
logs are actually happening. Alright. so the code's still ticking! Let's go back to our
overview. Does the TankAimingComponent have a Tick?
Well. let's take a look!
It's saying here that CanEverTick is true in the Tank
AimingComponent. but we don't have a Tick
method defined. And actually. we need to challenge the question. do we really
need this TankAimingComponent to Tick? Well. we haven't written any code
in the Tick yet. We've still got it as true here. We're kind of undecided. I'm telling you in
in architecture it does need to tick but maybe it doesn't. What we need to do
is to really find out whether it needs to tick. And looking at the length of this video. we're
going to do that in the next video. as we go through and discover how to squash
a bug in the Unreal Engine and probably report it to EPIC Games as well.
because it's a nasty one. But for the moment. if you have something like a question
to yourself that you know. should this tick. then just go "// TODO should
this really tick?" Alright.
and then what I will do is I will pop on the slides even for you that
tick question mark. so we can just raise that question and move on.
Alright. the final thing is at the bottom of the stack. which is the TankBarrel. In the TankBarrel.h
there is not declaration of Tick. In the TankBarrel.cpp
there's no mention of Tick. And you need to ask yourself the question.
is the TankBarrel now ticking or not. if we don't explicitly disable that Tick?
So. in the case of this TankBarrel then. if we look. it inherits from Static
MeshComponent. You'd find that if you did put a Tick function in and put a log that
it would actually print. which means that the StaticMeshComponent may well be ticking
above. But look. just leave these things. when you create a new class at default. If there's no reason
to turn off the ticking or to turn on the ticking. just leave it. There's no point in putting extra
code in. If the profiler. performance profiler later told us that we are
wasting a lot of time ticking here. very unlikely by the way. then we could do something
about it. So. I'm just going to leave the TankBarrel as is. keep it nice and simple.
OK. so that's an overview as to the call stack that's
occurring. So. what we need to do now is to actually get this
barrel moving. So let's just take a look. now that we've got these new
log entries and just see some slightly odd behavior. Look at this!
As I move the mouse around. if I leave it there.
watch! The logs are happening. the Elevate method's being called! But if I just move. ooh.
and there it's not! Now. you may think that's cause it can't
find a solution. So one reason it would not tick like this
is because there's no solution to the aiming solve.
So let's go to where we do the aiming here. and where it says AimAt.
we could say. OK there's an AimSolution. If we have a solution.
then move the BarrelTowards an (AimDirection).
which in turn calls this Elevate method. But if we
don't have a solution. let's just log something out here.
Let's use this new logging method.
Let's log here. No solution found at this particular
time. No aim solve found").
OK. now I don't really like logging at two different levels of detail like this. If we're going to
log No aim solve found here. rather than logging in the TankBarrel
that the Elevate has been called... We know that Elevate's getting called. I'm going to move that
and do the logging at a consistent level. keep all our logs in one place. So.
if we have an AimSolution. then it would make
sense to log say here.
and then. I'm just going to say Aim solution
found") at a particular Time); OK. so I've moved all my logging just
inside by the AimComponent. to find out when we do and when we don't get an aim
solution. Let's take a look!
Oop. I didn't compile! That would help! So. let's just compile that up and then
we're going to just take a look and set ourselves up for. unfortunately. a bug in one
of these methods. Now partly it looks like my fault. but actually it isn't. we'll see when we get to it.
So. what's going on here? "No aim solve found". Why
can't it find an aim solve most of these frames? Why is it only finding a solve
one in a few frames? Very well. if I point at the sky. of course. it can't find a way of
hitting that. and if I point to that mountain in the distance. it's just too far away for
my current projectile velocity. But why. on the floor here. will it only
find a solve some of these frames? Well. that's
a very good question and one we'll address in the next video. So.
I'm not going to deal with that right now. What I'm going to do is something slightly different for this video. I'm going to close
down VisualStudio and Unreal for you. And then. I'm going to use my
code management tool here in SourceTree. just to show you what's changed in this video.
so that you can see the code changes I made. because I made a few code changes and
this will be really easy. So now you should be able to just step through the video. pausing if necessary.
and seeing exactly what I did. So in the Tank.cpp I
disabled the tick. the green is what I changed. I also just removed the
tick function from the Tank.cpp itself. In the Tank
AimingComponent we made ourself a note to question whether it should tick or not
and then we did that logging. And by the way. if you like
this. tell me either on Facebook or in our forum or in the Q & A. which doesn't really quite
fit for comments. but if you wish. put it there on Udemy. And just say whether you like me reviewing what we
did this way. because it's just a new though I had. In the .cpp
file. we just removed some logs and that
log there and made a variable name change. In the Tank header file. we
also removed the Tick. and in the TankBarrel. we
just changed the name of the parameter here
from DegreesPerSecond to RelativeSpeed. And
we also commented that -1 means max downward and +1
means max upward. We did all this in the context of this diagram.
which helped us understand what's going on. And in the next video we'll discover... OK I
want you to discover what's going on with this inability to solve the aim in
certain situations. So I'll see you soon!