So welcome to Using Clamp() to Limit Values! In this we're going to learn how to make
our barrel actually move up and down. and furthermore. make it only move up and down
as much as we want it to. as a pass through the tank or point bolt upright. So see you in there!
OK guys. we can finally get this barrel on the move. So
firstly. this magic number here about the Elevation. I'm going to keep a magic number. but
I'm going to start off with it being 1. i.e. 100% of its speed. Then.
we're going to make sure that it actually does move at about
20 degrees per second. That's too fast isn't it? Let's go for
a little bit of a lower speed. I'll do that in the tank blueprint.
because 20 degrees per second is only going to take 2 seconds. we're not going to be able to see what's
going on. So. let's go down to say 5 degrees per second for testing. Now. I'm
doing this in the blueprint because I want to override the C++ value. I think that
20 degrees per second is perfectly reasonable as a default. but I think that 5 for testing
here makes more sense. OK. so we're going to call this method
with a value of 1 in the TankAiming
component there. which means 100% of your maximum speed. It's
still a magic number. it still needs to be tied through to what's coming out of here. but for now. let's just
use it for testing. So. let's go ahead and actually get this tank barrel elevating
and making sure that if we pass in a relative speed more or than one or less than -1
that it still only goes at the maximum speed. So. how are we
going to do that? Well. let's just get on with it! I'm going to talk about there being an Elevation
Change. in this particular
frame. And that's going to be how much? Well it's going to be the RelativeSpeed
times the MaxDegreesPerSecond. So at
this point. we've got a number in degrees per second. but of course. if we have something
per second and this is an ElevationChange at this frame. that's too long a
variable name for me to use. but you get the idea. Everything's this frame in the game. basically.
Then. we need to go get the world. And then. do you remember the method?
What am I looking for for the world? What am I doing here. rather than just watching
me? Have a think about it? How am I going to correct this to make sure that it's framerate
independent? Well. it's DeltaTime
Seconds. and that is a property. so no prackity things.
OK. so that's the elevation change that we need in this frame. hopefully that makes sense
to you. It's RelativeSpeed was 0. we'd get 0 out here. If it's 1 we'll get Max
DegreesPerSecond and everything in between. Alright.
so the next thing is. we need to think about what the unclamped
new elevation would be. so we can call it. Or Raw if you like.
RawNewElevation. And this is saying. well if we weren't
concerned about the fact that there's a maximum and a minimum possible elevation.
then the calculation would be really simple. It would be simply the Relative
Rotation of the barrel. dot Pitch...
Ooh. if I can spell properly! Now. RelativeRotation
is a property here of this scene component.
dot Pitch. and if we were just to take that
and add the Elevation change that we just calculated. whether it be
positive or negative. then we would have some new elevation. But imagine
that the current pitch of the barrel is 20 degrees and that this Elevation
Change works out more than that. and...
Well actually. let's use some real figures. say the. What have we got? MaxElevation of 40.
Alright. so imagine that the current barrel is just under 40. but this Elevation
Change would take it above 40. What's going to happen? Well. the barrel's going to exceed its Maximum
Elevation right. so we need to clamp to make sure that can't happen.
Now. before we go on to talk about how to clamp this Elevation. let's show the problem.
So. let's go ahead and Set the Relative
Rotation() of the barrel. and we're going to give
it a new (FRotator) and we're going to construct that with the
Elevation or the (RawNewElevation)) for now.
And 0 and 0 for yaw and roll.
OK. and close as many brackets as we opened. Cool!
So. hopefully this makes sense. We work out what the ElevationChange is. We work out what the New
Elevation would be. given the current Elevation plus the ElevationChange. You could
put this in an intermediate variable but I'd think that's a bit much. and then. you pass it
straight to the barrel. Let's see if this works! Let's go ahead and compile
our code. and then. let's see
what happens. Hopefully if the tank... Make sure your tank is saved. by the way.
and that you've got a MaxDegreesPerSecond in the Barrel of say 5. so that it moves at a
testable speed. Let's have a look! Oh cool. look at this! Now. watch the barrel. let's
notice when it stops! 6. 7.
8. 9. [Laughs]... OK. so
this is why we need to clamp the barrel elevation right. So. it should have stopped after 8
seconds. I think. because we had 40 degrees MaxElevation. and
it's gone all the way to vertical. It doesn't go past vertical. and that's
because we've hit the maximum possible rotator pitch
value. You can. in principle. pitch further. but this rotator won't pitch any
further. That's fine for the barrel. it's got plenty of range for the barrel. we don't want to even go that
high. If you look at the Barrel and you look at the parameters.
we set a Max Elevation of 40 and a Min of 0. so therefore. it
had 40 degrees to travel through. 5 degrees per second. It should have taken 8 seconds. it should have stopped
at 40 degrees and it didn't. so that is what we need to sort out next.
But you've done plenty of watching me write code and not very much writing
code without my help. so guess what's coming. It's challenge
time! I want you to clamp the elevation! You're going to use a method called
FMath::Clamp(). Now why is it colon colon? A couple of videos ago I
did something with a colon colon. that's a static method. Static methods
basically are things that are completely functional. it means that this method is going to
spit out a return value and not mutate or change anything. so it's pretty
easy to use. The IDE will tell you what it takes in and what it returns.
and you can also have a look online to see different
signatures and different ways of using this. There is a generics format
with chevrons. you know the angle brackets. But. take a look
online or use the IDE to work out how FMath::Clamp() works. and then. test that
you have indeed restricted your elevation in between the two parameters we set in the
header file. the Max and Min Elevation. OK. see you in a moment!
OK. so let's clamp this puppy! So auto...
I'm just going to call it Elevation. rather than anything more
complicated. I'm going to take Elevation off here. because we're going to be passing it through.
We're going to go FMath::Clamp() and it's going to
take a few things. Now look at this signature carefully! It's got a
generic template here. which means that you can tell it to work on a particular type.
So that's what's happening in the angle brackets there. We could tell it
the type of thing we want to clamp. Why don't we do that just for fun!
I'm going to say let's operate on  very explicitly. Then. the first
parameter is going to be the thing that you want to clamp. which is the (Raw
NewElevation). The next parameter is the Minimum. which is the
MinElevationDegrees and the other one is the Max
ElevationDegrees.
Where's that going? Let's take a look! MaxElevation
Degrees. well it's there so I'm going to ignore IntelliSense. because it
hasn't caught up. bless it. And I am just going to assume that this is going
to work. because I think I've used that method properly. Ah you don't have to put the float there. but in doing
so. I'm telling it to explicitly work on floats.
Alright. let's have a go!
If you don't do that. you may get some implicit type conversions. where something is converted from an int to
a float or whatever. and I prefer to be specific about what we're trying to do. Let's have a go!
So now. when we look at it from the side. I'm hoping that in the console. if you keep your eye on that. when that hits
8 seconds the barrel will stop moving. I'm also hoping that if we.
ah nice. that if we depossess the tank with F8 now and then have a look
at this tank. and then. if we were to inspect it.
which we could do through the World Outliner. we may be able to get
to the actual barrel inside that tank. We're going to need a bit of messing around.
over here in the Details tab and let's click on Barrel. And here you go. Rotation
39.999 near as...
40 degrees. So it's worked! On the up side. it's very likely to
work on the down side. but why don't we just try it anyway?
One way you could do that would be to go to your Tank Viewport. to go ahead
and rotate your tank Barrel's default position up to. it doesn't matter. say
30. and then. in your calling method. instead of Tank
AimingComponent saying Elevate. it could say depress. i.e. -1.
OK. so we're going to go from 30 degrees downwards to 0. Let's see if that works!
Then. all we've got to do is remove our magic number. and we are
golden. we'll have an Elevation working! So
there it goes! Down down down! I think I said 30 degrees. didn't I?
So it should take 6 seconds there and it stops at 0. Perfect!
Clamped barrel movement. that's what we like! So. I'm just going to put my barrel back.
I think a default of 0 looks good. I think that 5 degrees per second
actually is probably not far off now. So. I'm
going to push that default back to the code in the TankBarrle.h.
because actually 20 was a bad guess. And it's fine to make a bad
guess. but once you get better evidence. then come back and fix that default. A Max of 40
and a Min of 0. I think that's perfectly reasonable. I think it would be nice to get our turret to
say 45 degrees. Let's check that visually. make sure that doesn't look crazy.
Yeah. I think it will look crazy actually. so I'm going to stick with the 40.
And now. I'm going to make sure this barrel actually has
0 pitch. in the beginning. That's cool! And I actually think that a bit of negative pitch should
be possible. but the question is. is that possible on the back of the tank? And I
think it isn't. I think that if this turret was facing the other way.
we wouldn't be able to go any lower. I've already moved these barrels down a little bit on the model.
No. so it's going to have to be a range of something like 0 to 40 or it just
ain't going to make any sense. it ain't going to work. OK fantastic! So there's
the settings. after all that discussion. 5 degrees per second. 40. and 0. It's going to compile up
that blueprint. The final thing we need to do here is say. well this is all very
well. how about two more things? How about if I was to call Elevate with a value.
instead of 1 I say that 5 that we had before. Let's just
try that! What should happen is that the 5 will come in as a
RelativeSpeed. The Tank barrel will go RelativeSpeed 5. That's fine!
It'll come in here and actually it'll go wrong. at the moment.
because what's going to happen is the RelativeSpeed is going to multiply
up these DegreesPerSecond and it's going to move 5 times too fast. Let's see it doing that!
There you go. far too fast. OK. and if I called that with a... Do you want to
just see it again to prove it? It should take 8 seconds. it's taking just 2. under
2 seconds. So what we need to do is we need to clamp that Relative
Speed here. Now. we can just mutate RelativeSpeed. in this case.
if we want. which means you just change it.
So. why don't you go ahead and do that. As a little micro challenge. why don't you clamp a Relative
Speed to between -1 and +1.
Well. go on then. I'm not going to do it till you've tried. OK. so
RelativeSpeed = FMath::Clamp
I'm going to tell it that I want to work on a >float>
and that it's the (RelativeSpeed)
...-1
+1. OK. very explicit. Now. I said that FMath::
Clamp doesn't mutate anything. That's true. it spits out an answer without changing the state of
anything but then. if we assign RelativeSpeed back over the top of itself.
like this. so the result of this function called. assigned over the top of RelativeSpeed. then
RelativeSpeed here on line 12 is different to what it was when it came into the method.
That's cool! I think that we can leave the comments. I think they're not
doing any harm. We need to just check now that this works. with a
relative speed call of 5 in the
parameters. It should not move any faster than it originally did. Now
it should take 8 seconds to fully erect to 40 degrees. Here it goes. looks
good! And we've clamped that RelativeSpeed! That is fantastic!
Alright. so the final thing we need to do to get this Elevation working is. of course. tie it
up in the TankAimingComponent. We don't want this magic number in here. We just want to know
how much to move this Barrel by. and that amount is this DeltaRotator that we worked
out a few videos ago. which is the change in
Elevation that we need this frame. according to the TankAimingComponent. dot
Pitch. And we don't really care if that value is above or below 1. because it's
going to be clamped inside the TankBarrel
method. so. or class rather. So. let's go ahead and run this now.
What I'm hoping is that just pitch will just work.
Lots of justs in there. Now. we're going to have to look at it carefully to see if it is working.
if it compiles. It does! Let me go F11 so we can get full screen.
Alright. so what's happening here? If I point. say there. is that a reasonable
pitch? Forget the yaw. it's not going to work. so I'll aim just in front to save confusion.
So. it's feasible that it's pointing in the right direction. and then. you get to a
certain distance and the projectile is not going fast enough to get there. so it doesn't even
bother calculating. So. you could try this with a different
projectile launch velocity. just to convince yourself that it's probably
working OK. So. you can come into the Tank...
Where do we set this launch speed? If I get a launch speed of 8.000.
should be able to hit those far mountains now. So. if I now aim up...
You see it aiming up? I'll F11 it so you can see a bit better.
There you go. it's now aiming up into the distance. It's going to hit that hill. and then. you aim
above the hill. it no longer gets a solution. it resets to neutral. How about this right-
hand hill here? You can see it being very sensitive now to the height
up the hill. So I think it's working! Off the top of the hill. it doesn't solve and returns to
neutral. So. I think that Elevation is probably working. We'll know for sure when we start doing
rotation. and then. we start actually spitting out some projectiles and seeing their
path and everything will be much clearer. So. hopefully that made sense as to what we've
done there. We've sent the Pitch in. and then. we've processed it in here.
And yeah. I'll see you in the next video!