So I've
got something a little different for you mid-section here. We're going to have a fairly major challenge.
It's major in terms of how long it'll take you, rather than how difficult it is, and
that is to get the turret rotating. So, if you want to dive
in without any help, then I'll give you the challenge now. And then, for those of you who want a little bit
of extra guidance, I'll give that before showing the solution. So, you're
going to need to revise the last few lectures, I think if you need to, unless it's already fresh.
At least take a look at your commits*. You are committing aren't you?
And we're going to need you to work through the blueprints and the C++ code to
make this turret work and basically see if you can get the turret rotating, but
don't worry about how the barrel, that barrel moves. It
doesn't matter if it goes from A to B in a slightly strange way, we'll deal
with that as a separate entity and modification. But
see if you can get it working. Now, if you're really confident and pause the video now, go ahead
spend a while on it. It's going to be a fantastic way to completely integrate your knowledge,
over the last few lectures. If you're not so confident, then bear with me just a second while
I show you a few pointers. So, just a few reminders
for those of you who want the help. Remember that we set a Barrel Reference
on the Tank, and then, that Tank sends that reference down to the TankAimingComponent.
Remember that we changed the barrel from a StaticMeshComponent,
like the Turret currently is, into a TankBarrelComponent.
So, we're going to need to so something very similar, make a TankTurretComponent and reorganize
this hierarchy and get all that working, making a BlueprintSpawnableComponent.
Now all that sounds scary, but actually, most of this is in here
as a template. So, if you start with your TankPlayerController,
remember that that's where everything starts, you will need very quickly then to move down
to the Tank, where you will be making yourself BarrelReference
letters like this for the Turret. And then, we will be moving into the
custom class called TankTurret.h, and that will
be very similar to this, with slightly different wording of course. And
we won't be wanting max and min rotation, we can let the thing just keep going round
and round and round. And remember, of course, that all of this is being called from the
TankAimingComponent.cpp file, and we are
making a (DeltaRotator.Pitch) call. You can probably guess what you need to do,
in order to do the turret rotation. So,
there are enough hints for you, I think there. Let's go ahead,
go back to the challenge, let you really pause the video, enjoy this larger
challenge, take your time, and remember to use source control as your friend, when you
get a little bit of something working. Make a micro commit if you need to, just a commit if
a small amount occurred, and go for it, it'll really increase your confidence if you can get this done.
And if you can't get it done for any reason, don't worry, I know it's a big challenge. Just watch my solution
and learn what you can from it. So see you soon!
OK welcome back! If I had any sleeves
I'd be rolling them up to get stuck in, but I don't, I'm in a polo shirt, so no sleeves
for me. However, I will say this might well take more than one video to get done,
because it's a little bit more, a little bit more. OK, so we've got a magic
number sitting right in front of my face. Delete that, we just don't need it.
So, I think that in order to get started, we're going to need to
start by making this new class, right? Because nearly everything's going to depend on it. I can't wire
up the blueprint, I can't get my references, I can't do anything without a new class, so let's go
ahead and make a new class! Now, if you're not sure what the class should be, well we're modeling the Turret,
the Barrel rather remember, which was a StaticMeshComponent type.
So, we add a new C++ class. Now, there is no StaticMeshComponent
in this list, unfortunately, so we have to click Show All Classes.
And we go StaticMeshComponent like that, and then,
let's call it Tank.
OK, so let's create this class! Now, it would be prudent,
once this class is created, to open up the TankBarrel and use it
as a bit of a template for the Turret. Now, when you use another class as a template, you need to be a bit
careful that you don't end up inheriting behavior that's not relevant,
but on the other hand, you know we've done a lot of work in the Barrel and why not
use it. So, there's my TankBarrel.h and then the Turret's
to the right of it. By the way, if you want to change the order that these tabs open, say I open
Tank, you see mine opens on the right. If you don't like yours opening on the left, it's
Tools and Options, over here in VisualStudio, and then, you look for Tab
and then you'll find under Environment, Tabs and Windows, this top setting.
There, now Xcode people don't really have the same concept, because Windows works
differently in Xcode. Alright, so what did we do
in the TankBarrel to make it available to the blueprint. It was that line
there. Remember that, over in the Tank blueprint, we're going to want to add a
system component right, and we don't have Tank Turret, even
though we've made the C++ class. And that is simply because we need this line that
I've got highlighted. Paste it in as our class
annotation like that. Alright, that alone will make it possible to add it to the
blueprint. Let's try it! We need to compile, and then, if we go down to the
Custom component list here, there it is, Tank Aiming and Tank Barrel right now.
Once the code compiles, Tank Turret should appear in that list. Now we may have to
just repopulate the list, because it's not dynamic. There you go, Tank Turret!
Fantastic! So that was that bit. Now once you've got a Tank Turret, it needs to be
childed to the Tank appropriately. So, just make sure by
expanding and collapsing, whatever you need to do, to make sure it's at the right level, cause that's
really important or the sockets won't work. Cool! Alright, so
while we've still got a Turret to model, what is it about it? What have we changed about the
Turret? Well not that much, I mean you can't tell by flicking
through quickly, but that's one of the reasons, actually, I've hidden Collision on our version,
because you see how much simpler and lighter this is. Collision and Physics have gone
with the Collision. That makes it easier to look at, but
our Turret basically just had a StaticMesh on it. So, let's just go and set
the Turret Mesh like this. Ooh, two r's I think.
Great! It's go no offset, that's cool! So, we've got a Tank Turret now!
We can move our Barrel into this new TankTurret, and I think I can
safely say, let's ditch the old Turret. Let's go to the Viewport, it makes life a bit easier to see what's going on.
There goes the old Turret. If you highlight it and delete it, the new one can
just be called Turret, and then, we've got a bit of messing around
to do. Why is the Turret on the floor? Well, because it hasn't been parented
to the Tank's Turret socket. Boom! Why is the
Barrel up in the air? Because the Barrel has been reparented to this Turret and therefore, it's lost its
parent socket connection. Boom! Why is the Barrel still floating in
the air? Because it has an arbitrary location. It wants to have a location of 0,
so does the Turret. Fantastic, there you go! We have
a Turret, looks exactly the same, but of course, this blueprint
is completely different, because it's based on the TankTurret class, rather than a
StaticMesh. Let's go ahead and compile! I'm also going to Save All.
You'll notice that the little stars up here will disappear, when I do that; it's important in case anything crashes,
not to lose my work. Alright, how are we doing in this video? We're
about 7 and a bit minutes in, and I think we can keep going. So, let's go
and think about getting these setter references next, I think while we're still in
blueprint. So, in your Tank blueprint, in the Event Graph,
we're going to need a set Turret Reference Method.
So, let's go and make that happen on the Tank
Barrel.cpp file. Ooh, why am I looking there?! Well, I'll leave that open, I
need it, but it's actually on the Tank.cpp file.
We had ourselves a, let's put the Tank on the left
because the execution flow goes left to right.
So, there is the SetBarrelReference, of course, we're just going to want to make a Set
TurretReference. So, it's simply copying that method. We can do a
Find and Replace. There's a quick replace, Control H. Look for Barrel
and replace with Turret, in the Selection not the whole thing.
Alright, let's Replace All. That looks pretty cool! Alright,
now we're going to need the Tank header file, so I'm going to pop that on the left, in this case, after having
changed my preference, and we're going to have a very similar thing. It's going to need
to be blueprint callable, so that over in the blueprint
here we can actually well call it, simply enough. And instead
of having a TurretBarrelReference, we have a TurretReference. I've already got that same
Find and Replace. So, Control H makes it very easy to just do a quick
switch. And that should be it for the Tank, apart
from, we need to remember, that it delegates this down to the Tank
AimingComponent, and that doesn't currently have a SetTurretReference.
So, let's mosey on over to the TankAimingComponent header file
and implementation file, as it happens. I'm going to
organize these into the order of the call stack, and then, we have this SetBarrelReference
that can be duplicated into a SetTurretReference, getting rid of the TODO,
because well we're TODO-ing it. [Laughs] OK, let's Control
H it, do a Replace. That's cool! So useful having that
replacement ready to go like that, and then, the same in the implementation.
Pretty simple, we copy and paste, and
then, we do a Control H. Now, remember the rule with programming. If you're
doing something twice it's fine, if it starts thinking about doing it a third time, well
then maybe we need to be thinking about something more generic here, but this is fine for just
a Barrel and a Turret. We know that this pain of copying and pasting is going to end, because
we only have those two things and everything else in the Tank is somewhat different.
But be on the look out for doing things a third time, see if you could do them
another way. Alright, we've done enough code manipulation there. We've just cut and pasted
methods using what we do in the Barrel as an inspiration for what we're doing
in the Turret. So, let's just make sure this compiles now. Then, I think we'll set the reference
and call it a day for this video, get the rest of it done in another.
So my compile failed, pretty inevitable with a load of code like that.
I've probably just done a silly boo boo, where I have not changed the class name.
So, in the TankAimingComponent line 22, what are we
doing? Ah, OK it's a lack of forward declaration, that's all it
is. It doesn't understand what TankTurret is, so we come along and say class
UTankTurret. And we should also, while we're here, say, well does the Tank
AimingComponent.cpp need a TankTurret? Well of course it does!
Thats what I forgot but that's a good reminder about how these forward declarations would work.
OK, I'm going to assume, for a moment, that's the only
error, because compilation is fast here. When I say the only error it clearly
isn't the only error, a lot of these say error error error. By the way, they may say warning sometimes,
which isn't fatal but they're all errors, but I suspect that they're all a cascade
of what was going wrong there. Alright, so there's one more thing
on line 27, and then, we have Turret = TurretToSet.
It doesn't have a local member variable called Turret and that's simply because we didn't make one.
So, we're just going to copy that line, pop it in,
do a Find and Replace with Control H, look for Barrel
in the Selection. We'll probably have to reselect and relook
for the Barrel, and then, just do a Replace. Replace
or Replace All. OK, that should do it, let's see if it does!
Back over to the compilation. You can see how kind of wrote this is and
simple. As I say, remember the rule of three, twice copying fine, three times
probably worth putting a more robust structure in, but that would be much more complicated than we
need here. OK fantastic, so that's worked! So, I can stay over here, go to the Tank blueprint,
and I'm going to set the reference for the Turret, straight after the Barrel. So,
I'm going to go over here. SetTurretReference, perfect! That method has come
up. I'm going to go get the Turret, which is of the new type, the Tank Turret type,
pop it in there, and then, I think what would be prudent to do
now is just compile the blueprint. I'm going to save everything, in case we end
up with some null pointer error. We shouldn't, there's no pointers to protect yet, because we're just
setting them in the C++ code. It's very simple, we're just setting
something to a reference. But it is possible that if we don't
tie that up... In fact, we should probably protect it, you know, this BarrelToSet
coming in here. How about if that BarrelToSet doesn't come in? So, we could just simply
go, if not (BarrelToSet)
;
Return what? Well nothing, because it's a void method. So, we should do the same thing with the
Turret, using our same trick of Control H
and replacing, and that just protects the pointer. If you think,
oh well it could crash because of a null pointer, don't just sit there on that potential problem, let's deal with it.
OK, let's compile up, that'll be a good sign that all of our C++ code
works! Then, we'll play the game which will make us sure that all of the blueprints
still compile, and that is enough for one video. So let's play the game!
And that's working, I'm pretty happy, I'm going to Save All, and make
a commit. So, I shall see you in the next video!