Hello and welcome to Upgrading
to Unreal 4.12. In fact. I need to update the top-right of these slides. moving forward.
to indicate that we will be using 4.12 from here on. So. that's what we're going to be
doing. upgrading to 4.12. We will also be removing our versions
of 4.10 and 4.11. to free up lots of space on our disk.
and upgrading both projects like this. so see you in there!
So. I don't know if this is happening for you. but when I open my projectile blueprint.
now since the end of the last video just a few minutes ago. the blueprint is not
working properly. It doesn't matter what I do with the menus. I can't get all of the blueprint information
up. It's not a general problem with the Blueprint Editor. because it is fine for the Tank.
So. I've tried a few things to sort this out. and the thing that I found worked
most effectively was just opening the project in Unreal 4.12.
So. that's what we're going to do. learn a little bit about source control and also upgrade all our projects
to Unreal 4.12. So. I'm going to start with Buidling
Escape. The first thing I want to do is. make sure that my current state
of my project on the disk is in the correct place. so I have some
what we call. uncommitted changes here. That means there are some changes to the
repository since I last worked on it. and the
head tells me what my current disk state is. So.
I'm checked out at applying materials. plus there are a few changes
since then. That's not what I want. I want. before I do my upgrade. to
start where I left off. Now. I left off on BE44. as I call it
the Section Wrap-Up video. then I just updated the readme file. so that's
where I want to be. An easy way to get there is to use something called stash. This Stash
button just saves all of these changes. so that you could get back to them
if you wanted to. and then. checks you out in the last place. which is
now the correct place. We are here. checked out
on master. If we just say Checkout Master to be sure. you can see now
that we are nearly at the top of master. What it's telling us here
is that. my current disk state is here at BE44.
but at origin. i.e. on my Remote repository which
is up on Github. I've updated a readme. So. what I
want to do to get there is. this little arrow here says I need to pull that down. That means I'm able
to change in another computer. and I haven't currently brought that down to you.
Great! Now we're all in line. the master branch. the origin/
master. and the Head of origin I don't really care about. OK. so now my
local file system actually has this readme file in it. We could
just have a look at that. for instance. We could go to the repos.
we could go to BattleTank. back to our
Unreal BuildingEscape. and there's the README.md
file. And what would also be prudent would be to quickly open the BuildingEscape project.
It should open up in the version of Unreal it's associated with. which is 4.10
here. Make sure that we are exactly in the place we want to be. before we go
ahead and do our project upgrade. because you don't want to go upgrading a project in a state that's
not where you want to start from. So there it is. it's working
and it seems to be fine. OK great! So given
that that's where we're starting from. I'm going to write my commit message before I even
make this upgrade. because it's a very good habit actually to get into to write commit messages before
you do your piece of work. Then. when you're deep into something you can think. what on Earth
am I doing? So this is very simply. "Upgrade
project to 4.12".
OK. I'm not going to commit that yet but that's what I intend to do. Now.
how do we get it to 4.12? What you're going to need to do. if you haven't already got 4.12.3
or later. you click Add Versions and it should come up in the list. but I don't want
that. so I'm just going to remove that. I've got 4.12.3 here. so if I go and
launch that. While it's launching. notice that these
other projects tell you the version number. 4.10. 4.11 OK.
So. the Editor's going to launch. then we're going to need to. in 4.12 open
BuildingEscape. Now. it's going to give you a choice. It was made with a different
version. do you want to convert it or open a copy? OK. well I want
to go to More Options and Convert in- place.
There's more options at the bottom-left than Convert in-place. Because I have this project under source
control. I'm not worried about it breaking it. The reason they're being cautious
is. if you were developing a larger game. you're a year or two into production Unreal drops a new
version. the last thing you want to do is just suddenly convert your project
without being very sure that it's going to work in the new system. It may create you
weeks or months of work do convert. so they are quite cautious about
upgrading. Normally. you would think very carefully before upgrading to a new major version.
half-way through a project. But I have it under source control here. it's a very small project.
so I'm going to convert this project in-place. as they call it.
If we look in source control. now that it's doing that. at the master branch.
we should probably see some changes on the disk already. We have. there's a bunch of
stuff here. Not much actually. hardly anything to be honest. it's just changed
the engine association there. which is the thing that determines which engine version it opens
with when it opens. and a few other things in the solution files.
So. let's check we're in 4.12. Help. About Unreal Editor. and you can see that
we are in 4.12. Great! Now let's just play the game. make sure that that behaves!
It does appear to. I'm just going to make sure I can pick things up.
drop them down. Play testing this game. of course. is very easy
because it's a very small game. There we go. and I can get out the door
and fall to my death. [Laughs] hardly worth the escape! OK. so it all looks
good! I'm going to close everything up! I already know what  my commit message is
going to be. so I stage my changes. go to Commit. there it is ready to go. and
I'm going to push that up to Origin. which means I've connected to Github and I'm just sending it
to the cloud. And that is that. that is that project
updated! Fantastic! So now. let's open the other. the next repository
along. which is going to be
BattleTank. because
Bulls and Cows was not an Unreal project. if you remember.
OK. so the last thing I did was Setting Up Projectiles. Again.
we have more state changes. since then. so I'm going to Stash those.
They go on the left-hand side. here on the Stashes. It means you're not throwing it away.
but you're immediately keeping it on the side. as it were. and you're then
able to continue your work from where you left off. So. this is the right
place to be. Now. we go to the EPIC Games Launcher. Launch for
12.3. Now. I'm expecting.
by the way. this BuildingEscape association to change here. I would think we may
need to just relaunch the EPIC Games Launcher for that to say 4.12. We'll check all that at the end.
So it's saying. what do I want to open? Well I'm saying I want to open
BattleTank. which is a 4.11 version game. I'm going to
click More Options and Convert in-place again. because we're under source
control. We're all good! Yes. that is an Oculus Rift logo we see over
there. Sorry if you're jealous but we have to have them. it's part of our work. We have to buy them. we have to
expense claim them. It's a terrible terrible thing that has to be done! We've got to
teach you guys VR somehow. In fact. 4.12 that we're using
now. not only is it very easy to preview your game in VR. which you could in
a previous version. but you can actually build levels in VR. I haven't got that working because
I haven't got the Oculus Touch hand controllers yet. but don't worry. the moment I have I'll be showing you
level building in VR. in Unreal. which is wicked!
Alright. so here comes 4.12.3
re-spooling up now with the project. And what we're going to be able to do is free up
about 20 or 30 gigabytes of disk space shortly. OK now. check
that you know which version you're in. About Unreal Editor 4.12. Cool!
Play the game. make sure that what we've got works. Fantastic!
Let's just go to the main menu. make sure we can play it from
there. Start! Ooh. what on Earth was that?!
There were tanks flying off into the distance. Did you see that?
That was quite a lot of fun! Those other tanks that we put down...
Boom. what is going on here?! So. [laughs] what's happened
is. we have upgraded to 4.12 but we have a couple of issues. so
before I go any further I'm just going to check that this blueprint actually opens.
because that was the point of doing this. It looks a bit funny. but if you click Open Full Blueprint
Editor all is good. OK. so what I'm going to do is. I'm going to commit
this upgrade now. because we have upgraded but we have an issue.
OK. so with Unreal closed I'm going to Commit and say upgrade to 4.12.
And I'm just going to say that the "tanks fly
off" and push that to master.
Actually. I won't push that to master. because master is my branch for this particular
this particular video. So actually. I'm going to hold off committing. but in your case.
you would probably want to commit at this stage. so that you can go back so that
while you work on the fix of the tanks flying off you can always roll back to this
bit. you don't have to keep re-upgrading your project. I hope that makes sense. But I'm just going to
not commit and just try and fix it in line like this. So.
why are our tanks flying off? My first suspicion about
why they're flying off. if I could open the right project. Let's do it from the EPIC Games Launcher.
Let's re-cycle this EPIC Games Launcher now. because it's making
me nervous that these are the wrong versions. So. if you just close and reopen the EPIC
Games Launcher. I would have thought that by the end of that
it will re-read those editor preferences or those
engine version files and actually update those thumbnails. Let's see if that's the case.
4.12 on both you see! So now.
by the way. you can remove these other engine version in the back here. 4.10.4
you can uninstall. and 4.11.2
you can uninstall. You need to do that with Unreal closed and I don't really need to show you that. but
the idea at the end of this will be to uninstall those versions. Alright. I'm going to guess that
these tanks fly off just because they're colliding in the start. so if I lift each tank just
a little bit further off the ground and try playing. what happens?
Ah fine. that's what it was! So there's slightly different collision tolerances or something
in 4.12 and that was causing them to fly off. So. if you just
move your tanks a bit. we've got some glitches now. You see them kind of funkily jumping
around. Well. we can sort those out in up coming videos. but
let's stick with this and commit it that we have [Laughs]
funky dancing tanks. but at least they're not flying off! So. that's good enough for this video.
thank you for watching. and I will see you in the next one. Your challenge to
leave you with is to upgrade both projects to 4.12. if you haven't done it already. Building
Escape. test and commit. BattleTank. test and commit. and then. remove your
previous versions of Unreal as I explained. Finally.
consider deleting other vault local content. Just to tell you what that is.
it's here in the EPIC Games Launcher. If you scroll down you've got Vault. and if you've got a
big demo project. you can click and Remove Local Content. All of this will free up
lots of space on your disk. So. I am going to close
Unreal. and I am going to start those
uninstalls going. You have to have Unreal
fully closed. There you go. And that's from the uninstall going
ahead. And do that same with 4.11.2. and I will see you in the next video!
=======
Hello and welcome to Upgrading
to Unreal 4.12. In fact, I need to update the top-right of these slides, moving forward,
to indicate that we will be using 4.12 from here on. So, that's what we're going to be
doing, upgrading to 4.12. We will also be removing our versions
of 4.10 and 4.11, to free up lots of space on our disk,
and upgrading both projects like this, so see you in there!
So, I don't know if this is happening for you, but when I open my projectile blueprint,
now since the end of the last video just a few minutes ago, the blueprint is not
working properly. It doesn't matter what I do with the menus, I can't get all of the blueprint information
up. It's not a general problem with the Blueprint Editor, because it is fine for the Tank.
So, I've tried a few things to sort this out, and the thing that I found worked
most effectively was just opening the project in Unreal 4.12.
So, that's what we're going to do, learn a little bit about source control and also upgrade all our projects
to Unreal 4.12. So, I'm going to start with Buidling
Escape. The first thing I want to do is, make sure that my current state
of my project on the disk is in the correct place, so I have some
what we call, uncommitted changes here. That means there are some changes to the
repository since I last worked on it, and the
head tells me what my current disk state is. So,
I'm checked out at applying materials, plus there are a few changes
since then. That's not what I want. I want, before I do my upgrade, to
start where I left off. Now, I left off on BE44, as I call it
the Section Wrap-Up video, then I just updated the readme file, so that's
where I want to be. An easy way to get there is to use something called stash. This Stash
button just saves all of these changes, so that you could get back to them
if you wanted to, and then, checks you out in the last place, which is
now the correct place. We are here, checked out
on master. If we just say Checkout Master to be sure, you can see now
that we are nearly at the top of master. What it's telling us here
is that, my current disk state is here at BE44,
but at origin, i.e. on my Remote repository which
is up on Github, I've updated a readme. So, what I
want to do to get there is, this little arrow here says I need to pull that down. That means I'm able
to change in another computer, and I haven't currently brought that down to you.
Great! Now we're all in line, the master branch, the origin/
master, and the Head of origin I don't really care about. OK, so now my
local file system actually has this readme file in it. We could
just have a look at that, for instance. We could go to the repos,
we could go to BattleTank, back to our
Unreal BuildingEscape, and there's the README.md
file. And what would also be prudent would be to quickly open the BuildingEscape project.
It should open up in the version of Unreal it's associated with, which is 4.10
here. Make sure that we are exactly in the place we want to be, before we go
ahead and do our project upgrade, because you don't want to go upgrading a project in a state that's
not where you want to start from. So there it is, it's working
and it seems to be fine. OK great! So given
that that's where we're starting from, I'm going to write my commit message before I even
make this upgrade, because it's a very good habit actually to get into to write commit messages before
you do your piece of work. Then, when you're deep into something you can think, what on Earth
am I doing? So this is very simply, "Upgrade
project to 4.12".
OK, I'm not going to commit that yet but that's what I intend to do. Now,
how do we get it to 4.12? What you're going to need to do, if you haven't already got 4.12.3
or later, you click Add Versions and it should come up in the list, but I don't want
that, so I'm just going to remove that. I've got 4.12.3 here, so if I go and
launch that. While it's launching, notice that these
other projects tell you the version number, 4.10, 4.11 OK.
So, the Editor's going to launch, then we're going to need to, in 4.12 open
BuildingEscape. Now, it's going to give you a choice. It was made with a different
version, do you want to convert it or open a copy? OK, well I want
to go to More Options and Convert in- place.
There's more options at the bottom-left than Convert in-place. Because I have this project under source
control, I'm not worried about it breaking it. The reason they're being cautious
is, if you were developing a larger game, you're a year or two into production Unreal drops a new
version, the last thing you want to do is just suddenly convert your project
without being very sure that it's going to work in the new system. It may create you
weeks or months of work do convert, so they are quite cautious about
upgrading. Normally, you would think very carefully before upgrading to a new major version,
half-way through a project. But I have it under source control here, it's a very small project,
so I'm going to convert this project in-place, as they call it.
If we look in source control, now that it's doing that, at the master branch,
we should probably see some changes on the disk already. We have, there's a bunch of
stuff here. Not much actually, hardly anything to be honest, it's just changed
the engine association there, which is the thing that determines which engine version it opens
with when it opens, and a few other things in the solution files.
So, let's check we're in 4.12. Help, About Unreal Editor, and you can see that
we are in 4.12. Great! Now let's just play the game, make sure that that behaves!
It does appear to, I'm just going to make sure I can pick things up,
drop them down. Play testing this game, of course, is very easy
because it's a very small game. There we go, and I can get out the door
and fall to my death, [Laughs] hardly worth the escape! OK, so it all looks
good! I'm going to close everything up! I already know what  my commit message is
going to be, so I stage my changes, go to Commit, there it is ready to go, and
I'm going to push that up to Origin, which means I've connected to Github and I'm just sending it
to the cloud. And that is that, that is that project
updated! Fantastic! So now, let's open the other, the next repository
along, which is going to be
BattleTank, because
Bulls and Cows was not an Unreal project, if you remember.
OK, so the last thing I did was Setting Up Projectiles. Again,
we have more state changes, since then, so I'm going to Stash those.
They go on the left-hand side, here on the Stashes. It means you're not throwing it away,
but you're immediately keeping it on the side, as it were, and you're then
able to continue your work from where you left off. So, this is the right
place to be. Now, we go to the EPIC Games Launcher. Launch for
12.3. Now, I'm expecting,
by the way, this BuildingEscape association to change here, I would think we may
need to just relaunch the EPIC Games Launcher for that to say 4.12. We'll check all that at the end.
So it's saying, what do I want to open? Well I'm saying I want to open
BattleTank, which is a 4.11 version game. I'm going to
click More Options and Convert in-place again, because we're under source
control. We're all good! Yes, that is an Oculus Rift logo we see over
there. Sorry if you're jealous but we have to have them, it's part of our work. We have to buy them, we have to
expense claim them. It's a terrible terrible thing that has to be done! We've got to
teach you guys VR somehow. In fact, 4.12 that we're using
now, not only is it very easy to preview your game in VR, which you could in
a previous version, but you can actually build levels in VR. I haven't got that working because
I haven't got the Oculus Touch hand controllers yet, but don't worry, the moment I have I'll be showing you
level building in VR, in Unreal, which is wicked!
Alright, so here comes 4.12.3
re-spooling up now with the project. And what we're going to be able to do is free up
about 20 or 30 gigabytes of disk space shortly. OK now, check
that you know which version you're in. About Unreal Editor 4.12. Cool!
Play the game, make sure that what we've got works. Fantastic!
Let's just go to the main menu, make sure we can play it from
there. Start! Ooh, what on Earth was that?!
There were tanks flying off into the distance. Did you see that?
That was quite a lot of fun! Those other tanks that we put down...
Boom, what is going on here?! So, [laughs] what's happened
is, we have upgraded to 4.12 but we have a couple of issues, so
before I go any further I'm just going to check that this blueprint actually opens,
because that was the point of doing this. It looks a bit funny, but if you click Open Full Blueprint
Editor all is good. OK, so what I'm going to do is, I'm going to commit
this upgrade now, because we have upgraded but we have an issue.
OK, so with Unreal closed I'm going to Commit and say upgrade to 4.12.
And I'm just going to say that the "tanks fly
off" and push that to master.
Actually, I won't push that to master, because master is my branch for this particular
this particular video. So actually, I'm going to hold off committing, but in your case,
you would probably want to commit at this stage, so that you can go back so that
while you work on the fix of the tanks flying off you can always roll back to this
bit, you don't have to keep re-upgrading your project. I hope that makes sense. But I'm just going to
not commit and just try and fix it in line like this. So,
why are our tanks flying off? My first suspicion about
why they're flying off, if I could open the right project. Let's do it from the EPIC Games Launcher.
Let's re-cycle this EPIC Games Launcher now, because it's making
me nervous that these are the wrong versions. So, if you just close and reopen the EPIC
Games Launcher. I would have thought that by the end of that
it will re-read those editor preferences or those
engine version files and actually update those thumbnails. Let's see if that's the case.
4.12 on both you see! So now,
by the way, you can remove these other engine version in the back here. 4.10.4
you can uninstall, and 4.11.2
you can uninstall. You need to do that with Unreal closed and I don't really need to show you that, but
the idea at the end of this will be to uninstall those versions. Alright, I'm going to guess that
these tanks fly off just because they're colliding in the start, so if I lift each tank just
a little bit further off the ground and try playing, what happens?
Ah fine, that's what it was! So there's slightly different collision tolerances or something
in 4.12 and that was causing them to fly off. So, if you just
move your tanks a bit, we've got some glitches now. You see them kind of funkily jumping
around. Well, we can sort those out in up coming videos, but
let's stick with this and commit it that we have [Laughs]
funky dancing tanks, but at least they're not flying off! So, that's good enough for this video,
thank you for watching, and I will see you in the next one. Your challenge to
leave you with is to upgrade both projects to 4.12, if you haven't done it already. Building
Escape, test and commit, BattleTank, test and commit, and then, remove your
previous versions of Unreal as I explained. Finally,
consider deleting other vault local content. Just to tell you what that is,
it's here in the EPIC Games Launcher. If you scroll down you've got Vault, and if you've got a
big demo project, you can click and Remove Local Content. All of this will free up
lots of space on your disk. So, I am going to close
Unreal, and I am going to start those
uninstalls going. You have to have Unreal
fully closed. There you go. And that's from the uninstall going
ahead. And do that same with 4.11.2, and I will see you in the next video!
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1:Unreal/Section4/BT46 Upgrading to Unreal 4.12.srt