So
we're in this somewhat rambling video! You will be learning about Working Around
Awkward Bugs. and by the end of it. your
tanks will no longer be jittering around. And I'm just going to talk you through the process
that I went through. in order to find this bug in between videos. It took me about
2 or 3 hours to get to the bottom of it. I still didn't quite get to the bottom of it. but we'll see the process
and we'll see a work around. and that'll be good enough for us to move on.
So we've upgraded to 4.12! We have a commit
in our repository. We actually probably ought to tag
here. even though the commit says that we've upgraded to
4.12. I'm actually going to use the tagging system to add a tag to this. specifically
commit. saying 4.12 like that.I think that's just going to make
sense. as well. So. you can right-click the
commit. Tag. then it'll fill in the specific commit and then
4.12. And then. that'll just leave this tag here in the hierarchy. as we
proceed up. It'll remind me where I did my upgrade. a bit like this 4.11 upgrade there.
You see. it's just pretty handy to just immediately see where you went to
which version. Anyway. so we've upgraded to 4.12. and we have an issue.
Now this is not completely uncommon. the issue actually was there in 4.11.
but it's considerably worse in 4.12. Look at this guy over  here. he's got serious
issues going on. bouncing around all over the place. Now. this purple outline.
I've turned on by the way. is just here under Show and Collision. I think that's
probably the only thing I've changed. in between videos. So Show. Collision will turn
on your Collision Outliner. but it doesn't give you a huge amount of clues as to what on earth is going
on here. So the purpose of this video. really. is to just go through a process of
trying to work out how on earth these tanks have ended up in this
state and what it could be. So let's explore
a few things! I have now worked out what the bug is. Obviously I'm not going to show you all of the
thought process. because it was quite a lot of messing around. but I'll show
you the sorts of things that I did to get here. So firstly. let's
go look at the tank blueprint and remind ourselves how it's put together.
Here we go. in the Viewport. Now. we've got all of these components to it and we've got these
tracks. and then. the tracks themselves are made up of these Static Meshes.
which we can inspect. And the Static Meshes. if we turn the Collision Box here
on in the Static Mesh Inspector. you can see there's actually two sets of Collision
on here. We have the outer simplified Collision. and then. we have
this guy which I can turn on and off under LOD0. Enable Collision.
So I initially thought. well maybe it's something to do with this? Maybe we don't want this
complex. more complex. Collision Mesh? So I turned that off. and you can also turn it off in the
Import Settings. so it doesn't create this more complex Collision
Mesh. because we actually only want this simplified one on the outside. So I did that.
but unfortunately it doesn't change anything. but it has
reduced the amount of collision data. in the game. a little bit. So once
you're in the spirit of simplifying Collision Meshes. you may as well do the same thing for the
turret. You'll notice that has also imported with a more complex Collision Mesh
there. So I think it's worth just stopping that from happening on import and then under LOD0
just turning that off as well and saving it. And again. at all these stages. when you're
trying these things. it's worth just trying and see if it fixes things. It hasn't.
as it happens. fixed it! So you could try the same for the barrel. but this would be getting tenuous.
Now I'm going to do it for the barrel. Interestingly the problem is
related to the barrel strangely. even though you wouldn't expect it to be. It's very
tempting here to go. well it must be something to do with the tracks colliding with the ground.
So you could. for example. in your tank blueprint go to your
tracks and you could remove them even. and see if that
makes a difference. I don't see there's any harm in doing that. so let's remove the tracks and try playing.
And then. unfortunately you see it's still work. doing
the same thing. So I can use a Control Z hopefully. on the blueprint. to put them back.
So very odd right! Now. what other clues have we got? Always look
in your log. Is there anything in here? Well I'm not seeing anything right now. We could try playing
again and just leaving it running for a second. because it's a really weird sporadic error
and it's still still not solved.
OK. so it's starting to be a little strange. Now.
what else could this. what else could this possibly be?
You can look at things like the positioning of these
sockets. to see that perhaps the colliders of the track are
interacting with the colliders of the tank or something. I've tried that. tried moving all the sockets around.
no good it doesn't make any difference. There is something else I really want you to note here.
which is that we hid. on the Left and Right Tracks. the Collision...
Or no we didn't on the Left and Right Tracks. but on the Turret
we hid the Collision section. Do you remember in the C++ code? Let's go and have a look at it!
Because one thing about just coming in here and
fiddling with all the physics settings on the tank is. they may not all be there.
because we chose on the TankTurret.h to
say hidecategories = ("Collision"). so I'm actually going to reverse that decision for a moment. So
on your TankTurret.h. remove the bit that says hidecategories = ("Collision").
or you can simply. if you want to keep the code. you can comment it and then just close
your braces appropriately. And I think we did the same thing on the turret.
the barrel rather. So close the brackets and just comment out the hidecategories = ("Collision")
on the turret and the barrel. So what that's going to do for us
is. it's going to give us some more levers back again. when we're inspecting the turret
here in the tank blueprint. At the moment we don't have Collision. and because we disabled Collision it also
took the Physics sub-section with it. And it may be that you can't solve the bug without
a setting that's in one of those things. So it's a very useful tip to think.
well am I seeing everything? So now if we come back to the Turret. you'll see actually we've
got Collision back on. Alright. so
what is going on? On the Tank. what
could this be to do with it? It's almost certainly to do with Collision. but what is it about
Collision? I don't think there's anything on the tank itself. i.e. the top level
Actor. The Tank. the Static Mesh
Root. is there anything on there that could be possibly causing the problem? Well we need
to be simulating physics. we need to have gravity. You should ask the question. do
we want gravity enabled on the tracks? Well probably not so I'm going to go and turn
gravity off on the tracks and try and see if that fixes things. because we only
want to simulate gravity on the root object but that still hasn't helped. strangely.
So you can carry on down the tank and say. well what's this Auto
Weld setting? It's disabled at the top-level body. but it's there on the Left
and the Right Tracks. Now it turns out that this does have something to do with the bug. If we
turn off Auto Weld. which makes as it says all of the
rigid bodies joined into a single RigidBody of the parent. Look
what happens! Whoa. flying tank! So that's bad
obviously. but it's also good because we're getting a little closer. It's something
to do with the way that the tank's colliders are interacting with
themselves. So we want Welding on for the tracks and we want Welding on for
the Turret. if there's an option there. and there actually probably isn't and
why... Ah there is! Sorry there is and
also the Barrels. So they all have Auto Welding on. there is no Welding for the Azimuth
Gimbal. You may. by the way. hypothesize that it's something to do with this Camera Gimbal. so you
could delete it and test. recompile the blueprint. and play.
Now I have an unresolved compiler error. and that's because
things are relying on that Camera Gimbal. so I better put that back. [Laughs]
That and that's crashed the Editor! So
this is why it's really important to have yourself a stage here in your SourceControl. before
you go messing around trying to work out what the solution is. So let's go back to that Tank blueprint
and see if we can continue to dive
nose and workout what's going on. I can't really give you a challenge for this video. apart from
stop the video now and work it out for yourself. but you know that's a tricky one.
So I'm going to check that we haven't lost anything. The Left the Right Track. the Turret. and the Barrel
should all have Auto Weld on them. and none of them should have Enable Gravity. You see that
checkbox means that some are set and some aren't. So Auto Weld should be on.
Enable Gravity should be off. That's definitely what we want but unfortunately. the
tracks are still popping through the ground. Hmm.
How strange! Now. at one point. in fact. it's there in the logs. Look at this!
I saw this pop up! Ah. if I can see if
I can get the logs working. I'm being wholly incompetent right now or something's going on.
Oh come on! I'll just scroll up.
There's an error here somewhere. "Handled error" local pose is PLocalPose.isValid().
So it's talking about a pose not being valid. in some physics
engine body setup. Hmm. what pose? Well this isn't a
humanoid character. right. it's a tank. but I think what's going on... I don't know. by the way. the exact
cause of this bug. but what I think's going on is. Unreal is somewhat processing this tank as if
it's a humanoid character. and that's causing it problems. See what I've
noticed is this. if we say take the Barrel away. for a moment. completely
and compile. you'll notice the problem
goes away. We're taking the barrel away and the problem goes away. How strange right?
So let's put the barrel back. Control Z. if it'll let me.
Will it? Nope. so I'm gong to have to manually add the barrel
back. Tank Barrel. there it is. pop it in. and there's no harm in
refreshing these things anyway. to see if there's perhaps something wrong with the instance
of the Tank Barrel. So let's pop it back onto the socket
like that. reset its transform. We should be good to go. compile and play. So now
I've actually rebuilt the barrel to see if that solves the problem. and actually. for the moment.
it has! Look the barrel is fixed. the problem is fixed.
after having rebuilt the barrel. Hmm. so
there was something wrong with the barrel but let's look deeper. If you go to your Event Graph
now. remember where we set the Barrel Reference? It's no longer there look. when we play the
game. the barrel won't move. because when we deleted that barrel we lost
this reference. OK no problem! So let's just pop. in fact. let's just rename this thing
Barrel. I think that's how we had it before. And let's just put the reference
back. ready. so that the Set Barrel Reference code knows about the Barrel. Play the
game. Oh darn. the problem's back!
[Laughs] How strange is that?! So
one solution to this... Well it's not possible right. it's not possible to
make the solution. well let's not Set the Barrel Reference. we've got to Set the Barrel Reference. So what
can we do? Well it turns
out that if you were to turn the Collider off on the Turret. the Collision off
on the Turret that would also solve it. Now. one way you could do that is. you could
come into the. sorry. the Turret here. and you
could set the Collision Presets. to the Turret. to NoCollision.
compile. and play. Let's see what that does! That makes it go really funny.
Let's try doing the same on the Barrel now. So it's kind of shooting
in the dark. We'll just trying and find a solution that works. for the moment. No Collision on the Barrel. does that
work? Actually that does! So if there's no collision on the Barrel
or the Turret. then we are good to go. we don't have the
problem anymore. So look. I really don't know precisely what's going on here. In this
instance you would ask yourself. do I want to try living with it for a bit.
because I would report this bug to Unreal...
It's not really a bug yet. we don't know that it's a bug. but we know that we're not sure why this is happening
right. Why is it something to do with this hierarchy and this self interaction of
colliders? Why is it causing this problem? So you'd report it to Unreal. you'd say well actually I can
still play the game. even if my projectiles can't hit the turret and the barrel. for the moment.
You would note that it got worse from
4.11 to 4.12. Now. we don't know whether that means it's going to get better
or worse in a future version of 4.12. It may be the way we're using the engine
is. well. it's staying the same. but that that Unreal's
idea of how to do these things is diverging from us or it might be that this will get better. So
what I'm going to suggest is that we loop back to this later. if it causes a game play
problem and. in the meanwhile. that we ask Unreal what is going on. Can
you tell us why this is having this problem? Alright. so there's two
ways of solving it. One is to go to the Turret and the Barrel and turn on NoCollision.
If you don't want to do that you can leave it back at BlockAllDynamic. where the problem will
occur. and you can go to the Turret
Mesh and then you can Remove the
Collision Volume like that. And if you do that on the Turret Mesh. it will
also solve the problem. OK. so why is the tank jumping?
Oh. it's still doing it actually. so that's not a reliable way of doing
it. You're going to want to remove the Collision Mesh. also on the
Barrel or Turn off Collisions. I think those two things are equivalent.
so let's just try it the other way. Remove Collision Mesh on the Barrel.
play the game and just see if it's reliable now. I'm looking for it to not jump at all.
So while I wait to see if any of those tanks jump. when they
ominously aim at me. I was saying that why does the tank jump when we have this problem? Well
frankly. I don't know but what's going on is something like. we are messing up
the collision detection on the tank itself. because
of the way that these objects that are
in a hierarchy are interacting with one another. Possibly because Unreal is
making some assumptions about the rigging. i.e. the order in which these things
are parented. which would normally be like spine and then. you know. shoulder and arms
and stuff like that. being humanoid and it's not a humanoid. So
that's my best guess! We'll ask Unreal in the meanwhile and then we can crack on.
because we actually had this problem in our prototype. and some of you may have
spotted it in the video. the tank jumping off bits of the terrain when it shouldn't have done. I think this
was the same thing. it wasn't actually hitting something on the terrain but it was just having a weird
self collision glitch. and it's like putting an impulse through the tank and knocking it in the air.
But removing the Collision Meshes or turning off Collision. which is the same thing
really for the barrel and the turret. solves the problem. Now we can focus on the tank
base and on getting that doing what we want. So in the next video. we'll pick up
projectiles where we left off. and yeah. sorry about the
diversion to 4.12 but it was required. You've got more disk space. the latest version of Unreal.
and this fundamental bug is worked around but not resolved.
=======
So
we're in this somewhat rambling video! You will be learning about Working Around
Awkward Bugs, and by the end of it, your
tanks will no longer be jittering around. And I'm just going to talk you through the process
that I went through, in order to find this bug in between videos. It took me about
2 or 3 hours to get to the bottom of it. I still didn't quite get to the bottom of it, but we'll see the process
and we'll see a work around, and that'll be good enough for us to move on.
So we've upgraded to 4.12! We have a commit
in our repository. We actually probably ought to tag
here, even though the commit says that we've upgraded to
4.12. I'm actually going to use the tagging system to add a tag to this, specifically
commit, saying 4.12 like that,I think that's just going to make
sense, as well. So, you can right-click the
commit, Tag, then it'll fill in the specific commit and then
4.12. And then, that'll just leave this tag here in the hierarchy, as we
proceed up. It'll remind me where I did my upgrade, a bit like this 4.11 upgrade there.
You see, it's just pretty handy to just immediately see where you went to
which version. Anyway, so we've upgraded to 4.12, and we have an issue.
Now this is not completely uncommon, the issue actually was there in 4.11,
but it's considerably worse in 4.12. Look at this guy over  here, he's got serious
issues going on, bouncing around all over the place. Now, this purple outline,
I've turned on by the way, is just here under Show and Collision. I think that's
probably the only thing I've changed, in between videos. So Show, Collision will turn
on your Collision Outliner, but it doesn't give you a huge amount of clues as to what on earth is going
on here. So the purpose of this video, really, is to just go through a process of
trying to work out how on earth these tanks have ended up in this
state and what it could be. So let's explore
a few things! I have now worked out what the bug is. Obviously I'm not going to show you all of the
thought process, because it was quite a lot of messing around, but I'll show
you the sorts of things that I did to get here. So firstly, let's
go look at the tank blueprint and remind ourselves how it's put together.
Here we go, in the Viewport. Now, we've got all of these components to it and we've got these
tracks, and then, the tracks themselves are made up of these Static Meshes,
which we can inspect. And the Static Meshes, if we turn the Collision Box here
on in the Static Mesh Inspector, you can see there's actually two sets of Collision
on here. We have the outer simplified Collision, and then, we have
this guy which I can turn on and off under LOD0, Enable Collision.
So I initially thought, well maybe it's something to do with this? Maybe we don't want this
complex, more complex, Collision Mesh? So I turned that off, and you can also turn it off in the
Import Settings, so it doesn't create this more complex Collision
Mesh, because we actually only want this simplified one on the outside. So I did that,
but unfortunately it doesn't change anything, but it has
reduced the amount of collision data, in the game, a little bit. So once
you're in the spirit of simplifying Collision Meshes, you may as well do the same thing for the
turret. You'll notice that has also imported with a more complex Collision Mesh
there. So I think it's worth just stopping that from happening on import and then under LOD0
just turning that off as well and saving it. And again, at all these stages, when you're
trying these things, it's worth just trying and see if it fixes things. It hasn't,
as it happens, fixed it! So you could try the same for the barrel, but this would be getting tenuous.
Now I'm going to do it for the barrel. Interestingly the problem is
related to the barrel strangely, even though you wouldn't expect it to be. It's very
tempting here to go, well it must be something to do with the tracks colliding with the ground.
So you could, for example, in your tank blueprint go to your
tracks and you could remove them even, and see if that
makes a difference. I don't see there's any harm in doing that, so let's remove the tracks and try playing.
And then, unfortunately you see it's still work, doing
the same thing. So I can use a Control Z hopefully, on the blueprint, to put them back.
So very odd right! Now, what other clues have we got? Always look
in your log. Is there anything in here? Well I'm not seeing anything right now. We could try playing
again and just leaving it running for a second, because it's a really weird sporadic error
and it's still still not solved.
OK, so it's starting to be a little strange. Now,
what else could this, what else could this possibly be?
You can look at things like the positioning of these
sockets, to see that perhaps the colliders of the track are
interacting with the colliders of the tank or something. I've tried that, tried moving all the sockets around,
no good it doesn't make any difference. There is something else I really want you to note here,
which is that we hid, on the Left and Right Tracks, the Collision...
Or no we didn't on the Left and Right Tracks, but on the Turret
we hid the Collision section. Do you remember in the C++ code? Let's go and have a look at it!
Because one thing about just coming in here and
fiddling with all the physics settings on the tank is, they may not all be there,
because we chose on the TankTurret.h to
say hidecategories = ("Collision"), so I'm actually going to reverse that decision for a moment. So
on your TankTurret.h, remove the bit that says hidecategories = ("Collision"),
or you can simply, if you want to keep the code, you can comment it and then just close
your braces appropriately. And I think we did the same thing on the turret,
the barrel rather. So close the brackets and just comment out the hidecategories = ("Collision")
on the turret and the barrel. So what that's going to do for us
is, it's going to give us some more levers back again, when we're inspecting the turret
here in the tank blueprint. At the moment we don't have Collision, and because we disabled Collision it also
took the Physics sub-section with it. And it may be that you can't solve the bug without
a setting that's in one of those things. So it's a very useful tip to think,
well am I seeing everything? So now if we come back to the Turret, you'll see actually we've
got Collision back on. Alright, so
what is going on? On the Tank, what
could this be to do with it? It's almost certainly to do with Collision, but what is it about
Collision? I don't think there's anything on the tank itself, i.e. the top level
Actor. The Tank, the Static Mesh
Root, is there anything on there that could be possibly causing the problem? Well we need
to be simulating physics, we need to have gravity. You should ask the question, do
we want gravity enabled on the tracks? Well probably not so I'm going to go and turn
gravity off on the tracks and try and see if that fixes things, because we only
want to simulate gravity on the root object but that still hasn't helped, strangely.
So you can carry on down the tank and say, well what's this Auto
Weld setting? It's disabled at the top-level body, but it's there on the Left
and the Right Tracks. Now it turns out that this does have something to do with the bug. If we
turn off Auto Weld, which makes as it says all of the
rigid bodies joined into a single RigidBody of the parent. Look
what happens! Whoa, flying tank! So that's bad
obviously, but it's also good because we're getting a little closer. It's something
to do with the way that the tank's colliders are interacting with
themselves. So we want Welding on for the tracks and we want Welding on for
the Turret, if there's an option there, and there actually probably isn't and
why... Ah there is! Sorry there is and
also the Barrels. So they all have Auto Welding on, there is no Welding for the Azimuth
Gimbal. You may, by the way, hypothesize that it's something to do with this Camera Gimbal, so you
could delete it and test, recompile the blueprint, and play.
Now I have an unresolved compiler error, and that's because
things are relying on that Camera Gimbal, so I better put that back. [Laughs]
That and that's crashed the Editor! So
this is why it's really important to have yourself a stage here in your SourceControl, before
you go messing around trying to work out what the solution is. So let's go back to that Tank blueprint
and see if we can continue to dive
nose and workout what's going on. I can't really give you a challenge for this video, apart from
stop the video now and work it out for yourself, but you know that's a tricky one.
So I'm going to check that we haven't lost anything. The Left the Right Track, the Turret, and the Barrel
should all have Auto Weld on them, and none of them should have Enable Gravity. You see that
checkbox means that some are set and some aren't. So Auto Weld should be on,
Enable Gravity should be off. That's definitely what we want but unfortunately, the
tracks are still popping through the ground. Hmm,
How strange! Now, at one point, in fact, it's there in the logs. Look at this!
I saw this pop up! Ah, if I can see if
I can get the logs working. I'm being wholly incompetent right now or something's going on.
Oh come on! I'll just scroll up.
There's an error here somewhere. "Handled error" local pose is PLocalPose.isValid().
So it's talking about a pose not being valid, in some physics
engine body setup. Hmm, what pose? Well this isn't a
humanoid character, right, it's a tank, but I think what's going on... I don't know, by the way, the exact
cause of this bug, but what I think's going on is, Unreal is somewhat processing this tank as if
it's a humanoid character, and that's causing it problems. See what I've
noticed is this, if we say take the Barrel away, for a moment, completely
and compile, you'll notice the problem
goes away. We're taking the barrel away and the problem goes away. How strange right?
So let's put the barrel back. Control Z, if it'll let me.
Will it? Nope, so I'm gong to have to manually add the barrel
back. Tank Barrel, there it is, pop it in, and there's no harm in
refreshing these things anyway, to see if there's perhaps something wrong with the instance
of the Tank Barrel. So let's pop it back onto the socket
like that, reset its transform. We should be good to go, compile and play. So now
I've actually rebuilt the barrel to see if that solves the problem, and actually, for the moment,
it has! Look the barrel is fixed, the problem is fixed,
after having rebuilt the barrel. Hmm, so
there was something wrong with the barrel but let's look deeper. If you go to your Event Graph
now, remember where we set the Barrel Reference? It's no longer there look, when we play the
game, the barrel won't move, because when we deleted that barrel we lost
this reference. OK no problem! So let's just pop, in fact, let's just rename this thing
Barrel, I think that's how we had it before. And let's just put the reference
back, ready, so that the Set Barrel Reference code knows about the Barrel. Play the
game. Oh darn, the problem's back!
[Laughs] How strange is that?! So
one solution to this... Well it's not possible right, it's not possible to
make the solution, well let's not Set the Barrel Reference, we've got to Set the Barrel Reference. So what
can we do? Well it turns
out that if you were to turn the Collider off on the Turret, the Collision off
on the Turret that would also solve it. Now, one way you could do that is, you could
come into the, sorry, the Turret here, and you
could set the Collision Presets, to the Turret, to NoCollision,
compile, and play. Let's see what that does! That makes it go really funny.
Let's try doing the same on the Barrel now. So it's kind of shooting
in the dark. We'll just trying and find a solution that works, for the moment. No Collision on the Barrel, does that
work? Actually that does! So if there's no collision on the Barrel
or the Turret, then we are good to go, we don't have the
problem anymore. So look, I really don't know precisely what's going on here. In this
instance you would ask yourself, do I want to try living with it for a bit,
because I would report this bug to Unreal...
It's not really a bug yet, we don't know that it's a bug, but we know that we're not sure why this is happening
right. Why is it something to do with this hierarchy and this self interaction of
colliders? Why is it causing this problem? So you'd report it to Unreal, you'd say well actually I can
still play the game, even if my projectiles can't hit the turret and the barrel, for the moment.
You would note that it got worse from
4.11 to 4.12. Now, we don't know whether that means it's going to get better
or worse in a future version of 4.12. It may be the way we're using the engine
is, well, it's staying the same, but that that Unreal's
idea of how to do these things is diverging from us or it might be that this will get better. So
what I'm going to suggest is that we loop back to this later, if it causes a game play
problem and, in the meanwhile, that we ask Unreal what is going on. Can
you tell us why this is having this problem? Alright, so there's two
ways of solving it. One is to go to the Turret and the Barrel and turn on NoCollision.
If you don't want to do that you can leave it back at BlockAllDynamic, where the problem will
occur, and you can go to the Turret
Mesh and then you can Remove the
Collision Volume like that. And if you do that on the Turret Mesh, it will
also solve the problem. OK, so why is the tank jumping?
Oh, it's still doing it actually, so that's not a reliable way of doing
it. You're going to want to remove the Collision Mesh, also on the
Barrel or Turn off Collisions. I think those two things are equivalent,
so let's just try it the other way. Remove Collision Mesh on the Barrel,
play the game and just see if it's reliable now. I'm looking for it to not jump at all.
So while I wait to see if any of those tanks jump, when they
ominously aim at me, I was saying that why does the tank jump when we have this problem? Well
frankly, I don't know but what's going on is something like, we are messing up
the collision detection on the tank itself, because
of the way that these objects that are
in a hierarchy are interacting with one another. Possibly because Unreal is
making some assumptions about the rigging, i.e. the order in which these things
are parented, which would normally be like spine and then, you know, shoulder and arms
and stuff like that, being humanoid and it's not a humanoid. So
that's my best guess! We'll ask Unreal in the meanwhile and then we can crack on,
because we actually had this problem in our prototype, and some of you may have
spotted it in the video, the tank jumping off bits of the terrain when it shouldn't have done. I think this
was the same thing, it wasn't actually hitting something on the terrain but it was just having a weird
self collision glitch, and it's like putting an impulse through the tank and knocking it in the air.
But removing the Collision Meshes or turning off Collision, which is the same thing
really for the barrel and the turret, solves the problem. Now we can focus on the tank
base and on getting that doing what we want. So in the next video, we'll pick up
projectiles where we left off, and yeah, sorry about the
diversion to 4.12 but it was required. You've got more disk space, the latest version of Unreal,
and this fundamental bug is worked around but not resolved.
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1:Unreal/Section4/BT47 Working Round Awkward Bugs(1).srt