So welcome to using
SpawnActor to Spawn! In this video we will be doing exactly what I
just said, and by the end of it, you'll be able to point your tank barrel, click, and then
spawn these 1 by 1 meter projectiles, at the end of the barrel. Pretty fun hey!
So let's pick up where we left off! What we were trying to do
is to get this projectile blueprint working, and it didn't work, so we had to go to
4.12 and then we got an exasperation of our jitterbug and now we're
back to where we were. So the projectile blueprint, let's take a look at it! We have a
Projectile, a DefaultSceneRoot. That shouldn't have a Scale of 100! If yours has got
a Scale of 100, set it back to 1, and then, add yourself a sphere
so that we can actually see this guy. So I have a Projectile with a
DefaultSceneRoot with a Scale of 1 and a Sphere with a Scale of 1. Let's
compile and save that projectile. I'm going to delete the one that's already in the scene,
and just try popping a new one in from the blueprint
and play and there it is! It's a 1 meter sphere, all
very nice! Good! So that's going to be big enough to see. I'm going to delete the instance in the
world, in the World Outliner you can see there are no projectiles there right now. I'm just going to
save everything, and this is a good starting point. So what we're going to want to do is be
able to instantiate that projectile from code. So how are we going to go about
that? Well let's go ahead and open up our C++ and think
about it. One of the first things we're going to need is a reference to that projectile
here in the C++ right. So the tank itself is going to need
to know something about the projectile. So I'm going to make a UPROPERTY.
I'm going to make it (EditAnywhere).
That's pretty much the last time we're going to use a (EditAnywhere), because there's another option called EditDefaultsOnly, but
I'm just not going to go into it right now, there's a bit too much else going on in this video.
So Category = Setup. It's going to be about the setup of
the tank. Then, we're going to have, we're going to start just with a
UClass* pointer, and it's going to be called
ProjectileBlueprint.
Now there is an alternative to using a UClass* pointer here,
and let me show you, it's in the resources of your notes. If you click resource number 2, which is both
in the lectures, it should also be attached to this video, then you get here. And you can see
we can do UClass* or we get the TSubclasOf.
So what I'm going to do is, I'm just going to reference you to that in the code, and you can
read that on your own time and decide which way you want to do it. I'm going to do it with a UClass*
to start with, because it's just simpler and again it avoids me introducing too
many concepts in one video. So
I'm going to say "// Alternative"
there and just paste it in the code OK.
Fantastic! So we now have the ability to set a
projectile blueprint on every single instance of
the tank, actually, and we'll talk about the difference between EditAnywhere
and EditDefaultsOnly, later. I'm having to hold myself back from talking about that
now, because, as I said, there's enough to think about in this video, without worrying
about that, but it's very much on the top of my agenda to start talking about that. It's a protection
mechanism using the other one, basically. So
now let's go have a look at this tank blueprint! And we should now on the tank
itself, under the Setup, be able to choose the Projectile Blueprint.
Now, this lets me choose absolutely
anything, any class you see, because we said, in the
code, I want a UClass* a pointer to any
UClass. And that's fine but look, the designer can set anything, and most of these things
aren't going to work. One of them, of course, is the projectile blueprint
right down here, but let's do better than that.
Let's go to the other option [laughs] And you see, if you choose the wrong thing the Editor
crashes. So let's reopen, and now that I've shown you the reason let's go to the
other option, instead of a UClass*. So let's just let the Editor
reopen, assess the damage from it crashing.
I don't think anything drastic has gone wrong, we can fix it if it has.
Let's go back into our code. Instead of this UClass*, I'm going to go
and look at that alternative. Here it is! It's TSubclassOf,
and then the class would be a projectile, and then, we'd give it a name. OK,
so let's go use that! TSubclass
Of like that.
Generic format,
just pinning down the exact class. Remember that the projectile
bluepring is based upon the Projectile.h
class or the  class, and then, it doesn't need to be a
pointer now, because that's built into the way the TSubclssOf works. I can get rid of
this alternative, because we're using it. We need to make sure that a projectile
is available. Is it? No. We don't want to #include it, for reasons talked about
before. So now let's just go straight in and do a forward declaration of a AProjectile;
and then, now we should actually be able to set this.
Let's try! So you'll see the difference,
it'll all come together in a moment, when we get to the tank blueprint
and we go to the Tank, the top tank.
And then, where it says Projectile Blueprint, look at the magic when we click this dropdown now.
Hah, you can only choose a Projectile C++ class or a Projectile
blueprint. We want the blueprint, because we want all the modifications the designer may have
made, on top of the C++ in this blueprint, like how this thing looks and any
particle effects. Cool! So let's save everything! Run
the game and nothing happens, of course, but we actually
do have now available to us, in the C++, a
concept of a projectile blueprint, which is one of the things
you're going to need to do the spawning. The other thing you're going to need to do
the spawning is the concept of a barrel. Now, we had a barrel reference that we
pass straight through, if you remember, with this setter,
all the way through to the TankAimingComponent I believe, under SetBarrel
Reference. Yeah, but we're going to want a local barrel reference, so let's just make one
of those under private. It's just going to be a simple... What's the
class name? TankBarrel*
pointer Barrel = nullptr null pointer.
If you're not sure what it's for, make a comment. "// Local
barrel reference for spawning projectile".
It's commenting as to why you're keeping a reference here.
OK, so in the .cpp, under the setter, we're not just passing the barrel reference down
to the aiming component, but we can just say that Barrel =
BarrelToSet, like so.
So we're keeping a local reference to the barrel. If you want to, you can recompile.
I would say that's over-recompiling at this stage, and then, what we need to do
is we need to protect this pointer, if there's no barrel,
then we're out of here.
Otherwise... Now did that compile succeed or fail? It failed, let's just finish
the code we're writing, otherwise "// Spawn a projectile",
I'm inside the Fire() method here, "at the
socket location on the barrel".
OK, so that's what we're going to need to do. Let's fix up the compilation errors.
So I'm missing, on line 50 here, a semicolon,
and all it is, is that I've got TankBarrel* pointer when I need UTankBarrel* pointer. And it
understands TankBarrel because we have done a forward declaration of it.
OK, over in the C++, let's go ahead and recompile,
and then, we'll be ready to
discover the method you need to do the spawning. You can write the method, and we should be spawning projectiles
on the end of our barrel. While we talk about that, let's go to the barrel, see where the socket
location is. I'm going to move the socket just outside the end of the barrel, so we can definitely see it, and
then, save that tank barrel mesh. The compile is complete!
So we are pretty much good to go. Now look, this is the method you need, GetWorld().
From your GetWorld() you Spawn an Actor. Now,
that SpawnActor() method actually has a generic format, you can see in the
chevrons here . It's telling me what type do you want me to act
on. Well we want you to act on a
U, it's not U is it, it's .
So we're going to act on an . Then, there are several
signatures. Now, what I want you to do is use signature number 2 for this challenge.
I want you to go and find the class of the thing you're going to spawn, it's the projectile blueprint we just
setup, and then, the location and rotation only, you don't need this other parameter.
And you're going to get those things by querying the
socket. So you're going to go barrel and then you're going to do get something to do with the
socket, pass in an F name, and make it work. So that's your challenge. I'm not
going to hold your hand all the way through. I want you to fill in the rest of that method, and if I'd have
spelled it right, we are nearly good to go! So here's your challenge, back to the slides!
And spawn the projectile! Fill-in the SpawnActor() parameters
and test that it works. Go ahead, pause the video, see if you can get it spawning now!
OK, let's see if we can make this spawning stuff happen! I'm going to spread this out onto a few different
lines, just for clarity. So it is the Projectile
Blueprint that we setup, is the thing that we're going to spawn.
Now, where are we going to spawn it? We're going to go to the barrel, then
we are going to say... Now hold on, does it have a
concept of Barrel? It's complaining about Barrel. Let's see, we did a forward declaration, but
no we haven't #included the barrel, so we better do that.
OK, so that should, when it catches up, stop it complaining about that. So we can do a Barrel->,
and then, we can say GetSocket
Location().
And then, we need to pass that an F name. The auto-complete is not
catching up right now, but you need to do it by name, so (FName InSocketLocation).
So you construct the FName like this, and then, unfortunately we're now into string referencing.
Because it's a string, I want to go to the Barrel, go to the Socket Manager,
and go and actually copy the socket name and then
paste it in. Great, so that should get the socket location!
The next thing is to get the SocketRotation, which is almost the same
with rotation. So if you did all that yourself, well done!
That's really great news! I'm going to save that there. Think about whether
anything else needs to be included. Are we doing anything on the projectile?
Umm, we are using a projectile class here. We're
using a ProjectileBlueprint. I think we are going to need to, yes
we are going to need to include the projectile. Let's see the compilation error, if we don't.
Save everything as we go, just so that you see that error.
If the compilation fails, what
do we get? It doesn't like Tank.h, it doesn't like the declaration of
AProjectile, and then, Tank.h 47... It's
giving us a pretty cryptic error here, actually, but I think what's going on is
that we just need to be including the projectile.
So OK, let's try recompiling.
We'll just do that Save All as well, and it wanted me to save the battleground. There you go, that's good!
No stars, that's always good in case something crashes. Let's play the game! Ah, look at
that! How fun is that?! I can now spawn projectiles
wherever the barrel is pointing! Very cool!
Fantastic! That's great progress for this video! Let's save everything carefully, commit
our work, and I'll see you soon!