So let's talk about Projectile Movement
Components. strangely enough so we can make our projectiles move. By the end of the video.
you'll be in a situation something like this. where we can fire beachball size
projectiles at our other tanks. which will be a lot of fun! OK. see
you in there! Oh. boom off he goes! So
spawning massive projectiles at the end of our barrel is fun and all of that. but it's not
exactly making a great tank game. so let's make these projectiles move!
I'm going to introduce you to something called a ProjectileMovementComponent.
Now. we're going to start by using that here on the projectile blueprint. but I'll very
quickly take it off and we'll do it in C++. because this is a C++ course mainly.
but either way is valid. So let me just look at it with you first. Projectile Movement.
that's the name of the component. It's got a load of stuff on it.
In fact. it's got a bewildering amount of settings and levers that you can pull. which is one of the reasons I'm going to be
using it from code. instead of from here. But the projectile can bounce and it
can home in on things and it can have its movement constrained
to certain planes. And. it can be made to rotate
following the velocity. so imagine it was an old school bomb. then it would always kind of have its fins
facing behind it. It's a pretty comprehensive component. this actually!
So we could add it like this but I'm going not to. We're going to
remove it from the blueprint. and we're going to add it in the same way. that if you remember
on the tank blueprint we added the Aiming Component as an inherited component.
and we did that from code like this. Let's just open VisualStudio.
We added or created a default sub-object on
the tank. if you remember. Let's see where that happens. It's in the Constructor
of the tank. where we say CreateDefaultSubobject
AimingComponent. Where is it?
There it is! That line there. 17 in my code. on the Tank.cpp.
And that will add that code. that component to the
blueprint. without you having to do anything about it. because the tank is inherited from.
The tank blueprint is inherited from the tank C++. This guy gets
inherited. this Aiming Component. and it's in there whether you like it or not. and you can't change anything about it. you
hide all that complexity. Well let's do the same thing with the projectile. let's add this
projectile in code. Now just before I put you into the challenge to do
that. just as a little bit of a hint we're going to go to the. well I'm going to go to the
ClassViewer and I'm going to... Sorry Mac users. you can't see your classes.
but you can look on my screen. ProjectileMovementComponent.
the name of the class is going to be UProjectileMovementComponent. that's
the thing we're going to be after. So let's give you this as a challenge then!
What we want to do is. we want you to add a default sub-object.
Add the projectile movement component in C++. When it's done.
set the bAutoActivate property to false. immediately after you've done it
in the constructor. and then. refer to how we did things in the tank to do this. It's basically the
same with a different class name. So go ahead. pause the video. and see if you can make sure that we
have a movement component on the projectile. as an inherited component
by default.
I know you can do it! For those of you who are beginners. then put the extra effort in.
and for those advanced people. well done. I know it's probably simple for you.
Okey dokey. so let's do this thing! Firstly. we need to start
on the projectile. we need to have some sort of variable to store this. Now. this is a private variable.
Well it's just a helper property. so in the private section I'm going to
say a
UProjectileMovementComponent*
pointer. and I'm just going to call it Projectile
Movement; and we're going to initialize it to the null pointer.
to give it a known value. So there you go. we have our
variable called ProjectileMovement. Alright. now I'm going to go to the tank
and barrow this CreateDefaultSubobject. because it's a lot to type.
and we're going to go and do this over in the projectile's constructor. So
I'm going to say that. looking at the tank. TankAimingComponent
= is how we did it over there. So we're going to say Projectile
Movement = Create
DefaultSubobject of type. Now we had the type before. it's a UProjectileMovement
Component. and now it's going to want a name. so we're going to call it
(FName and then
("Projectile Movement"));
Simples hopefully. So that should have said it. I also said that
once we'd got this guy. we wanted to
set a property on it called AutoActivate. which is bAutoActivate. Now.
it's a pointer so we're going to need to use the arrow operator. So ProjectileMovement->
bAutoActivate = false; And what this
means is. it doesn't start flying off until we actually fire it. so
what we're going to do is compile up our code and make sure we understand
what's going on. So we're adding a new default sub-object to the
projectile blueprint and that is going to be the ProjectileMovement Component. We don't want the projectile
to go flying off at the moment that it's constructed. we only want the projectile
to go flying off when we fire. So
typically that may be at the same time. you may construct it and send it flying off at the same time.
but we want to make sure. for our testing now. that we just
have the thing instantiate and not move. So let's just try. let's compile up this projectile
blueprint. It failed for me. let's try again!
Maybe because we changed the default sub-property of the projectile
blueprint. it didn't like that happening on the fly. so let's just
give the Editor a chance to recover.
And actually it is there now. look Projectile Movement (Inherited). That's cool. I'll make sure it can
compile! Let's play the game and nothing's changed.
because all we've done is added this Projectile Movement Component. We haven't actually
done anything with it yet. But that does mean that over here in the C++
code. we have this ProjectileMovement thing. and we're ready to write our
Launch method or LaunchProjectile. So let's have a method called
void AProjectile:: class we're in
LaunchProjectile.
and we're going to launch it at some speed.
Now before I do anything else. let me declare this over in the header file.
That's a public method. in this case.
without the class name. Perfect! And it's the tank that's
going to launch the projectile. so why don't we just go ahead and call it from the tank straight away.
So the tank is going to spawn a
projectile in the correct location. and then. it's going to go ahead and launch the projectile
but it needs to have a concept of the projectile in order to do that.
So we actually spawn the projectile right here.
and this spawning actor actually returns us a projectile.
So we're going to just capture that value. auto Projectile
= and then this actually gives
us a projectile to work with. It's a local variable at this stage. which is absolutely fine.
Now. we can work on that projectile. We can say Projectile->
then we can call a method on it. which is LaunchProjectile().
Finally. we need to pass in a speed. Well we have a speed in the header file. remember it was a LaunchSpeed
and it was 4.000 by default. So let's pass in this LaunchSpeed
and there we go! Now. let's try this
and then. I'm going to briefly talk to you about the difference between EditAnywhere and EditDefaults
Only but firstly let's try it. Let's make sure that this actually
works. So as a recap. while it compiles.
we're sending LaunchProjectile through to the Projectile code. which is doing nothing
yet. but we can soon sort that out. Let me move my logs in here from
the tank firing. This log here. let's just
move it so there's nothing in the Tank.cpp. into the projectile
and just say... Oops.
I didn't quite cut that right. Let's try cutting again. pasting it in here.
Tank fires or Projectile fires now.
at. And then. let's put in
the speed.
Great! So let's just recompile. and then we're going to have
a log inside the actual projectile's launch. projectile method. telling us the time
that we fired and also the speed. so we should see 4.000 coming through. Unless.
of course. in the tank blueprint. you've overridden that value here
in the Launch Speed. then you'll get a different speed coming through. Let's take a look!
Ah. here you go! The tank fires at 4.000! If you go to the tank blueprint and turn it to say
3999 and compile and play.
you can see that that value from the Inspector or the Details Panel is overriding.
Great. so that is happening! We are nearly there. but the projectiles aren't actually
moving. so we've just got a tiny bit of work to do to make those guys actually fire.
Let's see what's going on in our execution path. So from the Tank.cpp
we launch a projectile at a given (LaunchSpeed). We know that value is coming through because
of the log that we've just done. We get to the Projectile.cpp
and. of course. we are not yet launching. So
the way that we do this is. we go and grab the ProjectileMovement component that we've got there.
It's a pointer remember? The method we're looking for is SetVelocityIn
LocalSpace. and then we can just get the ForwardVector
of the projectile itself.
And remember that when we spawn the projectile. in the first place. inside
the tank C++. we did it with a rotation of the same as the
barrel. So the projectile should be facing forward. in the same direction as the
barrel. So this ForwardVector will be hopefully the barrel's ForwardVector. Once we've got
that vector. it's just a unit vector. so we need to multiply it by this Speed. and that will
give us that initial launch velocity. The second thing we're
going to need to do is actually activate the projectile movement component.
Oh. I'm going to copy it. No good trying to type this morning. by the looks of it.
And then. we're going to say Activate(). which is a method.
so that the deactivation that we did on the start here is then counted
by the fact that we've called an Activate(). Now this is a method notice. I'm setting
AutoActivate is false is a property. It's just so this is saying that when we
construct it don't AutoActivate. but as soon as we launch set the
velocity. then go ahead and activate so the thing actually fires. Let's have a go.
see if it works! And if it does. I think that'll be enough for this video! Launching
beachball size projectiles is a pretty good outcome for one video.
So let's just see that it works! It compiled. let's try.
Oh look at that cool! Beachballs are away boom!
Awesome! Fantastic! So I am now going to leave. on the screen. the main code.
which is that bit there. For the rest of the code. remember you can always go to GitHub.
I'll just quickly show you this. If you go to my GitHub profile.
or if you wish you can go directly to the Unreal Course Repository
there. You go to BattleTank. you click on Commits. and you can see every single
video in the course. This one's not quite there yet but imagine it was. You click on
that and then. you'd be able to see all the code that's been added in this video. So a useful tip
for you. I'll put this in the resources of the lecture for you. and I
will see you soon. I'll put this in the resources of the lecture.
So see you soon!
=======
So let's talk about Projectile Movement
Components, strangely enough so we can make our projectiles move. By the end of the video,
you'll be in a situation something like this, where we can fire beachball size
projectiles at our other tanks, which will be a lot of fun! OK, see
you in there! Oh, boom off he goes! So
spawning massive projectiles at the end of our barrel is fun and all of that, but it's not
exactly making a great tank game, so let's make these projectiles move!
I'm going to introduce you to something called a ProjectileMovementComponent.
Now, we're going to start by using that here on the projectile blueprint, but I'll very
quickly take it off and we'll do it in C++, because this is a C++ course mainly,
but either way is valid. So let me just look at it with you first. Projectile Movement,
that's the name of the component. It's got a load of stuff on it.
In fact, it's got a bewildering amount of settings and levers that you can pull, which is one of the reasons I'm going to be
using it from code, instead of from here. But the projectile can bounce and it
can home in on things and it can have its movement constrained
to certain planes. And, it can be made to rotate
following the velocity, so imagine it was an old school bomb, then it would always kind of have its fins
facing behind it. It's a pretty comprehensive component, this actually!
So we could add it like this but I'm going not to. We're going to
remove it from the blueprint, and we're going to add it in the same way, that if you remember
on the tank blueprint we added the Aiming Component as an inherited component,
and we did that from code like this. Let's just open VisualStudio.
We added or created a default sub-object on
the tank, if you remember. Let's see where that happens. It's in the Constructor
of the tank, where we say CreateDefaultSubobject
AimingComponent. Where is it?
There it is! That line there, 17 in my code, on the Tank.cpp.
And that will add that code, that component to the
blueprint, without you having to do anything about it, because the tank is inherited from.
The tank blueprint is inherited from the tank C++. This guy gets
inherited, this Aiming Component, and it's in there whether you like it or not, and you can't change anything about it, you
hide all that complexity. Well let's do the same thing with the projectile, let's add this
projectile in code. Now just before I put you into the challenge to do
that, just as a little bit of a hint we're going to go to the, well I'm going to go to the
ClassViewer and I'm going to... Sorry Mac users, you can't see your classes,
but you can look on my screen. ProjectileMovementComponent,
the name of the class is going to be UProjectileMovementComponent, that's
the thing we're going to be after. So let's give you this as a challenge then!
What we want to do is, we want you to add a default sub-object.
Add the projectile movement component in C++. When it's done,
set the bAutoActivate property to false, immediately after you've done it
in the constructor, and then, refer to how we did things in the tank to do this. It's basically the
same with a different class name. So go ahead, pause the video, and see if you can make sure that we
have a movement component on the projectile, as an inherited component
by default.
I know you can do it! For those of you who are beginners, then put the extra effort in,
and for those advanced people, well done, I know it's probably simple for you.
Okey dokey, so let's do this thing! Firstly, we need to start
on the projectile, we need to have some sort of variable to store this. Now, this is a private variable.
Well it's just a helper property, so in the private section I'm going to
say a
UProjectileMovementComponent*
pointer, and I'm just going to call it Projectile
Movement; and we're going to initialize it to the null pointer,
to give it a known value. So there you go, we have our
variable called ProjectileMovement. Alright, now I'm going to go to the tank
and barrow this CreateDefaultSubobject, because it's a lot to type,
and we're going to go and do this over in the projectile's constructor. So
I'm going to say that, looking at the tank, TankAimingComponent
= is how we did it over there. So we're going to say Projectile
Movement = Create
DefaultSubobject of type. Now we had the type before, it's a UProjectileMovement
Component, and now it's going to want a name, so we're going to call it
(FName and then
("Projectile Movement"));
Simples hopefully. So that should have said it. I also said that
once we'd got this guy, we wanted to
set a property on it called AutoActivate, which is bAutoActivate. Now,
it's a pointer so we're going to need to use the arrow operator. So ProjectileMovement->
bAutoActivate = false; And what this
means is, it doesn't start flying off until we actually fire it, so
what we're going to do is compile up our code and make sure we understand
what's going on. So we're adding a new default sub-object to the
projectile blueprint and that is going to be the ProjectileMovement Component. We don't want the projectile
to go flying off at the moment that it's constructed, we only want the projectile
to go flying off when we fire. So
typically that may be at the same time, you may construct it and send it flying off at the same time,
but we want to make sure, for our testing now, that we just
have the thing instantiate and not move. So let's just try, let's compile up this projectile
blueprint. It failed for me, let's try again!
Maybe because we changed the default sub-property of the projectile
blueprint, it didn't like that happening on the fly, so let's just
give the Editor a chance to recover.
And actually it is there now, look Projectile Movement (Inherited). That's cool, I'll make sure it can
compile! Let's play the game and nothing's changed,
because all we've done is added this Projectile Movement Component. We haven't actually
done anything with it yet. But that does mean that over here in the C++
code, we have this ProjectileMovement thing, and we're ready to write our
Launch method or LaunchProjectile. So let's have a method called
void AProjectile:: class we're in
LaunchProjectile,
and we're going to launch it at some speed.
Now before I do anything else, let me declare this over in the header file.
That's a public method, in this case,
without the class name. Perfect! And it's the tank that's
going to launch the projectile, so why don't we just go ahead and call it from the tank straight away.
So the tank is going to spawn a
projectile in the correct location, and then, it's going to go ahead and launch the projectile
but it needs to have a concept of the projectile in order to do that.
So we actually spawn the projectile right here,
and this spawning actor actually returns us a projectile.
So we're going to just capture that value, auto Projectile
= and then this actually gives
us a projectile to work with. It's a local variable at this stage, which is absolutely fine.
Now, we can work on that projectile. We can say Projectile->
then we can call a method on it, which is LaunchProjectile().
Finally, we need to pass in a speed. Well we have a speed in the header file, remember it was a LaunchSpeed
and it was 4,000 by default. So let's pass in this LaunchSpeed
and there we go! Now, let's try this
and then, I'm going to briefly talk to you about the difference between EditAnywhere and EditDefaults
Only but firstly let's try it. Let's make sure that this actually
works. So as a recap, while it compiles,
we're sending LaunchProjectile through to the Projectile code, which is doing nothing
yet, but we can soon sort that out. Let me move my logs in here from
the tank firing. This log here, let's just
move it so there's nothing in the Tank.cpp, into the projectile
and just say... Oops,
I didn't quite cut that right. Let's try cutting again, pasting it in here.
Tank fires or Projectile fires now,
at. And then, let's put in
the speed.
Great! So let's just recompile, and then we're going to have
a log inside the actual projectile's launch, projectile method, telling us the time
that we fired and also the speed, so we should see 4,000 coming through. Unless,
of course, in the tank blueprint, you've overridden that value here
in the Launch Speed, then you'll get a different speed coming through. Let's take a look!
Ah, here you go! The tank fires at 4,000! If you go to the tank blueprint and turn it to say
3999 and compile and play,
you can see that that value from the Inspector or the Details Panel is overriding.
Great, so that is happening! We are nearly there, but the projectiles aren't actually
moving, so we've just got a tiny bit of work to do to make those guys actually fire.
Let's see what's going on in our execution path. So from the Tank.cpp
we launch a projectile at a given (LaunchSpeed). We know that value is coming through because
of the log that we've just done. We get to the Projectile.cpp
and, of course, we are not yet launching. So
the way that we do this is, we go and grab the ProjectileMovement component that we've got there.
It's a pointer remember? The method we're looking for is SetVelocityIn
LocalSpace, and then we can just get the ForwardVector
of the projectile itself.
And remember that when we spawn the projectile, in the first place, inside
the tank C++, we did it with a rotation of the same as the
barrel. So the projectile should be facing forward, in the same direction as the
barrel. So this ForwardVector will be hopefully the barrel's ForwardVector. Once we've got
that vector, it's just a unit vector, so we need to multiply it by this Speed, and that will
give us that initial launch velocity. The second thing we're
going to need to do is actually activate the projectile movement component.
Oh, I'm going to copy it. No good trying to type this morning, by the looks of it.
And then, we're going to say Activate(), which is a method,
so that the deactivation that we did on the start here is then counted
by the fact that we've called an Activate(). Now this is a method notice. I'm setting
AutoActivate is false is a property. It's just so this is saying that when we
construct it don't AutoActivate, but as soon as we launch set the
velocity, then go ahead and activate so the thing actually fires. Let's have a go,
see if it works! And if it does, I think that'll be enough for this video! Launching
beachball size projectiles is a pretty good outcome for one video.
So let's just see that it works! It compiled, let's try.
Oh look at that cool! Beachballs are away boom!
Awesome! Fantastic! So I am now going to leave, on the screen, the main code,
which is that bit there. For the rest of the code, remember you can always go to GitHub.
I'll just quickly show you this. If you go to my GitHub profile,
or if you wish you can go directly to the Unreal Course Repository
there. You go to BattleTank, you click on Commits, and you can see every single
video in the course. This one's not quite there yet but imagine it was. You click on
that and then, you'd be able to see all the code that's been added in this video. So a useful tip
for you. I'll put this in the resources of the lecture for you, and I
will see you soon. I'll put this in the resources of the lecture.
So see you soon!
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1:Unreal/Section4/BT49 Projectile Movement Components.srt