Hey
and welcome to Making AI Tanks Fire! in this video, what we're going to
do is, we're going to limit the firing rate down to 1 every 3 to 5 seconds,
whatever we set, and also make sure that these AI Tanks can
fire at us, so it'll become a bit more of a game in the process. So see you in there!
So we're back to that age old question, what's the least fun thing about this
game? Well lots of things need improving, but I would say the least fun thing is there is zero
challenge right now. We can just pick these other tanks off like sitting ducks,
quite literally, because they can't fire back. So let's focus our attention on
having them fire back, for now. Remember that we're running in an iterative cycle.
We've just been working on the controls of our tank, now we're just going to move on to thinking
about improving Player 2, and we'll be back to work on
controls and aiming and lots of other things later. So how are we going to
do that? Well I want the AI tanks to fire, so let's go
and have a look at our code and think about where that would happen. It would happen in
the TankAIController. Now, in this TankAI
Controller, we actually have a couple of very thin methods here, one gets the
ControlledTank and one gets the PlayerTank. Now if we go and look
at the header code for this, you'll notice that these getters are actually
private getters, and that's probably a bit of a warning sign that maybe
we've done a bit too much refactoring here. So thank you to those of you who pointed out
that possibly we've gone overboard with the creation of methods. If these getters aren't even
needed from the outside, i.e. they're not in the public interface,
why do we necessarily need separate methods for them. I would argue we don't.
So as part of this making this tank fire, let's go ahead
and make it work, as we are to start with, and then, I will ask you to do a defactor
[Laughs] the opposite of a refactor. So firstly, let's just make the fire work.
So let's use the existing clunky GetControlledTank()
method, and then, we can just say Fire(). Now remember that
it just fires where the barrel is currently pointing, so this is going to fire
every single frame. It's not fire if ready, but it's fire every
frame. So get rid of the comment, and let's just try building that and see
what comic effect we get from that! And then, we will get you to do some
de-factoring, because knowing how to refactor code and to factor out
methods is hugely important to extract functions. But doing the opposite sometimes is an
equally important skill. Look at this, hose pipes of
projectiles there! Look it's crazy! There's actually almost a little bit of a challenge
now, because we have to aim and hit these tanks before they do that to us.
[laughs] What a load of fun! So we have achieved our
aim of having the tanks fire every single frame. What I want
you to do now is get rid of these two methods, and to put it all inside the Tick() method
as neatly as you can. So here's your challenge!
Inline the two private getters. Remove the two methods, it's called inlining or
de-factoring. Put the code in the Tick() method. You can remove
the code and BeginPlay() as well. By the way, we don't need that any more, those checks. So
go ahead, pause the video, and see if you can inline the code now.
If you're not sure what I'm talking about, I'm literally just saying
remove those two methods and do what they do as simply and cleanly as possible,
inside the Tick() method.
OK welcome back! So the way that I'm going to attack this is, I'm
going to firstly delete this code at the top. We don't need to check about controllers possessing tanks,
it seems to be working most of the time and we're not having any issues with that.
So if (GetPlayerTank())! Well instead of GetPlayerTank
this is getting the player tank, this thing here. So what I'm going to
say is, auto...
Now we'll talk about why we do this every frame, in a second. ...auto PlayerTank =
that stuff. Now be careful, because previously it was a
PlayerPawn and then it cast to a tank, so let's to the cast all in one go.
PlayerTank is the result of going and finding
the FirstPlayerController's Pawn and casting it
to a ATank. Cool! So that does everything this
does, apart from the protecting of the PlayerTank pointer, but
we can do that right here, we already kind of were, if (PlayerTank).
Now, if you look at it, we've got the Cast, we've got the Get, and we've got the
pointer protection, we don't need GetPlayerTank anymore at all. And in
the header file, we can get rid of a declaration.
Fantastic! OK, so what next? GetControlledTank, well that's even thinner!
So let's take a look at that, and we can say auto Controlled
Tank or it could be AITank I guess, but
we're inside the TankAIController, so I think ControlledTank is more meaningful
and just that. And that's all that method did, so we can get
rid of it. Now make sure you've got rid of your code in BeginPlay(), because that was calling these methods, too!
Just remove GetControlledTank. We've lost quite a few lines of code here,
for the same behavior, and losing lines of code and ending up with the same behavior
is generally a good thing. So we're nearly there! These two lines
need to change, so instead of GetControlledTank, etc. I'm just going to write the new
line above it. ControlledTank->
AimAt() and then (PlayerTank).
Now we're nearly there, and then you look through the PlayerTank pointer and say GetActorLocation.
And I think that looks absolutely fine!
The ControlledTank should aim at the PlayerTank's location, almost reads in English!
Perfect! Same thing here, instead of GetControlledTank it is just Controlled
Tank->Fire(); and then, there is going to be a
TODO here. "// TODO don't fire every
frame". So we need to limit, or more specifically, we need to "limit
firing rate". We need to do that later, but for now, let's stay
focused on one job at a time, it was to de-factor this code like this.
So let's go ahead and compile and
see how this behaves. Oh, we love waiting
for compilation to happen! I'll resist the urge to fill this with filler! Ooh,
I just did! OK, so here we go! Let's see what happens, it still works!
I can still fire! Oh, and that's pretty good! OK
fantastic! So we have what we were looking for, which is
a simpler way of doing this, and also the AI tanks
are firing now, which is great! So we need to be limiting the firing
rate, as a next port of call, so let's think about that really quickly.
It's in the Tank that we would be limiting the fire rate, and what we would
want in the tank is something like a float called Reload
TimeInSeconds,
and we could make that 3 seconds.
Alright, so I'm going to make a float on the tank called ReloadTimeInSeconds.
Then, remember that the AIController, both the tank and us just call this
Fire() method. Well let's go look at the tank's Fire() method. This tank's Fire() method
currently just fires regardless, but how about if we didn't just
fire regardless, how about if we were to set a
timer and then only fire if that timer had expired
basically? So the way that I'd be doing that is a boolean
for isReloaded, and it's going to
be = to. Now, I'm going to introduce you to a new, more precise, world
timer. Instead of GetWorldGetTimeSeconds, we can also use
FPlatformTime::
Seconds. Now that actually returns a double.
Now let's imagine we have something called LastFireTime) a member variable, which we
don't. Well if this subtraction is greater than the Reload
Time in seconds, then
that means that we are reloaded, so let's make ourselves a last
fire time, double Last
FireTime starts of equalling 0. So
assuming that we fired, effectively fired, at time = 0, so this
does mean that our first shot won't be able to happen for 3 seconds but that's fine. So we
have this boolean isReloaded. OK, now I'm going to change the
logic around. Instead of saying if not (!Barrel)  I'm going to say,
if... Pull all of this into the if,
sort out my curly braces,
then say if (Barrel &&
isReloaded). So if we have a Barrel
and we're Reloaded, then spawn a projectile, fire it off,
and then, reset this LastFireTime
to the FPlatformTime::Seconds(), remembering that
these things are doubles. OK, when I declare
and actually initialize the value of LastFireTime to 0 here, it
will be a double automatically in C#. By the way, if you don't save
the f for float, then you get a double, but in this case, this thing
will be a float because we've explicitly said it's going to be a float here and this 0 here
will be interpreted as a double, not only because we've said double but because actually that's the default behavior
in C++. Let's see if this reload timer works! Take a
look at this code, make sure you're happy with that reload timer,
and then, let's compile. And the idea here is, we'll have a limited
firing speed, which will then be able to set... Later on, I'll show you how to set it
in the Inspector, but we're not going to do that now, we're not just going to slap an Edit Anywhere
on it, because I'm fed up with using that, I want to start showing you simple
alternatives. So this is pretty cool! Look I can fire! Boom!
I can't fire, can't fire, can't fire, and then, suddenly I can fire! And it's the same
with the AI tanks, so it's becoming somewhat more of an actual game now.
Things are happening! [laughs] OK great! So well done getting this far
in this video, and I will see you in the next one!