So
welcome to Edit Anywhere vs. EditDefaultsOnly! A quick apology,
I noticed that my indicator 4.12 is a little out of date. The
last three videos have said 4.11, when they're really 4.12, but I'm sure that's fairly obvious
from the names of the videos. So what we're going to do in this video is just mix things
up a little bit, and start using EditDefaultOnly, instead of Edit
Anywhere, and you'll see what the consequences of that are inside the
Editor. So see you in there!
So just before we get into the meat of this new lecture, this GetPlatform
TimeSeconds is a proper mystery to me. It's not properly documented, comes out at
16.8 Million seconds, which is
around 6 months. If I look at my system timer, on the surface,
that would mean it's the time in seconds, since the beginning of this year, but if
you do that calculations it's not quite, it's off by many days. Also if you change
your system Date and Time, you don't get any different result out of this guy, even if you
restart Unreal. Also if you pull the network cable out of your computer, it still doesn't
get anything, so it doesn't appear to be reading it off the Internet either! So I don't
know what this is, but it's a useful timer, it's a double, it's once a second,
and if you don't like it, if you're nervous about it like I am now, then you're welcome to use GetWorld
then TimeSeconds, like we have done in previous log
entires, which we can find here UE_LOG
GetWorld()->GetTimeSeconds(); that's just a float rather
than a double. So I don't know, mystery! If you know the answer, tell us at community.gamedev.tv
and yeah let's crack on with this lecture! Anyway
I'm going to recompile my code here, because I'm still running a code state from a previous
run. Now, by the way, this is a useful lesson. I have
not got the code in here. If we do a search for UE_LOG right now,
you'll find that the code state, as it sits on my disk, does not have that log that you were seeing
in the um, in the logs here, the one that's talking about
the number of times, you know that previous function I was using, the
FPlatformTime thing. But what had happened is, if you
open Unreal, if you roll your code state back and then open
Unreal without recompiling, it will run your previous code state because it remembers
it in the intermediate folders. OK, so now, when I just,  because
I've recompiled, it's gone back to the previous behavior where I left you on the last video.
So that is a pretty useful lesson, by the way, if you find that behavior is kind of odd,
it may be because you went back in your source control but didn't recompile
when you got into Unreal. Alright, that's just one of the issues with cacheing in Unreal.
Anyway, the point of this video is that we have set ourselves a parameter about how fast we can
reload. And if we go into the tank header
file, we may well want to say, well let's make this a UPROPERTY,
and let's imagine it's a firing UPROPERTY. So I'll pop it like this,
(EditAnywhere, Category = Firing), I think I'll put it up with the other firing property.
And I think while I'm here, I'll put the Setup property above. I'm just having a bit
of a reorganization of the Tank.h and the property is just for
fun. OK, so there's that UPROPERTY,
if I put EditAnywhere on it, let's compile and see what happens.
You know that what EditAnywhere is going to do is, it's
going on the tank blueprint to expose in the
Firing section here, under Launch Speed, a Reload
Time in Seconds and that's fine, but EditAnywhere means this can be edited
on any tank. Let me show you, if I go to this tank instance right
here, then in the world you select the tank, and if I now go
down to the Firing property, I could make this guy allowed to reload in just
1/2 a second, whereas this guy over here maybe needs to take 5 seconds
and this guy over here could maybe take 0.1 of a second. Let's see what
happens now, if I play the game. You see all the tanks are
firing at completely different rates. It's hard to see the guy in the far distance, unless I use
F11 to maximize. But you see all three tanks have a different firing rate and I have my
firing rate. Now that's unfair, basically,
and you may want to make the command decision that all tanks have to have the same
reload time in seconds, so let me show you what you do. Instead of Edit
Anywhere for the reload time, you use a different annotation, which
is EditDefaultsOnly, and if you look that up,
it'll tell you that, that means you can only edit the archetype. Now let's see what that means!
That means that we can only edit it on the tank or tanks
as a whole, therefore all tanks must have the same value. So let's just
see that in action! OK,
so now if I look around and I take a particular instance
of a tank, I'm just going to play to get myself back to the beginning. Now it's actually disappeared
out of the instance menu, i.e. when I'm in the Content
Browser or in the 3D View and I select a tank, I cannot see
in the Firing section anymore the Reload Time in Seconds.
Now you may think that's a mistake. Where has it gone? You know I've said EditDefault, so only does it
not work the same way... Well it does work the same way, apart from you can
only edit it on the blueprint. If we go to the blueprint, look it's there Reload Time in
Seconds, that's what EditDefaultOnly means. Now, if we play the game,
you'll find that all tanks must have that 3 second... Well the reason
there's a discrepancy right now is because I haven't compiled the, [Laughs]
is because Unreal is not quite stable enough to handle that
change. But when I'm confident that when I reopen Unreal, recompile the tank
blueprint, that that change will have properly propagated. So let's go there,
let's reopen the tank blueprint. It had no real excuse
to crash there but bless it. Let's 3 seconds,
let's compile that. It's compiled successfully. Compiled successfully
whatever. If I now play the game, you'll see that we all now have a 3 second
firing delay again, and there is no way to select an individual instance
and override it. You get the idea. That is what EditDefaultOnly does,
it lets you only change it on the blueprint, the archetype
the prefab whatever you want to call it, basically on all tanks.
So what I want you to do now is to question every use of EditAnywere. What I want you to
go through your project, do an actual search, get used to using your IDE search, look for
EditAnywhere. For each instance, decide where you want to be editing
anywhere or edit defaults only, make the changes, and then, test your game still works.
Okey dokey, so welcome back! Relatively simple challenge this one, Edit
Anywhere in the current project in VisualStudio,
and let's just go through. OK, so the projectile
blueprint. Do we want to be able to give different tanks different
projectile blueprints? i.e. if I click on this tank here and then look at it's properties,
do we want that to have a different projectile at runtime? I don't, I'm going to say Edit
DefaultsOnly, and I'm going to copy this into the copy
buffer and then ask the same question for the LaunchSpeed. No all tanks I want to have the same
LaunchSpeed. So let's move on! What's this guy here? This
is the setup of the barrel. Do we want different instances of
barrels to have different, no we don't, we want all the barrels to be the same for now. Now, of course,
in a bigger game you might have replaceable barrels, etc. but they're still
different archetypes, they're still different types of barrel. Alright,
so all of these are going to EditDefaultsOnly. How about these crosshair locations?
Well we only have one instance of a TankPlayerController,
in this case, but still I'm going to go EditDefaultsOnly. In fact, let's make it
our default go to annotation property, unless
there's a reason to do something else. Same with the tank turret, EditDefaults
Only. So I think that's actually it. Yep! It's saying the entire project
does not contain EditAnywhere anymore. So
let's now recompile, make sure that the game works and that we can still get
to the levers in American terms or the le-e-vers in English
accent, that we need to get to, to be able to change what we need to change.
OK, so the tank blueprint is unhappy.
I've recompiled it, I'm playing, that's fine!
So it still seems to play OK. A very easy
game to test, this one, at this stage. If we go to the tank blueprint, you'll find that we still have
the LaunchSpeed, the Reload Time, the Projectile Blueprint, all the things we
wanted, but when we click on an instance, none of those things are
there, which I think is better. So thank you to Daniel for pointing
that out. It's been several videos before I got it into the course, but I wanted to
have something to show you it on, i.e. that firing rate. So there it is!
EditAnywhere vs. EditDefaultsOnly. Enjoy and in future, let's use
EditDefaultsOnly as our default, and think carefully before
we say EditAnywhere!