Hello hello hello
and welcome to Adding a Quit Button! In this video
we are going to, guess what we're going to do it's pretty obvious, we're going to add a Quit
Button! Here it is Quit, and it will just stop the game! We're also going to fix a
bug, which we've previously had, that if you click Start the tanks are all flying off
and that's no longer happening. We're also going to simplify our collision system a lot. So see you in there!
So guys, we have tanks firing, we have problems with our
game, but we are making progress! We can shoot at them, they can shoot at us. We can't move
yet but let's stick to our plan, which we decided in the beginning
or I decided in the beginning, that we were going to work on the World, then the Tank, then the Controls,
then Player 2, then UI, before looping
back to the World and the Tank and the Controls. So let's do that! Let's go to UI
next, just for the sake of sticking to our original plan. The
idea is, we don't dwell for too long on any one area of the game,
before moving on and making sure that we have dealt with any major omissions.
So there are a couple of major omissions, that's omissions
o double m [Laughs] for the none English speakers. One is if we go to the main
menu, firstly, we can't quit the game. There's no quit button, which is going to be a pain.
And secondly, look what happens when we start the game! Oh dear, where have my tanks
gone?! Let's do that again just because it's fun! If we play the game,
Alt P, Start, boom and we have
a Serious Flying Tank Syndrome. But interestingly, we don't have
Serious Flying Tank Syndrome, SFTS
I think... Yes, SFTS! We don't have that syndrome here, when we play
in here. Now why not? Well you're welcome to pause and try and fix it yourself,
or I can tell you what's going on, what I believe's going on. I believe what's going on
is another one of these self collision issues. Basically, we're worrying...
We're running up against issues with Unreal because it's designed for making humanoid
characters and skeletal meshes, and we have got ourselves a clunky
tank here, with lots of different collision meshes on it all interfering with one another.
So what can we do to prevent this mess-up? Well, if we look at
our tank, at the moment, it's got a lot of different parts to it, as I say, and they've
all got their own separate colliders. There's no easy way, that I can see here
in this view, to see them. But as I say, you can go to the Game View and you
can go to the Battle Ground, play the game, F8 to de-possess,
Show, Collision, and you'll see there's a lot of collision meshes,
all on this thing, and some of them are inside each other and interacting with each other.
And now, I believe we've already turned off the collision on the
turret here, but we still have collision on the barrel. No we don't,
we've got rid of it there as well. What else have we got? Tracks!
Ah, now the tracks have still got colliders on them! Let me, for a minute, try removing
collision from the tracks. Save the game. So go to your track mesh,
remove collision from it, make sure there are not collision meshes on it, and now try playing
the game from the start menu. Let's see if that works!
Because I believe what's happening is, the tracks are effectively exploding off the tanks.
Ah, now they're OK, but we sit funny on the ground because our tracks
don't have a collider on them, so then if you look carefully at my tank, it's wheels
are going through the ground. So look, one simple
solution to this, right now, is to just
simplify completely this tank's collision properties.
So what we can do is, we can actually take the colliders off the tracks, as well.
Collision, remove...
Well I have, sorry excuse me! brain fart there. I removed them a moment ago!
But the other thing that has collision on it is the tank body,
and we could actually remove all the collision from that, both from the LOD0 but also
from Collision and then Remove Collision.
Now, of course, if we play the game from the main level or even from the
start menu, it should fall through the floor or not move at
all. Now listen, the reason it's hovering in the air is, because the tank
body is the thing with the physics on it. Remember if we look at the tank blueprint, the tank here
is the thing with the physics. It still has Simulate Physics, it's actually grayed
out, and that's because there is no collider, so it doesn't have a
body to simulate physics on. So what we can do is, we could go to the tank
body for now, and let me show you a new thing about colliders here.
We go to Collision and we Add a Box Simplified Collision.
So you're starting with nothing, if you've got anything just remove. Start with nothing and then Add
a Box Simplified Collision to the tank. Now let's have a look at that! In fact, this
default one here is nearly good enough, to be honest. It's nearly
there. I'm going to change to a, say a Left view or a
Front view. There you go! It's actually, as I explained before, the tank is aligned slightly
off, so the views are slightly messed up, but you know, we can get to what we need.
We can see this box is a little bit high. Where do you adjust this? Well you
can have a look in the Details tab, and then, you can come in here and
look for... Where is it? Primitives, there you go, under Static
Mesh Settings! You have Primitive, Boxes, and there's one box, element number
0, array starting at 0. And then, you can change the offset, there you go!
So now, I'm just moving that box, so that it just
leaves maybe a little bit of the track sticking out at the bottom, as if the track is dug into the ground.
Let's try that, that's now, because I've turned collision off on all the other
elements of the tank. The only collision we have on the tank is on the main body
and that's actually sitting pretty nicely. Let's have a look closer!
Yeah that's pretty cool! And then, I can get hit in the tank body.
Now let me just check that the other tanks also sit on the ground nicely.
You see they're not flying off, their tracks aren't exploding out of them anymore, and we
have an incredibly simple setup now. So let's just go and take a little closer look!
I hit F8 there to come out. I don't mind those tracks slightly embedded,
and now we have a much more reasonable, i.e. a much more easy to
reason about collision system on the tanks, In fact, if I
play the game, hit F8, Show, Collision
again, and then, just zoom in, it's a very very subtle purple box but it's just a
box around the tank. Much quicker to compute, much simpler to reason about,
no internal collisions. So let's do that for now, that seems like a good idea!
OK, the other glaring omission is that from that start
menu, that main menu, there is no quit button. I would just want a quit button
somewhere near the start button, and of course, that's going to be your challenge, because it's
about time that you got back and revised UI. Now, this is another benefit of this
spiral syllabus, is that we keep coming back to things before they
go completely stale in your mind. So it doesn't only help us
to keep the game fun, which is super important because the moment your game
stops being fun, if you can't get it back to fun you want to abandon it, [laughs] basically.
You also don't want to forget things. So here's your challenge! I want you to...
I want you to have a challenge! Here you
go, let's try again! OK add a quite button! Add a quit button to the
main menu. Call application quite from the blueprint. I'll let you decide exactly
what to call from the blueprint, all of this will be coded in the blueprint, and then, just test
that hitting quit stops the game playing. I'm not going to give you anymore hints than that, you need to
crank up your mind again, in terms of UI, revise some previous lectures
if you need to, but let's get a quit button on there!
Well go on there! You're adding it right? [Laughs] But you're not listening right now because it's paused,
so I'm talking to nobody, but then when you un-pause it, you'll be hearing me. Anyway I digress,
let's get on with it! So let's go and find... Where is
this start menu in the first place? Well good question, where did we put it?
I think we put it under UI, MainMenu. So there we go, here is the
main menu designer! So I think what I'm going to do, that would be prudent, is to take the
Start Button there and see if I can do a Copy and then a Paste.
Will it let me paste in here?
...
No, it won't let me paste. Why not? OK instead of doing it on this
3D View you can go the the Hierarchy here, Copy there, and then,
Paste in the Hierarchy, under the [Canvas Panel]. There you go! So
now we have two start buttons sitting on top of each other. One and
two, now where is the second one? The second one is at the top-left.
So that's it, basically you copy it in the Hierarchy rather than copying it
there. Now I'm going to get rid of this animations timeline at the bottom, because we're not animating anything.
I'm going to immediately rename this asset to
QuitButton, like so, and then, I'm
going to go about making sure that it's aligned with the other button.
And then changing the text, which should be Quit
Text, and then, the text should be QUIT,
I'll use capitals.
Cool! So we're nearly there! And then on the button itself, rather than the text
element what you want to do is, you want to come down to one of the events, and I'm going to
choose OnReleased, so you can push Quit but
it's not until you let go. So if you go oh I didn't really want to push Quit, you can kind of push it, move your
mouse off. Ah that may not work, but let's go with OnRelease anyway just to be
different. So we're going to choose OnReleased here.
So let's look where we are. Is this where we want to be coding it? Yeah, I think
this is perfectly reasonable! What have we got here? We've got the Event Graph for the UI.
It gets the WidgetReady, sets the Input Mode to UIOnly, gets the
Player Controller, it sets this Input Mode Game
Only, if you remember all that stuff. And the reason I can't edit is because I'm simulating, that was that big
simulating thing over the top there. I'm just going to de-spaghetti-fy this a little
bit. And now, I've got room for my quit button and I can search for "quit"
and then we've got Game, QuitGame. And it is as simple as that!
Actually, you just need to wire Quit to QuitGame. At Quit Preference,
Quit, or Background we're going to quit fully. So let's test it works!
Next, Compile up the blueprint, play the game from the main menu, hit Quit,
and the game stops running! Perfect! I think the final thing I'm going
to do on here is, just make this button in the Designer tab. Remember that
when you're in the MainMenu blueprint, you have a Graph tab which tells you how it works and a Designer
tab which tells you how it looks. I'm going to go into the Designer tab for myself,
I'm going to select the QuitButton, and I'm just going to make a slightly different background
color, just to give it the sense of quit-ability, if that's a
word.
OK that'll do!
That's red, it's pretty ugly, but at least we know that that's the quit button. Now notice,
I push the button down nothing happens. I can't actually
move away and not quit, that would take a little bit more work on the
UI, but at least it doesn't immediately quit the second you touch it. At least you can
think, oh I didn't really mean to quit! OK you can't stop it, but as an exercise
to the reader by the way, if you want a bit of an extra challenge, the key runs out there.
Make is so that you push down on Quit, if you move the mouse off and let go that
actually it doesn't quit. But for everybody else this is fine, we can start the game, the tanks
don't disappear, we have super simplified collision, we have a quit button,
and happy days are ahead! So see you in
the next video!