So welcome to Setup Track
Throttles! In this video we will do exactly that, and by the end of it,
what we will have is something like this, where ignore
what's going on, on the screen, on the 3D Viewport, just look at the console. I have now got left and
right track throttle values, coming through from my gamepad, which is pretty
cool and there are several changes that have been made to make that happen. So let's go and have a look!
And we don't currently have a track class. We do have a barrel and a turret class,
both of which were inheriting from StaticMeshComponent,
but when it comes to the actual tracks, they are just raw Static Mesh Components
with no ability for us to write any C++ code.
So that's the first thing I'm going to want you to do is, base tracks on C++
classes. create a TankTrack class. Inherit from
UStaticMeshComponent, make it BlueprintSpawnable very much
like the barrel and the turret. In fact, this whole thing is very much like the barrel and turret.
Replace the tracks on the tank blueprint and put the meshes back,
and then, just test that the game still works. Nothing will change but you will,
very importantly, have a C++ class in which you can write behavior about
tracks. So pause the video and base your tracks on a C++ class
now. Go on, you can do it!
It's just like the barrel and the turret.
OK welcome back! Let's have a little look at this! So
we're going to make ourselves a new C++ class, it's going to be a UStatic
MeshComponent, so we're going to have to Show All Classes.
We're going to type static mesh component and there it is!
We're going to call it TankTrack. Perfect!
Create Class leaving this Public checkbox
set. Remember that that just makes header files go in a public folder, and C++
files to in a Private folder. We're going to keep it like that for now, just for simplicity
and for consistency with other Unreal tutorials, particularly the ones made by
Unreal themselves. So while that's compiling,
why don't I go take a look... Oh I can't! I'll just be patient in that case. What I will
do, actually, is go take a look at the turret! This is the meta =
(BlueprintSpawnableComponent) annotation that I need, so I'm going to grab
this (BlueprintSpawnableComponent), I'm going to get rid of
the hidecategories comment, because we're not going to hide the collision category. So I'll
get rid of that, it's extra commenting we don't need. I'm going to go to the TankTrack
header file, put in the meta = (BlueprintSpawnableComponent).
Now remember what that means. That means that in the tank blueprint, at the moment, if I do
the dropdown and go to Custom classes I have a barrel in the
turret but no track. If I compile my code with this
header tool directive in this (BlueprintSpawnableComponent),
then... Well let's do it! ...then, it will appear in that list!
While it's compiling I want to do another thing. Look if we look in here at Left Track,
you see it says (Static Mesh Component), then it gives us a load of gray text which tells us
about what a Static Mesh Component is. But right now, if I come in
and add myself a Tank Track, which is now available,
and then say Left Track. Well I'll do the Left Track in a minute. Look if I
hover over it's got no information. OK, so let's give it some information, that information goes
here in that comment block. So let's just look
at the static mesh for inspiration, "StaticMeshComponent
is used to create an instance of a UStaticMesh." OK, so "TankTrack
is used to set maximum driving
force, and to move
the tank" or "to apply forces
to the tank." OK, so
that comment there, when you compile, will come through to this
hover over menu there, where it says TankTrack brackets TankTrack, we'll then usefully
get a little bit more information about it. So do get in the habit, in your C++, of decorating
new classes with some information like that, so that when you
hover you get that. Cool! So what is it about the Left Track that we need to replace? It's
just the Static Mesh. So this new tank track here
is going to replace it with the TankTrack Static Mesh.
I'm going to delete that Left Track now. I've still got the
Right Track, if we wonder about any properties. Call it Left Track,
parent the socket to Left Track,
check the Viewport that the tank still looks feasible, compile up the
blueprint, and let's play the game. The Left
Track looks very much like the Right Track, but the difference is, if you hover over the Left Track, it's based
on our C++ class, whereas the Right Track is a plain old (Static Mesh Component).
Great! Let's now just run this from the main
menu, because we have had problems with that before.
Yeah, it's all working fine! Great! So I'm now just going to do the
same for the Right Track. In fact, I'm just going to delete the Right Track, duplicate the
Left Track, call it Right Track, change
the socket, and Compile
and save. Actually the blueprint, now let's play the game from the menu,
and it works absolutely fine! Great! So that's a good starting
point! In under five minutes we have ourselves a pair of tracks that
give us C++ code that we can access. Cool! So what we want to do now
is drive the tank with that, so we're going to need to give
ourselves an input, for a start. So under the Project Settings
go to Input, and ax, create yourself a new Axis Mapping. I'm going to call it
Left Track Throttle. Now this is the sort of thing the
player would actually see, when they are setting up the controls
themselves. I'm going to use the Left
Trigger. There you go, Gamepad Left Trigger,
and then, I'm going to make a Right Track Throttle
and I'm going to make it the Gamepad Right Trigger.
Gamepad
Right Trigger Axis. Now you want Gamepad Left Trigger Axis as well.
Not Trigger but Trigger Axis OK, because we want it to be analog, you want a
variable amount of throttle. So they are the action mappings that I've setup.
Fantastic! I'll leave this open, just in case I need it! Then, what we want to be able to do in
the Input Setup of the tank is, outside of this block which is no longer, by the way,
just Camera Input Binding, it's more generally because it's got Fire
information here. It's Aiming Input Binding, isn't it? So this block on the right
here is about Aim Input Binding. So immediately you see that if a
comment's not right, just change it. And what we want to be able to do over
on the left here is, we want to be able to go OK let's go find
this throttle thing, which is the Left Track Throttle event
coming in. I'm also going to want the Right Track throttle. They are the input bindings
we just setup, and we're going to want a blueprint callable
method that does something with that. This axis is going to spit out a value
between -1 and +1. Well, it could be bigger than that, if the scaling
is changed here, but by default, it'd be between -1 and +1. A mental
note for later, we may want to do some clamping inside of our actual
throttle code, to make sure that a user can't change their scale and make
the tank actually go any faster. This just wants to change how controls feel, not how the tank behaves.
But anyway, we want to be able to drag out of here, run a
blueprint callable event, and then, pass in the Axis Value.
So in order to do that, we're going to need to make ourselves a public
section of the track.
Then, we're going to need something like void SetThrottle or Throttle
Request. What shall we go with? ThrottleRequest... No, SetThrottle! You can set
it to throttle directly! SetThrottle(float Throttle).
OK, so that's great, but that's not going to be
blueprint callable, unless we say that it's a UFUNCTION.
(BlueprintCallable, and
Category = Input) for neatness.
OK, so we have a BlueprintCallable function there. So before I go
and try and compile this, let's implement this function!
UTank
Track::SetThrottle like so. And I think the first thing we should do is just
log out the value. It's always a good thing to do, so let's search for UELOG
in the current project. Go get this log that we previously had in the Launch
Projectile. We don't need it anymore, let's cut it so that we've only got a log in one place.
In the TankTrack let's paste it and we could
say... Instead of the the time, in fact,
I think I'm going to not use the Time for now, I'll keep it for the next thing, but I think I'm going to say
auto Name = GetName();
see what that comes out as.
And as a string, I'm just going to say this track's throttle
...
colon and then we're going to print out the throttle.
That should work! I think this
also Name = GetName should work, it should come out as an fstring with a star on it.
I think that might work, let's try it! It's going to be quicker than waiting for
UnrealTo, Oh sorry, VisualStudio to
auto-complete. Let's see if that's going to work! So the idea is, I'm going to
say Left Track throttle set to and then it's going to show me... And well it won't
until I actually wire it up, but we can wire it up in the blueprint in just a second,
as soon as the compilation has happened. Yeah cool! So now the compilation happened, we should
be able to look for something called throttle. Set Left Track Throttle function. There's
your blueprint callable function! Again, if you want sensible
comments on there, you can put comments in the top of the
just above the method here, this SetThrottle. You could
do it in the header file, for example, and you can come in here and just say
"// Sets a throttle between -1
and +1, and if we were to compile that up,
then next time we go for SetThrottle, we should get something a bit more helpful. But
while it's compiling, let's wire in the Axis Value to the Throttle input, the float.
I'll put the Left Track in the middle there, it's a bit ugly but it's better than things crossing over.
Let's look for throttle again. Set Throttle
on the (Right Track). You see "Sets a throttle between -1 and +1".
That's helpful and that happened, as I say, because I put a
comment here above the function. OK, so there is
the Right Track. Let's just pull the value
through, Compile this blueprint, and go
have a look. If it compiles, save it in case it crashes. Compile,
play, in we go! Now, I'm using my gamepad, I'm turning
on the gamepad on my computer. It's an Xbox One gamepad, in this case.
We have 0 reports of throttle! Forget what's going on in the main game screen, let's focus
entirely on this output log at the bottom-left. Look at that, I'm pulling my left track throttle between
0 and 1 and the right track between 0 and 1. Awesome!
That's working perfectly! Let me just show you one other thing, this Input Scaling! Let's
turn the Left Track Throttle Input Scaling to 2.5, so you can see what that's
doing! Now if I pull the left track in, it goes between 0 and 2.5
at full travel, but the right track can only go to 1. Now that's a bit weird, we don't
really want that to happen. We do want to limit the full travel, because, at the moment, if
we let this carry on, the player could change... If you give the player
this control over this axis speed, it's control sensitivity
is what you'd normally see in menus, they would actually be able to make the tank go faster. So we're
going to want to clamp these values later, so when you have a thought like that
put it in. It's going to be in here somewhere in SetThrottle, and we're going to make a "// TODO
clamp actual throttle
value to..so
player can't overdrive" or something like that. Just
capture your idea that you want to do that. That is
fantastic! I'm not going to actually put in the applications of the forces, I don't think,
in this video, because we're going to have to think about how much force needs to be applied and a few
other things, and we've done enough for this video. So as a quick recap,
what we've done is, we have based our Left and Right Tracks on
our own classes, which are in turn based on Static Meshes. We have wired
up some Throttle Input Mapping, like this. So by making some axis,
providing references to the tracks, and then, passing the Axis Value
through into this Throttle method. We've then written this Throttle  method. that, at the
moment, just prints. So pretty cool! Good work for one lecture!
See you in the next one!