Welcome to what it says on
the screen. Physics Material & Friction! In this video we
are going to talk about Physics Material and Friction. Sorry to be trite.
So the point is. the tank is going to be able to move. because we will have assigned physics materials to the
tracks and we will have adjusted the frictional values and  driving forces.
so that our tank can move in a slightly strange way. for the moment. but at least it's moving.
So we've been applying a force to the tank. We determined. by having the
tank float in the air. that it should be sufficient force to make this guy accelerate
but he's stuck to the ground. What are we going to do about that? There is a certain amount of
friction between the tank and the ground. As you can see. when we get hit by a projectile we
slide for quite a long way. but we do come to a halt. So
let's now tweak two things. the power or the force rather that
we are pushing the tank with and the friction between
the tank and the ground. Let me show you how to adjust both of those things. So
if we go to the tank blueprint. just to remind ourselves how it's put together.
and take a look. a good place to orientate ourselves. It's these tracks
that are in contact... Well it looks like it's the tracks that are in contact with the
ground. but actually. right now. it's not is it? If we go to the BattleGround. play the game.
depossess with F8. and make sure that collision is on.
under the Show menu. you'll see that actually we've just put... It's very very hard to
see this. it's a very thin purple box. But we've just put a
[Laughs] I got hit. We've just put a single box collider on
the tank. so there's this big slab we're trying to move around.
and when we get to hills and things that's not going to respond very well. so we are going to
now move back to having discreet components. And if we have any problems with
self-collision then we will overcome them now. rather than working
around them. Last time we worked around them. because it was good enough to get moving. This time we need to
confront the issues head on. So one thing I want to say. before we do that.
is that I am on Unreal 4.12.4. If you're
on an earlier version of Unreal on that please upgrade to 4.12.4. because
we were experiencing problems in any previous versions. particularly in 4.12.3.
with the way that components with colliders
on them interact with each other. It's something to do with welding. OK. so
let's go ahead and change the way these colliders work! There's our tank body.
Remember that it has a primitive on it. which is just a box right now.
OK. so what we're going to do is just show collision.
I'm going to take a Left view. I think will be from the front.
strangely because of the way our tank is orientated. Um. and I'm going to
change the Y extents to bring it in. a little bit of clearance between the body collider and
the tracks. Change the Z Extents a bit and then move it up.
in the Z position
like so. So now we have a collider. which mainly covers the
body of the tank. Great! Let's look at that in
3D. You can see that it's covering mainly the body.
Now that paves the way for us to actually put collision back on the tracks. so let's go
ahead and do that! We can go to the tracks. we can go and find the track mesh. which
is here. Where is it? It didn't
come up! Um. go find it. There we go?!
Left Track mesh. turn on collision. and you can create yourself a 26
DOP Collision Mesh. something like that which looks about right. It's going to behave quite well going
up and down slopes. without being overly complicated. And now.
when we go back. let's go ahead and just play the game and see how we get on with those two
separate Collision Meshes. Now if you find that one of your tracks falls
into the ground or something like that. please check your Unreal 4.12.4.
Also. check that this works from the main menu. this is a great
time to be checking that. because what we've noticed is a problem with the way that
the tank is constructed in terms of a timing problem. It's what we call a race condition.
And the place that this may manifest. if you're having a bug. is
as follows. What you have is the tank and then you have the Left
and Right Tracks as sub-objects. and you'll notice that you should have a property ticked on those.
called Auto Weld. if I can find it.
Here you go! It's under Physics and then the extended physics
properties. You need to do the drop-down under Physics. off the Left and Right Track. under the
extended properties you have Auto Weld. If you were to turn Auto Weld off. let's
see what happens. You see it ignores those
track colliders. it's just landing on the body collider. So we do need Auto Weld
on. because we want the collision meshes of the tracks
to weld into the same mesh as the body. as it says here. "If true
and is attached to a parent. the two bodies will be joined into a single rigid body." "Physics settings like
collision profile and body settings are determined by the root". So they're saying that the root
up here. the Tank. will determine the Mass and all these physics settings. but these Left and Right Tracks
will contribute to the overall collision. OK. so you do want Auto
Weld on. Now it's possible that you could get a problem where
Auto Welding doesn't work say from the main menu but does work from the game.
and this could be to do with the time that the objects are constructed and whether the
welding works properly or not. at that time. If you're having
that trouble then there is a way to get around it in blueprint. but I don't think you'll be getting the trouble in
Unreal 4.12.4. I haven't seen it once in this version. So
if you're really stuck for any reason or you're getting any horrible behavior here. then remember you can always
go to GitHub. and you can go and get our project at this stage by
following through to Unreal. then the section. then the commits.
find the video. this video which isn't there yet. and then go and get the code by clicking
on it or by clicking over here on the right. and then. you can clone or download
the repo. OK. so that's important! Alright. so I think we've said enough about that.
We have now got the tank resting on its tracks.
so why isn't it moving? Well firstly. let's get control over the friction between the tracks
and the ground. If we go ahead and look at these tracks and scroll down.
inside the tank blueprint. you'll see you've got this Physical Material
override option. under Collision section. Well there is no
material. so let's make ourselves our first physics material. I'm going to put that in the Tank
folder. because it's very much related to the tank. and then. I am
going to go to Add New. scroll down to Physics. and it's actually the only thing in it.
Physical Material. I'm going to call it TrackMaterial
or just Track. because it is of type Physics Material.
So we don't need anymore naming than that. And if we go into it. we can see we've got a few basic
settings. one of them is Friction. Let's turn the track
Friction down to say 0.2. Now
there is an issue of Friction Combine Mode. and this is set in
two places. This is answering the question. how do I combine the Friction setting
on the track with the Friction setting on the ground. Now where is that
friction setting on the ground? Well it's in the actual Grass_
LayerInfo here. Whatever you've painted the ground with. at that point. whether it's
grass. mud. ice. whatever. in that LayerInfo you can see
that there is a Physics Material option. Now the grass doesn't have a Physics Material.
at the moment. We could give it one but that's beyond what we need to be doing here.
We could assign different Physics Materials to grass. snow. ice. and have the
tank behave differently but for now let's keep it simple. So we won't do that but I just want to point
out that the friction is not just determined by the track's friction but it's
combined with the friction of the ground. There is also a project
level setting under Project Settings and Physics. which
determines. in general or by default. how these things are combined. and it's here.
Friction Combine Mode. I'm not going to change that. I'm just going to give you the context.
The way that we're going to make our friction work is quite simple. We're going to override the Friction
Combine Mode and choose Minimum. and that means that we
are going to most likely. given that the other thing that we're touching the ground
doesn't even have a Physics Material. we're most likely going to end up with this 0.2 as the minimum of
the two physics values. OK. so let's see how much difference
that makes. We need to assign this Physics Material to both the Left and the Right Tracks.
Now that we have it. we can just go to Collision in the tank blueprint.
select the Left and the Right Track. with the Control button. and then
for Physics Material Override set Track. Remember to Compile. And now let's just try
moving the tank. It's not quite moving. See that other tank though. it
slid down the slope a lot faster. so there is a lot less friction on it.
And that looks fairly reasonable to me. so the next thing to do is
to increase the force with which we move the tank. Now this isn't an ideal way to move
this tank. We're moving this tank by shoving it along the ground on these
flat colliders. There are other ways that you could approach this.
You could. for example. put some hidden wheels. a bit like these actual
wheels underneath the track. and you could use things called Physics constraints which
are down here in the Physics section. And you could try and make axles
and make some wheels move. but you'll end up with your own problems doing that. with different types
of problems. And you could try and have wheels
that revolve and pull the tank along. but the way that I'm going to show you how to do this.
by just making the tank pretty slippery and then using some code to stop it sliding
sideways and looking like it's on ice. is going to be more general. It'll allow you to make
hover tanks. it'll allow you to do basic things with certain types of aircraft or air
hockey. and you're going to learn more by doing it this way. So let's pursue this
root. Alright. so these tracks have got this track material on
now. As I say. the only thing that's making it not be able to move is that we haven't got enough
driving force. So I'm going to turn my driving force up. In my case. it's now
4 Million. Let's try that and see if it's enough! I'm going to pull
both throttles to 100%! And it's not enough. so let's iterate
up again to 40 Million. Now we're a thousands times bigger force than we expected
to be now but that's because of the amount of friction! There's a huge difference between pushing a frictionless
tank and expecting a tank with 40 tons
of force to slide on massive tracks. it would take a huge
amount of force! And there you go. it's moving around! In fact. I'm going to turn my game controller on
and just have a quick go from the game controller. before I put you into your challenge. which is just going to be
to tune up your physics. your combination of friction and track.
sorry track friction and driving
force. Cool that's fun! OK. one final thing before
we do that! Let's go to the Project Settings. Input. and I'm going to bind the
Shoulder buttons for a reversing throttle on the Left and Right.
I'm going to get rid of these left and right keys. I think. and instead of that. I think I'm going to look for
Shoulder button. Left Shoulder gives me an input scale of say
-0.5. Driving back at half speeds is like pulling the
trigger in halfway. and the Right Shoulder will give
me -0.5 as well. Bear in mind. if you ever expose this
as a sensitivity to a user. which you probably wouldn't do in this case. you might with the triggers
but you probably wouldn't with the Shoulder buttons. Then they could if you allowed the user to
change this 0.5. they could potentially make their tank go faster than somebody else's. so beware of that.
but. for now. it's absolutely fine.
We'll worry about that if and when we every expose that value. Now. this is me holding both Shoulder
buttons on my gamepad down. and if I hold down both triggers
then I can go forward. if I hold down just the right trigger
or just the left trigger. that's sliding all over the place
but we'll sort that out later. And if I hold down one Trigger and one Shoulder button I can rotate.
So look. we have agency. we can move the tank and we can aim the tank. so
we are. starting. starting to get there! I think I've got too much friction
or too little friction rather but it's difficult to say. because shortly we're going to stop
these projectiles from actually making us fly like this because
they don't need to be doing that. We can handle the projectile collisions. rather than with
physics. as just actual events. and then. decide how to process those events.
So I'd like you to tweak your Physics Settings. Set your track
Max Driving Force. I'm using 40 Million Newtons in my
case. What is 40 Million Newtons. by the way? Well a kilogram
weighs about 10 Newtons. 9.8 something. it depends where you're on
the Earth. Call it 10! so 40 Million Newtons is
4 Million kilograms. which is 4.000 tons! So [Laughs]
that's a lot of force. but with a 40 ton tank
sitting flat on the ground. it's possible that it needs that much
force to move. so it's still within the realms of possibility. The problem is that we don't have revolving
wheels. and the reason is that it's quite hard to model a tank. they're quite a unique
way of moving. They're neither wheels nor are they slabs. that's the thing about tracks;
they're wheels. they're kind of moving slabs with wheels on the inside.
So set your track physics material. friction value! I'm using 0.2 for this. and by the
way. a friction coefficient of 0.2. you might wonder what it means. I hate
things without units. right? Well actually. the friction coefficient of 0.2 is
unit-less. which is why I've not put a unit there. but what it is. is it's a force.
It's just like contact force and it's 0.4 times the contact force.
However hard the track is pushing into the ground. typically on flat
ground. that would be half the weight of the tank. however hard that track is pushing into
the ground. what this friction force means is that the tank will start to slip. when
you push it sideways. forward. backwards. left. right. with 20%
of that contact force. OK. on that track. That's what a Friction
Coefficient mean. it's a proportion of the contact force at which point
you start to slip. So go ahead. pause the video. tweak up your physics settings now.
and when you un-pause the video it'll be the end of the video. So just
tweak your physics settings. and why not share what you've done with your physics settings over
in our new community. You're probably aware that I've made www.community.gamedev.tv
here for you. There's a lounge that anybody can join. there's
more importantly Unreal. and you can go straight to the Battle Tank section. and you can go ahead and just
discuss in there. and you're going to find all sorts of interesting things. Please do check out
this here. the HoverTank project. One of our students
has made a fantastic looking hover tank! Look at this for inspiration! Low poly.
erie. landscape. some nice effects on it. So do
share your work in there. and I will see you in the next
video!
=======
Welcome to what it says on
the screen, Physics Material & Friction! In this video we
are going to talk about Physics Material and Friction. Sorry to be trite.
So the point is, the tank is going to be able to move, because we will have assigned physics materials to the
tracks and we will have adjusted the frictional values and  driving forces,
so that our tank can move in a slightly strange way, for the moment, but at least it's moving.
So we've been applying a force to the tank. We determined, by having the
tank float in the air, that it should be sufficient force to make this guy accelerate
but he's stuck to the ground. What are we going to do about that? There is a certain amount of
friction between the tank and the ground. As you can see, when we get hit by a projectile we
slide for quite a long way, but we do come to a halt. So
let's now tweak two things, the power or the force rather that
we are pushing the tank with and the friction between
the tank and the ground. Let me show you how to adjust both of those things. So
if we go to the tank blueprint, just to remind ourselves how it's put together,
and take a look, a good place to orientate ourselves. It's these tracks
that are in contact... Well it looks like it's the tracks that are in contact with the
ground, but actually, right now, it's not is it? If we go to the BattleGround, play the game,
depossess with F8, and make sure that collision is on,
under the Show menu, you'll see that actually we've just put... It's very very hard to
see this, it's a very thin purple box. But we've just put a
[Laughs] I got hit. We've just put a single box collider on
the tank, so there's this big slab we're trying to move around,
and when we get to hills and things that's not going to respond very well, so we are going to
now move back to having discreet components. And if we have any problems with
self-collision then we will overcome them now, rather than working
around them. Last time we worked around them, because it was good enough to get moving. This time we need to
confront the issues head on. So one thing I want to say, before we do that,
is that I am on Unreal 4.12.4. If you're
on an earlier version of Unreal on that please upgrade to 4.12.4, because
we were experiencing problems in any previous versions, particularly in 4.12.3,
with the way that components with colliders
on them interact with each other. It's something to do with welding. OK, so
let's go ahead and change the way these colliders work! There's our tank body.
Remember that it has a primitive on it, which is just a box right now.
OK, so what we're going to do is just show collision.
I'm going to take a Left view, I think will be from the front,
strangely because of the way our tank is orientated. Um, and I'm going to
change the Y extents to bring it in, a little bit of clearance between the body collider and
the tracks. Change the Z Extents a bit and then move it up,
in the Z position
like so. So now we have a collider, which mainly covers the
body of the tank. Great! Let's look at that in
3D. You can see that it's covering mainly the body.
Now that paves the way for us to actually put collision back on the tracks, so let's go
ahead and do that! We can go to the tracks, we can go and find the track mesh, which
is here. Where is it? It didn't
come up! Um, go find it. There we go?!
Left Track mesh, turn on collision, and you can create yourself a 26
DOP Collision Mesh, something like that which looks about right. It's going to behave quite well going
up and down slopes, without being overly complicated. And now,
when we go back, let's go ahead and just play the game and see how we get on with those two
separate Collision Meshes. Now if you find that one of your tracks falls
into the ground or something like that, please check your Unreal 4.12.4.
Also, check that this works from the main menu, this is a great
time to be checking that, because what we've noticed is a problem with the way that
the tank is constructed in terms of a timing problem. It's what we call a race condition.
And the place that this may manifest, if you're having a bug, is
as follows. What you have is the tank and then you have the Left
and Right Tracks as sub-objects, and you'll notice that you should have a property ticked on those,
called Auto Weld, if I can find it.
Here you go! It's under Physics and then the extended physics
properties. You need to do the drop-down under Physics, off the Left and Right Track, under the
extended properties you have Auto Weld. If you were to turn Auto Weld off, let's
see what happens. You see it ignores those
track colliders, it's just landing on the body collider. So we do need Auto Weld
on, because we want the collision meshes of the tracks
to weld into the same mesh as the body, as it says here. "If true
and is attached to a parent, the two bodies will be joined into a single rigid body." "Physics settings like
collision profile and body settings are determined by the root". So they're saying that the root
up here, the Tank, will determine the Mass and all these physics settings, but these Left and Right Tracks
will contribute to the overall collision. OK, so you do want Auto
Weld on. Now it's possible that you could get a problem where
Auto Welding doesn't work say from the main menu but does work from the game,
and this could be to do with the time that the objects are constructed and whether the
welding works properly or not, at that time. If you're having
that trouble then there is a way to get around it in blueprint, but I don't think you'll be getting the trouble in
Unreal 4.12.4, I haven't seen it once in this version. So
if you're really stuck for any reason or you're getting any horrible behavior here, then remember you can always
go to GitHub, and you can go and get our project at this stage by
following through to Unreal, then the section, then the commits,
find the video, this video which isn't there yet, and then go and get the code by clicking
on it or by clicking over here on the right, and then, you can clone or download
the repo. OK, so that's important! Alright, so I think we've said enough about that.
We have now got the tank resting on its tracks,
so why isn't it moving? Well firstly, let's get control over the friction between the tracks
and the ground. If we go ahead and look at these tracks and scroll down,
inside the tank blueprint, you'll see you've got this Physical Material
override option, under Collision section. Well there is no
material, so let's make ourselves our first physics material. I'm going to put that in the Tank
folder, because it's very much related to the tank, and then, I am
going to go to Add New, scroll down to Physics, and it's actually the only thing in it,
Physical Material. I'm going to call it TrackMaterial
or just Track, because it is of type Physics Material.
So we don't need anymore naming than that. And if we go into it, we can see we've got a few basic
settings, one of them is Friction. Let's turn the track
Friction down to say 0.2. Now
there is an issue of Friction Combine Mode, and this is set in
two places. This is answering the question, how do I combine the Friction setting
on the track with the Friction setting on the ground. Now where is that
friction setting on the ground? Well it's in the actual Grass_
LayerInfo here. Whatever you've painted the ground with, at that point, whether it's
grass, mud, ice, whatever, in that LayerInfo you can see
that there is a Physics Material option. Now the grass doesn't have a Physics Material,
at the moment. We could give it one but that's beyond what we need to be doing here.
We could assign different Physics Materials to grass, snow, ice, and have the
tank behave differently but for now let's keep it simple. So we won't do that but I just want to point
out that the friction is not just determined by the track's friction but it's
combined with the friction of the ground. There is also a project
level setting under Project Settings and Physics, which
determines, in general or by default, how these things are combined, and it's here,
Friction Combine Mode. I'm not going to change that, I'm just going to give you the context.
The way that we're going to make our friction work is quite simple. We're going to override the Friction
Combine Mode and choose Minimum, and that means that we
are going to most likely, given that the other thing that we're touching the ground
doesn't even have a Physics Material, we're most likely going to end up with this 0.2 as the minimum of
the two physics values. OK, so let's see how much difference
that makes. We need to assign this Physics Material to both the Left and the Right Tracks.
Now that we have it, we can just go to Collision in the tank blueprint,
select the Left and the Right Track, with the Control button, and then
for Physics Material Override set Track. Remember to Compile. And now let's just try
moving the tank. It's not quite moving. See that other tank though, it
slid down the slope a lot faster, so there is a lot less friction on it.
And that looks fairly reasonable to me, so the next thing to do is
to increase the force with which we move the tank. Now this isn't an ideal way to move
this tank. We're moving this tank by shoving it along the ground on these
flat colliders. There are other ways that you could approach this.
You could, for example, put some hidden wheels, a bit like these actual
wheels underneath the track, and you could use things called Physics constraints which
are down here in the Physics section. And you could try and make axles
and make some wheels move, but you'll end up with your own problems doing that, with different types
of problems. And you could try and have wheels
that revolve and pull the tank along, but the way that I'm going to show you how to do this,
by just making the tank pretty slippery and then using some code to stop it sliding
sideways and looking like it's on ice, is going to be more general. It'll allow you to make
hover tanks, it'll allow you to do basic things with certain types of aircraft or air
hockey, and you're going to learn more by doing it this way. So let's pursue this
root. Alright, so these tracks have got this track material on
now. As I say, the only thing that's making it not be able to move is that we haven't got enough
driving force. So I'm going to turn my driving force up. In my case, it's now
4 Million. Let's try that and see if it's enough! I'm going to pull
both throttles to 100%! And it's not enough, so let's iterate
up again to 40 Million. Now we're a thousands times bigger force than we expected
to be now but that's because of the amount of friction! There's a huge difference between pushing a frictionless
tank and expecting a tank with 40 tons
of force to slide on massive tracks, it would take a huge
amount of force! And there you go, it's moving around! In fact, I'm going to turn my game controller on
and just have a quick go from the game controller, before I put you into your challenge, which is just going to be
to tune up your physics, your combination of friction and track,
sorry track friction and driving
force. Cool that's fun! OK, one final thing before
we do that! Let's go to the Project Settings, Input, and I'm going to bind the
Shoulder buttons for a reversing throttle on the Left and Right.
I'm going to get rid of these left and right keys, I think, and instead of that, I think I'm going to look for
Shoulder button. Left Shoulder gives me an input scale of say
-0.5. Driving back at half speeds is like pulling the
trigger in halfway, and the Right Shoulder will give
me -0.5 as well. Bear in mind, if you ever expose this
as a sensitivity to a user, which you probably wouldn't do in this case, you might with the triggers
but you probably wouldn't with the Shoulder buttons. Then they could if you allowed the user to
change this 0.5, they could potentially make their tank go faster than somebody else's, so beware of that,
but, for now, it's absolutely fine.
We'll worry about that if and when we every expose that value. Now, this is me holding both Shoulder
buttons on my gamepad down, and if I hold down both triggers
then I can go forward, if I hold down just the right trigger
or just the left trigger, that's sliding all over the place
but we'll sort that out later. And if I hold down one Trigger and one Shoulder button I can rotate.
So look, we have agency, we can move the tank and we can aim the tank, so
we are, starting, starting to get there! I think I've got too much friction
or too little friction rather but it's difficult to say, because shortly we're going to stop
these projectiles from actually making us fly like this because
they don't need to be doing that. We can handle the projectile collisions, rather than with
physics, as just actual events, and then, decide how to process those events.
So I'd like you to tweak your Physics Settings. Set your track
Max Driving Force. I'm using 40 Million Newtons in my
case. What is 40 Million Newtons, by the way? Well a kilogram
weighs about 10 Newtons, 9.8 something, it depends where you're on
the Earth. Call it 10! so 40 Million Newtons is
4 Million kilograms, which is 4,000 tons! So [Laughs]
that's a lot of force, but with a 40 ton tank
sitting flat on the ground, it's possible that it needs that much
force to move, so it's still within the realms of possibility. The problem is that we don't have revolving
wheels, and the reason is that it's quite hard to model a tank, they're quite a unique
way of moving. They're neither wheels nor are they slabs, that's the thing about tracks;
they're wheels, they're kind of moving slabs with wheels on the inside.
So set your track physics material, friction value! I'm using 0.2 for this, and by the
way, a friction coefficient of 0.2, you might wonder what it means. I hate
things without units, right? Well actually, the friction coefficient of 0.2 is
unit-less, which is why I've not put a unit there, but what it is, is it's a force.
It's just like contact force and it's 0.4 times the contact force.
However hard the track is pushing into the ground, typically on flat
ground, that would be half the weight of the tank, however hard that track is pushing into
the ground, what this friction force means is that the tank will start to slip, when
you push it sideways, forward, backwards, left, right, with 20%
of that contact force, OK, on that track. That's what a Friction
Coefficient mean, it's a proportion of the contact force at which point
you start to slip. So go ahead, pause the video, tweak up your physics settings now,
and when you un-pause the video it'll be the end of the video. So just
tweak your physics settings, and why not share what you've done with your physics settings over
in our new community. You're probably aware that I've made www.community.gamedev.tv
here for you. There's a lounge that anybody can join, there's
more importantly Unreal, and you can go straight to the Battle Tank section, and you can go ahead and just
discuss in there, and you're going to find all sorts of interesting things. Please do check out
this here, the HoverTank project. One of our students
has made a fantastic looking hover tank! Look at this for inspiration! Low poly,
erie, landscape, some nice effects on it. So do
share your work in there, and I will see you in the next
video!
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1:Unreal/Section4/BT55 Physics Materials & Friction.srt