So welcome to Fly-by-Wire Control System!
Let's just dive right in and find out what this is all about!
So back to our trusted question. what's the least fun thing about this game right now?
It's probably not the crazy physics. Think about Goat Simulator. that actually thrives
on crazy physics. so does. what's it called... Who's Your Daddy
and games like that. You don't necessarily have to get your game finished and polished.
in order for it to be highly successful. but it does need to stay fun. So I think
the thing that needs dealing with now is two birds in one stone. Firstly.
I don't necessarily want to have to drive my tank with the Shoulder buttons
and Triggers. Interesting and direct as it is. I want to add the
ability to use the Left Thumb-stick on the controller. for example. in
order to drive the tank and possibly the standard W. S. A. D key
combination. And in order to do that. we're going to need to introduce a new
layer of controller. Fly-by-Wire layer. that turns our intentions
into actual dry track commands. Furthermore. we're
going to need that in order for the other tanks. the enemy tanks. to be able to be driven by
AI. because the AI will not be able to directly
drive these tracks in the way that I'm kind of naturally doing
now. by choosing left and right and the appropriate
mix of throttles; the AI's not going to be able to do that without some help. So let me explain
this in a slide for you. what I plan to do. We start off with a
Human or AI Intention. and the AI Intention may be to
move forward or to turn left or right or whatever. and the Human Intention would be
very similar. Now the things that you can do very specifically
is. you can ask to go clockwise at a speed between -1 and +1.
where +1 clockwise is clockwise as fast as you can go. where a value of
0 coming out of this layer is do nothing. and a value of -1 is
go anti-clockwise. as fast as you can go. And the other thing you could do
is. you could say I want to go Forward. on the same basis or. of course. backwards.
So how does that relate to a controller? There's an Xbox
controller for you. Well if you want to go forward. you could take the Left Thumb-stick. for example.
and you could push Forward in order to go forward at full speed and Back to go backwards. Pretty
simple! If you want to rotate Clockwise. that could be interpreted as
moving the stick left and right. and. of course. there could be any mix
of those two. I could say I want to go mainly forward but turn right a little bit. as I do so.
etc. So that would feel. I think. very natural. that control system. and
it's also a control system. that if the AI was to put its robotic
hands on this controller it would actually be able to control the tank too. because
it's an API that the AI could use. so that's the clever
thing about abstracting the control like this. So in order to make this
work we need a Fly-by-Wire layer. We're going to call it a Tank Movement Component. we're going to make
that in a bit. But it's a fly by wire layer. what that means in an
aircraft. Fly-byWire means that you don't directly control the control surfaces
anymore. but you put a control input in and the Fly-by-Wire system
works out what your intention is. so pulling back on the stick as I intend to pitch
upwards; and then it does what it needs to do with the control systems. in order
to make that intention come true and that's what's happening with this Fly-by-
Wire system here. How does it do it? Well it's very simple actually. it only needs
to spit out two values right. +1 and -1 to the Left Track
and +1 to -1 to the Right Track. That's all it can do!
And by organizing things like this. the cool thing is we can
be sure that the AI also has exactly the same
controls as we do. It's literally like it's a robot holding the controller.
and in a lot of games. and including in Unreal if we're not careful. you will
find that the AI moves very differently to the human players. in some games.
What can tend to happen is that the AI may steer the tank kinematically.
for example. it may just move it's position without any respect for the physics.
so we don't want that. and if we just use Unreal's pathfinding and AI out of
the box that's what would happen. But we want to restrict the AI to the
same control system and the same type of tank as us. it makes the game much more fair. much more fun
and it's a very useful technique to know about. But I want to go one step further.
because I'm ambitious with this. and I want to make sure that we can mix in
our control inputs from the Right and Left
Shoulder buttons and Triggers. Now I'm not showing all of the lines. because that would just mess up the
diagram. but the point is that I could choose to control the tank by pushing.
using the Left Thumb-Stick. or I could immediately let go of the Left
Thumb-Stick and start using the Shoulder Buttons stroke Triggers and
either way the movement would work on my player tank. The AI.
of course. is constrained to talking by the Fly-by-Wire system. So we're going to
end up with a Jewel Control Mapping. one that goes into the Fly-by-Wire system from the Left Thumb-Stick
and another control mapping. which we already have. which goes from all the Shoulder buttons
and triggers directly into the tracks. And we're going to show how to make sure
whether we can mix these things. without doubling up. to make sure that if you say pull both
triggers in for maximum forward speed. and then. push the
left stick forward what would happen then? Well it shouldn't be going faster than its maximum speed. so we'll
learn all these tricks. which will allow you to make games where you have very rich
control systems. where you can allow the player to have some
freedom to do things in more than one way. even at the same time. So I hope that sounds
exciting for you. so that's the idea! Alright. so for the rest of this video
we're just going to talk about this C++ class and what it's going to be based on. because we need to
think a little bit carefully about what we're going to base our TankMovement
Component on. So we are going to create a new C++ class.
and it isn't going to be any of the standard ones in the list. I'm afraid. because there isn't
anything that's quite right. So we're going to go to Show All Classes.
Now. how would you find this the first time for yourself? Well you want a Movement Component. so you might want to
start typing that. "movement" and you get a whole bunch of stuff! And you can see
the hierarchy here. it's the top of this list we want. the Actor Movement Components.
So an ActorComponent clearly isn't enough. just adding an empty component.
A MovementComponent. well what does that do for us? It's "an abstract
component class that defines functionality for moving" primitive components every tick.
OK that's fine! It's not quite enough. so
let's keep going. NavMovement! OK that defines functionality of the MovementComponent
that moves any agent that may be involved in AI pathfinding. So
what is AI pathfinding? It's artificial intelligence agents in
the game. finding a path. finding a path from where they are to you.
So we've got a big old hill in the middle of our landscape right? Let's just take a look at it!
That lump in the middle here. and I hope you've got some sort of obstruction
in your landscape. it makes it more fun. If you haven't add something like this hill.
And what the idea is. is if an AI tank was to start the other side of the hill from us.
it will work its way around the hill. if the hill is seen as an obstruction.
So we want to be doing pathfinding. and this can be done automatically by
Unreal and it's very cool! Alright. so that is
the reason that we're going at least that deep into the hierarchy. Let's go back.
let's type "movement. and let's keep
going. Now is NavMove... Blah! I'll put my teeth back
in and try again! Is NavMovementComponent enough. or do we need a PawnMovementComponent?
"It also provides ways to accumulate and read directional input in a generic way".
Add Input Vector. Consume Input Vector possibly. We could possibly
need as much as a PawnMovementComponent. but why don't we start with the simplest
thing we can. If we're going to allow the AI tanks to do pathfinding
the simplest movement component that we can use. bearing in mind
that every time we go down this tree we get more stuff added on more complexity
added on. is going to be a NavMovementComponent. And
that will come with the pathfinding tools that we need. and then they're going to butcher
in order to make these AI tanks behave. So. a lot
of talking to tell you to ultimately make yourself a new class.
based on the NavMovementComponent. and let's call it Tank
MovementComponent.
There we go! Alright. so hopefully you understand the reasoning for that. We're going to be doing a
lot more work inside the TankMovementComponent. of course. once
we get into the next video. where we will start to setup the actual Fly-by-Wire system.
But for now. your job... We don't need a challenge slide in this video. it's just a lot
of explanation of what's to come. But your job is just to make sure that you have this
TankMovementComponent. like so. and that it's based on a
NavMovementComponent. and that your code still compiles
and that your game still plays as it used to. Obviously
there's going to be no difference in behavior. because we've just added an empty C++ class.
So congratulations on watching this video. I hope you've enjoyed it! I hope this
Fly-by-Wire malarkey makes sense. That is an overview
of what we're doing. I'll just... Ah no. I'll leave the controller on! I'll leave that on the screen for you. so
you can digest what we're doing and why we're doing it. and I will see you
in the next video!
=======
So welcome to Fly-by-Wire Control System!
Let's just dive right in and find out what this is all about!
So back to our trusted question, what's the least fun thing about this game right now?
It's probably not the crazy physics. Think about Goat Simulator, that actually thrives
on crazy physics, so does, what's it called... Who's Your Daddy
and games like that. You don't necessarily have to get your game finished and polished,
in order for it to be highly successful, but it does need to stay fun. So I think
the thing that needs dealing with now is two birds in one stone. Firstly,
I don't necessarily want to have to drive my tank with the Shoulder buttons
and Triggers. Interesting and direct as it is, I want to add the
ability to use the Left Thumb-stick on the controller, for example, in
order to drive the tank and possibly the standard W, S, A, D key
combination. And in order to do that, we're going to need to introduce a new
layer of controller, Fly-by-Wire layer, that turns our intentions
into actual dry track commands. Furthermore, we're
going to need that in order for the other tanks, the enemy tanks, to be able to be driven by
AI, because the AI will not be able to directly
drive these tracks in the way that I'm kind of naturally doing
now, by choosing left and right and the appropriate
mix of throttles; the AI's not going to be able to do that without some help. So let me explain
this in a slide for you, what I plan to do. We start off with a
Human or AI Intention, and the AI Intention may be to
move forward or to turn left or right or whatever, and the Human Intention would be
very similar. Now the things that you can do very specifically
is, you can ask to go clockwise at a speed between -1 and +1,
where +1 clockwise is clockwise as fast as you can go, where a value of
0 coming out of this layer is do nothing, and a value of -1 is
go anti-clockwise, as fast as you can go. And the other thing you could do
is, you could say I want to go Forward, on the same basis or, of course, backwards.
So how does that relate to a controller? There's an Xbox
controller for you. Well if you want to go forward, you could take the Left Thumb-stick, for example,
and you could push Forward in order to go forward at full speed and Back to go backwards. Pretty
simple! If you want to rotate Clockwise, that could be interpreted as
moving the stick left and right, and, of course, there could be any mix
of those two. I could say I want to go mainly forward but turn right a little bit, as I do so,
etc. So that would feel, I think, very natural, that control system, and
it's also a control system, that if the AI was to put its robotic
hands on this controller it would actually be able to control the tank too, because
it's an API that the AI could use, so that's the clever
thing about abstracting the control like this. So in order to make this
work we need a Fly-by-Wire layer. We're going to call it a Tank Movement Component, we're going to make
that in a bit. But it's a fly by wire layer, what that means in an
aircraft, Fly-byWire means that you don't directly control the control surfaces
anymore, but you put a control input in and the Fly-by-Wire system
works out what your intention is, so pulling back on the stick as I intend to pitch
upwards; and then it does what it needs to do with the control systems, in order
to make that intention come true and that's what's happening with this Fly-by-
Wire system here. How does it do it? Well it's very simple actually, it only needs
to spit out two values right, +1 and -1 to the Left Track
and +1 to -1 to the Right Track. That's all it can do!
And by organizing things like this, the cool thing is we can
be sure that the AI also has exactly the same
controls as we do. It's literally like it's a robot holding the controller,
and in a lot of games, and including in Unreal if we're not careful, you will
find that the AI moves very differently to the human players, in some games.
What can tend to happen is that the AI may steer the tank kinematically,
for example, it may just move it's position without any respect for the physics,
so we don't want that, and if we just use Unreal's pathfinding and AI out of
the box that's what would happen. But we want to restrict the AI to the
same control system and the same type of tank as us, it makes the game much more fair, much more fun
and it's a very useful technique to know about. But I want to go one step further,
because I'm ambitious with this, and I want to make sure that we can mix in
our control inputs from the Right and Left
Shoulder buttons and Triggers. Now I'm not showing all of the lines, because that would just mess up the
diagram, but the point is that I could choose to control the tank by pushing,
using the Left Thumb-Stick, or I could immediately let go of the Left
Thumb-Stick and start using the Shoulder Buttons stroke Triggers and
either way the movement would work on my player tank. The AI,
of course, is constrained to talking by the Fly-by-Wire system. So we're going to
end up with a Jewel Control Mapping, one that goes into the Fly-by-Wire system from the Left Thumb-Stick
and another control mapping, which we already have, which goes from all the Shoulder buttons
and triggers directly into the tracks. And we're going to show how to make sure
whether we can mix these things, without doubling up, to make sure that if you say pull both
triggers in for maximum forward speed, and then, push the
left stick forward what would happen then? Well it shouldn't be going faster than its maximum speed, so we'll
learn all these tricks, which will allow you to make games where you have very rich
control systems, where you can allow the player to have some
freedom to do things in more than one way, even at the same time. So I hope that sounds
exciting for you, so that's the idea! Alright, so for the rest of this video
we're just going to talk about this C++ class and what it's going to be based on, because we need to
think a little bit carefully about what we're going to base our TankMovement
Component on. So we are going to create a new C++ class,
and it isn't going to be any of the standard ones in the list, I'm afraid, because there isn't
anything that's quite right. So we're going to go to Show All Classes.
Now, how would you find this the first time for yourself? Well you want a Movement Component, so you might want to
start typing that, "movement" and you get a whole bunch of stuff! And you can see
the hierarchy here, it's the top of this list we want, the Actor Movement Components.
So an ActorComponent clearly isn't enough, just adding an empty component.
A MovementComponent, well what does that do for us? It's "an abstract
component class that defines functionality for moving" primitive components every tick.
OK that's fine! It's not quite enough, so
let's keep going. NavMovement! OK that defines functionality of the MovementComponent
that moves any agent that may be involved in AI pathfinding. So
what is AI pathfinding? It's artificial intelligence agents in
the game, finding a path, finding a path from where they are to you.
So we've got a big old hill in the middle of our landscape right? Let's just take a look at it!
That lump in the middle here, and I hope you've got some sort of obstruction
in your landscape, it makes it more fun. If you haven't add something like this hill.
And what the idea is, is if an AI tank was to start the other side of the hill from us,
it will work its way around the hill, if the hill is seen as an obstruction.
So we want to be doing pathfinding, and this can be done automatically by
Unreal and it's very cool! Alright, so that is
the reason that we're going at least that deep into the hierarchy. Let's go back,
let's type "movement, and let's keep
going. Now is NavMove... Blah! I'll put my teeth back
in and try again! Is NavMovementComponent enough, or do we need a PawnMovementComponent?
"It also provides ways to accumulate and read directional input in a generic way".
Add Input Vector, Consume Input Vector possibly. We could possibly
need as much as a PawnMovementComponent, but why don't we start with the simplest
thing we can. If we're going to allow the AI tanks to do pathfinding
the simplest movement component that we can use, bearing in mind
that every time we go down this tree we get more stuff added on more complexity
added on, is going to be a NavMovementComponent. And
that will come with the pathfinding tools that we need, and then they're going to butcher
in order to make these AI tanks behave. So, a lot
of talking to tell you to ultimately make yourself a new class,
based on the NavMovementComponent, and let's call it Tank
MovementComponent.
There we go! Alright, so hopefully you understand the reasoning for that. We're going to be doing a
lot more work inside the TankMovementComponent, of course, once
we get into the next video, where we will start to setup the actual Fly-by-Wire system.
But for now, your job... We don't need a challenge slide in this video, it's just a lot
of explanation of what's to come. But your job is just to make sure that you have this
TankMovementComponent, like so, and that it's based on a
NavMovementComponent, and that your code still compiles
and that your game still plays as it used to. Obviously
there's going to be no difference in behavior, because we've just added an empty C++ class.
So congratulations on watching this video, I hope you've enjoyed it! I hope this
Fly-by-Wire malarkey makes sense. That is an overview
of what we're doing. I'll just... Ah no, I'll leave the controller on! I'll leave that on the screen for you, so
you can digest what we're doing and why we're doing it, and I will see you
in the next video!
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1:Unreal/Section4/BT56 Fly-by-Wire Control System.srt