So welcome to
A Better Component Architecture! In this video we are actually going to get the
IntendMoveForward and Backwards working. from our stick. I'm using the
the controller left stick now rather than the shoulder buttons. and were going to have it
done a slightly different way. with Initialize method on the TankMovementComponent. And furthermore.
the TankMovementComponent is going to be added here in Blueprint. rather than being inherited.
and we'll see how this works and how it keeps our code even cleaner. So I'll see you in there!
Okey dokey. so we want to actually move forward now! So that means
that. in the TankMovementComponent here. we need to be able to access the
tracks. So how are we going to access the tracks! Well before we dive in and do it. how we
did with the AimingComponent. if you remember the tank received
references to the AimingComponent in Blueprint. and then. we
passed that SetBarrel and SetTurret reference through to the AimingComponent.
Well that's fine. that's a valid way of doing it. It's particularly a valid way of doing it when
we compose our AimingComponent into our tank. through C++.
But the rest of our objects are composed in here in the Inspector.
We equally could have added this AimingComponent like this. custom
Tank Aiming and then we would have all it's properties. We decided not to do it for the Aiming
Component. In fact. we've decided not to do it for the MovementComponent. But let's try things a slightly
different way with the MovementComponent. let me explain briefly with the aid of a
diagram. So we have a Tank and we're passing those references to the
Aiming Component. as I just told you. We're also calling methods on the Aiming Component.
But the Aiming Component. the only reason we need a barrel and turret on the
Tank is because the Aiming Component needs it. so it's kind of a bit backwards. we're passing it around
a loop right. and the same thing with the movement. The movement now needs access to Left and Right Track.
but we don't need to pass those references to the Tank. Why not just make it so that only
the Movement Component has those references. it would be a lot simpler. And it particularly gets simpler
when you have even a third and a fourth component. and it will simplify the interface
of our tank. particularly the public interface here. We can get rid of these references.
So let's leave the aiming as it is. it works. it's fine. we may fix it later. but
for comparison let's try doing the MovementComponent this different way.
So let's think about how we're going to do it. We're privately. in the MovementComponent.
going to need ourselves a couple of tracks. right UTankTrack.
Now UTankTrack will currently be unknown to this class.
so we do a forward declaration. class UTankTrack.
And while we're here. why don't we tell everybody what this component's about? " * Responsible
for driving the tank
tracks". Basically. that's what this component does! OK. so we
have a UTankTrack and it's LeftTrack. and we're good people so
we initialize to the null pointer. so that we have a
known memory address that we're pointing to. RightTrack.
so we have a Left and a RightTrack available here. OK.
so on the TankMovementComponent. let's write ourselves an initialize
method: void UTankMovementComponent : :
Initialise()
spelt the British way. of course! So we have a UTank
Track* pointer called LeftTrack
ToSet. and we have a UTankTrack*
pointer RightTrack
ToSet). Quite verbose but they fit on the screen. so they're good with me!
OK. so these things are very much like we did in the TankAimingComponent.
if you remember. Let's look at its C++! We had these setters here. so it's very similar to
that. but we're going to do both of the things that we need. both of the tracks in a single
method. in this case. So first thing. we better protect these so if...
Which way around should we do it? if not ( I LeftTrackToSet
or not Right
TrackToSet). then what are we going to do? We're going to get
it out of here. We may want to report and error if we have any problems. OK
so now what are we going to do? Well it's simply LeftTrack
= LeftTrackToSet. It's this sort of stuff that we love
programming for! RightTrack = [laughs] RightTrackTo
Set. Sorry about the sarcasm. OK great! So now let's go ahead and
declare this method. Now it's going to need to be public because
we're going to need to be calling it from the blueprint. and it is part of the public
interface of the MovementComponent to initialize it. It's something that needs doing. when the
component is added. We may as well go ahead and make it a UFUNCTION straight away. It's going to
be in the Setup category.
and it's going to be a BlueprintCallable Initialize
method. That's correct! OK let's go see this in action over in the blueprint!
And I'll put you back to the code. while it compiles. So we have a Blueprint
Callable Initialize that's going to take in the two TracksToSet and just set the local
variables. so that. in our IntendMoveForward. we've got hold of the variables that we need.
Now was that a succeed or a fail? It was a fail and
it's something to do with my void. And on line 23
what have I done?
" 'void' should be preceded by" a semicolon. and I've just missed a
semicolon there. interestingly on line 20. O.K.  Easy
to miss. O.K. especially with these strange UFUNCTION's in the way. which
make things a little harder for us. But anyway. we are getting used to it as we improve
our Unreal mod. It's worth it isn't it! It's a pretty powerful engine. all this effort's
got to be worth the pain. surely. Surely it's got to be. OK.
so I failed the compile again! What have I done wrong this time? And this time
it's because. in the...
Hmm I don't know? Let's read the error message. It uses an
"undefined class 'UTankTrack' " in the TankMovementComponent header file.
That's
because we want it to be a pointer to a UTankTrack. not a UTankTrack
class. Alright. so let's try that again! We don't want an instance
of a UTankTrack class. because we can't have that at this stage without having the
UTankTrack available. We just want a pointer. I just missed the pointers. Good. so there's two different
error types you've seen and know how to correct in future. Let's go for third time
lucky compilation on this! I'll leave the code on the screen.
Ah hah! That sounds much better to me! So
let's go and take a look at the tank blueprint now. Now when
we are in the tank blueprint. we no longer need the TankMovementComponent here.
inherited. so we can remove the code that puts that in. And while we're there.
where is the TankMovementComponent? It's not available yet! TankAiming
is but TankMovement isn't. Why can't we add TankMovement. at the moment? Well if you look in your Tank
AimingComponent header file. you'll see that the class has this annotation that makes it Blueprint
Spawnable. So let's do the same thing to the MovementComponent.
And while we're at it. let's go ahead and in
the Tank.cpp
let's get rid of the Create
DefaultSubobject MovementComponent. OK so we don't need to do that anymore.
So let's try compiling. and then while it's compiling.
I'll flick through the code files for you. so that you can see all the things we've changed. In fact. a better way
of you seeing what we've changed is for me to go to the source control and to show you the
un-staged changes in progress. So here you go! I've removed.
from the Tank.cpp. the CreateDefaultSubobject. because we're going to be adding it ourselves in Blueprint.
We have added an initialize method in here. inside
the TankMovementComponent.cpp. that  just lets you set both the
Left Track and Right Track reference. at the same time. And finally. we have
put a forward declaration of UTankTrack in. because we need that for these pointers
at the bottom. We've annotated the class to make it BlueprintSpawnableComponent.
which we'll use in just a second. and we have declared the Initialize() method.
So there are all the changes so far. Cool! While I went
through that... Hang on. we don't need to restart the EPIC Games Launcher! We
need to find Unreal. it's crashed! So my eyes got drawn up to the EPIC Games
Launcher. because Unreal had crashed. So we don't
need to restore anything. Let's go ahead and make sure the code is compiled.
which it is! Let's go to the tank blueprint
and take a little look at it. So in the tank blueprint now. we can see
that the MovementComponent isn't there anymore. and we can add a TankMovement
Component. from the Custom section. TankMovementComponent rather. from the Custom
section. There it is! It's available now. because we made it a BlueprintSpawnable
Component. remember here. OK so there
it is! Now. once we've got it. firstly this this Tank Movement Component here in the Input
Setup. that is one we created in C++. We need to get rid of that.
and bring in our new Tank Movement reference. There it is! Great. so that will
fix that! And then. the second thing we need to do is. on BeginPlay. we want to
look for this Initialize() method. There we go. Initialize (TankMovement)!
Great! It's already found the reference to the TankMovement
Component instance. this guy here. which is fantastic! So then we just need the Left and the Right
Track to come in like so.
Great! And
I'm going to prevent the lines from crossing. just because it's neater. easier to see what's
going on. Compile that up! I'm going to Save All because
if it crashes I don't want to lose any work. And play. and it seems to work. we seem
to have the game running! So what I want you to do now as a challenge is.
finish the movement. finish IntendMoveForward. make sure the tank
actually moves. and also make sure the speed is variable. So go ahead pause the video and make that simple
finishing to our architecture now!
OK welcome back! So in
IntendMoveForward(). this is where we get to very clearly say what we
intend to do. So LeftTrack. and then we can reach through the LeftTrack pointer
to. I think it was SetThrottle was it or Throttle or I can't remember?
Let's go and have a look! TankTrack.cpp. SetThrottle
was the method I'm looking for. so SetThrottle.
Maybe it's the semi-colon on the end of that log
entry that's throwing things off. I don't know. I'm going to
ignore it and just get on. and set the throttle to the throw value. And we're going to do the same on
the RightTrack.
I'm just going to check the TankMovement
Component header file. to make sure I've spelled these right. I have! And
let's also make sure... OK. the problem here is that we have
not #included "TankTrack.h".
so therefore when it looks at the LeftTrack object it doesn't know
about any of the methods on it. because it hasn't included the header file. but once that gets included.
these two things should work. and to be honest. this is a as simple as we need.
Let's go ahead and compile! I'll leave the code on my screen while I'm compiling!
The things that are highlighted in blue are the only things that have changed. I'm going to grasp my controller.
for all I'm worth. and then. let's celebrate if this works! I'm going to hit F11.
I'm going to pull... There you go! The Shoulder buttons. they're the two Shoulder buttons
taking me backwards. Now I'm going to try on the left stick backwards. Cool! And the left
stick forwards. that works as well. So I can go forward and backwards. using just the left stick.
I can still rotate using the Shoulder buttons; later. we'll bring that into the left stick as a second
possibility. It's nearly there! All the problem is. is if I'm left stick forward and then
I pull the two... Oops! It glitched. it had a self collision. or
collided off some imperfection in the terrain there. which is something we can sort later.
So what I'm saying is that. if I'm going both Shoulder buttons forward
and then I push the stick forward. as well. I end up going twice as fast. That's something we'll need
to sort. and because it's something we need to sort. we'll need to put a TODO in here.
"// TODO prevent
double-speed due
to dual control use". or something like that. OK. so if we put in an
Input on the stick. using the IntendMoveForward. and we go ahead
and directly input in the throttles.
then these two things are adding together and we need to prevent that in the long term. OK
so I'm just going to have little tiny tidy up in the blueprint. to prevent the crossed wires. slightly obsessively.
and I'm not going to go mad though. And that's it! Anyway. well done
on getting this far with the movement. and I'll see you in the next video!