So welcome to Completing Manual Tank Movement! In this video we will be
doing exactly what we say on the tin. which is just finishing off the manual tank movement. so
that using the Left Stick alone now. I can Fly-by-Wire control my tank
forward. backwards. left. and right. So I'll see you in there!
OK guys. so we're halfway through getting this TankMovementComponent sorted!
There are other things we could be doing right now. like sorting out the TankAimingComponent
and bringing it in. but look let's get this finished. we haven't finished the MovementComponent. So we can go back
and forth. but we can't go left and right. so let's sort that out. I'm not going to
challenge you to do that. because it's actually relatively simple. We have
an option here to IntendMoveForward. but we no longer need
that log entry there. I think I'll just ditch the log entry. actually. now.
I'll be brave. We have a TODO about preventing "double-speed due
to dual control use". "Due to dual control use"? I actually think we have that in two places! Let's look
at the Task List. Yeah we do. "clamp actual throttle value".
Yeah so that's actually the
same thing. so I'll get rid of it there. What we're saying is we don't want
two inputs from the Shoulder Buttons. etc. to double up. Anyway. so we don't
need that in two places. We'll leave that one in there. What I want to
do now is an IntendRotateClockwise. that's what we want to do next.
So I'm going to Copy that. because it's relatively similar.
IntendRotate... Or IntendTurn
Right. how's that? Yeah. let's go IntendTurnRight! Now.
what is the issue here? We still want to prevent double-
speed rotation. but what is the issue with what we're doing with the tracks? Well it's
actually pretty simple! Look we are just setting the LeftTrack
to... Well if we're going to turn right. the left track's going to go forward and the right track's going to go
backwards. So if we are fully with full Throw turning right. then
this is what happens. and if you're partially turning right. then you'll have both
of these tracks set to partial throttle. So that's pretty easy isn't it?
See if it works! Of course. I'm just going to pop into the public sector.
the IntendTurnRight declaration.
it's going to be a part of the Input part
and semicolon. I think we're good to go? Oh sorry. Unreal
doesn't like... Let me just try this one more time. I never remember. are you allowed to put a semicolon
on the end of a U function? I should make an effort to remember. Let's see!
Because if you can it's better. because VisualStudio doesn't keep indenting
accidentally for you. But I think it's going to complain. unfortunately. Yeah. it depends on
every... Let's just check it is this it's complaining. line 25.
Yep sorry! You're not allowed to put semicolons on the end of
U function annotation. It's a shame. because it forces VisualStudio to
misbehave. Alright. while that's compiling let me show you something else useful.
I often open say the tank blueprint. It opens in another window. but it doesn't always open
in another tab like this; it did in this case. because I just opened it.
But if you want to be sure that things always open in a new tab. you can go to Edit and Editor
Preferences. and then. if you look under your Editor Preferences.
you've got. under User Interface.
Asset Editor Open Location. We want to open that in
the Main Window. If you want to do that. that's great! That's that setting
there. And what that'll mean. if you open a new asset like this Barrel. it'll just open right up here in
this main window. I'd prefer that! If you do well then bully for you. there's an option!
OK so where are we? We're going to test this! The compilation has
happened. I saw that happen. that's fine! I think we can pretty much... Do we need to
do anything in the blueprint? I better compile the blueprint! OK. and we can pretty much just play!
And let's try left and right. Nothing on
the left and right. at the moment. because I haven't bound input. So you go to the Settings.
the Project Settings. Input. and
we need to make ourselves an axis. which is going to be Turn Right.
And then. we're going to assign
that to the Gamepad Left Thumbstick X-Axis. Now we only
need a Turn Right and Move Forward. because. of course. if you go negative in either of these then
they obviously give the negative value. so you don't need Move Backwards or Turn Left.
But I'm giving them a very specific name. because it makes clear what a positive value
is. A positive value is turning right. Alright. so to the tank blueprint
Batman! In the Input Setup we have this Intend Move Forward
thing here. Well it's going to be very very much like that right. We're going to go and find the Turn Right
event. we're going to drag
it off to Intend Move Forward on the
TankMovementComponent. It very kindly finds the TankMovementComponent. We could share that
reference between the two parts of the blueprint like that. so there's just a single TankMovementComponent.
It's kind of personal choice whether you do that or don't do that. Compile it up.
I'm gong to Save All. and let's see if we can turn on the spot now!
Now I'm using the Left Stick on the controller!
No. not at all! OK so.
what's going wrong? Let's go and have a look at the code. Let's make sure that we actually
are getting this IntendTurnRight being called.
so let's put our UE_LOG back in. In fact. if you've deleted some code
and you wish you hadn't. what you can do is you can go to your source control. you can look at your unstaged
changes. go find the thing that you deleted the code in. which in my case is
the Tank Movement Component.cpp. go find your log file. which was there.
your log entry. and you can paste it straight back in from there. which is pretty handy.
OK. so we're going to UE_LOG Intend turn right
at throw. Let's
just log that out and make sure that that's happening. Meanwhile.
I'm just going to check the other prerequisites that we have. Turn Right is
the string. I'm going to check that's right. When we
look at the blueprint. Gamepad Left Thumbstick X-
Axis is correct. Look at the tank blueprint. InputAxis
Turn Right. Yep that's right! It looks very different to this one.
and that's just because the word Right is much shorter than Forward.
Ah look. I'm calling the wrong thing. I'm calling Intend Move Forward!
I need it to be Intend Turn Right.
and that is the problem. So I'm kind of debugging it on two levels at the same time.
so that's just saving me time. I have written a log statement
over in the C++ to help me diagnose this. but I suspect
it's just going to work now anyway. There you go. it works now! And if we look in the
console. we do see these Intend Turn Rights coming in. In fact. if I clear the log
and play again. we'll find you can see those. and you can see the amount of throw
and how it's working. So we cannot only turn left and right but we can move around. so we actually
finally have motion. Now that bug there is the tank either self
colliding or hitting an imperfection in the terrain. so we need to find a solution to that
later. but we'll live with that for right now. because what is good is that we can move this aim
point around and we can move the tank. I'm actually
finding now with these controls. I don't like my Y axis being that way around.
I prefer my Y axis inverted. and. of course. that's incredibly easy because you go to
AimElevation and you just go to -1
on the Gamepad Right Thumbstick Y-Axis. And that is the sort
of thing that would be set through an invert Y axis control for the player.
And now that feels a lot better for me. and I feel like I can move around.
and I can aim at these tanks. and I could even bind a fire key. of course. to
say the Right Trigger or to the A Button. I think I'll make it the A Button. so
let's do that now. Action Mapping. Fire. we've already got it. and this is
where our work on the project starts to compound. because we've already
got places for everything and it's starting to make a
lot more sense. So do I have an A Button here?
I think it's Gamepad Face Button Bottom. [laughs] let's try that!
Face Button Bottom. reminds me of the minions films. bottom he he he. [Laughs] OK.
that's it! That's right! So the Face Button Bottom he he [Laughs]
is the A there. so that gives me what I want. Fantastic!
So that is a lot of the MovementComponent now done.
We can move and the other tanks. of course. aren't moving. apart from the one
that's sliding down the hill due to friction. And of course. the reason they're not moving is
because they are not. well there's a few reasons actually. There's no Navmesh on the terrain
and also we have not intercepted the code at the right place. in order to
find out if even if there was a Navmesh. and if these AI tanks
were going to be trying to navigate to us. We haven't set any of that up. so that's
obviously why they're not moving. So you'll find out what a Navmesh is and how we get into this AI
stuff a little bit later. well in the next video. I just want to take a
quick look at the TankMovementComponent header file with you. while we're working on it.
and make sure that it all makes sense and that things are in the right places.
So just taking a look at this. it looks fine! We need an Initialize. we need a public
Initialize because we're going to call it from blueprint. and then. IntendMoveForward.
IntendTurnRight is very simple. that's consistent with the responsibility of the tank.
It's "Responsible for". not from. "driving the tank
tracks". and then. we just have a couple of private references to our tracks.
Why do we need those references? Because we use them in several different methods across the
class. So it all looks very clean and simple to me. The only thing I would say is. in the
Initialize() method we don't need to be checking pointers. because
there's no need. If we passed in a null with LeftTrackToSet or RightTrackToSet.
well then these things will just get set to null and they were null before. so it's really not
doing anything. that code. But what we can do is move it from here
down to the IntendMoveForward() method. because there you
do want to make sure that the LeftTrack. not the LeftTrackToSet.
and the RightTrack. not the RightTrackToSet. exists before you
try doing anything with them. And actually. it's the same deal there with the
IntendTurnRight. you want to be protecting your pointers. So I'm going to get rid of the log
entry. have my pointers protected here. leave my
notes about doubling up on the controls. do a final compile of this.
to make sure it works. and then. we'll look forward to looking at the artificial
intelligence and how that's going to work. That's going to be a lot of fun!
So just quick. wait for the compile.
play it.
forward. backwards. rotate. rotate. barrel moves. all looks good!
Final thing to do. of course. is to play it from the main menu. because you can
have problems with raise conditions and the order in which things are constructed. So forward.
backwards. left. right. aim. and fire all works! Great
news! So well done getting that far! I will leave. for you. the changes that I've
made to the code. I'll just quickly flick through them now. so you can pause the video if you need
to. So in the Tank Movement Component.cpp we have removed some
useless pointer protection on the Initialize. We have added
pointer protection to the IntendMoveForward. and then. we have done the
IntendTurnRight basically by just setting one of the throttles backwards. very very
similar to the forward. Then. what else have we done? We have
not much else to be honest. that is mainly it. We've then. of course.
wired everything up in the tank blueprint. like so. down at the bottom here.
So your challenge. if you haven't already followed me along in this video. is to get this far. get your tank moving
left. right. up. down. Get your control systems how you want them. and I will see you
in the next video!