Hey and welcome to
DotProduct() Vector Operator! The ratio of how
fun this video sounds compared to how fun it's going to be is really really high!
By the end of it. we are going to have our tanks actually moving forward
and backwards. in order to obtain a broadside position on us. Yes. they overshoot.
but that's because they themselves have to use the same control system
that we are using and are subject to the same physics system. So I will see you in there!
So currently. if we look at the logs that come out of our game. when we're playing.
we get this vectoring vector. which is this
thing that's logged here this MoveVelocityString. which is the MoveVelocity if you remember
that comes in from the AI Pathfinding System. And it is
not what we call a unit vector. this vector is long. If you looked at
that in 3D space it's got a definite length to it. thousands or hundreds of thousands
of units long. So one of the first things we want to do is noramalize
this. just to get a unit vector out. We're only actually interested
in the direction in which the
AI is asking us to move. we will decide how fast we're going to move in
that direction. So before we go into how we're going to do these Dot
Products and cosigns and things. let's just do that. Let's just go  MoveVelocity Dot...
I'm here in. by the way the TankMovementComponent inside the RequestDirectMove() method.
MoveVelocity.GetSafeNormal() and if you read what that
method does. you'll find that it gets you a
normal vector of this MoveVelocity. without changing MoveVelocity.
It doesn't mutate it. so that's the safe bit. it means it doesn't change this thing. And it
provides us a normalized vector. Let's see what that normalized vector means. I'll just Compile
that code! All I've added is what I've highlighted there. GetSaveNormal.
and we still convert it to a string and print it out. and then. we'll just see how that
changes this vector. So we play! I better clear the logs actually. so
we don't have to scroll down. There you go! Now we're still getting these direction vectors out of the
AI tanks. but each one of these vectors. if we were to plot them in 3D space. has a
total length of 1. So it might just be X = 1. Y = 0. Z = 0.
i.e. straight down the X axis. or if it's a total off of that.
then you're going to see components in the other directions. But if you were to sum these X.
Y. and ?Z components up or square them rather and sum them up.
and then. take the square root of what you've got. the whole Pythagoras thing. you'd get a length of 1.
I'm not going to bore you with that but these are unit vectors; they are in the same direction
but they have just a length of 1. We did visit unit vectors earlier in the
course. So that is the unit vector for the direction
in which the AI intends
for the tank to move forward. In fact. let's give it a better name! Let's
call this thing AIForward
Intention. And I'd better stop it being a string.
and I don't think we need this log entry anymore. I'll just comment
out the log. So we have an AIForwardIntention! We get
what that is. we've seen the logs of it. it's a unit vector in the direction the AI would like the tank
to move. Great! OK let's just move the TankName. In fact. I'm going
to get rid of the TankName altogether. There's another thing that would be
useful to have. which is the
TankForwardDirection. right now. So we just need TankForward. Now how do you get the
TankForward? Have a little bit of a think about it yourself. We're on the MovementComponent. what do we do to go
from the MovementComponent to the tank itself? We GetOwner()
and then through the Owner we GetForwardVector.
GetActorForwardVector. because the Owner is an Actor.
And I'm going to also GetSaveNormal. So what that
will give us is a unit vector. in the direction the tank is facing forward. Let's look at that
physically in the game world. If we look at this Tank_BP2
here. it's facing along the red arrow. the X axis. and that would be the
vector it returns. It's a vector in the direction of the X axis. the tank's local
X axis that is. the tank's forward axis. Don't get confused. by the way. with this X
down here. this is the Global X axis. This tank just happens to be aligned down the Global
X. If we look at this guy he isn't. he is not aligned down the Global
X. the Global X is off to the left here. If you click this little button
in the top of your viewport... Look where I'm clicking. it's difficult for me to
explain where. but it's in the top of the viewport. it's a little box or a world. If you click it from the
world to the box. then it will show you the vector in terms of the tank
local forward. That's what we're talking about. we're talking about this little local X here
for both tanks. OK that red arrow is what it's going to return.
with a length of 1. So we've got these two things. we've got the direction of tank
currently facing and we've got the direction the AI would like the tank to be
heading. And tanks generally drive forward. they don't just drive sideways. So
our job is to try and come up with a movement scheme that means that
the tank goes forward. and at an appropriate speed. depending on the
difference between where the AI wants it to be facing and where it is facing. So what do we
need? We need something called a Cosine Function. if you remember your school. So
what we're going to have on this axis. is on the X axis we've got the angle between
these two things. between the AIForwardIntention and the tank's forward vector.
And on the Y axis we have the Throw. where we want to end up
with the Throw that we're going to put into IntendMoveForward(). the control Throw.
This is so the AI can literally control the controller. So let's think about
this. If the angle between the ForwardIntention and the TankForward vector is 0.
that means the tank is already facing directly in the direction that the AI wants it to
be going. Therefore. what do we do? We go forward at full speed. this 1
Throw up here. As that angle closes down towards 90
degrees. at 90 degrees that means the AI is saying go
to your. say let's call it... Well we have IntendTurnLeft or Right?
I can't remember. IntendTurnRight I think? Yep! So let's call 90 degrees and
90 degree right turn. If the AI's intending a
90 degree right turn or that it wants you to go 90 degrees to your
right. how fast forward should you be moving at that point? Well you shouldn't be moving forward. because the thing is
to your right precisely. And then. as we move to a position
where actually the AI wants you. the AIForwardIntention is 180
degrees out of phase with the tank's forward. i.e. the AI wants you going backwards.
what do you do? You drive backwards as fast as you can. you put a Throw in of -1
and so on for things to your left. And then. again
we get back to... OK it's directly in front of you! This 360 degrees
difference is the same as a 0 degree. this diagram wraps
around itself alright. So we get to 360 it's the same deal. it's basically
saying the AIForwardIntention is aligned with the TankForward. Let' go forward at full
speed! And the cool thing about this is. it varies smoothly
in between these situations as well. So a cosine is perfect for what
we want with the forward speed. So what we need or what we could use that
would be very appropriate is something called the vector DotProduct(). Now don't go mad about the math. I've
extracted a tiny piece of the Wikipedia article on the DotProducts right there for you.
And I will just talk about the math. because really it is just a mathematical
function. so there's not point in putting fluffy interpretation around it until
we've understood the math. So the DotProduct. A dot B. means the magnitude of A.
How big is vector A? Which we've already calculated. by the way. it is this guy here TankForward
times the magnitude of B. We've already got that. that's the AI
ForwardIntention. times the cosign of the angle between them. the thing that we just
said we wanted. So a DotProduct is pretty ideal. because it takes the
magnitude of these two things and it multiplies by
the cosign of the angle between them. But we want the magnitudes to be one
before we start. because we don't want the size of this Move
Velocity or anything that... This TankForward vector would be
a normal vector. even if we didn't do GetSafeNormal. By the way. this is just being
safe. But we don't want the size of the MoveVelocity to impact our answer. we want
our answer to come out as between 1 and -1. So I am
already making sure that these things. the size. these
lines here mean the size of A and the size of B. I'm making sure the size of those are both 1 at the
most OK. so that we're really focusing on just the angle.
So another way of interpreting the DotProduct is. it takes in two FVectors. It
outputs a float. What is it? It's the "Projection of one vector onto
the other". it's the parallel-ness. How parallel are we
if I am already facing in the direction AI wants me to be. to be 100%
parallel. I have a value of 1. If I'm facing in the opposite direction. I'm 100% not parallel.
I have a parallel-ness of -1 and so on. for everything in between.
The value of this DotProduct is maximum when the vectors are parallel and 0 when they're
perpendicular. And the diagram. one way of looking at it is like
this. So say B is the TankForward direction. but A is the AI
ForwardIntention.
then what you've got there is you've got the projection. You're saying well. how
aligned are they? And that is what we're getting out of the
DotProduct here. I know it's a bit mathematical. it's clear to people who understand
math. it's difficult for people who don't. But let's just see it in action. that's going to be the key now!
So we already have these two things. What I want you to do is
use the DotProduct()
to actually drive the tank. and see what the result is for yourself. I want to give you that satisfaction.
So I want you to use FVector::DotProduct(). Take a DotProduct().
between AIForwardIntention & TankForward. feed the result into IntendMove
Forward(). and then. share the resulting movement with the community. over on our community site.
preferably as a little video. So go ahead. do that. and I'll see you there!
OK so let's take a little look at what code we need to write! We want to say something like
auto Throw required or
RequiredThrow... Or Forward
Throw = FVector::
DotProduct()
between the (TankForward.
and the AIForwardIntention).
OK. now let's send that to IntendMoveForward.
(ForwardThrow).
Simples! OK let's see what happens there! Let's Compile
this up! While it's compiling. I'll leave the code on the screen. I think I've
spelled ForwardThrow wrong. I have. so I need to recompile!
OK there you go! So I've just done that and that. as I've highlighted.
And then. let's get ourselves some AI tanks in
a position that we can deal with. So let's go to the Top perspective and just remind ourselves
where the Player Start is. Great. it's there! Where's Tank_BP1?
Not that close to us. let's move it a bit closer.
And Tank_BP2.
OK let's have a look then. Oh look. here it goes! It's driving forward.
and then it's oscillating back a little bit. and it's kind of moving
until it's side on. Let's have a look at the other tank. Where's the other guy?
What I'll do is go into Perspective view.
In fact. what I would like is. I would like to be a little bit more out in the open
or at least to have my tank say here. And then.
this other tank. let's bring him over here so we can see
what's going on. OK I'm going to go to F11 or P to play.
Let's watch this other tank. he's already side on so he's not moving. This guy wasn't
side on. so he's got himself into a side on position. How cool! How about we put that tank
over there and watch him.
He's moving. This other guy isn't right now. Is he stuck in the ground?
Let's see what's up with him! OK there's something
fishy about this other tank. So before I spill too much blood on the other
tank. what I'm going to quickly do is just go and get a new Tank blueprint and pop it down.
in case we've fiddled with the parameters of that tank too much. Now there you go!
So look at that tank he goes back! He overshoots because of his
momentum. because remember he's applying forces to the tank he's not just
moving the tank position. so he goes full throttle backwards! He goes ooh no throttle. but he's over-
shooting because of the momentum and then he's going to try and move forward again. And that's
pretty cool right! The two tanks are moving forward and back.
so that they get broadside onto us. and they are obeying the
same physics that we have to. They have inertia. if they don't control
their tank right they overshoot just like we do. None of these perfect robotic tanks.
So that's a real result for this lecture! I hope you're glad with the result of that and
pleased with it. should I say. And I will see you in the next lecture!