So welcome to CrossProduct() Vector Operator! In
this video we are going to actually make the tanks not only move forward and backwards but be able to
turn as well. By the end of it we will have some crazy situation. something like this.
where these AI tanks are not exactly masters of their own movement but
they are moving and trying [laughs] to get towards us. despite all the slipping and flipping. So I will see you in there!
So the first thing I'm going to do is pop into VisualStudio
and just comment. temporarily. out the Intend... Ooh. [Laughs] ...Intend
MoveForward. without my Insert key on. and just compile that
back up. And what that's going to do. obviously. is just stop the tanks moving forward and backwards.
I just want to focus on their rotation. for a moment. entirely so we can see that
independently. So we'll freeze them in the forward backward direction. like that. and
now they'll just sit there again. They'll still aim. obviously. but they're just going to sit there.
Cool! So let's talk about how we want things to work. with regards to
rotation. So we have the AI providing this
same vector. So this tank here. right now. would probably have a vector heading straight
towards me. Whereas if he was around the hill. then remember he may have a vector that takes him
around the hill rather than straight towards me. and he has his local forward.
Remember you can use this little square for local stroke global. it has this local tank
forward. red. vector here. Now the question comes. how do we decide how to
rotate? We've done the forward and backwards. at least for now. and now we need to decide
how to rotate. So the deal is that if the tank is already... If
this guy was already facing us. like this. then it wouldn't need to rotate at
all. and if he was facing 90 degrees on. it would want to rotate as fast as
possible. It's almost exactly what we were doing before but like in reverse. pretty much.
So this is where the Sine Function comes in. Very much like the
Cosine Function. in fact. it's exactly the same shape. it's just shifted along by 90
degrees. So let's think it through! But firstly. what are the axes? Well the
X axis is the angle between the AIForwardIntention and the TankForward. just as before.
and the Y axis is the Throw that we're going to pass but this time to Intend
TurnRight(). rather than to IntendMoveForward. So
if there's not angle. i.e. if the AIForwardIntention is already
aligned with its. if it's already facing in the direction the AI wants it to go.
then how fast should we turn right? Not all all!
If we're 90 degrees out. it's going to turn right as fast as possible.
If we're 180 degrees out. it's not going to turn at all. Now we'll talk about that again
in a second. because that seems odd but it's OK. And if it's 270
degrees out. i.e. if it's on the right instead of the left or the left instead of the right.
then we go in the opposite direction. so this should
always turn us in the correct direction. So let's say that
90 degrees means that the tank wants to be going to its left.
sorry to its right. to its right. then that means it turns
right at full speed. If it wants to be going behind where
it is. then we'll talk about it in a sec. It looks like we do no
turn. but we'll think about what happen. And if the thing that it wants to go towards is to
the left of it. then it will turn right at a value of -1.
i.e. turn left. OK. hopefully I've gone through that slowly enough. You get the idea. Now let's
talk about this bit where I'm precisely behind the enemy tank. i.e. it's
sitting here. Let's put it in Rotate Mode. with the E key.
just as a reminder. If we're in this situation where I'm behind this other tank. what's it going to do?
Well the fact is I'm never going to be exactly behind it. These are floating
point values. these rotations. and I'm moving and the other tank
is likely to be moving forward or backwards.
so I'm never going to be exactly behind it. And if I am exactly behind
this guy. then the moment there's any deviation
from being behind it it's going to be unstable and its going to move up to one of these other
points. it's going to move away right. So what's going to happen is that if I'm
slightly to its left. behind it. then it's suddenly going to
turn left. turn left. turn left. turn left. and head towards me all right. vice
versa. So it's just going to move away from this point really quickly. it's not a stable
point. So we don't have to worry about the fact that this curve makes it not turn. when it's behind us.
Alright. so we need to Vector Cross Product. it's more complicated.
The Vector Cross Product is this thing here. it is the magnitude
of the two vectors that we're sending in. which remember is the same as before. These are these
AIForwardIntention and TankForward things
here. And we just group these a little differently.
Let's put ForwardThrow right next to where we call IntendMoveForward.
OK so we can just see these two vectors as independent. Great!
And then. it's sin of the angle between the two. different to before by 90
degrees. we've just talked about that. times n which is a unit vector
perpendicular to the plane. it says the plane in Wikipedia. What it's talking about is the plane
defined by a and b. So a and b create a plane. just like
over in Unreal here. If we click on this dude the red and the green
arrows say. define the ground play. blue is perpendicular to it.
And the direction that it's in depends on the left-hand rule. If you
put your left hand out now and you put say your
thumb along the red... Well let's do this so it's easy. Put your forefinger along
the red line. your index finder. and then. put your next finger along your middle
finger. on your left hand. down the green arrow and your thumb pointing upwards.
That's the left-hand rule! So the X is your index finger.
the Y. the green. is your middle finger. and then. your thumb. in this case.
tells you which direction the Z would be in. or the n vector. so
it is directional. Let's look at a table a bit like we had before.
It takes two FVectors on the input. but the order of them matters now. The
order that you cross these things in actually does matter; if you swap an and b around
then the direction of n changes. it swaps. The output's an
FVector this time. previously we had a float. What does it do? It kind of measures
this perpendicularity. it tells how perpendicular these guys are. You can
get a maximum vector out of this thing. when the two things are at right angles and a
minimum vector when they're parallel. so that's perfect! So when the
AIForwardIntention and
the TankForward are parallel. then you get 0.
and when they're perpendicular you get a maximum value.
The vector you get out is always orthogonal to both. Orthogonal means pointing in the
other direction. it's perpendicular to both of them exactly like these axes.
The only difference from these axes is. of course. the green and the red could squeeze in together or go
opposite and we'll look at that in a second. So in a
diagram we've got this. This is a and b down the same thing. this is us pointing at the enemy tank. This
now is where we are and the enemy tank or the
targeted tank is precisely to our left. Forget the magenta line for a minute.
In this case. the targeted tank is precisely behind us and there is no
turning going on. and then. as the animated .gif comes around.
this is where the targeted tank is on the right of us. Now the magenta
line is the cross product. So if it's on the right. it's demanding a rotation. it's
representing a rotation. Now it's weird that it's a vector but that's just how it is.
and you'll see how we use that in a moment. So in this case. there's no rotation. now magenta line.
When we see a target on our left. we rotate as fast as possible
to the right. That's what an upward arrow is going mean. rotate as fast as possible to the right
to get back towards facing it. When it's behind us we don't rotate at all. but
as I've said. as soon as we start rotating we'll continue rotating in that
direction. And then if our target's on the right-hand
side. then this arrow is representing us wanting to turn left. as fast as possible. You
can read all about that on Wikipedia. if you want to find more about the Cross Product.
What I want to do now is get into actually using it. so just like before
you can do this. but I've just got one more thing to tell you. It's a vector that
comes out of the Cross Product. and we also need to think about what would happen if the tank was
on a hill. Let's say that we're not just constrained to a plane
here. But this tank is kind of sitting up on a hillside like
this and has fallen down and is let's say rotated a little bit. because it's
sitting on the hill. then what are it's vectors doing? Well the Forward
Intention vector may be a 3 dimensional vector from this tank down to this tank. but the
forward vector is here. But that's OK. the Cross Product will
still be a vector pointing up. something like the blue arrow. It'll be a different angle
to the blue. but it'll be pointing up kind of up and right here. But it still has a
Z component. a component in the World Space up directoin.
So these two vectors that... Sorry I'm supposed to go to the code.
These two vectors. that we're going to be taking a Cross Product of. are both in World
Space. The TankForward and the AIForwardIntention are in World
Space. So whereas I've been demonstrating TankForward using
the local coordinates. the TankForward as far as what we're getting out of the code is
actually that red arrow there. so it's world space. And then. the
vector that we are getting for AI
ForwardIntention is also in World Space. and. in this
case. would probably be a line pretty much straight from this tank down to this tank. it would drive it down the hill.
OK. so what you get out of this. out of the Cross Product. also should
be interpreted as a World Space vector. and it won't be parallel to the
ground but we can just look at its Z component. i.e. the component around the blue
line here. to find out whether we should rotate left or right. as far as gravity is
concerned. So we're determining our rotations based on gravity.
Alright. let's put this tank back in terms of rotations. probably the easiest
just to reset the rotator here. I'm going to put it back in terms of location.
And then. I'm going to give you a challenge.
which is I want you to cross AIForwardIntention and TankForward. just like we did
before. but find the Z component of the resulting vector. that's just a dot Z.
And feed the result into IntendTurnRight(). then share the resulting movement with the
community. ideally on community.gamedev.tv in the Unreal section.
under the Battle Tank subsection. See you soon!
OK
welcome back! So let's have a go at this then! So we're going to have an auto
RightThrow
= FVector:: there's a static method on FVector called Cross
Product. These are really handy. we'll use these things a lot. So which way around do we do these? Frankly
we need to just try it! We could reason it with a left-hand rule and think
about which way things are increasing. but it's much easier and quicker just to
have the framework. which is if we get it wrong it's going to rotate in the wrong direction. and
try it one way. I've actually got a feeling that what I'm doing is the wrong way. but I don't mind
making that mistake. we can correct it. OK. so I get the CrossProduct between
the two. Now. the RightThrow isn't just that. because look these types are
incompatible. The RightThrow is currently coming out
as an FVector. you see that. Because the CrossProduct returns a vector ForwardThrow.
came out as a float. but the right flow is an FVector. That's why. well one of the reasons why we need
to take the Z component of it. Now if we look at the type of RightThrow it's a
float. IntendTurnRight
with (RightThrow). OK let's
try it! This may be the wrong way to be doing the CrossProduct.
and let's see the symptoms. if it is the wrong way of doing the Cross Product.
It's just simply quicker to try it both ways.
in this simple case. than it is to be working out what it should be. Now
is this guy turning towards us? No not really. Let's try the other guy.
Let's just move this other guy in front.
He's trying but they're not really turning
to face us. Now I'm not convinced. Let's just put him off
to that side.
OK I'm not convinced they're turning to face us. Let's try
doing it around the other way.
Recompile. and then if it works what we'll
do just very briefly at the end is turn the forward movement back on and see what the total
movement looks like. OK let's have a look now!
No. I think that's worse! O.K. so what I'm going to do is
swap them back to how they were.
And then. I'm going to turn in
the forward movement as well. and then. let's compile
that and see how the total behavior is. In fact. I'm going to get my controller on
and get ready to run away from these tanks. just in case it works.
So play the game. F11. OK now let's see what happens! I'm
going to move out of the way. have a little look around. Ooh. I'm very slippy! We'll sort
the slippy-ness out later. How are these guys doing? Yeah. he's coming
towards me. trying to broadside me. I think one of the reasons
they're not behaving right... Let's just have a look at the Nav Mesh! Hit P... Ah look. there's a big hole in the Nav
Mesh! You see that? This guy's sitting near an edge of the Nav Mesh. and if he slides
into the hole in the Nav Mesh then we're in trouble. because
he's not going to be able to navigate any longer. So what I'm going to do. just to
sort that out very quickly. is to go to the World. go to the NavMeshBounds. lift them up a little bit.
let them recalculate. so that this hole over here that this tank is near to
gets filled in. And then. replay the game.
hit F11 so you can see better. [Laughs] This is fun!
You see these tanks are being forced to use our control system. It's balmy tank battles here!
And the acceptance radius isn't working. at the moment. in that they're coming all the way
up to us. but look we've got movement! We've got a kind of fun game. we've got weird
AI tank behavior. they're chasing us and they're aiming at us! So congratulations
on some sort of tank movement. We've still got bugs with them hitting the ground. we've got
all sorts going on. but it's fun and the game is still fun.
so this is what we're after! Alright. see you in the next video!
=======
So welcome to CrossProduct() Vector Operator! In
this video we are going to actually make the tanks not only move forward and backwards but be able to
turn as well. By the end of it we will have some crazy situation, something like this,
where these AI tanks are not exactly masters of their own movement but
they are moving and trying [laughs] to get towards us, despite all the slipping and flipping. So I will see you in there!
So the first thing I'm going to do is pop into VisualStudio
and just comment, temporarily, out the Intend... Ooh. [Laughs] ...Intend
MoveForward, without my Insert key on, and just compile that
back up. And what that's going to do, obviously, is just stop the tanks moving forward and backwards.
I just want to focus on their rotation, for a moment, entirely so we can see that
independently. So we'll freeze them in the forward backward direction, like that, and
now they'll just sit there again. They'll still aim, obviously, but they're just going to sit there.
Cool! So let's talk about how we want things to work, with regards to
rotation. So we have the AI providing this
same vector. So this tank here, right now, would probably have a vector heading straight
towards me. Whereas if he was around the hill, then remember he may have a vector that takes him
around the hill rather than straight towards me, and he has his local forward.
Remember you can use this little square for local stroke global, it has this local tank
forward, red, vector here. Now the question comes, how do we decide how to
rotate? We've done the forward and backwards, at least for now, and now we need to decide
how to rotate. So the deal is that if the tank is already... If
this guy was already facing us, like this, then it wouldn't need to rotate at
all, and if he was facing 90 degrees on, it would want to rotate as fast as
possible. It's almost exactly what we were doing before but like in reverse, pretty much.
So this is where the Sine Function comes in. Very much like the
Cosine Function, in fact, it's exactly the same shape, it's just shifted along by 90
degrees. So let's think it through! But firstly, what are the axes? Well the
X axis is the angle between the AIForwardIntention and the TankForward, just as before,
and the Y axis is the Throw that we're going to pass but this time to Intend
TurnRight(), rather than to IntendMoveForward. So
if there's not angle, i.e. if the AIForwardIntention is already
aligned with its, if it's already facing in the direction the AI wants it to go,
then how fast should we turn right? Not all all!
If we're 90 degrees out, it's going to turn right as fast as possible.
If we're 180 degrees out, it's not going to turn at all. Now we'll talk about that again
in a second, because that seems odd but it's OK. And if it's 270
degrees out, i.e. if it's on the right instead of the left or the left instead of the right,
then we go in the opposite direction, so this should
always turn us in the correct direction. So let's say that
90 degrees means that the tank wants to be going to its left,
sorry to its right, to its right, then that means it turns
right at full speed. If it wants to be going behind where
it is, then we'll talk about it in a sec. It looks like we do no
turn, but we'll think about what happen. And if the thing that it wants to go towards is to
the left of it, then it will turn right at a value of -1,
i.e. turn left. OK, hopefully I've gone through that slowly enough. You get the idea. Now let's
talk about this bit where I'm precisely behind the enemy tank, i.e. it's
sitting here. Let's put it in Rotate Mode, with the E key,
just as a reminder. If we're in this situation where I'm behind this other tank, what's it going to do?
Well the fact is I'm never going to be exactly behind it. These are floating
point values, these rotations, and I'm moving and the other tank
is likely to be moving forward or backwards,
so I'm never going to be exactly behind it. And if I am exactly behind
this guy, then the moment there's any deviation
from being behind it it's going to be unstable and its going to move up to one of these other
points, it's going to move away right. So what's going to happen is that if I'm
slightly to its left, behind it, then it's suddenly going to
turn left, turn left, turn left, turn left, and head towards me all right, vice
versa. So it's just going to move away from this point really quickly, it's not a stable
point. So we don't have to worry about the fact that this curve makes it not turn, when it's behind us.
Alright, so we need to Vector Cross Product, it's more complicated.
The Vector Cross Product is this thing here, it is the magnitude
of the two vectors that we're sending in, which remember is the same as before. These are these
AIForwardIntention and TankForward things
here. And we just group these a little differently.
Let's put ForwardThrow right next to where we call IntendMoveForward.
OK so we can just see these two vectors as independent. Great!
And then, it's sin of the angle between the two, different to before by 90
degrees, we've just talked about that, times n which is a unit vector
perpendicular to the plane, it says the plane in Wikipedia. What it's talking about is the plane
defined by a and b. So a and b create a plane, just like
over in Unreal here. If we click on this dude the red and the green
arrows say, define the ground play, blue is perpendicular to it.
And the direction that it's in depends on the left-hand rule. If you
put your left hand out now and you put say your
thumb along the red... Well let's do this so it's easy. Put your forefinger along
the red line, your index finder, and then, put your next finger along your middle
finger, on your left hand, down the green arrow and your thumb pointing upwards.
That's the left-hand rule! So the X is your index finger,
the Y, the green, is your middle finger, and then, your thumb, in this case,
tells you which direction the Z would be in, or the n vector, so
it is directional. Let's look at a table a bit like we had before.
It takes two FVectors on the input, but the order of them matters now. The
order that you cross these things in actually does matter; if you swap an and b around
then the direction of n changes, it swaps. The output's an
FVector this time, previously we had a float. What does it do? It kind of measures
this perpendicularity, it tells how perpendicular these guys are. You can
get a maximum vector out of this thing, when the two things are at right angles and a
minimum vector when they're parallel, so that's perfect! So when the
AIForwardIntention and
the TankForward are parallel, then you get 0,
and when they're perpendicular you get a maximum value.
The vector you get out is always orthogonal to both. Orthogonal means pointing in the
other direction, it's perpendicular to both of them exactly like these axes.
The only difference from these axes is, of course, the green and the red could squeeze in together or go
opposite and we'll look at that in a second. So in a
diagram we've got this. This is a and b down the same thing, this is us pointing at the enemy tank. This
now is where we are and the enemy tank or the
targeted tank is precisely to our left. Forget the magenta line for a minute.
In this case, the targeted tank is precisely behind us and there is no
turning going on, and then, as the animated .gif comes around,
this is where the targeted tank is on the right of us. Now the magenta
line is the cross product. So if it's on the right, it's demanding a rotation, it's
representing a rotation. Now it's weird that it's a vector but that's just how it is,
and you'll see how we use that in a moment. So in this case, there's no rotation, now magenta line.
When we see a target on our left, we rotate as fast as possible
to the right. That's what an upward arrow is going mean, rotate as fast as possible to the right
to get back towards facing it. When it's behind us we don't rotate at all, but
as I've said, as soon as we start rotating we'll continue rotating in that
direction. And then if our target's on the right-hand
side, then this arrow is representing us wanting to turn left, as fast as possible. You
can read all about that on Wikipedia, if you want to find more about the Cross Product.
What I want to do now is get into actually using it, so just like before
you can do this, but I've just got one more thing to tell you. It's a vector that
comes out of the Cross Product, and we also need to think about what would happen if the tank was
on a hill. Let's say that we're not just constrained to a plane
here. But this tank is kind of sitting up on a hillside like
this and has fallen down and is let's say rotated a little bit, because it's
sitting on the hill, then what are it's vectors doing? Well the Forward
Intention vector may be a 3 dimensional vector from this tank down to this tank, but the
forward vector is here. But that's OK, the Cross Product will
still be a vector pointing up, something like the blue arrow. It'll be a different angle
to the blue, but it'll be pointing up kind of up and right here. But it still has a
Z component, a component in the World Space up directoin.
So these two vectors that... Sorry I'm supposed to go to the code.
These two vectors, that we're going to be taking a Cross Product of, are both in World
Space. The TankForward and the AIForwardIntention are in World
Space. So whereas I've been demonstrating TankForward using
the local coordinates, the TankForward as far as what we're getting out of the code is
actually that red arrow there, so it's world space. And then, the
vector that we are getting for AI
ForwardIntention is also in World Space, and, in this
case, would probably be a line pretty much straight from this tank down to this tank, it would drive it down the hill.
OK, so what you get out of this, out of the Cross Product, also should
be interpreted as a World Space vector, and it won't be parallel to the
ground but we can just look at its Z component, i.e. the component around the blue
line here, to find out whether we should rotate left or right, as far as gravity is
concerned. So we're determining our rotations based on gravity.
Alright, let's put this tank back in terms of rotations, probably the easiest
just to reset the rotator here. I'm going to put it back in terms of location.
And then, I'm going to give you a challenge,
which is I want you to cross AIForwardIntention and TankForward, just like we did
before, but find the Z component of the resulting vector, that's just a dot Z.
And feed the result into IntendTurnRight(), then share the resulting movement with the
community, ideally on community.gamedev.tv in the Unreal section,
under the Battle Tank subsection. See you soon!
OK
welcome back! So let's have a go at this then! So we're going to have an auto
RightThrow
= FVector:: there's a static method on FVector called Cross
Product. These are really handy, we'll use these things a lot. So which way around do we do these? Frankly
we need to just try it! We could reason it with a left-hand rule and think
about which way things are increasing, but it's much easier and quicker just to
have the framework, which is if we get it wrong it's going to rotate in the wrong direction, and
try it one way. I've actually got a feeling that what I'm doing is the wrong way, but I don't mind
making that mistake, we can correct it. OK, so I get the CrossProduct between
the two. Now, the RightThrow isn't just that, because look these types are
incompatible. The RightThrow is currently coming out
as an FVector, you see that. Because the CrossProduct returns a vector ForwardThrow,
came out as a float, but the right flow is an FVector. That's why, well one of the reasons why we need
to take the Z component of it. Now if we look at the type of RightThrow it's a
float. IntendTurnRight
with (RightThrow). OK let's
try it! This may be the wrong way to be doing the CrossProduct,
and let's see the symptoms, if it is the wrong way of doing the Cross Product.
It's just simply quicker to try it both ways,
in this simple case, than it is to be working out what it should be. Now
is this guy turning towards us? No not really. Let's try the other guy.
Let's just move this other guy in front.
He's trying but they're not really turning
to face us. Now I'm not convinced. Let's just put him off
to that side.
OK I'm not convinced they're turning to face us. Let's try
doing it around the other way.
Recompile, and then if it works what we'll
do just very briefly at the end is turn the forward movement back on and see what the total
movement looks like. OK let's have a look now!
No, I think that's worse! O.K. so what I'm going to do is
swap them back to how they were.
And then, I'm going to turn in
the forward movement as well, and then, let's compile
that and see how the total behavior is. In fact, I'm going to get my controller on
and get ready to run away from these tanks, just in case it works.
So play the game, F11. OK now let's see what happens! I'm
going to move out of the way, have a little look around. Ooh, I'm very slippy! We'll sort
the slippy-ness out later. How are these guys doing? Yeah, he's coming
towards me, trying to broadside me. I think one of the reasons
they're not behaving right... Let's just have a look at the Nav Mesh! Hit P... Ah look, there's a big hole in the Nav
Mesh! You see that? This guy's sitting near an edge of the Nav Mesh, and if he slides
into the hole in the Nav Mesh then we're in trouble, because
he's not going to be able to navigate any longer. So what I'm going to do, just to
sort that out very quickly, is to go to the World, go to the NavMeshBounds, lift them up a little bit,
let them recalculate, so that this hole over here that this tank is near to
gets filled in. And then, replay the game,
hit F11 so you can see better. [Laughs] This is fun!
You see these tanks are being forced to use our control system. It's balmy tank battles here!
And the acceptance radius isn't working, at the moment, in that they're coming all the way
up to us, but look we've got movement! We've got a kind of fun game, we've got weird
AI tank behavior, they're chasing us and they're aiming at us! So congratulations
on some sort of tank movement. We've still got bugs with them hitting the ground, we've got
all sorts going on, but it's fun and the game is still fun,
so this is what we're after! Alright, see you in the next video!
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1:Unreal/Section4/BT63 CrossProduct() Vector Operator.srt