So welcome to using Enum
(erations), Enumerations in Unreal Engine 4! What we're going to be doing,
by the end of this video, is wiring up something, which I think is quite nice, here in the blueprint. We're going
to have all of the colors that we want for various different tank aiming states, reloading, aiming,
and locked right here in the Designer, and the minimal amount of Blueprint we need.
And then over in the C++ we're going to create a firing state Enum.
Now creating Enums is a little different in UE4, we'll see how, and then we're going to use that
in an event driven way, to change the color of the aiming
reticle in front of us, automatically as the aiming component state changes. So that will be pretty fun!
So we talked about the idea that the TankAimingComponent could be in one of
three possible states. Those states are, firstly, we would start in
reloading, i.e. the cursor is red, and we are not able to fire right now because
the tank has not finished reloading. The moment it's finished reloading it would go to amber if the
barrel's moving or green if the barrel has stopped moving. So that's one of
three possible states. Reloading, aiming like
this where the barrel is moving, or the final
state is locked, which means it's loaded,
ready to go, and the barrel has stopped moving. So we've got
reloading, aiming, and locked. Alright now they are three different states
that the TankAimingComponent could be in. How do you
encode those sort of states? Well a meaningful way to encode these states is not
using numbers. Although behind the scenes it's going to be using numbers, we want to use an Enum.
Remember around lecture 35 we used an Enum in the Bull Cow game?
We're going to revisit using Enums. Now it's a little bit different in
Unreal. If we look at Unreal's coding standards
the way that we did it in the Bull Cow game... In fact, we should go and look at the way we did it
in the Bull Cow game, just for a second. That could be fun, just so we can see our code! I think I'll do it
the way that you would be able to do it, which is to go to Github and
then go to the Unreal course. So Github.com forward slash UnrealCourse. We go back
to BullCowGame. I'll just go look at the final code,
I think here. I think it's in FBullCowGame.h. And remember that we did this
Enum class, we made it a strongly typed Enum, and we called it EGuessStatus,
prefixed with E because it's an Unreal coding standard, and then we had all these different Guess
statuses. We're going to do something very much like this, but we're going to have three
statuses, which as I said are going to be reloading, aiming, and locked
alright, but you can't just do this in Unreal. Yes you'll put
your Enum class above the main class. So here in TankAimingComponent.h,
yes it will go in here or it could go above
here, but I'm going to put it here. In fact, no I'm not, I'm going to
put it above the forward declarations, because the forward declarations are, if you like, to do with
this class below it. That's where they're used. So I'm going to put my Enums here, "// Enum
for aiming state" is going to go here. But you can't just
put it in just like this, because there are two things you need to do that are different. Let's look at the Unreal coding
standards.
And if you go there to the Coding Standard, and this link is in your
resources for the lecture, and then you look for Strongly-Typed Enums you'll get this. You'll see
that the new way of doing things is like this. Very much like we did before but two changes. Number one,
you need to annotate with UENUM. This is
a preprocessor directive, for the Unreal Header Tool, and it just needs to
know that you're declaring an Enum here. It's to do with something called the reflection system, we don't need to go into that now.
Advanced people have got a link that will tell them a bit more about this UENUM()
type it uses behind the scenes, that's in resources. But for the rest of you, you just need know when you're declaring
an Enum you need to put UENUM(). And the other thing is, you need to tell it the underlying data type you
want that Enum to use. This is presumably for cross platform
independence and perhaps for performance reasons as well. Now it's using a
uint8 standard, which is fine. That's an 8 bit
integer, which means between 0 and 255. In other words, you have
256 different possible members you could put in your Enum, so that is plenty
for us. Alright, and then when you want to go ahead and actually use
the Enum, you of course use it in the same way as we did back in the Bull Cow
Game. And I'm going to leave that to you, as part of a challenge. So I want you to create an
Enum called EFiringStatus. Use the following pattern UENUM() and then
on the next line enum class and then EFiringStatus
: uint8, use uint8 that's fine for what we have.
Remember, of course, you can introduce new lines here and I encourage you to do so,
before the curly braces, and then we want, it doesn't matter which order, but locked
aiming and reloading. I'm going to go in the order of reloading, aiming, and locked because
that's kind of the order things happen in. Then, I want you to specify those three,
which we just talked about, and then create a private member variable inside
the TankAimingComponent and initialize it to the reloading
state. And then, don't connect it up in Blueprint,
ignore that. So initialize it to the reloading state and that's it! See if you can write this
and get it to compile. So go ahead, pause the video, and do that now.
OK welcome
back! Let's see how this works! So here we are, UENUM().
We've just got to do that first or it won't work. And then, what does it
say? "enum class" thingy. OK so enum class,
E because it's the coding standard. EFiringState:
and then it wants us to specify a uint8.
OK fantastic! And now we can come into
our curly braces and start saying what we want. Well I want Reloading,
Aiming,
and Locked. OK that I think is the declaration
of the ENUM. We have now EFiringState as a type,
so we can come down here into private and we can say...
Here...
FiringState... Actually, type is EFiringState
FiringState = and then you have to qualify it EFiringState: :
Reloading; So there you have
declared a variable, which is a variable of type EFiringState
which can only take the values of EFiringState, these guys up here. And we are
initializing it to Reloading. Let's go ahead and make sure this
compiles now, and then, I will show you some stuff in Blueprint if it compiles
and works. Because we're going to be able to very nicely access
that in Blueprint and then allow the designer part of ourselves to
assign colors to the different states in Blueprint, which is where you want to be doing it right?
And that's where we've got the nice color pickers and all the rest of it. So the compile is
complete. If we come into the tank PlayerUI blueprint... Now let's just take a
step back, remember that what we did is in the Tank Player Controller, that thing that
gels the tank that it's controlling to the Player UI.
We set this Blueprint Aiming Component Reference variable, a Blueprint variable...
[Laughs] blue plint... Hey Blueprint variable. Where is that variable?
It's in the Player UI blueprint, under the My Blueprint tab, and then, if you scroll
down under variables you get this BP Aiming Component Reference. Let's get that!
If you drag from that now, then well you're not going to
have actually this FiringState. Why not? Four marks if you can tell
why. So over here, what we need to do is make this FiringState available to the Blueprint!
There's two things we need to do for that. Firstly, we need to make it a UPROPERTY
and (BlueprintReadOnly) seems appropriate.
And then, we do need to give a Category, and I'm going to call it
"State"). That'll be fine! OK and
in quotes from now on remember. Now I'm going to move this up! Why am I moving it up? Because it needs to be
protected doesn't it? We are asking to access this
property from a subclass. What's the subclass? The subclass
is the TankAimingComponent blueprint. Remember that the parent is the
C++ class, so it needs to be in protected. And
if you want, you can put those out as a comment, and it needs to be a UPROPERTY. Let's go ahead and
recompile! Then, what we're hoping to find is that, when we
come off this BP Aiming Component that we will actually be able to find this
state. What's it called? It's called FiringState! So
once the compile is complete we come off here, we say Get Firing State.
Fantastic! Now what comes off the back of Get Firing State? It's an ENUM! Cool!
So with an ENUM look what we can do! One of the things we can do is select. Let's
choose Select. So we go from the AimingComponent, we find the FiringState,
because we've made it a UPROPERTY, and then, we go and find the ENUM. Look Reloading,
Aiming, Locked, that's all come through. Perfect! Now look what we can do! This is pretty cool!
We need to create a color. Now there are lots of ways you
can create colors here, but most of them require more than
one node. Even the Make Color doesn't require more than one node, but if it does if
you want a color picker, alright. So the node that I found that allows you to make a
color and have a color picker all in one is, simply to use the
Select Color node. So search for select color the American way, no U's in your color.
And then, what we're going to do is we're going to have three of these nodes. So I'm going to use...
I think I'm going to use B actually. This boolean here lets you pick
A, but it'll pick B by default, so let's use B for red.
Remember to slide
this up, which is your value in the H, S, V, the Hue, Saturation, and Value.
This slider is the Value, remember to slide that up. That is red,
and then that's what we should use for reloading. So we pick a red. We're not picking
A, we're picking B, and that's Reloading. Great! Now let's duplicate that and
pick the next color down. So Duplicate.
I'm going to make this one an amber, OK
picking B and that's going to be the Aiming.
OK and then finally, I'm going to paste this in again.
Copy and Paste, I use Control C and Control V there, in this case.
I'm going to pick a different color, a different color, a different color a green, not
too garish a green, and into Locked. So hopefully you can see what's
happening there. All of these nodes are not picking A, they're picking B by
default. That's why I'm choosing that, so we don't even have to tick these boxes. We
have the FiringState ENUM coming in from the Aiming Component,
and then, what we do with the Return Value, which is now a color,
because colors come in and colors go out, it's polymorphic, it can change with the
type. Then, we do this! It's event driven, we don't really care when this ENUM
changes, but when the ENUM does change, we want to change the color of the node.
Let's Compile and see. Now what did we initialize
to in the code? We initialize to Reloading. If we look over in the blueprint,
we would expect that to be red. So let's see if it is, let's play the game!
We get a crash, that's not super unusual with Unreal.
So I'm going to reload. Now sometimes that's because one of my categories...
When I make changes, sometimes that's because one of my categories in a recent bug is not
in quotes here. So we will, as we go through, make sure all our categories are in
quotes. You're welcome to stop the video and go and do that with all your category equals statements, if you like.
Restore my assets. See
what we've got in the graph. Now, unfortunately I didn't save, so I'm going to quickly put that back together.
OK let's try playing the game now that it's fixed!
Ah it's red! Perfect! So the final thing is just to check that that is actually coming through from the
code. We can't unfortunately just expose it and change it, because if you remember
the way, if we go to the tank blueprint, the way that we're doing this is an inherited component,
it has no details exposed. We're going to fix that soon, but for now,
let's just go back to the code for the sake of one short compile.
Change this state to, I don't know what do you want? Let's say
Aiming in the
declaration here, and then, let's go and recompile the code.
And all I'm going to do is just check that that comes through and that if we have
Aiming as a default. Is Aiming one that I set? Yep, Aiming!
Then, when we go through to the blueprint, we look at the color we're setting under Aiming.
It's amber, let's see if we end up amber. We do! Perfect!
So now we have the ability to change the reticle color, based on the
state of the Tank Aiming Component. So up next, we're going to give the Tank Aiming Component
a little bit more love, so that it is doing exactly what we want it to do.