So hey. welcome back
and welcome to Refactoring our Aiming Component. What we're going to do in this video is. we're going
to change the architecture of the AimingComponent to use a single initialize method like
this. just like the Movement Component did. and then. to strip a whole load of code
out of the tank and start moving the functionality over to the AimingComponent. And yeah.
we're going to hit a brick wall in it. but I want you to hit that brick wall yourself.
Or you may not. you may do things slightly better than I have. but I want you to try and do this
reorganization. So look back at the video where we setup the Tank
MovementComponent. and see if you can get the TankAimingComponent to the
same sort of architecture. where it is actually added here in
the Blueprint Editor and not added as
a default sub-object. So refactor the AimingComponent. try and move the Aiming
Component to the same architecture. as I said. Don't worry if you can't get it working. but see if
you can get it at least as far as compiling. If you find your game hard crashes when you play
or something. don't worry too much. but just see if you can get compiling and connected up in
Blueprint. like I've got there. And that's going to be a great exercise for you! If you
struggle with this. don't worry. it's a pretty open-ended exercise. You're very welcome to stop and
just follow my solution. You don't need to feel bad about it. I'm setting a pretty nebulous challenge
to allow for lots of different ranges of abilities to get their teeth stuck into this.
OK so go ahead. pause the video. have a go at that. and when I come back. I will be going through
and doing the refactor myself with you.
So just before we dive in and start refactoring. let's just give ourselves a little bit of context.
Remember that the Movement Component is nicely separated with the Left and Right
Tracks. only bound to that component. but the Aiming Component still has this messy
loop. where the Tank has reference to the Barrel and they have these setters
being passed down. etc. So what we're going to do is move the Aiming Component into the same
paradigm as the Movement Component. that is added in Blueprint using an Initialize()
method. etc. So I'm going to go through this with you and do some refactoring. You're welcome to try and do
the refactor yourself. You know the experienced among you can certainly do that. just
bring the Aiming Component into the same pattern as the Movement Component. And then. I'm going to lead us to
the point at which we have a horrible hard crash. which will be with no particularly obvious
source. and then. we're going to use the debugger. the VisualStudio debugger
to actually fix that up. So let's just start this refactor process.
Let's have the tank blueprint open. so we can remind ourselves that one of the things we are
trying to get rid of is this Set Turret and Set Barrel Reference.
In fact. let's be brave and just delete them. we don't need those anymore. We're going to have an Initialize()
method on our TankAimingComponent. of course. So let's go
break some stuff! Over in the tank header file. let's start off!
I think I'm actually going to start at the top and just fix up my copyright notice. as I
did in the TankMovementComponent. So let's just do the Copyright notice for the tank header
file and the TankAimingComponent header file.
They're the two things we're going to be working on. It kind of signals to me. I've touched this thing recently.
Sure if I had of set it in the Project Settings in the beginning then it'd be set. but whenever
you notice a problem like this. let's fix it as we go. So in the tank header file we have this
SetTurret and SetBarrel reference. Don't need them. let's get rid of them! Both the SetTurret and SetBarrel
References. Let's remove those and let's remove the code that actually does that setting.
So that's great! We can also get rid of. in the ATank
BeginPlay(). you'll notice we're not using it. so let's just ditch it. And let's ditch it from the
header file as well. if it's in there. You can always put it back. it's really easy to put back again
OK. And SetupPlayerInputComponent. we're not using that either. so I'm taking Setup
PlayerInputComponent out of the Tank as well. as we're trying to clear
up the Tank. Let's clear it up properly! OK. now over in the Tank.
the other thing that we're doing is creating a default sub-object of a TankAimingComponent.
Remember what that does? It makes this TankAimingComponent inherited here. which we don't have
any details for. and it's different to the TankMovementComponent. so we're going to stop doing
that! Let's delete the TankAimingComponent DefaultSubobjectCreation there.
and then. let's
recompile. I think it'll recompile at this stage.
Now. I did a lot of code in a very short amount of time there. so what I'll do is I'll do you the favor.
Now that hitting Compile has saved all the tabs in VisualStudio. I can  come
into SourceTree. while it compiles. and I can show you what I've done. I've deleted a load of code from the
Tank.cpp. all of this stuff that you can see on the screen there. I'll leave it for you for a second.
And then. you can see what I've done in the header file.
removed the relevant references that's all. and then. in the AimingComponent I've just
changed my Copyright notice. OK. so there are the changes. Now the hot reload worked.
Now lets go look at the tank blueprint! We no longer have this inherited TankAimingComponent.
Fantastic! So let's add it back! Now. will it be visible? Well it will be visible in the
Custom section. if we made it the correct type of U...
Well let's go and have a look! Remember in the TankMovementComponent header file.
we annotated as a (BlueprintSpawnableComponent).
Well let's go and have a look in the TankAimingComponent header
file. and it is already a (BlueprintSpawnableComponent). If
yours isn't. of course. you need this annotation on the TankAimingComponent. Great! So
because it's BlueprintSpawnable I can come in here and I can add it as a
TankAimingComponent. Great! There it is looking just like the TankMovementComponent. and we can
actually see the properties on it now. That's fun! Now what we need is one of these Initialize()
methods for the TankMovementComponent. So I'm going to go... Ah sorry. not for
the TankAimingComponent. I'm going to go look at the TankMovementComponent's Initialize() method. and
I think I won't copy it because it's so different but I just want to remind
myself how that works. I'm using the English spelling of Initialise and I'm just
setting some references. So on the TankAimingComponent. we have
these pointers to the Barrel and Turret. which is great! We don't need them on the tank anymore.
by the way. So if you look at the tank. we don't need a Barrel reference anymore. Let's delete that from the
Tank. that's no longer necessary. And then. in the Tank
AimingComponent we're going to need a new Initialize() method. Now it's going to need to be public.
isn't it? And it's also going to need to have the same signature as it does in the MovementComponent. so
I will use the MovementComponent for that. Here (BlueprintCallable. Category
= "Setup") and then it's this Initialize. So let's just use that as inspiration.
And then. be very careful to immediately change it from a UTank
Track pointer to a UTank
Barrel pointer and a UTank
Turret pointer. And then. it's
going to be BarrelToSet
and TurretToSet. OK so we've made an
Initialize here. Let's go and define that now over in the .cpp.
I'm going to do it in place of. actually. We don't need anymore of
this SetBarrelReference and SetTurretReference. We're replacing those with just
a single initializer there. which just says Barrel =
BarrelToSet and Turret
= TurretToSet. No need to protect
these incoming values. if they're null well we're going to get null. That's fine!
OK. now I removed a couple of setters from the TankAiming
Component. so these two SetBarrel and SetTurretReferences they can go in the same Aiming
Component. we simply don't need those anymore. And the TankAimingComponent is reduced down to
a constructor. which actually because of Unreal magic we can put in the private section.
and I'm going to prefer to do that just so it gets it out of my public interface. Then. I have an Initialize
which takes a couple of things and an AimAt. Protected. we
have this FiringState. which we did a couple of videos ago. So yeah. we're all good to
go! Let's just have a little recompile of this code. see if we
missed anything. If it compiles. then I'll show you
the code changes. and then. we'll start to create the actual problem
because I've missed something. Some of you may have seen what I've missed here.
I've done this refactoring. let's just see what compile error I have.
" 'Barrel': undeclared identifier" in TankAimingComponent 22.
OK that's an interesting error. That error has nothing to do with the fact that
it's an undeclared identifier. It's because. earlier on. when I made
this Initialize method I didn't put
the class in front of it. so the compiler has read through that. got very confused. and thinks
the error is on line 22. whereas it's actually on 20. So let's recompile! That's definitely
worth knowing! So when you see an error. just zoom out a little bit. don't get
super focused on it. Ooh. it doesn't understand what this Barrel is! Yeah. but it doesn't understand what the Barrel is
because it got stuck trying to read the line before. Yeah. so don't really trust
the errors too too much. So we have another compile failure. which is again on
line 27. We have a Barrel it doesn't understand.
and that is because. in the Tank. I got rid of the Barrel
reference. I'm going to pop the Barrel reference back in the Tank. for the moment. in it's header file.
Why? Because we are not dealing
with taking out this code in the Tank. the Fire code right now.
so let's put that back. Now the source control will tell me
what I took out of the tank header file. right now. and you can see one of the things I
took out was this Barrel reference. So I'm going to put it back by copying
it from source control. popping it back in like that. OK it's got a few extra characters with
it but we'll live. But I'm going to say "// TODO
Remove". because we know we're going to have to remove this at some point. because we want all of this stuff to go
over to the AimingComponent. That's not the idea now. we're trying to do as little as possible.
while it still compiles. We're just trying to get our thing compiling again. OK. so let's go back and
Compile. Don't boil the ocean here! You should be having a feeling. at
this point. that you're a long way from a piece of compilable code. and that should worry you
because you may not be able to get back to compilation. which means you'd need to revert to your
previous commit. which would be a waste of your time. So hurry up to get it compiled!
There you go. it has compiled! That is good! Alright. and that's all
working. So let's Save All in here and then go into the
tank blueprint. and we should now have. if we search for "initialize". a
Tank Aiming Component initializer. We do! That's Fantastic! So let's now
do the TankAimingComponent initialization. It doesn't matter
whether it's done before or after the MovementComponent. the key is that we soft reference this Barrel
and this Turret. here in
the blueprint.
Great OK. so that is done! So let's just compile
this up. That compiles. OK let's Save All and try playing.
Oh dear. we get a hard crash
of Unreal! Well every time we've had a hard crash of Unreal my normal response is.
oh well that often happens. let's not worry about it! Let's just try opening the Editor again! But there are some times
Unreal has a paddy. when we make changes to blueprints. One thing I think of is.
do my categories all have. are they all string referenced? Well they're not here. So
one of my reactions to those types of hard crashes. at the moment. with the current bugs in
Unreal.  is to make sure these guys are string reference in here. And while I'm at it I
would probably do a search for Category = or just Category
across the entire project. And we've paid lip service to doing this before
but let's now go and do it. Let's check where category appears. and wherever
it appears. make sure it's properly string referenced. I know I skipped on there.
so I'm going to have to go back and get that.
So by paying lip service to something I mean saying oh we ought to. without
doing anything. Always capture the idea or just deal with it immediately. Only
don't deal with it immediately if doing so would really break your context. in that you feel
like you're opening too many ideas in your mind in one go. Otherwise.
if you can deal with it immediately do. otherwise at least put a TODO in your code.
so that you do come back and deal with it later. because. of course. we're going to be in the good habit
of dealing with TODOs regularly. So I'm just going to search through that once more.
to make sure all my categories have a string
referenced value against them. I think I missed one. OK fine. so
that's done! OK. so that was a suspicion that it could be that. Let's recompile!
And once it's recompiled. I will open the tank blueprint.
which is actually slightly broken which is interesting. Fix up the execution flow.
Compile that. Save All. and play and we get
a hard crash again! Oh dear! So the interesting thing about this
situation is. why is this hard crashing? So you could start saying. well let's look at
the Tank implementation file. for a start. and let's look at all
instances where we used say a Barrel. And you can say. well the Barrel pointer is
protected there. you know. that's fine. etc. You could go through
and start to try and work out where the problems are. Is it in the TankAiming
Component? I don't know. Let's go look at the implementation file. Can we see somewhere
where we're using unprotected pointers. Barrel. there's not Turret in this
guy. MoveBarrelTowards is missing pointer protection. We should
probably do that. because we use a Barrel and a Turret down here. and it makes no sense to
try and move a Barrel without them. So we'd better say if not
(!Barrel or II not
!Turret) then .
So could it be that? Now I'm guessing here. Now there's a better way than guessing.
but let's just compile and see what happens! What I'm trying to get you the feeling of is. we're a long
way from... Well we're not a long way from from compilation. we're a long way from a running project.
You should be feeling by this amount of time working and this amount of changes. we're 12
minutes into this video or a bit more. that I want to bring this
to some sort of conclusion. because my source control is sitting with a bunch of uncommitted changes. I've
obviously done work here but something's not working. So
ah. it's compiled! Does it play?
No it crashes! Alright. so at this point.
because of the length of this video and also because of the amount of code you've changed and
the fact that you've made some progress right. we've refactored. A bunch of this
stuff initializes into the TankAimingComponent! We've
connected it up in Blueprint and it didn't compile. Then. we did a load of work. and
now it does compile but it's hard crashing. I'm going to. I'm going to suggest that you
would make a micro-commit here. In fact. I'm even going to make a Commit. and then.
later I'm going to squash a couple of different commits together. So I'm going to say. here
simply "Moved
to" Blueprint "composition
of Aiming Component
now compiles but
HARD CRASHES on run". And it's
OK to make a temporary commit like that. to say OK I've got it as
far as it compiling. Let's capture this work and now go about the
job of trying to stop this hard crash. because at least it's compiling. Alright. and yes
this messes up my list of lecture names. but we can actually
squash things together later. I'm actually going to rename this commit to the same as the
lecture name. but don't be afraid to make a commit because I will be showing you how you could. if you
really have a particular vision for how your commits work. Just get it
committed. because you can change stuff later. Alright. so we have got a
fair distance down the road. We have changed the architecture. but
we have a hard crash. In the next video. we are going to focus on how
we're going to find the source of that hard crash. by attaching the VisualStudio
Debugger. so that's going to be pretty cool! I'll see you in there!
=======
So hey, welcome back
and welcome to Refactoring our Aiming Component. What we're going to do in this video is, we're going
to change the architecture of the AimingComponent to use a single initialize method like
this, just like the Movement Component did, and then, to strip a whole load of code
out of the tank and start moving the functionality over to the AimingComponent. And yeah,
we're going to hit a brick wall in it, but I want you to hit that brick wall yourself.
Or you may not, you may do things slightly better than I have, but I want you to try and do this
reorganization. So look back at the video where we setup the Tank
MovementComponent, and see if you can get the TankAimingComponent to the
same sort of architecture, where it is actually added here in
the Blueprint Editor and not added as
a default sub-object. So refactor the AimingComponent, try and move the Aiming
Component to the same architecture, as I said. Don't worry if you can't get it working, but see if
you can get it at least as far as compiling. If you find your game hard crashes when you play
or something, don't worry too much, but just see if you can get compiling and connected up in
Blueprint, like I've got there. And that's going to be a great exercise for you! If you
struggle with this, don't worry, it's a pretty open-ended exercise. You're very welcome to stop and
just follow my solution. You don't need to feel bad about it, I'm setting a pretty nebulous challenge
to allow for lots of different ranges of abilities to get their teeth stuck into this.
OK so go ahead, pause the video, have a go at that, and when I come back, I will be going through
and doing the refactor myself with you.
So just before we dive in and start refactoring, let's just give ourselves a little bit of context.
Remember that the Movement Component is nicely separated with the Left and Right
Tracks, only bound to that component, but the Aiming Component still has this messy
loop, where the Tank has reference to the Barrel and they have these setters
being passed down, etc. So what we're going to do is move the Aiming Component into the same
paradigm as the Movement Component, that is added in Blueprint using an Initialize()
method, etc. So I'm going to go through this with you and do some refactoring. You're welcome to try and do
the refactor yourself. You know the experienced among you can certainly do that, just
bring the Aiming Component into the same pattern as the Movement Component. And then, I'm going to lead us to
the point at which we have a horrible hard crash, which will be with no particularly obvious
source, and then, we're going to use the debugger, the VisualStudio debugger
to actually fix that up. So let's just start this refactor process.
Let's have the tank blueprint open, so we can remind ourselves that one of the things we are
trying to get rid of is this Set Turret and Set Barrel Reference.
In fact, let's be brave and just delete them, we don't need those anymore. We're going to have an Initialize()
method on our TankAimingComponent, of course. So let's go
break some stuff! Over in the tank header file, let's start off!
I think I'm actually going to start at the top and just fix up my copyright notice, as I
did in the TankMovementComponent. So let's just do the Copyright notice for the tank header
file and the TankAimingComponent header file.
They're the two things we're going to be working on. It kind of signals to me, I've touched this thing recently.
Sure if I had of set it in the Project Settings in the beginning then it'd be set, but whenever
you notice a problem like this, let's fix it as we go. So in the tank header file we have this
SetTurret and SetBarrel reference. Don't need them, let's get rid of them! Both the SetTurret and SetBarrel
References. Let's remove those and let's remove the code that actually does that setting.
So that's great! We can also get rid of, in the ATank
BeginPlay(), you'll notice we're not using it, so let's just ditch it. And let's ditch it from the
header file as well, if it's in there. You can always put it back, it's really easy to put back again
OK. And SetupPlayerInputComponent, we're not using that either, so I'm taking Setup
PlayerInputComponent out of the Tank as well, as we're trying to clear
up the Tank. Let's clear it up properly! OK, now over in the Tank,
the other thing that we're doing is creating a default sub-object of a TankAimingComponent.
Remember what that does? It makes this TankAimingComponent inherited here, which we don't have
any details for, and it's different to the TankMovementComponent, so we're going to stop doing
that! Let's delete the TankAimingComponent DefaultSubobjectCreation there,
and then, let's
recompile. I think it'll recompile at this stage.
Now, I did a lot of code in a very short amount of time there, so what I'll do is I'll do you the favor.
Now that hitting Compile has saved all the tabs in VisualStudio, I can  come
into SourceTree, while it compiles, and I can show you what I've done. I've deleted a load of code from the
Tank.cpp, all of this stuff that you can see on the screen there. I'll leave it for you for a second.
And then, you can see what I've done in the header file,
removed the relevant references that's all, and then, in the AimingComponent I've just
changed my Copyright notice. OK, so there are the changes. Now the hot reload worked.
Now lets go look at the tank blueprint! We no longer have this inherited TankAimingComponent.
Fantastic! So let's add it back! Now, will it be visible? Well it will be visible in the
Custom section, if we made it the correct type of U...
Well let's go and have a look! Remember in the TankMovementComponent header file,
we annotated as a (BlueprintSpawnableComponent).
Well let's go and have a look in the TankAimingComponent header
file, and it is already a (BlueprintSpawnableComponent). If
yours isn't, of course, you need this annotation on the TankAimingComponent. Great! So
because it's BlueprintSpawnable I can come in here and I can add it as a
TankAimingComponent. Great! There it is looking just like the TankMovementComponent, and we can
actually see the properties on it now. That's fun! Now what we need is one of these Initialize()
methods for the TankMovementComponent. So I'm going to go... Ah sorry, not for
the TankAimingComponent. I'm going to go look at the TankMovementComponent's Initialize() method, and
I think I won't copy it because it's so different but I just want to remind
myself how that works. I'm using the English spelling of Initialise and I'm just
setting some references. So on the TankAimingComponent, we have
these pointers to the Barrel and Turret, which is great! We don't need them on the tank anymore,
by the way. So if you look at the tank, we don't need a Barrel reference anymore. Let's delete that from the
Tank, that's no longer necessary. And then, in the Tank
AimingComponent we're going to need a new Initialize() method. Now it's going to need to be public,
isn't it? And it's also going to need to have the same signature as it does in the MovementComponent, so
I will use the MovementComponent for that. Here (BlueprintCallable, Category
= "Setup") and then it's this Initialize. So let's just use that as inspiration.
And then, be very careful to immediately change it from a UTank
Track pointer to a UTank
Barrel pointer and a UTank
Turret pointer. And then, it's
going to be BarrelToSet
and TurretToSet. OK so we've made an
Initialize here. Let's go and define that now over in the .cpp.
I'm going to do it in place of, actually. We don't need anymore of
this SetBarrelReference and SetTurretReference. We're replacing those with just
a single initializer there, which just says Barrel =
BarrelToSet and Turret
= TurretToSet. No need to protect
these incoming values, if they're null well we're going to get null. That's fine!
OK, now I removed a couple of setters from the TankAiming
Component, so these two SetBarrel and SetTurretReferences they can go in the same Aiming
Component, we simply don't need those anymore. And the TankAimingComponent is reduced down to
a constructor, which actually because of Unreal magic we can put in the private section,
and I'm going to prefer to do that just so it gets it out of my public interface. Then, I have an Initialize
which takes a couple of things and an AimAt. Protected, we
have this FiringState, which we did a couple of videos ago. So yeah, we're all good to
go! Let's just have a little recompile of this code, see if we
missed anything. If it compiles, then I'll show you
the code changes, and then, we'll start to create the actual problem
because I've missed something. Some of you may have seen what I've missed here.
I've done this refactoring, let's just see what compile error I have.
" 'Barrel': undeclared identifier" in TankAimingComponent 22.
OK that's an interesting error. That error has nothing to do with the fact that
it's an undeclared identifier. It's because, earlier on, when I made
this Initialize method I didn't put
the class in front of it, so the compiler has read through that, got very confused, and thinks
the error is on line 22, whereas it's actually on 20. So let's recompile! That's definitely
worth knowing! So when you see an error, just zoom out a little bit, don't get
super focused on it. Ooh, it doesn't understand what this Barrel is! Yeah, but it doesn't understand what the Barrel is
because it got stuck trying to read the line before. Yeah, so don't really trust
the errors too too much. So we have another compile failure, which is again on
line 27. We have a Barrel it doesn't understand,
and that is because, in the Tank, I got rid of the Barrel
reference. I'm going to pop the Barrel reference back in the Tank, for the moment, in it's header file.
Why? Because we are not dealing
with taking out this code in the Tank, the Fire code right now,
so let's put that back. Now the source control will tell me
what I took out of the tank header file, right now, and you can see one of the things I
took out was this Barrel reference. So I'm going to put it back by copying
it from source control, popping it back in like that. OK it's got a few extra characters with
it but we'll live. But I'm going to say "// TODO
Remove", because we know we're going to have to remove this at some point, because we want all of this stuff to go
over to the AimingComponent. That's not the idea now, we're trying to do as little as possible,
while it still compiles. We're just trying to get our thing compiling again. OK, so let's go back and
Compile. Don't boil the ocean here! You should be having a feeling, at
this point, that you're a long way from a piece of compilable code, and that should worry you
because you may not be able to get back to compilation, which means you'd need to revert to your
previous commit, which would be a waste of your time. So hurry up to get it compiled!
There you go, it has compiled! That is good! Alright, and that's all
working. So let's Save All in here and then go into the
tank blueprint, and we should now have, if we search for "initialize", a
Tank Aiming Component initializer. We do! That's Fantastic! So let's now
do the TankAimingComponent initialization. It doesn't matter
whether it's done before or after the MovementComponent, the key is that we soft reference this Barrel
and this Turret, here in
the blueprint.
Great OK, so that is done! So let's just compile
this up. That compiles. OK let's Save All and try playing.
Oh dear, we get a hard crash
of Unreal! Well every time we've had a hard crash of Unreal my normal response is,
oh well that often happens, let's not worry about it! Let's just try opening the Editor again! But there are some times
Unreal has a paddy, when we make changes to blueprints. One thing I think of is,
do my categories all have, are they all string referenced? Well they're not here. So
one of my reactions to those types of hard crashes, at the moment, with the current bugs in
Unreal,  is to make sure these guys are string reference in here. And while I'm at it I
would probably do a search for Category = or just Category
across the entire project. And we've paid lip service to doing this before
but let's now go and do it. Let's check where category appears, and wherever
it appears, make sure it's properly string referenced. I know I skipped on there,
so I'm going to have to go back and get that.
So by paying lip service to something I mean saying oh we ought to, without
doing anything. Always capture the idea or just deal with it immediately. Only
don't deal with it immediately if doing so would really break your context, in that you feel
like you're opening too many ideas in your mind in one go. Otherwise,
if you can deal with it immediately do, otherwise at least put a TODO in your code,
so that you do come back and deal with it later, because, of course, we're going to be in the good habit
of dealing with TODOs regularly. So I'm just going to search through that once more,
to make sure all my categories have a string
referenced value against them. I think I missed one. OK fine, so
that's done! OK, so that was a suspicion that it could be that. Let's recompile!
And once it's recompiled, I will open the tank blueprint,
which is actually slightly broken which is interesting. Fix up the execution flow,
Compile that, Save All, and play and we get
a hard crash again! Oh dear! So the interesting thing about this
situation is, why is this hard crashing? So you could start saying, well let's look at
the Tank implementation file, for a start, and let's look at all
instances where we used say a Barrel. And you can say, well the Barrel pointer is
protected there, you know, that's fine, etc. You could go through
and start to try and work out where the problems are. Is it in the TankAiming
Component? I don't know. Let's go look at the implementation file. Can we see somewhere
where we're using unprotected pointers. Barrel, there's not Turret in this
guy. MoveBarrelTowards is missing pointer protection. We should
probably do that, because we use a Barrel and a Turret down here, and it makes no sense to
try and move a Barrel without them. So we'd better say if not
(!Barrel or II not
!Turret) then .
So could it be that? Now I'm guessing here. Now there's a better way than guessing,
but let's just compile and see what happens! What I'm trying to get you the feeling of is, we're a long
way from... Well we're not a long way from from compilation, we're a long way from a running project.
You should be feeling by this amount of time working and this amount of changes, we're 12
minutes into this video or a bit more, that I want to bring this
to some sort of conclusion, because my source control is sitting with a bunch of uncommitted changes. I've
obviously done work here but something's not working. So
ah, it's compiled! Does it play?
No it crashes! Alright, so at this point,
because of the length of this video and also because of the amount of code you've changed and
the fact that you've made some progress right, we've refactored. A bunch of this
stuff initializes into the TankAimingComponent! We've
connected it up in Blueprint and it didn't compile. Then, we did a load of work, and
now it does compile but it's hard crashing. I'm going to, I'm going to suggest that you
would make a micro-commit here. In fact, I'm even going to make a Commit, and then,
later I'm going to squash a couple of different commits together. So I'm going to say, here
simply "Moved
to" Blueprint "composition
of Aiming Component
now compiles but
HARD CRASHES on run". And it's
OK to make a temporary commit like that, to say OK I've got it as
far as it compiling. Let's capture this work and now go about the
job of trying to stop this hard crash, because at least it's compiling. Alright, and yes
this messes up my list of lecture names, but we can actually
squash things together later. I'm actually going to rename this commit to the same as the
lecture name, but don't be afraid to make a commit because I will be showing you how you could, if you
really have a particular vision for how your commits work. Just get it
committed, because you can change stuff later. Alright, so we have got a
fair distance down the road. We have changed the architecture, but
we have a hard crash. In the next video, we are going to focus on how
we're going to find the source of that hard crash, by attaching the VisualStudio
Debugger, so that's going to be pretty cool! I'll see you in there!
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1:Unreal/Section4/BT67 Refactoring our Aiming Component.srt