So welcome to
Attaching a Debugger to Unreal! What we're going to do in this video is exactly what I've
said on the tin. and by the end of it. well firstly the game will play which will be good.
We'll have found out what was wrong. by using the debugger. and also we'll be doing a little bit of
other logging in Blueprint. which you can see here. We'll be printing out some references
just as another kind of form of debugging. temporary debugging. So
this video is all about debugging. let's dive in and do it!
OK. so let's just remind ourselves of the sorry state we're in. If we try and play our
game. we get a hard crash of the Editor. Now normally when I get a crash like that. I
say well Unreal does that sometimes. particularly when we change blueprints. So
we reopen Unreal and we just run again. and see if we still get another
hard crash. because sometimes it does just do that. We just close Steam.
OK. so if I play. I'm getting another hard crash. So what on Earth do you do about these? This
is the topic of this video. You could potentially think about trying to
write to an external log file. perhaps you know an external fine. and then look
at that log to see what happened. But I want to show you. perhaps a better way. or an
easy quick way and a very generally applicable way. which is to use the VisualStudio
Debugger. So what we're going to do is. we're going to open up our instance of the Unreal
Editor. but not click play. because it's just going to die when we do that. So you go to the Debug
menu. and then. Attach to Process. And in Xcode or other IDEs
it'll be a similar idea to this. So we look through our list of processes.
and one of those would be the UE4 Editor. that is our Editor that is running down here
at the moment. So we attach the debugger to the UE4.
for instance. Now that will automatically change your user interface a  little bit. and it'll
go ahead and load some windows and do some attaching in the background. We don't need to worry
ourselves too much about exactly how that's working and what it's doing. but now it says
Ready and we can go back to Unreal and click play. Now what's happened
here is. Unreal is still there but it's just sitting ready to
crash. and VisualStudio has intercepted this and it says look
"Exception thrown: read access violation." This was a null pointer. So it was a null
pointer issue. and then. we can click Break. Now what Break will do is. it
stops the execution of Unreal. just before it's closed itself. We can't go
back to it. it's not in a good state. but we can see some very useful
information. So what is showing is the TankAimingComponent. On line
28 there's a little yellow arrow. it's saying this is the next statement that will be executed.
So it's sitting here and it's saying that this... Now what is this? This
is the TankAimingComponent. and you can see that from the type here.
has a value of null. so that it's the TankAimingComponent
pointer that has no value. Why not? Well what called Aim
At? I think it was the Tank that called AimAt. so let's go and find that. If you have trouble you can
bring back your solution explorer. go find your Tank.cpp.
and let's look at that code. Now that code is actually here. it's just under this menu.
So what we're going to need to do to make this work
is actually allow Unreal to finish crashing. because what
Unreal has done is it's popped a window up in the foreground. over the top of VisualStudio.
We could move ourselves out of the way to look at the tank. that's another option. but let's just let
Unreal finish crashing. put it out of it's misery. That way you do that is. you click Continue in
VisualStudio. "Pass exception on to the program being debugged?" That's
going to pass the exception back to Unreal but it can't handle it. It doesn't like following null pointers.
it just dies and bails out. So now we're left just in VisualStudio without Unreal
running. That's fine for now! So let's look at the Tank. What we used to do
in the Tank's constructor is that we would add a TankAimingComponent
as a default sub-object. We tried that architecture. we decided not to do it like that
and compose the tank in Blueprint. but we never actually replaced
the finding of the TankAimingComponent. Now we're not going to do that in this video. We are just going to
focus on protecting this pointer. before we try and use it. In fact. I'm going to get you to do that
because I've talked enough. So protect the null pointer we've just found. ensure the game still
runs with that. and don't worry about setting that pointer yet. and don't worry that the aiming
won't work. OK. so go ahead. pause the video. protect up that pointer.
and I'll see you when you come back.
OK. so welcome back! This is a very standard thing
that we do quite a lot. So AimAt should be saying to itself. if not
TankAimingComponent then. and we do it all on one
line just so we keep it short and sharp. then . We just are protecting
the pointer there. OK so if you do that and then go back to
the Unreal project. we're going to need to recompile our code.
of course. And then. once we do that. what I'm hoping will happen is that the game will run
and it will run in such a way that it doesn't aim. because the aiming
component pointer isn't set. but it at least runs and that is the point
of pointer protection. In fact. this shows you exactly the difference between not protecting your
pointers and protecting them. It's the difference between a hard crash and just some functionality not quite
working. which you can work with. So we play the game now. and you see no aiming is
happening but we are not crashing. which is awesome! Now
just to set us up for what's coming next. there are a couple of issues here. If you're in the
smart amongst you'll have noticed that here we have a bunch of warnings
about trying to read properties. We'll come to this in the next couple
of lectures. But also notice. if you're sharp. that the crosshair is red.
Now if we look in the UI over here. in the Player UI
blueprint. in the Event Graph. we said that Reloading
would be red. OK. well that's fine. but where would
we have declared. in the TankAimingComponent header file.
this Enum we said we wanted the default state to be aiming?
Now aiming should be amber. so what's going on? Why are we getting a red crosshair?
Well what's going on is the same thing that you are
seeing reported in the console. It's all to
do with when things are happening. It's to do with when
this BP Aiming Component Reference is actually set. over in the PlayerController blueprint
and whether or not it's actually finding a reference. So
in the spirit of debugging. which this video's all about. let's just briefly look at what
this AimingComponent Reference is set to. You can pull off it. you can
say string to turn it into a string.
like so. And then. we can come off of here and say print. Print the String.
Now when are we going to print the string? Well on the Get. The Get actually happens every
frame. but we're not concerned about when that Get happens. because we've left it to the engine
to worry about this execution flow. But we're saying. every time we ask about the color and opacity
of this crosshair. print out the value of the AimingComponent
for me. so that we can check it's not none. OK. let's see what it actually is.
Play! Now that print comes by default. You see it on the viewport there.
on the left-hand side in blue? And it will also be printed into the log. You can see the
log getting bigger and bigger. If I scroll down the log. you'll see none none none none none. So
we're actually not getting an Aiming Component Reference. So where was that set
to the Aiming Component Reference? We can take a look! It was set in the tank. under the TankPlayer
Controller here. And it was set where we get Controlled Tank. and then.
we try and set this Aiming Component. it's not happening. So the subject of the next video is going to
be working out why that is not happening. But for now. we have
made great progress. We're actually not going to set the
TankAimingComponent pointer yet. because we need to think very carefully
about how we put out tank together. when we put out tank together. where we put our
tank together. and what we're doing about Aiming Component References
and building up the UI and what gets done where. and more importantly what gets done when.
So that's what we're going to talk about next!