Hey hey hey! So welcome to
Constructor and Begin Play Timing! A little bit more fun that it sounds. What
we're going to know. by the end of this. is I'll explain the donkey as we go through. but what
we're going to know at the end of it is exactly what order C++ and Blueprint Construction
and Begin Plays get called in. And this becomes super important. as we build on our
architecture. So let's dive in and see how this happens!
So with all this talk of what happens when. you might quite rightly be
feeling. I'm not quite sure what's happening when now. I've kind of lost the plot?
So let's look at that a bit more carefully. I'm going to go to the Tank
UI blueprint graph. I'm just going to remove this debug stuff that I put in
last time. which is where we took the Tank Aiming Component Reference and
printed it out as a string. We know that that's not getting set. we'll look at Y architecturally
later. So I'm just going to reconnect the A point. as it was before. and leave that
code as not working. I think what is worth doing though is putting a comment in here. just
like you would in code. "TODO Check this
is set".
OK because this is not getting set at the right time. but this is not the aim of this video. The aim of this video
is to start looking at what happens when. both in terms of the constructors
and the BeginPlays. You saw in the last video how to print rather from Blueprint.
and you know very well how to log from VisualStudio.
I just want to show you one other thing about printing from Blueprint. before I set you a very early
challenge in this lecture. When you print something you've got a couple of options here.
You can print to. you can choose the String. but I would just hard code
the String in there for now. You can print to the screen. which comes up on the viewport. but you can also print to the
log. Now this will come out as gray text on the log. This Text Color here
determines the Text Color that is
coming into the screen. not onto the log OK. So the log's just going to come out black and white.
And for that reason. when you print I'm going to want you to
consider using a prefix. Now I'm going to just use the word donkey. because that hardly appears anywhere.
[Laughs] but you could use a UUID if you wanted. What do I mean by a UUID?
If you ever want to get yourself a short sequence of something unique. like our coupon
code. you can just type "UUID Generator" into Google and get something like this. Any part of
this string. it depends how long you want it. You could use a UUID in
here and you could say something colon. and then. you can say Tank
Blueprint constructed
type of thing OK. But that's now what we're doing here. I'm just showing you that
technique so you are now ready to do your challenge. So you're challenge is this! I want you
to convince yourself. with logs. what happens when. Log out the Construct
and the BeginPlay for the tank. both in C++
and in Blueprint. So in the C++ I want you to put something in the Constructor and
in the BeginPlay. If the BeginPlay is not on the tank. you need to put it back. and
then. add a single unique prefix to all of your log entries. Not a
different one for every log. but they all want to be prefixed with say donkey. because what you're then going to
be able to do is filter the logs. so that you can see the wood for the trees and just see the things you're interested
in. OK. so the logs that you get from C++. if
you log a warning verbosity will come out yellow. the ones that come from Blueprint will come out as
the standard color. Put the same prefix in front of all of these logs and let's see what
happens in what order. Do the Blueprint Constructors run and then the C++. or the
other way around. and when does BeginPlay run? Convince yourself of this. Go ahead. pause the video.
and let's make this discovery now.
OK welcome back! So not really any particular place
to start. I'm going to start on the tank blueprint here. We already have BeginPlay.
What I'm going to do is wire in this Print statement. straight after BeginPlay. I can do that by
taking the execution off here. I can say Print. just for fun.
You see what it did. by the way. when I did Print like that? It automatically made it put it in the loop.
so we're good to go. It will automatically be printing to the screen and the log. I'm happy with that!
The thing I'm interested in is it prints to the log. I tend to leave these as default. we don't need to change
anything. That way we get any logs we see in the viewport tend to have come from Blueprint.
and any logs we see on the log may have come from Blueprint or C++. I'm going to
prefix this with the word DONKEY. just so that we can see it in the logs. You'll see it working in a minute.
And then. I'm going to say BP or Tank_BP.
and this is the BeginPlay.
OK so that's that one! Let's just see it work. before we carry on nice and lean!
Now where is it? You see we've got a lot of stuff in the logs here. I could search through them or I could just look for
"donkey". [Laughs] And there are no other donkeys. You get three Tank_BP BeginPlays.
I think to keep things simple I'm going to delete one of the AI tanks. clear
the logs. The filter will stay. play again. and you see we've
just got two and they are the two tanks. One of them is the AI tank. that's probably this
3489 one. It's probably the AI tank. you can confirm that in the World Outliner.
Yes it is! And the C_0 is us. the player tank.
Cool. so then we've done that for BeginPlay! Now. by the way. if you didn't know what I meant in the challenge. for any
reason. and you didn't finish the challenge. then I'll take responsibility for it not quite being clear
enough. But I do want you to stop the video now and continue this for
the Construct of the tank. and then. I want you to put the logs into this
C++ as well. because I think the challenge should now be totally clear. Alright. so
moving into here. I'm just going to copy this Print String node and go to the Construction.
click into the Construction graph. and click Paste. Control C. and
Control V. I'm just going to change this slightly to Tank_BP Construct.
compile it and run it. and you'll notice that.
best to clear the logs first. that you can see what's going on now. The tank blueprint
constructs the tank blueprint BeginPlay for the player. and then. the tank blueprint
BeginPlay for the AI tank. But where is the Construct for
the AI tank? Hmm. interesting hey. Well look at this!
What happens with this AI tank actually. if we take it out of the scene.
clear the logs. go to our Content Browser... Look see what's happening?
Even when I move the mouse over the word Tank_BP. you see this Construct's getting
called all the time. There's actually an option inside the tank blueprint. If we go into the tank blueprint.
you can actually see under Class Settings of the
tank blueprint. blueprint Run Construction. In fact. I think it says
more than that? Yeah. Run Construction Script on Drag. We can turn that off if we want.
under the details of the tank blueprint. under the Class Settings.
Then. if I clear the log. when I hover over the tank... Actually. it's not working. It's
still doing it. so there you go. but that is supposed to influence that. If you then drop
the tank into the world. clear the log. then you can see that
moving it around isn't affecting it until I let go. Up. down.
OK. Now if we go back to the Tank_BP and turn that back on and Compile.
I think you'll find what happens now is as I move the tank. every single frame
yeah it's calling Construct. So that's the effect it has. it always calls construct as I hover over
here. but this tick box here decides whether every frame or just
when you let go of the tank. does it call it's construction; I'm going to do it only when I let go of the tank.
With a more complex game object. with slow construction. this is just an optimization for the Editor.
so that dragging things around doesn't slow things down. So to recap. if I
move the tank now. when I let go it constructs that tank. So that is when that tank gets
constructed OK. That's why that was missing from the list. Pretty
cool! OK. now let's go find any logs that we've got in here. I don't like having too many logs
around. so I'm going to search the current project for UE_LOG in a case sensitive way.
And actually it's not anywhere! So we don't seem to have any logs. That's fine!
In the Tank.cpp Constructor. I'm going to go UE_LOG
(LogTemp. Warning. and then I'm
going to put the TEXT in that says something very simple.
Tank... Oh. do we want the name of the tank? We probably do. auto Tank
Name = GetName(). something like that.
which is going to be a string which we're going to put in here. And we need to do
this star operator on. A strange overloaded operator they use there.
And then. I'm just going to say %s. Let's see what the blueprint one
prints like. It says the tank name. DONKEY colon.
and then. Tank_BP BeginPlay. So that
should do us something like this. DONKEY: Tank
C++ Construct. OK. let's
test that nice and lean. So we Compile. check to make sure that this
whole paradigm is working. and then. we can do the same thing for Begin Play. Of course. we've got to put BeginPlay back.
and there's going to be something a little bit interesting in BeginPlay. We need to decide if we call Super
or not but we'll worry about that in a moment. OK let's play! There we go. we're getting
the identifiers on these tanks. Let's just clear the log and start afresh.
We're seeing that the Tank C++ Construct works for both of these guys. and
then. the Tank Blueprint Construct is working. then the BeginPlay. Cool! So
that's giving us an idea as to what's doing what when. Now let's go ahead
and put BeginPlay back in. we removed it before.
And I'm just going to have a look. Did we get a Tank Blueprint
BeginPlay. No! Look we're not getting the Blueprint BeginPlay of
the Tank. Oh yes we are! Sorry. it's here! It's here. OK that's fine! So
now notice something interesting. ATank: :BeginPlay(). just add it
back in and let's not call Super.
but I'm going to put Super question mark there for a moment.
Now let's put tank back into... We can put it in the private section because of Unreal
magic. Remember it's a virtual method. it's void because nothing comes back.
BeginPlay() no arguments
override because we want to check that we're matching a signature. so we're re-adding BeginPlay().
Let's recompile and see what happens. It'd be interesting to
see. that when we don't call Super. whether or not the blueprints Begin
Play gets called. because it'd be quite easy to remove BeginPlay and put it back
and not put Super. I want you in the habit. if you ever add BeginPlay() back. to really think. do I want Super or do I
not want to call the Super class behavior. So let's clear the logs.
play the game. and look at this. the tank blueprint BeginPlay
is no longer running. Please take note OK. that will cause you monsterous
problems later. if you're not careful. You're going to want your tank blueprint BeginPlays to work.
otherwise all that code that sits here in Event Graph is not going to run after
BeginPlay. So the reason it's not being called is because we need to be calling Super.
So this is a good option to put in Super: :BeginPlay()
and then to comment"// Needed for" Blueprint "Begin Play
to run!" I'm even going to put an exclamation. I think it's a bit weird. but it's
obviously doing some hookup in the Super class. you could look in the source code if you were super-keying. that makes
this work. so you do need that! A really important lesson here! So
we're nearly there! We are going to now just look at the results. and then. I think
because the video's ten minutes long. I think we will talk about the results in the next lecture.
So let's clear the logs. play the game. OK cool!
So we have the Tank 38 DONKEY. DONKEY here is just
here to filter the logs. Remember if I didn't put the word DONKEY in front. what's all this DONKEY about? Remember
that let's clear the logs and have a look now! Not so easy. we've got other errors which
we're going to talk about in a bit. once we get our architecture right. and then. somewhere in here these
logs and different colors really hard to see but DONKEY easy to see. [Laughs] OK
a simple trick for you there. So what we're getting is we're getting the C++
Constructor for both of the tanks and then we're getting the Blueprint Constructor
and then the Blueprint BeginPlays. That's the sequence that's happening when we play from here.
I did also say I wanted you to do it from the MainMenu. so let's go to the MainMenu.
Clear the Logs. play the game. When you click start. let's see what
happens. You get exactly the same thing. but you get one extra thing which is that the
AI tank does run it's Constructor. on entry. into
the BattleGround scene. OK. so that's the difference and it can catch you out. If
you keep playing from this BattleGround. It's not a true test of the game. because this tank that's
sitting there has already been constructed. OK. so that's the
thing we get. When we play from here we get. look at the count log entries. we get four
of them with no Tank 38 Blueprint
Construct. it just doesn't exist. Go from the MainMenu.
play here. you get six entries. and one of those
is Tank 38 Blueprint Construct. which is
this one here. happens quite early. OK cool! enough said on that!
Congratulations! I hope you now understand a lot more about what happens in what order. This is going to become
very important as we move forward with Unreal in general but also with this project. And I'll see you in
the next video!