So welcome to
Dependency Mapping! What we're go to do in this video is learn a very useful technique for analyzing
our C++ and header files and finding out what depends
on what. So let's dive in and make that happen!
So let's just have a quick recap of what we've done lately. We've refactored our
AimingComponent. in order to make it completely
independent. so it could sit on the tank independently of anything else.
Basically it could be added and removed from the tank at will. except from of course.
we need to initialize it here. I'm just going to remove this
Print String. by the way. We don't need these Print Strings. so wherever I see these logs I'm just going to get
rid of them. Also. by the way. my tabs are still opening
in the wrong place. I want them opening here in the main window. The way to make that change stick is
to go to Edit. and Editor Preferences.
under Appearance you go Asset Editor Open Location. Let's make that the Main
Window. but this time let's click Set as Default. Yes we want to update the default
settings. and Yes we want to write to the settings
file. It may impact other developers. OK what you'll see in source control is
that we have a new file here. which is the DefaultEditor
PerProjectUserSettings.ini. What a mouth full! Anyway. we refactored our
AimingComponent. The purpose was that we then have this independent AimingComponent that can be
added or removed from the tank at will. We then went on and talked about the constructor
and begin play timing. and we did some timing decoupling of our architecture.
We prevented the startup from being
dependent on the order that things happen in. So more specifically what we did.
if we remember. is we want into... Where's the TankPlayer
Controller? Our TankPlayerController had this Event Found
Aiming Component reference. which goes ahead and only creates the crosshair
when the AimingComponent is found. if you'll remember. and then. we
set this blueprint variable. While we're on here. if you don't like these lines
doing this crossing through. you can add something called a reroot node. which
is at the bottom of your blueprint menu. You can then drag
into that and then out of that. and what you get is you get a
simpler. cleaner. line. I would only do this once your blueprint design has
been settled and simplified. because otherwise you create constraints that
mean you can't move things around so easily. Anyway that's where we got to with
that. And then. we used the ensure assertion to catch
things like null pointer errors. in a much more helpful way. but at this stage
in the project we have a horrible problem looking. which is that our architecture isn't
very nice. And how do we even know our architecture's not very nice? Well the symptom
is that we've still got problems. not everything is working. we've got
some null pointers. etc. Now we can go through and sort those out but
I want to show you a formal way of mapping your architecture. and whenever you feel that your
project's getting a little bit out of hand. this is what we need to do. What I want you to do
is to go to the Private folder and start with the Projectile.cpp.
and note that yes it includes the BattleTank
and yes it includes the Projectile header but it doesn't include anything else. Everything
includes BattleTank. so everything depends on BattleTank.h because
this is the Battle Tank project. That's fine but projectile depends on
nothing else. So I'm going to start drawing a diagram. only about
the aiming part of the architecture. and I'm going to start there with a projectile class
saying it doesn't depend on anything. So let me continue. the Tank.
The Tank depends on all this stuff in the middle. not the BattleTank. not the Tank
itself obviously. but it does depend on the Barrel. the Projectile. the Aiming. and the Movement
Components. Let's look at that on a diagram. The Tank depends on the
Barrel. the Projectile. the Aiming.
and I've left out the TankMovementComponent for clarity. as I said. OK. I'm
going to do one more. and then. I'm going to leave it to you to do this  Dependency Mapping. which you literally do through
the .cpp files like this. OK so the TankAI
Controller.cpp. what does that depend on?
Tank. OK so you what you do is you come in and you draw the AI Controller and you
say it depends on the tank. Now I don't care how your diagram is laid down. mathematically this thing
is called a graph and all I care about is how it's connected. There's an infinite number of
ways you could draw this. But I want you to carry on this process and finish off this
diagram. by working down the .cpp files. I'm not going to put a challenge slide up.
because it would mess up the transition of this nice diagram. but I want you to pause the video and
finish this dependency diagram right now. It's really important you spend the time thinking about this.
OK so how have you got on? I'm just going to carry on! It's a very simple task actually.
but it brings up some really interesting questions. You'll just be able to see that this is not
right. So the TankAimingComponent depends on the Barrel and the Turret.
TankAimingComponent depends on. which means that it imports the code of. That's what I mean
by depends on the Barrel and the Turret. OK what does the Barrel
depend on? Nothing. because it's just two. What does the MovementComponent depend on? We don't care
because we're not dealing with that. at the moment. What does the PlayerController depend on? The AimingComponent
and the Tank. Wow! The PlayerController depends on the AimingComponent
and the Tank! How do you guys let me get it into this state?! I'm surprised
nobody noticed me sneaking you into this horrible corner! The Track and
the Turret depend on nothing. So look just take a look at that. what does it look like to you?
Well it may seem acceptable to you but it certainly isn't to me. This is what we call
spaghetti! This is not a good architecture! How do we know formally it's
not a good architecture? We have loops. well we at least have diamonds here.
so the Turret... Where's a diamond? A diamond here with the Barrel and
the Player Controller. So what you've got is you've got two ways of going from the Player
Controller down to the Barrel. I don't like that. that is pretty minging.
We have two things referencing the Barrel. that's not too bad but
it's not necessary here. We don't need both the Tank and the Aiming Component to know about the
Barrel. In fact the tank doesn't need to know about the barrel. If you remember. I even
started to hint at that in the Tank header file. I said. down here.
that we could remove the Barrel pointer in the future. So we're starting to get
the idea. but look that architecture stinks. it just isn't good.
So what are we going to do about it? What target architecture do we want? Well what I want
to head towards is just that. Now let's flick between them a couple of times.
I know they move slightly but the AI Controller and the Player Controller. at the top here. are in the same
place there. The Tank has disappeared.
We actually don't need to send everything through the tank. We could. in this architecture. put the
Tank where I'm indicating on the diagram. above the Aiming Component. and we could send all
these commands through the Tank if we needed to. You would tend to only do that if
this code that's calling the Tank is not re-factorable for
whatever reason. but as we can refactor this code. we can re-point this to call
straight to the Aiming Component. OK. so we don't have a Tank at all.
the Aiming Component is still here but it's just in the middle now. and then. Projectile.
Barrel. and Turret are at the bottom but look at how simple and clean this is.
For aiming [we're talking about aiming here]the AI Controller
and the Player Controller just talk straight to the Aiming Component. the Aiming Component needs the Projectile.
the Barrel. and the Turret to do it's job. Simple and it's not that hard
for us to get to that architecture. By the way. while we're there let's just look at the Movement Component architecture. It's pretty much like this. as we are.
So firstly. what we have is Input. it's not really a C++
class in the same way. so I'll put it green and also put a dotted line
to indicate it's not the same type of dependency. But of course. if you go to your project and you go to
the tank blueprint. then we have this dependency here where Input
Binding uses the Tank Movement Component. so I wanted to bring that to the surface.
We also have the AI Controller. somewhat implicitly
depending on the Movement Component via the Pathfinding Logic. You'll remember how that
worked. If we look at the TankAIController.cpp
it makes a call into MoveToActor. the Pathfinding Logic does stuff with that.
and eventually. in the MovementComponent. we end up with RequestDirectMove.
So we do have a dependency there. I think because we have that dependency
between the AI Controller and the Pathfinding. I'm going to pop it at the top of
the file here. So this is saying that the AI Controller has a
dependency here. I'm going to write "// Depends on movement component
via pathfinding system". I wrote it a few seconds offline. so you don't
just see me typing it. So that's up in the header. so that we can shake out the dependencies.
We could do the same thing with the Input. although there's no way to write
that. so I can't actually comment on the Input. It's going to be pretty obvious
what Input depends on in the blueprint. it's not quite as easy to search for.
So finally. the Movement Component depends on
the tracks right. So if we go to the TankMovementComponent. it should
depend on tracks. So that's effectively our movement architecture. All we need to
do to get to the architecture is to just go into the Tank.cpp
and remove the TankMovementComponent header file. because we're not actually using
that. If you're not sure. then what you do is you do a search for
UTankMovementComponent
in this file. Anyway it's already not showing up. The other thing
we need to do is to go to the tank header file and remove the UTankMovementComponent
reference there. And I think that's the majority of
it actually. it's just getting rid of those things... Ah here yes! The TankMovement
Component pointer. in the tank header file. we don't need that either. So we've
flushed all the Movement Component stuff out of the Tank. We still have this
architecture. There is no Tank featuring there. There is no Tank featuring here.
And what we're going to do. in the next video. is to focus on
getting to this architecture. It's going to be a big refactor video. so make sure
that you've got 20 minutes. at least. to watch the video and
more time to actually do the challenge of the refactor yourself. So it's going to be fun. it's going to be a much
nicer system for it. I'm just going to pop back into Unreal and make sure that we compiled.
If you compile a second time. of course. it's much quicker. I'm just going to make sure that things
work. i.e. that I can move. I just turned my controller on. and that
they can move. Yep. so movement still works! So in good shape and
I'll see you in the next video!
=======
So welcome to
Dependency Mapping! What we're go to do in this video is learn a very useful technique for analyzing
our C++ and header files and finding out what depends
on what. So let's dive in and make that happen!
So let's just have a quick recap of what we've done lately. We've refactored our
AimingComponent, in order to make it completely
independent, so it could sit on the tank independently of anything else.
Basically it could be added and removed from the tank at will, except from of course,
we need to initialize it here. I'm just going to remove this
Print String, by the way. We don't need these Print Strings, so wherever I see these logs I'm just going to get
rid of them. Also, by the way, my tabs are still opening
in the wrong place. I want them opening here in the main window. The way to make that change stick is
to go to Edit, and Editor Preferences,
under Appearance you go Asset Editor Open Location. Let's make that the Main
Window, but this time let's click Set as Default. Yes we want to update the default
settings, and Yes we want to write to the settings
file. It may impact other developers. OK what you'll see in source control is
that we have a new file here, which is the DefaultEditor
PerProjectUserSettings.ini. What a mouth full! Anyway, we refactored our
AimingComponent. The purpose was that we then have this independent AimingComponent that can be
added or removed from the tank at will. We then went on and talked about the constructor
and begin play timing, and we did some timing decoupling of our architecture.
We prevented the startup from being
dependent on the order that things happen in. So more specifically what we did,
if we remember, is we want into... Where's the TankPlayer
Controller? Our TankPlayerController had this Event Found
Aiming Component reference, which goes ahead and only creates the crosshair
when the AimingComponent is found, if you'll remember, and then, we
set this blueprint variable. While we're on here, if you don't like these lines
doing this crossing through, you can add something called a reroot node, which
is at the bottom of your blueprint menu. You can then drag
into that and then out of that, and what you get is you get a
simpler, cleaner, line. I would only do this once your blueprint design has
been settled and simplified, because otherwise you create constraints that
mean you can't move things around so easily. Anyway that's where we got to with
that. And then, we used the ensure assertion to catch
things like null pointer errors, in a much more helpful way, but at this stage
in the project we have a horrible problem looking, which is that our architecture isn't
very nice. And how do we even know our architecture's not very nice? Well the symptom
is that we've still got problems, not everything is working, we've got
some null pointers, etc. Now we can go through and sort those out but
I want to show you a formal way of mapping your architecture, and whenever you feel that your
project's getting a little bit out of hand, this is what we need to do. What I want you to do
is to go to the Private folder and start with the Projectile.cpp,
and note that yes it includes the BattleTank
and yes it includes the Projectile header but it doesn't include anything else. Everything
includes BattleTank, so everything depends on BattleTank.h because
this is the Battle Tank project. That's fine but projectile depends on
nothing else. So I'm going to start drawing a diagram, only about
the aiming part of the architecture, and I'm going to start there with a projectile class
saying it doesn't depend on anything. So let me continue, the Tank.
The Tank depends on all this stuff in the middle, not the BattleTank, not the Tank
itself obviously, but it does depend on the Barrel, the Projectile, the Aiming, and the Movement
Components. Let's look at that on a diagram. The Tank depends on the
Barrel, the Projectile, the Aiming,
and I've left out the TankMovementComponent for clarity, as I said. OK, I'm
going to do one more, and then, I'm going to leave it to you to do this  Dependency Mapping, which you literally do through
the .cpp files like this. OK so the TankAI
Controller.cpp, what does that depend on?
Tank, OK so you what you do is you come in and you draw the AI Controller and you
say it depends on the tank. Now I don't care how your diagram is laid down, mathematically this thing
is called a graph and all I care about is how it's connected. There's an infinite number of
ways you could draw this. But I want you to carry on this process and finish off this
diagram, by working down the .cpp files. I'm not going to put a challenge slide up,
because it would mess up the transition of this nice diagram, but I want you to pause the video and
finish this dependency diagram right now. It's really important you spend the time thinking about this.
OK so how have you got on? I'm just going to carry on! It's a very simple task actually,
but it brings up some really interesting questions. You'll just be able to see that this is not
right. So the TankAimingComponent depends on the Barrel and the Turret.
TankAimingComponent depends on, which means that it imports the code of. That's what I mean
by depends on the Barrel and the Turret. OK what does the Barrel
depend on? Nothing, because it's just two. What does the MovementComponent depend on? We don't care
because we're not dealing with that, at the moment. What does the PlayerController depend on? The AimingComponent
and the Tank. Wow! The PlayerController depends on the AimingComponent
and the Tank! How do you guys let me get it into this state?! I'm surprised
nobody noticed me sneaking you into this horrible corner! The Track and
the Turret depend on nothing. So look just take a look at that, what does it look like to you?
Well it may seem acceptable to you but it certainly isn't to me. This is what we call
spaghetti! This is not a good architecture! How do we know formally it's
not a good architecture? We have loops, well we at least have diamonds here,
so the Turret... Where's a diamond? A diamond here with the Barrel and
the Player Controller. So what you've got is you've got two ways of going from the Player
Controller down to the Barrel. I don't like that, that is pretty minging.
We have two things referencing the Barrel, that's not too bad but
it's not necessary here. We don't need both the Tank and the Aiming Component to know about the
Barrel. In fact the tank doesn't need to know about the barrel. If you remember, I even
started to hint at that in the Tank header file. I said, down here,
that we could remove the Barrel pointer in the future. So we're starting to get
the idea, but look that architecture stinks, it just isn't good.
So what are we going to do about it? What target architecture do we want? Well what I want
to head towards is just that. Now let's flick between them a couple of times.
I know they move slightly but the AI Controller and the Player Controller, at the top here, are in the same
place there. The Tank has disappeared.
We actually don't need to send everything through the tank. We could, in this architecture, put the
Tank where I'm indicating on the diagram, above the Aiming Component, and we could send all
these commands through the Tank if we needed to. You would tend to only do that if
this code that's calling the Tank is not re-factorable for
whatever reason, but as we can refactor this code, we can re-point this to call
straight to the Aiming Component. OK, so we don't have a Tank at all,
the Aiming Component is still here but it's just in the middle now, and then, Projectile,
Barrel, and Turret are at the bottom but look at how simple and clean this is.
For aiming [we're talking about aiming here]the AI Controller
and the Player Controller just talk straight to the Aiming Component. the Aiming Component needs the Projectile,
the Barrel, and the Turret to do it's job. Simple and it's not that hard
for us to get to that architecture. By the way, while we're there let's just look at the Movement Component architecture. It's pretty much like this, as we are.
So firstly, what we have is Input, it's not really a C++
class in the same way, so I'll put it green and also put a dotted line
to indicate it's not the same type of dependency. But of course, if you go to your project and you go to
the tank blueprint, then we have this dependency here where Input
Binding uses the Tank Movement Component, so I wanted to bring that to the surface.
We also have the AI Controller, somewhat implicitly
depending on the Movement Component via the Pathfinding Logic. You'll remember how that
worked. If we look at the TankAIController.cpp
it makes a call into MoveToActor, the Pathfinding Logic does stuff with that,
and eventually, in the MovementComponent, we end up with RequestDirectMove.
So we do have a dependency there. I think because we have that dependency
between the AI Controller and the Pathfinding, I'm going to pop it at the top of
the file here. So this is saying that the AI Controller has a
dependency here. I'm going to write "// Depends on movement component
via pathfinding system". I wrote it a few seconds offline, so you don't
just see me typing it. So that's up in the header, so that we can shake out the dependencies.
We could do the same thing with the Input, although there's no way to write
that, so I can't actually comment on the Input. It's going to be pretty obvious
what Input depends on in the blueprint, it's not quite as easy to search for.
So finally, the Movement Component depends on
the tracks right. So if we go to the TankMovementComponent, it should
depend on tracks. So that's effectively our movement architecture. All we need to
do to get to the architecture is to just go into the Tank.cpp
and remove the TankMovementComponent header file, because we're not actually using
that. If you're not sure, then what you do is you do a search for
UTankMovementComponent
in this file. Anyway it's already not showing up. The other thing
we need to do is to go to the tank header file and remove the UTankMovementComponent
reference there. And I think that's the majority of
it actually, it's just getting rid of those things... Ah here yes! The TankMovement
Component pointer, in the tank header file, we don't need that either. So we've
flushed all the Movement Component stuff out of the Tank. We still have this
architecture. There is no Tank featuring there. There is no Tank featuring here.
And what we're going to do, in the next video, is to focus on
getting to this architecture. It's going to be a big refactor video, so make sure
that you've got 20 minutes, at least, to watch the video and
more time to actually do the challenge of the refactor yourself. So it's going to be fun, it's going to be a much
nicer system for it. I'm just going to pop back into Unreal and make sure that we compiled.
If you compile a second time, of course, it's much quicker. I'm just going to make sure that things
work, i.e. that I can move, I just turned my controller on, and that
they can move. Yep, so movement still works! So in good shape and
I'll see you in the next video!
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1:Unreal/Section4/BT73 Dependency Mapping.srt