So welcome to
to Starting from Green! What on Earth do I mean by that? Well let's dive into the video and find out!
OK so let's make this stuff, about the order in which we refactor, more
concrete! Here are the changes we're going to be making, in terms of our class dependencies.
The red arrows are the things that are going. Basically the Tank is out of here. The green
arrows are new dependencies, like the AI Controller is going to talk straight to the Aiming
Component, and the Aiming Component's going to talk to the Projectile, and the gray ones are the boring old ones
that are staying the same. So that's fine but it doesn't really give us a handle
on a sensible order to refactoring, so let's take a
different view on things. Let's map out the methods in Tank. Why
in Tank? Well because Tank's the thing that we're going to be removing. It's the Tank code
here that we're going to be chopping into and removing nearly all of
basically and moving into the AimingComponent. So let's look at the AimAt() method!
It requires or depends upon the AimingComponent
pointer and the launch speed, they are the member variables that this AimAt
uses. There you go the AimingComponent and the LaunchSpeed. Fine! How about Fire()?
Well the Fire() method uses all of these things, the ReloadTime, Barrel,
LastFireTime, etc. Let's take a look! They're all in here!
OK so what's quite interesting though is that they both use the Launch
Speed. So what this means is, if we want to try and move one method at a time,
which is what I recommend, this is what I mean by keeping it close to compiling. Well I'm going to
firstly favor AimAt. Why? Well it really should be relatively
simple. The AimingComponent pointer is not even going to be needed, once this
is in the AimingComponent. The LaunchSpeed, if we were to take the Launch
Speed out, if we were to actually chop this LaunchSpeed code out of the Tank.h
here, cut it out, then what would happen is we know that the firing
would fail because of this diagram, but that's OK, we can live with that. In fact, what we could
do is, we could leave the LaunchSpeed here and leave ourselves a copy and say "// TODO
remove once firing is
moved to aiming component". So we can leave ourselves a copy,
so that our code still runs. So let's do that, let's do
aiming first. Now this is where we talk about the discipline of Red, Green, Refactor!
This comes from Test Driven Development. You start off in a situation where stuff
doesn't work. That's the situation we're actually in and this is the important point,
is that right now your aiming doesn't work. This is why this video
is called Getting to Green! We need to get to green, we don't aim at
the moment. OK so we can't refactor something that doesn't work, so let's fix
aiming before we're refactoring. In fact, we're not even going to refactor aiming
in this video, we're going to do it in the next one. This video is about fixing aiming, because there are some
problems with it. So your first thought, before you refactor, should be let's get
the functionality just working. So you have a commit before
you start any of this, you do some code that works, you commit to say it works,
and then you do your refactor. So we're trying to get to green. Then, you refactor, which is the blue
and then you repeat. So we're going to go around this loop, once for
AimAt and then once more for the Fire method.
OK so Red, Green, Refactor, remember that! OK we need to get
to green! What's not working? Wow, there's a lot of errors
here! Some of these would be ensure statements, let's see what we've got. The first one
TankAimingComponent, on line 30 of Tank.cpp
we have an ensure fail. So let's go to Tank.cpp line 30! What's going
on here then? Well we know this is going to fail then, because we never set that TankAiming
Component, but due to the things we've learned in the last couple of videos, we know there's an easy way of
doing that. What I want you to put in your TankAimingComponent BeginPlay(),
which is after the tank has put itself together, is you can go find the AimingComponent
by just saying FindComponentByClass UTank
AimingComponent and that's it! Oops,
provided you put your semicolon in the right place and you get the indentation right.
That's it, we're just adding that line. At BeginPlay() the tank goes and
finds its own AimingComponent. Now I know this is writing code into the old architecture,
but we need to get to working code before we refactor, that is the point I'm trying to
stress here. So I'm going to recompile the code. By the way, these ensure
statements will only come up once per cycle of
compilation, so if you're wondering why they're not coming up you need to recompile with new code or
they won't come up again. OK now we've got a different error here,
which is saying that the Barrel on Tank line 38
is failing. Let's go look at that, this one
here. Now, this is where we operate discipline, this is about firing not aiming.
Attempting to fix this now, not the time to do it, because we are
focusing on moving AimAt code. We don't care that firing doesn't work, we are trying to get
AimAt into the green section now. So to break
this big problem down, this big mess down, that's what we're doing we're saying let's forget it
and just focusing on aiming. It does still, of course, raise the question as to
why is aiming still not working? [Laughs] Interesting
hey! It actually does have something to do with Barrel tangentially,
but it's nothing to do with that ensure you're getting on line 38, trust me but it's going to be your
job to work out why. So get aiming working. If your aiming code doesn't work, you're
aiming code may work. You may have noticed the stupid bug that I introduced
a few videos ago, you may not. If you didn't and your aiming's not working go
and find it. It can be hard to track this bug. Use some log statements, follow the
execution through, think about where aiming starts. Let me give you a hint, in this case,
my aiming starts my tank with the PlayerController, the AI tanks
with the AIController. Follow the execution through, find out what's running and what's
not. I suggest you use a single log statement, put it somewhere, compile,
see if it's being run, move it move it move it, and find out where the problem is. Have a go,
pause the video, and see if you can get aiming working, if yours isn't. If yours
is working, then what I'd like you to do is to have a look at
my code. In fact, I'll give you a hint, it's in this file
here. The problem is actually on this screen. So if your aiming works, it's because you haven't
made the mistake that's on this screen. Where on this screen is the code that is
stopping my aiming working. OK pause the video, have a go at that, and I'll see you
in a moment.
OK welcome back! So let's start with the TankPlayerController. Let's say
why is the, in fact, I'm going to take a shortcut. I'm not going to start with
TankPlayerController, because look my aiming's not working and the AI tank's
aiming is not working. So if you remember the cool stack, it's
probably not the AIController or the PlayerController, because neither of
us are aiming. OK, so let's take that as an assumption. It's unlikely that
bug is in two places. Let's just save a little bit of time and go to the tank.
Let's see if we get this far. So I'm going to make a single UE_LOG. In
fact, the first thing I'm going to do is rip out any existing UE_LOGs, because we got too
many in the project potentially. Let's go and have a look! Do we need to be doing this DONKEY
Construct? No we've learned our lesson there, let's get rid of that. Do we need to be
printing out the TankBeginPlay? No we've learned our lesson there, let's get rid of
that! Do we need to be saying this? Actually
we don't! It's not happening but we've got an ensure here, we don't need to be logging this error. It's
pretty obvious what's happening with the ensure, so ensure you don't even need any of this stuff in
TankPlayerController. So I'm going to change
this to be consistent, actually. I'm going to say if not (!ensure(AimingComponent))
and then that. OK so that gets rid of that log and does a
tiny change to the BeginPlay() of the AIController and we're good
to go! So we have no logs left! OK so now I'm not going to get noise on the log!
Let's go back to the Tank, where we were, and ask the question, does AimAt get called?
UE_LOG(LogTemp, Warning,
something very simple, I'm just going to say TEXT
("I'm here")). That's all I'm going to say, and I'm going to move
that log around. So let's go and compile, have a quick look, clear the logs.
Clear your filter! Important if you've got a filter on, you ain't seeing nothing in the logs that doesn't
contain that word. I'm going to play the game
and see if we get lots of I'm here logs. What do we get? We get a long pause
and we do get "I'm here" "I'm here" "I'm here", so the code is getting that far!
Let's move on! What happens next? We go into the TankAimingComponent and we call AimAt, so
let's go there! Now we're pretty confident this call is going to happen,
we're pretty confident it's got a Barrel, otherwise this ensure would fail,
so maybe this MoveTowardsBarrel is not happening.
Let's try that! It's OK to binary search, do not go through every single stage,
but to try it as long as you home in on the problem. Let's see if
we get this far, moving the barrel. Compile! While you're compiling,
Clear your Logs because otherwise you can't be 100% sure that this new stuff
is, you know that this "I'm here" code isn't a log that was already there.
And then, let's play, and we get none of the I'm here's, I don't
think. Let me see, we get a lot of errors, but as we play here, we're not
seeing "I'm here's" at the bottom. OK, so you can even just
search for "here", not a single instance. So it's not getting there. Now,
this brings us to the bug that I introduced. The bug was quite interesting. I said,
as I rushed through, let's just do two different ensure statements,
so that we get two different tests, and we can tell if it was the Barrel or the Turret. But look at my logic, it
stinks. This says, if (ensure(Barrel). Well if there's a Barrel or if there's a Turret,
basically if the situation is somewhat normal in either respect, leave
this perfectly good code. How daft, what I meant to say was if not
(!ensure(Barrel) II or if not ensure(Turret))
then . And it's this lack of not that
means that you don't even get an error to tell you what's going on, and that's the sort of things that can be
hard to pin down, which is where that technique of putting the log in and moving the log
through the execution can be a sensible way of doing it and you don't have to
go straight to the problem. What I mean by binary searching is that, you know, this
can be the START of the execution flow, this can be the END of the execution flow.
You can try logging here if you want, but then, you're welcomed to dive in the middle and go,
well you know it's OK here but it's not OK here, so the problem must be in the middle here.
It's a bit like the binary search we did in the first section, I believe.
But anyway you get the idea, you can hone in on the problem, you don't have to go line by line by line,
and you can kind of chop the space. That's what I meant by that! OK,
so hopefully that will solve it. Let's compile! And if it does solve it,
where are we in terms of our general overview? Well then,
we're at green, we actually have aiming working. If we have aiming working, then
we're in a position to refactor it. There you go, aiming works on me and it works on these other tanks!
This other tank's not moving, so I'm just going to re-instantiate him, in case he's
busted. Hit F11 for full screen, and you can see that
both tanks are doing their comic moving and we're all aiming. Good not the
new architecture but we are in a green functionality as
working, even if code is in a messy stage. Fantastic! You know what we do now
don't you? What we do now is we commit, so I'm going to
Save all my work, and then, I'm going to commit this
lecture, because we have made significant
progress here. We have got to the point where
our code is ready to be refactored. And this is the starting point we'll
fall back to, if we can't make the refactor work, so always get to green,
Commit, then start your refactor. See you in the next video!