So hi
and welcome to Aiming Without the Tank! By the end of the video we will have refactored all our
aiming code. so that aiming still works. and we will have broken a bunch of dependencies. Our
diagram will be looking like this. by the end. Notice that the Tank is almost
extracted from the equation. and we've lost at least a couple of dependencies. We've lost the
lines from the AI Controller and the Player Controller into the Tank. which is good news. So see you in there!
So we are good to go on this aiming refactor.
So just before I start and set you into a challenge. I want to get rid of this annoying log
entry. If you'll remember. in the Tank blueprint. we've got a couple of logs
that we'd put in to do with the construction order. I'm going to get rid of that on the Tank Blueprint
Construction Script and this Print String in the Event Graph
and just recompile. and just make sure that if we clear the logs now and move and
hover over these things or play the game that we only get what we want.
which is just this one error here about the Barrel. which is to do with firing
and we are going to ignore for now. OK let's get to it! In fact.
I'm going to challenge you to to ahead and aim without the tank. Move just the aiming
code from the tank. Remember that we were going to keep a copy of the LaunchSpeed in the tank.
so that all the inbound calls and all the
code in the tank still compiles. The firing doesn't work. but the code needs to compile.
Move any forward declarations and includes that you need to. and just check that all
tanks can now aim. even though we're not doing the aiming via the tank
anymore. So go ahead. pause the video. see if you can make that part of the refactor now.
OK
welcome back! So I'm going to use. actually. my raw slide here. just as a way of
keeping track of what dependencies we've broken as we go through. So
where do we start then? We need to. as I said. get
rid of aiming on the Tank. So let's start at the top of the Tank.h. Does it
need a TankAimingComponent? Well it shouldn't need a TankAimingComponent.
Let's just see where we use that. in the current document.
We use it here. we keep a pointer to the AimingComponent. so that can all go.
The protected section of the tank. with this AimingComponent pointer can go.
Do we use this anywhere else? Nope. so now the forward declaration
of UTankAimingComponent can go in the Tank.
Let's talk about the same thing. the TankAimingComponent. Let's do a Find.
without case sensitivity and see what we need to get rid of.
Do we need to be finding the TankAimingComponent? No not anymore. that was just to get
this to green. We're going to get rid of the AimAt method alltogether.
and that is the only reference to TankAimingComponent. So we can
remove the #include for TankAimingComponent altogether. from the
Tank.cpp. So what have we just done in terms of dependencies? We have just
got rid of this dependency. The Tank no longer depends on the Tank Aiming
Component. That is cool news! So let's just take
a look at what code changes I've made. because I appreciate that a refactor video like this can
be a little bit hard to follow. So what I need to do is just save all in Visual
Studio. pop into the code tracking tool.
SourceTree here. and just show you that in the Tank.h. Let's
start there. these are the changes that I've made on the screen. on the right-hand side there. I deleted those
lines and in the Tank.cpp I've deleted those lines.
OK fantastic! Let's carry on with this refactor. because we have definitely more work
to do. We need to get to compilation as quickly as possible. In the tank header
file. we had an AimAt() method. That is the thing that we are
wanting to move into the TankAimingComponent. So let's cut the AimAt
and make sure that it already is in the TankAimingComponent.
Now it is but look. the signature is different. And the reason the signature
is different is because the AimingComponent used to need to know the LaunchSpeed that was stored on the tank.
but now we're going to have a copy of the launch speed
right here on the AimingComponent. So. let's go get that. Here's our
TankAimingComponent. sorry our Tank. and here is our LaunchSpeed.
Let's put that in the AimingComponent. We don't need to the TODO to say remove it.
because this is going to be the only place it ends up. Now what happens is.
when we call AimAt. we don't actually need a launch speed. That's going to affect
things upstream right. that's going to affect the AI Controller and the Player Controller.
but we'll fix that in a second. Yeah. it will affect them a
little bit. It won't affect the signature. because they never did call into Tank with the LaunchSpeed.
but they do need to get the AimingComponent. we'll see that in a minute. The basic point
is. we're moving the AimAt over into here. and then. let's take a look at the Tank
AimingComponent and it's AimAt() method. We just need to change its signature.
OK so there's a start! Now. at this
point I would say let's compile. let's see what's not going to work. I can anticipate what's not
going to work! For example. the AI Controller and the Player Controller
are going to have problems trying to call into the Tank. right now. I think.
because there's not AimAt method in it. but let's use the Compiler to help us find what's
wrong and we can just start going through its issues. So AimAt is no longer a member
of Tank. There you go. in the TankPlayerController! Let's go sort that out!
Now. to sort that out. I'm going to do the PlayerController. you're going to do the AIController.
Well I say that. if you haven't already done this challenge. I'm giving you a second chance.
which is I'm going to help you by doing this with the PlayerController. and then. you can pause the video as a
second chance at the challenge. if you need it. and you can do the AI. So
what's happening in this TankPlayerController?
It goes and gets the ControlledTank. Now what does GetControlledTank do. firstly?
I think it's a really thin method that does almost nothing. Yeah.
it just returns the Pawn. and it actually doesn't need to cast this Pawn to a
Tank. because a Tank is a Pawn. So we can remove the cast
and. in fact. while we're at it. let's look for ATank in this document.
Where else do we use ATank? It's the only place
we actually use the ATank type. So because I've removed the cast.
I can actually get rid of the #include Tank.h in the TankPlayerController.
What does that do for our dependencies? It gets rid of this line here.
Progress! OK that's cool! So let's go look at
the TankPlayerController.cpp. Do we also have ATank.
sorry. the TankPlayerController header file? I'm just going back to the header
file. because I was just in the .cpp. We have a ATank. yeah where are we using that? Let's find
it. in this GetControlledTank. Let's
ditch GetControlledTank! I'm ditching the method altogether and the forward declaration!
Again. that is because we've broken this PlayerController to Tank link. This is good. this
is progress in the right direction! So we don't
even need a GetControlledTank method. We can just GetPawn(). when we're supposed to be getting
ControlledTank. so let's get rid of this method altogether.
and in the header field. which we've already just done I think. Yeah.
Now let's go search for GetControlledTank.
like so. And then say. well where do we
use it? Well we use it up here. we go and get an AimingComponent up here in BeginPlay().
and then we go and find it. and then we ensure we have it. and then we
report that we found it. We do that at BeginPlay(). We want to do exactly the same
thing every time we aim. and the reason we need do it every time is because we may have depossessed
the Tank. we may have died and depossessed the Tank. So we want to do something
very similar to this. So instead of GetControlledTank it's just GetPawn now.
in this instance. and that should fix that bit. And then. down here
we want to do a very very similar thing. In fact. I'm just going to use this
code here and put it straight in here.
We find the AimingComponent. the same way. inside the AimTowardsCrosshair.
If we don't have it we . otherwise we
don't need to get the ControlledTank AimAt. we just need to say Aiming
Component AimAt.
So hopefully that makes sense. let's reuse the compiler
to help us with where we are. and once it compiles. I will show you
the source control changes again. so you can catch up. By the way. if you're having
trouble following what I'm doing. in a big refactor video like this. remember that you can always go
to github.com/UnrealCourse. click on BattleTank. click on the
Commits here. or go to this URL which I will paste in the lecture
resources for you. and then. you will see the next
video. BT76. But let's imagine it's already there. you can see all the changes by
clicking on it. OK so that's that! Now let's go back to Unreal.
see how far we've got. Where's Unreal? There it is! Compile Failed! Let's find
out why! So this area is an interesting one. In the TankPlayerController 21
it's talking about missing a pointer type. Let's go look at it! It's actually a
bogus error. It's got a problem at line 21 because. when I deleted
whatever I deleted here... What did I delete there? Let's look at the source control.
in the TankPlayerController.h I deleted something.
Yeah the GetControlledTank. I forgot to take the UFUNCTION annotation
with it. so that's what's confusing it. Let's get rid of that!
Perfect! Now let's try the compile again! So that's a strange sort of error.
You see the error's telling you it's expecting a pointer type. whereas it's actually just reading a UFUNCTION
and then expecting something below that it's not seeing you know. so it's a bogus error.
I get a lot of these bogus errors! Let's try compiling now. see how well we've done with
our code changes! We have another compile failure.
so " 'AimAt': is not a member of 'ATank' in the TankAIController. So here
is your second mini challenge. We seem to have done it OK for the PlayerController. it's at
least compiling. Let's see if we can get the AIController. if you can get the
AIController to do exactly the same pattern as we just followed with the playercontroller. Go ahead pause
the video and see if you can get that working!
OK welcome back! So the TankAIController.
well firstly. it includes a Tank.h. we don't want that. Remember over here.
we don't want the AIController including the Tank. so I remove the #include.
I'm also going to go to the header file and say. do I really want the
Tank in there. It's not in there. so we're good. so we can focus
in the C++ file of the AIController. We remember. don't need
these casts. In fact. we can't even have these casts now that we've removed the #include.
So ATank is a Pawn. so we don't need to change the type. we can do all
these operations on a Pawn perfectly well. So we ensure...
Well let's actually. let's use our normal pattern. If
not (!ensure(PlayerTank)) && Controlled
Tank))
in return. And what this means
is. all of this code now doesn't need to be in braces. doesn't
need to be indented. Shift. Tab to take them back. much simpler. OK so we move to the Actor and
then we say ControlledTank AimAt the (Player. Well it's
not the ControlledTank that we do that with is it? It is the
AimingComponent of the ControlledTank.
So we're just going to say auto AimingComponent
=
ControlledTank
FindComponentByClass
UTank AimingComponent. Now we actually need to create
a dependency here. because we want the AIController to depend on the Aiming
Component. So we're going to do a #include that we didn't have before.
It's one of the green lines on our graph.
That's pretty cool! So now it will recognize UTankAimingComponent. when it
catches up with us. So we
go get the AimingComponent. and then. as the AimingComponent...
...AimAt that we do. Now. ControlledTankFire. Fire wasn't working
before. we don't expect it to work now. but it should be
OK. Fire should be still a method... No it's not! It's not a
method on a Pawn anymore. because remember we removed the Tank include. We
were casting from Pawn to Tank. Pawns don't
have a Fire() method on it. We're not trying to fix firing. firing doesn't work anyway. We
comment it out and we put a TODO which is
"fix firing". OK we're focusing on aiming. let's
recompile! Keeping the scope of these things down is really important.
Notice how long these videos would be. if I wasn't breaking it
into stages for you. And each of these videos represents you sitting down between a couple of cups of coffee.
your green tea [Laughs] or whatever you drink. and we want to keep these small. So aiming
is working! Aiming is working! Awesome! Let's see if we've got any new
errors on our console! We actually haven't even got any errors
on our console now. because we're not trying to fire. because I just commented out that
Fire line in the AIController. We have Aiming
working. under the new architecture. which is fantastic news. If you look
over on our diagram. look how good a job we've done. we've nearly decoupled the Tank.
We're still working. we've still got these two things talking to the Projectile. Great news.
this is a perfect time to just go into your project. Save
All. close it down...
What have we got here? "Graph is linked to a private object(s) in an external package."
"Try to find the chain references". "(may take some time)?"
The Tank Blueprint failed to save. This happens sometimes.
It's OK. that's not the end of the world. there isn't anything too valuable in the Tank Blueprint. What I would
be tempted to do is save what you can here. not the Tank Blueprint.
Close down your VisualStudio.
Oops. I've just reopened it! And then. reopen your Tank. but just
before you commit. if you get an error just before you commit like this. then open it up again. Oh I know why!
You know why? I had two copies of the Unreal Editor open. that's what the problem
was. You can actually get that in Windows. you see them here? So only have
one of these open. Let's just make sure that our aiming works.
It does! If you want to be super sure you compile. to make sure you're compiling on the latest code.
You can see that it is! The Tank Blueprint. it's saying that it's got a problem. Let's compile
it and now we really are happy. Save All. Another useful bit of value there.
two editors open could lead to weird errors. And let's Commit our work. because we've done a
great job! See you in the next video!