So hey and welcome
to Finishing our Refactoring! In this video we are going to finish our refactoring
to our new architecture. and we will be in a position to have a nice
clean basis to move forward. with our new functionality. So I'll see you in there!
OK guys. so you guessed what we're doing in this video! We've done
Aiming without the Tank. now we need to do Firing without the Tank. So I've slightly
rejigged our architecture diagram. I've made this line here. from
the AI Controller to the Aiming Component. gray again. because well it's now like that.
And this is what we need to do. we need to break these dependencies on the
Projectile and the Barrel from the Tank. and then. we need to introduce this Aiming Component to
Tank dependency. basically moving all our code out of the Tank. And I'm going to put you
straight into the challenge! File without the Tank. Move all the remaining firing
code out of the tank. Yes the tank will end up with no useful code. to
the point that we could delete the tank class but we're not going to because we're probably going
to need it later. and deleting classes is a hassle in Unreal.
Re-specify your Projectile in the blueprint. There's a hint for you. Let me just show
you what I mean by that. So if we go to the Tank blueprint. at the moment.
you're going to be moving this bit here. where we specify the Projectile
Blueprint. you're going to be moving it to the TankAimingComponent and it will be broken. So remember
to respecify that. Remember to also rebind the firing in the blueprint.
the firing input mapping goes to the Tank. at the moment. it's going to go straight to the Aiming
Component and good luck!
Okey dokey! Let's roll up our
virtual sleeves or even our real sleeves and get our hands dirty
with this puppy! I'm going to right-click and close all but the AimingComponent. In fact. I'm going to
close everything. and i'm going to get my workspace how I want it for this
work. I want the Tank open. then the Tank.cpp.
and then I want the TankAimingComponent header file. and then I want the TankAimingComponent.cpp.
Why? Because I have some sort of OCD. OK. let's go to the Tank and
let's take a look! We have no #includes that we don't
want in the Tank. That's good news! We have a Barrel and a Projectile in the Tank. do we want them?
Well let's look at our target architecture. No we don't. so let's delete them!
We don't need those forward declarations anymore! Great! OK do we want a Fire()
method on the Tank? Uh oh. no we don't! So let's cut the Fire() method off the Tank
and put it in the TankAimingComponent. Now ask yourself. does it make
sense for the TankAimingComponent to have a public BlueprintCallable
firing method? I think it does. that makes a lot of sense! We're going to need to
remap our input. In fact. as we've broken it. let's do half
of the input remapping right away. which is we might as well break this link.
We're not calling Fire on the Tank anymore. we're going to be calling it on the AimingComponent.
So that's that! Now that means we don't even need a
public interface in the Tank. although there's no harm in leaving it there.
The Construct will leave. the BeginPlay() will leave. now
all of this stuff. What do we have? We have a
ProjectileBlueprint. a LaunchSpeed. ReloadTime.
a Barrel pointer. and a LastFireTime. Let's take all of that.
although we're not going to need all of it. and paste it into the bottom of the
TankAimingComponent. Now a couple of things. firstly. we already had a TODO to remove this
Barrel; we don't need it look there's a Barrel above. so we don't need two. let's get rid of that.
I like to have my methods at the top so... Oops. what did I just do?
Cut that. that's right! Sorry! I like to have my methods at
the top. so MoveBarrelTowards I'm going to put here under the
Constructor. Any other methods? No. Now this
LaunchSpeed. you see it's here and it's here. we already had a TODO to remove it. Let's TODO
that. OK. so on the TankAimingComponent.
what do we end up with? A Constructor made
private. just because I have OCD about public interfaces.
We have
a protected FiringState. we want that.
We have a MoveBarrelTowards private helper method. That's fine! We have
the Barrel and the Turret. it makes loads of sense. We have a default LaunchSpeed. Yep
that's fine! We have a Projectile! Right. it doesn't understand the
class AProjectile. Do we want it to? Do we want ATankAiming
Component to depend on the Projectile? Yes! It's that green arrow. we need to introduce it. So
what do we do? Well we forward declare
AProjectile. So if we're adding it in the header file. we're
probably going to want to add it in the C++ file. Do we use projectiles in the
C++ file anywhere? I'm pretty sure we do. I can't
see it at a glance. Let's just search for "projectile"
in the Current Document.
I looks like we actually don't. we only need it in the forward
declaration. That's a bit strange. I think that we probably are going to need it.
Where do we use it in the header file?
In the ProjectileBlueprint! We don't actually. in this case we only need it
in the header file. because we're just dealing with a blueprint. so I'm probably
going to end up changing this line to a dotted line effectively. but
let's carry on! So here we go. we've got these three. we've got all that stuff. let's get
rid of the .cpp and see what needs to happen here!
Not very clear to me. looking at it. what needs to happen
now. It's all a little but confused. so what I'm going to do is use the
compiler to help me. I could go through carefully and reason about it. but of course. the compiler is
here to check these dependencies for us. So this is a good time to flip back over
and hit Compile. Now remember. as in the previous video. if you're not sure go to GitHub.
it's linked in the resources. and find out what code
changes I'm making. OK. so the Tank. " 'Fire': is not a member of 'ATank' ". so that's a very
simple thing. That's because we need to take the Fire() method out of the
Tank and put it in the TankAimingComponent. There it is! So I deleted it
in the header file. and when you do that. when you move a method from one class to another. remember to
re-annotate like this. Okey dokey. that's
cool! What else is in the .cpp? Just the
just the BeginPlay() stuff. Now. by the way. does BeginPlay() needed for the Blueprint
Begin play to run. that's true. but if you were to take out the method altogether and not
override it. then that wouldn't be the case. So for the sake of less
lines of code. why don't we just do that. We pretty much need no
code whatsoever in our tank. by the way. We can pretty much just
take all of this stuff out. maybe just leave the Constructor there.
take all of this even the BeginPlay(). just to prove the point.
And all we're doing in the Constructor is stopping the Tank itself from ticking. just for
performance purposes. Why does it need to tick? It's just a placeholder for the moment. So that's the
Tank. it's stripped down to absolutely nothing. which is quite fun.
OK cool! AimingComponent is probably
in a better state. Let's use a the compiler to tell. Would you do this on a bigger project?
Possibly. The compiler is pretty good at only compiling the stuff it needs to. so there's no
harm in using the compiler to work out what your next port of call is with your refactor.
It's not kind of lazy or cheating. I don't think. it's fine to just
OK. let's kind of check in and see where we need to go. So
"use of undefined type 'AProjectile' ". in TankAimingComponent. So we actually did
need the projectile. I though we didn't. I missed this when I saw it. so we.
of course. do need to #include the Projectile.
Wicked!
OK. Now there's somewhere else... Before I even move on. I've just realized there's
somewhere else that's bound not to work. which is that the TankPlayerController.
what does it do when we fire? Well we don't. remember we fire
directly from input binding. so we can't do anything
there until it compiles. because it won't appear in the blueprint. we can't go in and connect that up yet.
How about the TankAIController? Well that doesn't fire yet
and that's OK. We weren't firing before we started this moving
of the firing code into here. so we don't need to fix it
yet. not till we're compiling. not will we're compiling. Let's get it compiling!
So I think we're good to try recompiling again. and it'll be a pretty
simple job. I think. to get the AITankCompiling and even getting us firing should be
relatively simple as well. So let's see! Ah. Compile Complete! Brilliant! What happens
if we play? Well we can aim. I can't fire. Not
surprising! Let's go bind the input. on the Tank! Now the way you do this is. you take the Tank
AimingComponent. give yourself a bit more space maybe. Actually. also ask the
question. is this comment block reasonable. AimInputBinding? It's really firing
or Ballistics
Input binding. Keep everything up to date. keep your comments up to
date. They're bad enough that they don't keep themselves up to date. Come off the AimingComponent and say Fire.
because it's the right type of annotation on there you can do it. When you press the key.
you Fire straight into the Aiming Component. Let's try it! Now. why did that crash? I
don't have a particularly good reason why that crashed. We made a change to a blueprint. Unreal
gets a bit touchy about that sometimes. I'm not too worried that that crashes there. that's why we save regularly.
You go back to your tank blueprint. and you just swear a little bit under your
breath. and try again. So
there's an error on that. Ah we Compiled.
It is important we Compiled! Tank Aiming Reference comes in
Fire comes in. Now this is why it's a good habit.
actually. when you do this. to compile your blueprint and then save it. Or
you could go to File and Save All here. Now let's try playing!
Can I fire? Ooh interesting. hard crash when I try and
fire! Why would that be? In the TankPlayerController?
No it doesn't happen there. so it would be in the TankAimingComponent. which we really need to
rename to BallisticsComponent. at some point. Is there any reason? Are we not
protecting something? So if not (!ensure(Barrel)). we need a Barrel to fire. That's true!
The Projectile Blueprint! [Laughs] Ha ha. the thing I told you to... The thing I
told you to make sure... So by the way. look this ProjectileBlueprint.
we need to have that ProjectileBlueprint there in order
for this to work. In fact. for firing to work at all. we need a ProjectileBlueprint.
So we'd better say if not (!ensure(Barrel && ProjectileBlueprint)).
Yeah that would save that crash for us.
So I'll recompile! While I'm recompiling. let's pop into the tank.
Let's go do the... What am I going to? Not the Tank itself. it's not on there
anymore. it's on the TankAimingComponent. and it's here. Projectile Blueprint. under the
Setup section. Projectile Blueprint! Ah hah! I didn't even warn you about
that and I made the mistake myself. but I have put the relevant  in place now.
to prevent that hard crash from happening in that instance again. Play!
Now. can I fire? Yes I can! I can fire and then I wait 3 seconds. and I can
fire again. Cool! Now we just need to fix the AI Tanks! We are
very very nearly there! TankAIController.cpp.
TODO fix tank firing. limit the firing rate. we'll leave that as a thing.
It's not the ControlledTank that fires. it is the AimingComponent!
I think it's pretty much as simple as that actually.
I've done all the other work. Let's go and see! Compile our
code and then hopefully we are there!
OK let's see if this
works! I'm firing. they're firing. I'll F11 it.
Yeah they're firing every 3 seconds. Good we are operating
on the new... [Laughs] We are operating on the new architecture! That is
fantastic news! So let's go to our architecture diagram! What have we done? We've got
rid of the Tank dependencies. from the Tank. altogether. We're
in this state. In fact. the Tank is basically completely sidelined and
irrelevant right now. I'm just going to whip through. in the next minute or
two and just check that this is actually the dependency map that we actually have. So let's go
back to where we started all of this and whip through the dependencies
and just make sure that we've got exactly what we hope to have. So
we're going to reopen VisualStudio. The Projectile should depend on nothing. It does. The
Tank should depend on. nothing actually. We can remove the #includes from the
Tank. The AIController should depend on only
the AimingComponent. That's correct! The AimingComponent
should depend on the Projectile. the Barrel. and the Turret.
Yep. the Barrel should depend on nothing. Check!
The TankMovementComponent should only depend on the Track. it's tangential to what we're doing with aiming
but we remember that that's true. The PlayerController should only depend on the Aiming
Component. Yep! The
Track should depend on nothing and the Turret should depend on nothing. Look. awesome! If you really want to be
thorough here. you can check that that same set of dependencies works in terms of your forward
declaration. so I'm looking for the word Class here. Should the AIController have
a forward declaration of Tank? No. it doesn't need it. so let's do that. let's get
rid of that! Should the AimingComponent have forward declarations for
anything? It doesn't look like it needs them or it wouldn't be compiling.
Should the Barrel... Again it doesn't have any. Yes the MovementComponent
needs the Track. does the PlayerController need the AimingComponent? Yes!
Does the Track need anything? No and it doesn't have anything and neither does the Turret.
Ahhh. what a refactor! Let's do a
final compile. Please remember that you can go to GitHub
and you can look at the Commit. which isn't showing on my screen yet because I haven't made the commit.
but the previous one was and that was your code changes.
Just check it compiles. play the game.
I'm even going to turn my XBox controller on.
Just wait for it to warm up and then I'm going to move away
myself. try and get away from these pesky enemy tanks if
I can. Now I need to replay.
Here we go! Now I can move
and I can fire. and we're back in the position where we've now got a chance of actually setting
this UI to how we want it. All of these physics problems. by the way. will be fixed on a future iteration
of the game. So look. huge congratulations on getting this far! It's a lot of
work to get to a new architecture! I hope you'll agree that our architecture is a lot cleaner
than it used to be. a lot simpler to reason about. We understand a lot more about Unreal.
which is the whole point of this course. And I will see you in the upcoming videos. where we actually start
to add new functionality. on top of this new quality base that we have built!
=======
So hey and welcome
to Finishing our Refactoring! In this video we are going to finish our refactoring
to our new architecture, and we will be in a position to have a nice
clean basis to move forward, with our new functionality. So I'll see you in there!
OK guys, so you guessed what we're doing in this video! We've done
Aiming without the Tank, now we need to do Firing without the Tank. So I've slightly
rejigged our architecture diagram. I've made this line here, from
the AI Controller to the Aiming Component, gray again, because well it's now like that.
And this is what we need to do, we need to break these dependencies on the
Projectile and the Barrel from the Tank, and then, we need to introduce this Aiming Component to
Tank dependency, basically moving all our code out of the Tank. And I'm going to put you
straight into the challenge! File without the Tank. Move all the remaining firing
code out of the tank. Yes the tank will end up with no useful code, to
the point that we could delete the tank class but we're not going to because we're probably going
to need it later, and deleting classes is a hassle in Unreal.
Re-specify your Projectile in the blueprint. There's a hint for you. Let me just show
you what I mean by that. So if we go to the Tank blueprint, at the moment,
you're going to be moving this bit here, where we specify the Projectile
Blueprint, you're going to be moving it to the TankAimingComponent and it will be broken. So remember
to respecify that. Remember to also rebind the firing in the blueprint,
the firing input mapping goes to the Tank, at the moment, it's going to go straight to the Aiming
Component and good luck!
Okey dokey! Let's roll up our
virtual sleeves or even our real sleeves and get our hands dirty
with this puppy! I'm going to right-click and close all but the AimingComponent. In fact, I'm going to
close everything, and i'm going to get my workspace how I want it for this
work. I want the Tank open, then the Tank.cpp,
and then I want the TankAimingComponent header file, and then I want the TankAimingComponent.cpp.
Why? Because I have some sort of OCD. OK, let's go to the Tank and
let's take a look! We have no #includes that we don't
want in the Tank. That's good news! We have a Barrel and a Projectile in the Tank, do we want them?
Well let's look at our target architecture. No we don't, so let's delete them!
We don't need those forward declarations anymore! Great! OK do we want a Fire()
method on the Tank? Uh oh, no we don't! So let's cut the Fire() method off the Tank
and put it in the TankAimingComponent. Now ask yourself, does it make
sense for the TankAimingComponent to have a public BlueprintCallable
firing method? I think it does, that makes a lot of sense! We're going to need to
remap our input. In fact, as we've broken it, let's do half
of the input remapping right away, which is we might as well break this link.
We're not calling Fire on the Tank anymore, we're going to be calling it on the AimingComponent.
So that's that! Now that means we don't even need a
public interface in the Tank, although there's no harm in leaving it there.
The Construct will leave, the BeginPlay() will leave, now
all of this stuff. What do we have? We have a
ProjectileBlueprint, a LaunchSpeed, ReloadTime,
a Barrel pointer, and a LastFireTime. Let's take all of that,
although we're not going to need all of it, and paste it into the bottom of the
TankAimingComponent. Now a couple of things, firstly, we already had a TODO to remove this
Barrel; we don't need it look there's a Barrel above, so we don't need two, let's get rid of that.
I like to have my methods at the top so... Oops, what did I just do?
Cut that, that's right! Sorry! I like to have my methods at
the top, so MoveBarrelTowards I'm going to put here under the
Constructor. Any other methods? No. Now this
LaunchSpeed, you see it's here and it's here, we already had a TODO to remove it. Let's TODO
that. OK, so on the TankAimingComponent,
what do we end up with? A Constructor made
private, just because I have OCD about public interfaces.
We have
a protected FiringState, we want that.
We have a MoveBarrelTowards private helper method. That's fine! We have
the Barrel and the Turret, it makes loads of sense. We have a default LaunchSpeed. Yep
that's fine! We have a Projectile! Right, it doesn't understand the
class AProjectile. Do we want it to? Do we want ATankAiming
Component to depend on the Projectile? Yes! It's that green arrow, we need to introduce it. So
what do we do? Well we forward declare
AProjectile. So if we're adding it in the header file, we're
probably going to want to add it in the C++ file. Do we use projectiles in the
C++ file anywhere? I'm pretty sure we do. I can't
see it at a glance. Let's just search for "projectile"
in the Current Document.
I looks like we actually don't, we only need it in the forward
declaration. That's a bit strange, I think that we probably are going to need it.
Where do we use it in the header file?
In the ProjectileBlueprint! We don't actually, in this case we only need it
in the header file, because we're just dealing with a blueprint, so I'm probably
going to end up changing this line to a dotted line effectively, but
let's carry on! So here we go, we've got these three, we've got all that stuff, let's get
rid of the .cpp and see what needs to happen here!
Not very clear to me, looking at it, what needs to happen
now. It's all a little but confused, so what I'm going to do is use the
compiler to help me. I could go through carefully and reason about it, but of course, the compiler is
here to check these dependencies for us. So this is a good time to flip back over
and hit Compile. Now remember, as in the previous video, if you're not sure go to GitHub,
it's linked in the resources, and find out what code
changes I'm making. OK, so the Tank, " 'Fire': is not a member of 'ATank' ", so that's a very
simple thing. That's because we need to take the Fire() method out of the
Tank and put it in the TankAimingComponent. There it is! So I deleted it
in the header file, and when you do that, when you move a method from one class to another, remember to
re-annotate like this. Okey dokey, that's
cool! What else is in the .cpp? Just the
just the BeginPlay() stuff. Now, by the way, does BeginPlay() needed for the Blueprint
Begin play to run, that's true, but if you were to take out the method altogether and not
override it, then that wouldn't be the case. So for the sake of less
lines of code, why don't we just do that. We pretty much need no
code whatsoever in our tank, by the way. We can pretty much just
take all of this stuff out, maybe just leave the Constructor there,
take all of this even the BeginPlay(), just to prove the point.
And all we're doing in the Constructor is stopping the Tank itself from ticking, just for
performance purposes. Why does it need to tick? It's just a placeholder for the moment. So that's the
Tank, it's stripped down to absolutely nothing, which is quite fun.
OK cool! AimingComponent is probably
in a better state. Let's use a the compiler to tell. Would you do this on a bigger project?
Possibly. The compiler is pretty good at only compiling the stuff it needs to, so there's no
harm in using the compiler to work out what your next port of call is with your refactor.
It's not kind of lazy or cheating, I don't think, it's fine to just
OK, let's kind of check in and see where we need to go. So
"use of undefined type 'AProjectile' ", in TankAimingComponent. So we actually did
need the projectile, I though we didn't. I missed this when I saw it, so we,
of course, do need to #include the Projectile.
Wicked!
OK. Now there's somewhere else... Before I even move on, I've just realized there's
somewhere else that's bound not to work, which is that the TankPlayerController,
what does it do when we fire? Well we don't, remember we fire
directly from input binding, so we can't do anything
there until it compiles, because it won't appear in the blueprint, we can't go in and connect that up yet.
How about the TankAIController? Well that doesn't fire yet
and that's OK. We weren't firing before we started this moving
of the firing code into here, so we don't need to fix it
yet, not till we're compiling, not will we're compiling. Let's get it compiling!
So I think we're good to try recompiling again, and it'll be a pretty
simple job, I think, to get the AITankCompiling and even getting us firing should be
relatively simple as well. So let's see! Ah, Compile Complete! Brilliant! What happens
if we play? Well we can aim, I can't fire. Not
surprising! Let's go bind the input, on the Tank! Now the way you do this is, you take the Tank
AimingComponent, give yourself a bit more space maybe. Actually, also ask the
question, is this comment block reasonable, AimInputBinding? It's really firing
or Ballistics
Input binding. Keep everything up to date, keep your comments up to
date. They're bad enough that they don't keep themselves up to date. Come off the AimingComponent and say Fire,
because it's the right type of annotation on there you can do it. When you press the key,
you Fire straight into the Aiming Component. Let's try it! Now, why did that crash? I
don't have a particularly good reason why that crashed. We made a change to a blueprint, Unreal
gets a bit touchy about that sometimes. I'm not too worried that that crashes there, that's why we save regularly.
You go back to your tank blueprint, and you just swear a little bit under your
breath, and try again. So
there's an error on that. Ah we Compiled.
It is important we Compiled! Tank Aiming Reference comes in
Fire comes in. Now this is why it's a good habit,
actually, when you do this, to compile your blueprint and then save it. Or
you could go to File and Save All here. Now let's try playing!
Can I fire? Ooh interesting, hard crash when I try and
fire! Why would that be? In the TankPlayerController?
No it doesn't happen there, so it would be in the TankAimingComponent, which we really need to
rename to BallisticsComponent, at some point. Is there any reason? Are we not
protecting something? So if not (!ensure(Barrel)), we need a Barrel to fire. That's true!
The Projectile Blueprint! [Laughs] Ha ha, the thing I told you to... The thing I
told you to make sure... So by the way, look this ProjectileBlueprint,
we need to have that ProjectileBlueprint there in order
for this to work. In fact, for firing to work at all, we need a ProjectileBlueprint.
So we'd better say if not (!ensure(Barrel && ProjectileBlueprint)).
Yeah that would save that crash for us.
So I'll recompile! While I'm recompiling, let's pop into the tank.
Let's go do the... What am I going to? Not the Tank itself, it's not on there
anymore, it's on the TankAimingComponent, and it's here. Projectile Blueprint, under the
Setup section. Projectile Blueprint! Ah hah! I didn't even warn you about
that and I made the mistake myself, but I have put the relevant  in place now,
to prevent that hard crash from happening in that instance again. Play!
Now, can I fire? Yes I can! I can fire and then I wait 3 seconds, and I can
fire again. Cool! Now we just need to fix the AI Tanks! We are
very very nearly there! TankAIController.cpp.
TODO fix tank firing, limit the firing rate, we'll leave that as a thing.
It's not the ControlledTank that fires, it is the AimingComponent!
I think it's pretty much as simple as that actually,
I've done all the other work. Let's go and see! Compile our
code and then hopefully we are there!
OK let's see if this
works! I'm firing, they're firing, I'll F11 it.
Yeah they're firing every 3 seconds. Good we are operating
on the new... [Laughs] We are operating on the new architecture! That is
fantastic news! So let's go to our architecture diagram! What have we done? We've got
rid of the Tank dependencies, from the Tank, altogether. We're
in this state. In fact, the Tank is basically completely sidelined and
irrelevant right now. I'm just going to whip through, in the next minute or
two and just check that this is actually the dependency map that we actually have. So let's go
back to where we started all of this and whip through the dependencies
and just make sure that we've got exactly what we hope to have. So
we're going to reopen VisualStudio. The Projectile should depend on nothing. It does. The
Tank should depend on, nothing actually. We can remove the #includes from the
Tank. The AIController should depend on only
the AimingComponent. That's correct! The AimingComponent
should depend on the Projectile, the Barrel, and the Turret.
Yep, the Barrel should depend on nothing. Check!
The TankMovementComponent should only depend on the Track, it's tangential to what we're doing with aiming
but we remember that that's true. The PlayerController should only depend on the Aiming
Component. Yep! The
Track should depend on nothing and the Turret should depend on nothing. Look, awesome! If you really want to be
thorough here, you can check that that same set of dependencies works in terms of your forward
declaration, so I'm looking for the word Class here. Should the AIController have
a forward declaration of Tank? No, it doesn't need it, so let's do that, let's get
rid of that! Should the AimingComponent have forward declarations for
anything? It doesn't look like it needs them or it wouldn't be compiling.
Should the Barrel... Again it doesn't have any. Yes the MovementComponent
needs the Track. does the PlayerController need the AimingComponent? Yes!
Does the Track need anything? No and it doesn't have anything and neither does the Turret.
Ahhh, what a refactor! Let's do a
final compile. Please remember that you can go to GitHub
and you can look at the Commit, which isn't showing on my screen yet because I haven't made the commit,
but the previous one was and that was your code changes.
Just check it compiles, play the game.
I'm even going to turn my XBox controller on.
Just wait for it to warm up and then I'm going to move away
myself, try and get away from these pesky enemy tanks if
I can. Now I need to replay.
Here we go! Now I can move
and I can fire, and we're back in the position where we've now got a chance of actually setting
this UI to how we want it. All of these physics problems, by the way, will be fixed on a future iteration
of the game. So look, huge congratulations on getting this far! It's a lot of
work to get to a new architecture! I hope you'll agree that our architecture is a lot cleaner
than it used to be, a lot simpler to reason about. We understand a lot more about Unreal,
which is the whole point of this course. And I will see you in the upcoming videos, where we actually start
to add new functionality, on top of this new quality base that we have built!
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1:Unreal/Section4/BT77 Finishing our Refactoring.srt