Hey. and for want of a better
name I'm going to call this Adding TickComponent() Back! It's a little bit more than that. we'll
be about halfway towards this crosshair changing color. based on firing state. by the
end. and the trickiest bit would be adding the TickComponents
back to a AActorComponent. You've got BeginPlay() and
TickComponent rather than Tick. and we're going to see how to do that. amongst a whole bunch of other things.
So just before I start this one. I'm getting some real strange things going on with my
project. so I've gone back to my previous checkout. which is just
here. the last video. Remember how you clear things out. you select
these directories .vs. Binaries. Intermediate.
and Saved. and the solution file. and the database file on
PC. very similar on the Mac. Delete the whole lot.
rebuild the VisualStudio project files. Yes you can do that on a Mac. but you have to go down
to Services. at the bottom of the right-click menu. and then generate Xcode
project. Once your project is generated. you won't be able to open Unreal. because
it will not have been compiled. so you need to go in and build your project.
Once that's built then you'll have a clean build. so sometimes it's worth doing
this. What happens. occasionally between videos. is I go ahead and explore and try
some stuff and then reset my commit. If you're doing that. if you're doing something
exploratory and you decide. hang on what I've just tried to do hasn't worked at all. I'm going to go back
to my last known working position. my last commit. Then.
sometimes you can just reopen the Editor and recompile your code. but sometimes you'll end up with
too much stuff that cached and the Editor may end up in a funny state. So then. you
need to clear this out. as per the video in the previous section about clearing derived
files. So once it has compiled in VisualStudio. it's a question of just
reopening in the Editor. and you should be good to go.
What it's doing here is it's trying to spawn my Oculus program.
and that's because I've probably got VR plugins turn on.
If you get a VR device and you don't want it trying to open it. you can turn all these plugins
off. You can then
restart the Editor. once those things have been saved. and it won't try and open
those plugins again.
So there you go!
Alright. so let's have a look where we are! Anything to look at on the console? No. Let's play the game!
It all seems to be OK!
Good to go! Alright. so let's start looking at the issues. What we're trying
to do here is. we're trying to get the cursor to change color. So
this is going to be in the TankAimingComponent.
and let's start with this bit here. where
we say isReloaded. So. at the moment. we're using a boolean
and a local boolean in the Fire() method called isReloaded. What we want to do
is keep track of whether we're reloaded every single frame. So the first challenge we have
to overcome is putting a Tick method back into this. So we currently
don't have a Tick. How do you find out what the Tick signature is for
an ActorComponent? Remember if we go to the header file for this guy that
it is a ActorComponent. Well one way is to go to the
definition of an ActorComponent. go and look at the actual code that you're going to be overriding.
search for Tick or TickComponent. I happen to know that it is.
Just cancel that search. because I've accidentally searched in the entire project
but it's found it. I meant to search in just this file but it's OK. On line
478 of the ActorComponent. here we go. we have the signature for Tick
Component. There it is! So you can copy that. probably the easiest way.
and go ahead and put it into the private
section. because we're not going to be calling it from any of our other classes of the TankAiming
Component. Notice it's a bit weird. it needs a DeltaTime.
an enum about the LevelTick type. and an FActorComponent
TickFunction. So just paste it in but. of course. we need override
just to signal that we want to check that against the parent class. to make sure that we've
got exactly the right naming. And then. I'm going to go ahead and put this
under the Constructor. inside the C++ file.
without the virtual. without the override on the end.
and that's it. we're good to go! Now the only other thing we need to do to make it tick is. where it says
PrimaryComponentTick.vCanEverTick. in the Constructor. that needs to be
true. OK. let's just check that this is
ticking. UE_LOG(LogTemp.
Warning. TEXT
("Aiming Comp. ticking"). OK
fantastic! Save that and go ahead and Compile! I'll show you the source
control. so you can see what's changed while it compiles.
We have switched this boolean in the constructor and popped the Tick
signature in. And the other place you can get that signature is here from Unreal docs.
UActorComponent::TickComponent and the signature is here. I'll put that in the resources of the
lecture for you. Cool! Compile failed! So we've made a
boo boo! Where did I make a boo boo?
OK unresolved externals mean linker errors about unresolved
externals. mean that I have a mismatch in my signature somewhere. So let's look at it
in the header file! I say virtual void TickComponent in the C++
file. What I'm missing is the name of the class
OK. so that's the problem there. Let's try and recompile.
So whenever you see a linker area. the first thing is
to try and see. why can't it link these two things together. and it's because typically.
you have a mismatch in signature. Let's play the game! It's taking a long
time to play. which suggests it's either going to crash or an ensure is going to fire off.
The game started but what's going on? Now we've got some serious errors here!
Unresolved externals. that'll be from the last build.
Starting HotReload. HotReload successful. OK so further down.
"Handled error". "Barrel && ProjectileBlueprint" on
line 72 of the TankAimingComponent. Let's go look at that! We have an assertion failure on line
72. So here we check both the Barrel pointer
and the ProjectileBlueprint pointer simultaneously. This will happen. by the way. immediately
that the game starts. because currently the AI is firing immediately when the
game starts. you probably noticed that. So one thing I can do is. move this assertion down to
where we need it. which is here. We don't need it until we're reloaded and about to fire.
And the other thing we can do is split this into two assertions. one about the Barrel
and one about the ProjectileBlueprint. and that will give us more
information than we currently have about this error. Let's see if there are any other errors! This is the
stack trace for that error. Nope! So I'm going to clear the log. recompile.
and play the game. So the change there is to take this assertion from
the top of the TankAimingComponent Fire() method and move it down into the
if statement. so that it is done just in time. Playing the game is
still taking a while. Now we get to find out whether it's the Barrel or the ProjectileBlueprint that's causing the
problem.
Firstly. I can fire so. at some point. that does have a ProjectileBlueprint
pointer set and the Barrel moved. Which one is it? The ProjectileBlueprint!
OK. so I'm not going to worry too much about that. right now.
because we're about to change the logic anyway so that we... In fact. let's change the logic now!
Let's say that LastFireTime = FPlatformTime in Seconds
on BeginPlay(). so that neither of us can fire until we
have waited for an initial reload. for the gun to load in the first place.
Let's do that on the BeginPlay(). so here's a little challenge
for you. I just want you to add BeginPlay() in. which is much simpler than the
TickComponent. and then. insert that line of code there about the
last fire time. which will make sure we can't fire until we've waited for the reload time. in the
beginning. I'm not going to put a challenge slide. I'm going to keep you on your feet.
There's not always going to be a challenge slide there. I'm hoping you're listening. too.
OK so I'm going to use that line of code. because I've already got it in the paste buffer.
I'm going to take the class name. because I know I'm going to need that. it's going to be void
the class name BeginPlay(). It doesn't actually take any parameters. which is helpful.
Then. we've got this guy here. which I'm going to put in curlies.
And then. all that remains. in order to do that. is to comment
why we're doing this. "// So that first fire is after
initial reload". And then. we just need to go
virtual void BeginPlay() override on here. which I'd prefer to put just
above the TickComponent.
Perfect! Now let's see if that prevents. see what
that prevents. Firstly. it may prevent this error. It may just be that the Projectile
Blueprint is not available. not set quite that early. It is
set. of course. on the Tank against the TankBlueprint.
on the TankAimingComponent here. and it is set but maybe it doesn't get set quite early enough.
So we have a Compile Failure. it's probably something simple: " 'void' should be preceded
by" something on the TankAimingComponent. header file 45.
and that's because I can't spell virtual! OK
let's refresh. clear the logs because I want a nice
clear slate to start from. and then. see how we get on. So this is all about overriding
methods in Actor
Components. OK. let's play the game. see what happens. It played nice and quick.
Aiming is working. and I can't fire for
presumably 3 seconds. Yes. in the beginning! Let's just retest that one!
I'm firing. I'm clicking clicking clicking clicking. and the AI tanks aren't firing either.
until we get to the 3 second mark. I'm just going to make sure the AI tanks
do eventually fire. I'm going to do that by going F11. get my controller
out. my Xbox controller. and just move away.
and make sure that eventually these guys can actually fire. We must sort that bug with selft-
collisions with the ground. Yep. I just saw one fire there! OK. so that
initial firing is working now. The next thing I want to do. just before
we finish off this particular video. is to rather than in the
Fire use this... Where are we? ...this isReloaded. we want to use
the enum we've already setup. So how are we going to do that? Well
we'll do it up in the Tick. won't we? We're going to use that logic.
In fact. I'll cut that logic now. and I'll say if
(FiringState
!= not equal to EFiringStateReloading.
So if it's not reloading. then go ahead and fire OK.
So now. we need to set the logic for it reloading or not reloading. we do this in Tick.
We don't need the log anymore in here. but we can say if and then
this logic. which is the difference between
the PlatformTime and the LastFireTime. By the way. if you don't like Platform
Time. then you are welcome to say something different. which we've done before
which is GetWorld GetTimeInSeconds. I'm not going to change it until it causes a problem.
It will cause a problem later. but I just thought I'd put that as an aside. You can go
GetWorld arrow GetTimeInSeconds. Anyway. if the PlatformTime -
the LastFireTime is greater than the ReloadTime. i.e. if we have reloaded. then
what do we do with this state? Well then EFiringState
or FiringState = EFiringState. to fully declare it
Reloading. OK. that's all
very well. let's try it! But of course. it's never going to leave the Reloading state with this
particular code is it. because this guy is going to set it to Reloading. But
nothing is going to be setting it to another state. which is the Aiming or the Locked state.
but we'll do that in another video. So let's just try now! What do we get? We get
continuous firing from the AI tanks and that's expected. as I
say. because if you look over in the TankAimingComponent we are not
initializing. We need to initialize to Reloading. that's going to be
our initial state is that it's not ready to fire. Let's try that! So it
initializes to Reloading. Every frame it asks the
question. has it been the ReloadTime since
we last fired? When did we last fire? On BeginPlay(). So let's see
what the behavior is like now. No firing for 1. 2.
3. and then. of course. it never leaves the ReloadingState.
which is expected at this point. because we need further logic under here
which we will do in the next video. So I just flesh out the further logic.
"// TODO Handle
aiming and locked states".
There you go! But let's not do that now. this video is plenty long enough. Congratulations
on getting that far! I'm going to Save All my code.
quickly review with you what has been done. in terms of the source
control changes. and then. we will start finishing... [Laughs] Start finishing.
Finish this in the next video. So we have a BeginPlay()
that's been put in. We on BeginPlay() set the initial
fire as if it's fired. phantom fire in the beginning. On
Tick we ask whether or not the Reload
Time has passed or not. Later. we'll handle the rest of the states. we move some checks
and split them up. from up here down into there. and we moved the
whole idea. instead of using a local boolean. we're using the member
variable FiringState enum. And then. the changes in the header file are just the
changes we had to put in the header file. to support those code changes. So fantastic! I'll see you in the
next video!
=======
Hey, and for want of a better
name I'm going to call this Adding TickComponent() Back! It's a little bit more than that, we'll
be about halfway towards this crosshair changing color, based on firing state, by the
end, and the trickiest bit would be adding the TickComponents
back to a AActorComponent. You've got BeginPlay() and
TickComponent rather than Tick, and we're going to see how to do that, amongst a whole bunch of other things.
So just before I start this one, I'm getting some real strange things going on with my
project, so I've gone back to my previous checkout, which is just
here, the last video. Remember how you clear things out, you select
these directories .vs, Binaries, Intermediate,
and Saved, and the solution file, and the database file on
PC, very similar on the Mac. Delete the whole lot,
rebuild the VisualStudio project files. Yes you can do that on a Mac, but you have to go down
to Services, at the bottom of the right-click menu, and then generate Xcode
project. Once your project is generated, you won't be able to open Unreal, because
it will not have been compiled, so you need to go in and build your project.
Once that's built then you'll have a clean build, so sometimes it's worth doing
this. What happens, occasionally between videos, is I go ahead and explore and try
some stuff and then reset my commit. If you're doing that, if you're doing something
exploratory and you decide, hang on what I've just tried to do hasn't worked at all, I'm going to go back
to my last known working position, my last commit. Then,
sometimes you can just reopen the Editor and recompile your code, but sometimes you'll end up with
too much stuff that cached and the Editor may end up in a funny state. So then, you
need to clear this out, as per the video in the previous section about clearing derived
files. So once it has compiled in VisualStudio, it's a question of just
reopening in the Editor, and you should be good to go.
What it's doing here is it's trying to spawn my Oculus program,
and that's because I've probably got VR plugins turn on.
If you get a VR device and you don't want it trying to open it, you can turn all these plugins
off. You can then
restart the Editor, once those things have been saved, and it won't try and open
those plugins again.
So there you go!
Alright, so let's have a look where we are! Anything to look at on the console? No. Let's play the game!
It all seems to be OK!
Good to go! Alright, so let's start looking at the issues. What we're trying
to do here is, we're trying to get the cursor to change color. So
this is going to be in the TankAimingComponent,
and let's start with this bit here, where
we say isReloaded. So, at the moment, we're using a boolean
and a local boolean in the Fire() method called isReloaded. What we want to do
is keep track of whether we're reloaded every single frame. So the first challenge we have
to overcome is putting a Tick method back into this. So we currently
don't have a Tick. How do you find out what the Tick signature is for
an ActorComponent? Remember if we go to the header file for this guy that
it is a ActorComponent. Well one way is to go to the
definition of an ActorComponent, go and look at the actual code that you're going to be overriding,
search for Tick or TickComponent, I happen to know that it is.
Just cancel that search, because I've accidentally searched in the entire project
but it's found it. I meant to search in just this file but it's OK. On line
478 of the ActorComponent, here we go, we have the signature for Tick
Component. There it is! So you can copy that, probably the easiest way,
and go ahead and put it into the private
section, because we're not going to be calling it from any of our other classes of the TankAiming
Component. Notice it's a bit weird, it needs a DeltaTime,
an enum about the LevelTick type, and an FActorComponent
TickFunction. So just paste it in but, of course, we need override
just to signal that we want to check that against the parent class, to make sure that we've
got exactly the right naming. And then, I'm going to go ahead and put this
under the Constructor, inside the C++ file,
without the virtual, without the override on the end,
and that's it, we're good to go! Now the only other thing we need to do to make it tick is, where it says
PrimaryComponentTick.vCanEverTick, in the Constructor, that needs to be
true. OK, let's just check that this is
ticking. UE_LOG(LogTemp,
Warning, TEXT
("Aiming Comp. ticking"). OK
fantastic! Save that and go ahead and Compile! I'll show you the source
control, so you can see what's changed while it compiles.
We have switched this boolean in the constructor and popped the Tick
signature in. And the other place you can get that signature is here from Unreal docs.
UActorComponent::TickComponent and the signature is here. I'll put that in the resources of the
lecture for you. Cool! Compile failed! So we've made a
boo boo! Where did I make a boo boo?
OK unresolved externals mean linker errors about unresolved
externals, mean that I have a mismatch in my signature somewhere. So let's look at it
in the header file! I say virtual void TickComponent in the C++
file. What I'm missing is the name of the class
OK, so that's the problem there. Let's try and recompile.
So whenever you see a linker area, the first thing is
to try and see, why can't it link these two things together, and it's because typically,
you have a mismatch in signature. Let's play the game! It's taking a long
time to play, which suggests it's either going to crash or an ensure is going to fire off.
The game started but what's going on? Now we've got some serious errors here!
Unresolved externals, that'll be from the last build.
Starting HotReload, HotReload successful. OK so further down,
"Handled error". "Barrel && ProjectileBlueprint" on
line 72 of the TankAimingComponent. Let's go look at that! We have an assertion failure on line
72. So here we check both the Barrel pointer
and the ProjectileBlueprint pointer simultaneously. This will happen, by the way, immediately
that the game starts, because currently the AI is firing immediately when the
game starts, you probably noticed that. So one thing I can do is, move this assertion down to
where we need it, which is here. We don't need it until we're reloaded and about to fire.
And the other thing we can do is split this into two assertions, one about the Barrel
and one about the ProjectileBlueprint, and that will give us more
information than we currently have about this error. Let's see if there are any other errors! This is the
stack trace for that error. Nope! So I'm going to clear the log, recompile,
and play the game. So the change there is to take this assertion from
the top of the TankAimingComponent Fire() method and move it down into the
if statement, so that it is done just in time. Playing the game is
still taking a while. Now we get to find out whether it's the Barrel or the ProjectileBlueprint that's causing the
problem.
Firstly, I can fire so, at some point, that does have a ProjectileBlueprint
pointer set and the Barrel moved. Which one is it? The ProjectileBlueprint!
OK, so I'm not going to worry too much about that, right now,
because we're about to change the logic anyway so that we... In fact, let's change the logic now!
Let's say that LastFireTime = FPlatformTime in Seconds
on BeginPlay(), so that neither of us can fire until we
have waited for an initial reload, for the gun to load in the first place.
Let's do that on the BeginPlay(), so here's a little challenge
for you. I just want you to add BeginPlay() in, which is much simpler than the
TickComponent, and then, insert that line of code there about the
last fire time, which will make sure we can't fire until we've waited for the reload time, in the
beginning. I'm not going to put a challenge slide, I'm going to keep you on your feet.
There's not always going to be a challenge slide there, I'm hoping you're listening, too.
OK so I'm going to use that line of code, because I've already got it in the paste buffer,
I'm going to take the class name, because I know I'm going to need that, it's going to be void
the class name BeginPlay(). It doesn't actually take any parameters, which is helpful.
Then, we've got this guy here, which I'm going to put in curlies.
And then, all that remains, in order to do that, is to comment
why we're doing this. "// So that first fire is after
initial reload". And then, we just need to go
virtual void BeginPlay() override on here, which I'd prefer to put just
above the TickComponent.
Perfect! Now let's see if that prevents, see what
that prevents. Firstly, it may prevent this error. It may just be that the Projectile
Blueprint is not available, not set quite that early. It is
set, of course, on the Tank against the TankBlueprint,
on the TankAimingComponent here, and it is set but maybe it doesn't get set quite early enough.
So we have a Compile Failure, it's probably something simple: " 'void' should be preceded
by" something on the TankAimingComponent, header file 45,
and that's because I can't spell virtual! OK
let's refresh, clear the logs because I want a nice
clear slate to start from, and then, see how we get on. So this is all about overriding
methods in Actor
Components. OK, let's play the game, see what happens. It played nice and quick,
Aiming is working, and I can't fire for
presumably 3 seconds. Yes, in the beginning! Let's just retest that one!
I'm firing, I'm clicking clicking clicking clicking, and the AI tanks aren't firing either,
until we get to the 3 second mark. I'm just going to make sure the AI tanks
do eventually fire. I'm going to do that by going F11, get my controller
out, my Xbox controller, and just move away,
and make sure that eventually these guys can actually fire. We must sort that bug with selft-
collisions with the ground. Yep, I just saw one fire there! OK, so that
initial firing is working now. The next thing I want to do, just before
we finish off this particular video, is to rather than in the
Fire use this... Where are we? ...this isReloaded, we want to use
the enum we've already setup. So how are we going to do that? Well
we'll do it up in the Tick, won't we? We're going to use that logic.
In fact, I'll cut that logic now, and I'll say if
(FiringState
!= not equal to EFiringStateReloading.
So if it's not reloading, then go ahead and fire OK.
So now, we need to set the logic for it reloading or not reloading, we do this in Tick.
We don't need the log anymore in here, but we can say if and then
this logic, which is the difference between
the PlatformTime and the LastFireTime. By the way, if you don't like Platform
Time, then you are welcome to say something different, which we've done before
which is GetWorld GetTimeInSeconds. I'm not going to change it until it causes a problem.
It will cause a problem later, but I just thought I'd put that as an aside. You can go
GetWorld arrow GetTimeInSeconds. Anyway, if the PlatformTime -
the LastFireTime is greater than the ReloadTime, i.e. if we have reloaded, then
what do we do with this state? Well then EFiringState
or FiringState = EFiringState, to fully declare it
Reloading. OK, that's all
very well, let's try it! But of course, it's never going to leave the Reloading state with this
particular code is it, because this guy is going to set it to Reloading. But
nothing is going to be setting it to another state, which is the Aiming or the Locked state,
but we'll do that in another video. So let's just try now! What do we get? We get
continuous firing from the AI tanks and that's expected, as I
say, because if you look over in the TankAimingComponent we are not
initializing. We need to initialize to Reloading, that's going to be
our initial state is that it's not ready to fire. Let's try that! So it
initializes to Reloading. Every frame it asks the
question, has it been the ReloadTime since
we last fired? When did we last fire? On BeginPlay(). So let's see
what the behavior is like now. No firing for 1, 2,
3, and then, of course, it never leaves the ReloadingState,
which is expected at this point, because we need further logic under here
which we will do in the next video. So I just flesh out the further logic,
"// TODO Handle
aiming and locked states".
There you go! But let's not do that now, this video is plenty long enough. Congratulations
on getting that far! I'm going to Save All my code,
quickly review with you what has been done, in terms of the source
control changes, and then, we will start finishing... [Laughs] Start finishing.
Finish this in the next video. So we have a BeginPlay()
that's been put in. We on BeginPlay() set the initial
fire as if it's fired, phantom fire in the beginning. On
Tick we ask whether or not the Reload
Time has passed or not. Later, we'll handle the rest of the states, we move some checks
and split them up, from up here down into there, and we moved the
whole idea, instead of using a local boolean, we're using the member
variable FiringState enum. And then, the changes in the header file are just the
changes we had to put in the header file, to support those code changes. So fantastic! I'll see you in the
next video!
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1:Unreal/Section4/BT78 Adding TickComponent() Back.srt