So welcome
to Are Two Floats Equal?! Why am I calling the video that? Hmm. let's dive in and find out!
OK. so let's handle these Aiming and Locked states now!
So in order to differentiate between Aiming and Locked. we're going to need to know
rather if the Barrel is moving. So I'll write the surrounding code and then I'm going to give you a challenge
to write the IsBarrelMoving() method. So we're going to say else if
(IsBarrelMoving). wishing we had that method. it's called wishful coding.
Then. if we had a way of detecting that the Barrel was
moving. we would set the FiringState too. And then. i"m going to copy the beginning over.
because there's a lot of noise there. EFiringState::
Aiming. Then. we move down one.
Finally. else... And the order does matter here if you think about it.
else we're just going to be in the FiringState of
Locked. So we're saying that Reloading. the fact that it has
been... Oh look. there's an error here! ...the FPlatformTime - the LastFire
Time needs to be less than the ReloadTimeInSeconds. in
order for us to be in a state of Reloading. that overrides everything else. If that's not the
case then we ask the question. Is the Barrel Moving? If the Barrel's moving. well then
I'm in an Aiming state. we're free to fire but we're in an Aiming state. otherwise
we're in the Locked state. So we've done that. in theory. handling the locked
state. What we need is an IsBarrelMoving method. so I'm going to go ahead and ask
you to do that. Write bool IsBarrelMoving(). compare the Barrel's current
forward vector with the AimDirection that we're using. within the AimAt()
method. Now. when you try and compare two FVectors.
you're actually remembering that FVectors are a struct containing floats.
so what you're really trying to do is compare floating point values. Now we can
ask the question whether floating point values are larger or smaller than each other. but never ever
ever ever ever ask whether two floats are equal. It just doesn't make any
sense to even ask the question. it's like saying. are two people the
same height? You can't even ask the question without specifying
a tolerance within which you are asking the question. Are two people.
who are about 180 centimeters. the same height? I don't know. it depends
whether you care about the millimeters. it depends whether you care about the microns. etc.
So when you compare two floats. you must do it in a way that says they are
equal within and then insert a tolerance. And that's exactly what this static
method. called Equals. that's available on every FVector does for us.
We'll take one FVector. like the barrel's current forward. we'll say ::Equals().
and then. inside the ::Equals there are two parameters. One is the other vector
and then the other is the tollerence. and I'm going to use 0.01
just for a small number. Anyway. test that it works by seeing if it changes
the color of the crosshair. And I've got a hint coming up next. so if you're ready for the
challenge without a hint go ahead. pause the video now. If you want a tiny bit more information. here it comes!
I suggest that you promote the AimDirection
local variable. inside the AimAt()method. up to a member variable for ease.
OK go ahead. pause the video. and have a crack at that now!
OK welcome back!
Let's make this IsBarrelMoving thingy happen! I'm going to do it.
I think. under the Initialize. In fact. I'm going to move Initialize above
TickComponent. OCD. that's what I call it! OK so we do the Begin
Play(). then we do our kind of manual Initialize. then ticking happens. and then. we ask questions
like void. spelled UTank
AimingComponent.
I should have copied that. shouldn't I. And then
::IsBarrelMoving(). comsa!
OK great! I'm going to go ahead and declare that right away! Where do we put
it? It doesn't really matter. I think it makes sense. somewhere like below the MoveBarrel
Towards. It's a boolean. if I made it void in the TankAimingComponent I was wrong.
I'll fix that in a second. It's bool IsBarrelMoving()
and it needs no parameters. It's self explanatory what it does but the
return type os bool. OK. so how are we going to do this? The first thing is that
we should never be calling this method when there is no Barrel.
so we need to protect against the idea of there being no Barrel.
when we call this. Now if there was no Barrel would we want to...
I want to talk a little bit more about the ensure statement. We only use ensure
for things that we never ever ever expect to happen in our production game. If this
stuff is likely to happen in the production game. then it's a failure condition you need to
handle. So is it possible that our code would call IsBarrelMoving when there's no
Barrel? Umm it really shouldn't. so I'm going to use an
ensure here. So if not (!ensure(Barrel)).
then we're going to return. Now careful. return
what. true or false? You can't just say return out of a method that returns a boolean.
Now. let's think about what the most sensible failure case is. If I ask the question
of a method. is the Barrel moving and there is no barrel pointer.
if we've got a choice between true and false. assuming we're not returning a richer
error like an enum. then I'm going to give it false in this case. because how can
the barrel be moving if the Barrel pointer's not set? OK you could argue
if it was anymore fringe than this. I would suggest you don't return a bool but you
return an enum. that gives a meaningful piece of information back. So your options would
be yes it's moving. no it's not moving. or don't ask me I can't even look through the Barrel pointer.
right now mate. which might be a slightly longer enum state than we need but you get the idea.
So with that protection in place. let's dive in! Auto.
I'm going to say BarrelForward. a very thin
variable here. it's just for self documentation. and we're going to look through the Barrel pointer.
which we protected. GetForwardVector(). which I'm pretty sure we've
used before. OK. so what are we going to return from this method? We're pretty much ready to
return. we're ready to return.
pseudocode it. We're going to return the boolean that is not
the "vectors are equal". So if
the forward direction and the
AimDirection. which is where? Let's go find it. AimDirection here! If
they're equal. then the Barrel is not
moving. If they're not equal the Barrel is moving. so it's the inversion of whether they're equal.
So I'm going to say if I BarrelForward.Equals.
And now. you can find out about this method. by the way. this dot Equals. It's here.
I've put it in the resources of the lecture for you. and it tells you what it does. it does a comparison with a
Tolerance. as I said. to
what? Well to this AimDirection. We need to promote that. in a second. I'm going to give it 0.01
for no particular reason. apart from it's a small number. which means that they look equal enough to be
good enough for me. The only thing is that AimDirection is out of scope now. Of course. it's not
inside this method. and it no longer needs to be just a local variable inside
this AimAt() method. We can take the auto off. which
turns it from an initialization and declaration simultaniously into a
nothing. because it doesn't know anything about AimDirection. And that's simple. we move AimDirection
into an FVector local
member of the class. comsa. OK.
so we have an AimDirection to compare to towards now. When VisualStudio catches up. all these
red squigglies will go away and we should be in good condition. So that's basically
the crux of IsBarrel. the way I'm doing it. So let's go ahead and compile
and see what we get out of this now! By the way. make sure you've
switched your chevron around here. in the question in
TickComponent. Is the time since the LastFireTime
less than the ReloadTimeInSeconds. not greater than in this case O.K.. otherwise
you won't be in the Reloading state. So that's an important note there. Also
if you don't like FPlatformTime. and you probably shouldn't like FPlatformTime. I'm showing it to you as
an alternative. You can use GetWorld GetTimeSeconds. that will work
just as well if not better. So I'm going to leave it until
we actually need to make a change back to GetWorld GetTimeSeconds. but just a note for you.
OK let's play the game and see what happens! It's red and I can't fire. that's good! After 3 seconds.
what happens? Well we get a big glitch and then OK
nothing! It's not working! So what's wrong? Let's have a look at the stack trace.
Ooh. lots of stuff's going wrong here! So we've got something moaning about the
color and opacity. which is a Blueprint variable
that we have. if you remember. on the UI. So let's go
and look at that. While we've got these errors. let's deal with them one at a time. So on the
UI here we read under the PlayerUI
a Blueprint variable. in the graph which is here. which is the BP Aiming Component
Reference. Let's turn that into a string and then print it.
Oh no. we don't need to. because we
know that that is being set. because it is actually setting a color. So let's not necessarily
do that but note the following. the BP Aiming Component Reference
Blueprint variable here is currently private. Let's make that public by
clicking the little eye there. because it's being set from one blueprint and read from another.
So make that public and Compile! That should get rid of
this error about trying to access that Blueprint variable. Now we've
got a projectile Blueprint ensure failure on the TankAimingComponent
line... What line? I love these line numbers. 100!
So on line 100 we are not having a
ProjectileBlueprint available. That is probably because the AI tank is firing
too early. So have prevented it from firing at the beginning?
Yes we have. so it's not that. Let's have a look!
Let's recompile and have a look and see how it's behaving now.
Play! The AI tanks. when are they firing? They're firing after...
Yep. and I can fire after 3 seconds! Let's just see if my crosshair goes amber. Yeah
and then green! Actually it's working! So because I've had some ensure problems
and because we know that the ensures only work once per compilation
cycle or once per opening of the Editor. I'm actually going to close the Editor.
and then reopen it just to ensure that
we don't have any problems after that. because I don't want to ignore these ensures. It's
easy to look past them. when you're trying to get something done. and to not deal with them. So now
I'm reopen to make sure. Now I'm waiting a few seconds.
You see it goes green when the barrel is moving. it's amber. and when I fire it goes red
for 3 seconds. That looks good! I'm getting no errors in the Console
here. so that is a lot better. Let me show you the code I've added in SourceControl. briefly.
And remember. you can always look this up by going to the GitHub repository for the
course. and we're good to go!
So what has happened in this video. that's wrong? We haven't moved the
Initialize. that's just source control getting confused about the changes. We have switched
the chevron around. the comparison around. in this FPlatformTime time.
We've written this code here to do with the Barrel moving states.
Then. of course. we've written the entire IsBarrel moving method. which was these three lines
there. The header file changes are just the required things
to make all that work. So great. it's good news. we actually have aiming working.
which is quite satisfying. and it's much nicer now that you know
when you can and can't fire. I'm just going to get my controller out and have a play
and have a quick think about what's the least fun thing about this. And I think the least
fun thing now is this slightly ridiculous moving
metrics. which is where the tank's physics is a bit sluggish. because it
skids sideways so much that I can't really control it. That's actually starting to become annoying
now. so is the fact that they're bouncing off the ground like that!
Both of those things are somewhat annoying. so that's what we're going to fix next. but at least we
have a crosshair that gives us some affordance. as they call it. as to when we can
and can't fire and why we can or can't fire. So I look forward to seeing you in the next
video!
=======
So welcome
to Are Two Floats Equal?! Why am I calling the video that? Hmm, let's dive in and find out!
OK, so let's handle these Aiming and Locked states now!
So in order to differentiate between Aiming and Locked, we're going to need to know
rather if the Barrel is moving. So I'll write the surrounding code and then I'm going to give you a challenge
to write the IsBarrelMoving() method. So we're going to say else if
(IsBarrelMoving), wishing we had that method, it's called wishful coding.
Then, if we had a way of detecting that the Barrel was
moving, we would set the FiringState too. And then, i"m going to copy the beginning over,
because there's a lot of noise there. EFiringState::
Aiming. Then, we move down one.
Finally, else... And the order does matter here if you think about it,
else we're just going to be in the FiringState of
Locked. So we're saying that Reloading, the fact that it has
been... Oh look, there's an error here! ...the FPlatformTime - the LastFire
Time needs to be less than the ReloadTimeInSeconds, in
order for us to be in a state of Reloading, that overrides everything else. If that's not the
case then we ask the question, Is the Barrel Moving? If the Barrel's moving, well then
I'm in an Aiming state, we're free to fire but we're in an Aiming state, otherwise
we're in the Locked state. So we've done that, in theory, handling the locked
state. What we need is an IsBarrelMoving method, so I'm going to go ahead and ask
you to do that. Write bool IsBarrelMoving(), compare the Barrel's current
forward vector with the AimDirection that we're using, within the AimAt()
method. Now, when you try and compare two FVectors,
you're actually remembering that FVectors are a struct containing floats,
so what you're really trying to do is compare floating point values. Now we can
ask the question whether floating point values are larger or smaller than each other, but never ever
ever ever ever ask whether two floats are equal. It just doesn't make any
sense to even ask the question, it's like saying, are two people the
same height? You can't even ask the question without specifying
a tolerance within which you are asking the question. Are two people,
who are about 180 centimeters, the same height? I don't know, it depends
whether you care about the millimeters, it depends whether you care about the microns, etc.
So when you compare two floats, you must do it in a way that says they are
equal within and then insert a tolerance. And that's exactly what this static
method, called Equals, that's available on every FVector does for us.
We'll take one FVector, like the barrel's current forward, we'll say ::Equals(),
and then, inside the ::Equals there are two parameters. One is the other vector
and then the other is the tollerence, and I'm going to use 0.01
just for a small number. Anyway, test that it works by seeing if it changes
the color of the crosshair. And I've got a hint coming up next, so if you're ready for the
challenge without a hint go ahead, pause the video now. If you want a tiny bit more information, here it comes!
I suggest that you promote the AimDirection
local variable, inside the AimAt()method, up to a member variable for ease.
OK go ahead, pause the video, and have a crack at that now!
OK welcome back!
Let's make this IsBarrelMoving thingy happen! I'm going to do it,
I think, under the Initialize. In fact, I'm going to move Initialize above
TickComponent. OCD, that's what I call it! OK so we do the Begin
Play(), then we do our kind of manual Initialize, then ticking happens, and then, we ask questions
like void, spelled UTank
AimingComponent.
I should have copied that, shouldn't I. And then
::IsBarrelMoving(), comsa!
OK great! I'm going to go ahead and declare that right away! Where do we put
it? It doesn't really matter. I think it makes sense, somewhere like below the MoveBarrel
Towards. It's a boolean, if I made it void in the TankAimingComponent I was wrong.
I'll fix that in a second. It's bool IsBarrelMoving()
and it needs no parameters. It's self explanatory what it does but the
return type os bool. OK, so how are we going to do this? The first thing is that
we should never be calling this method when there is no Barrel,
so we need to protect against the idea of there being no Barrel,
when we call this. Now if there was no Barrel would we want to...
I want to talk a little bit more about the ensure statement. We only use ensure
for things that we never ever ever expect to happen in our production game. If this
stuff is likely to happen in the production game, then it's a failure condition you need to
handle. So is it possible that our code would call IsBarrelMoving when there's no
Barrel? Umm it really shouldn't, so I'm going to use an
ensure here. So if not (!ensure(Barrel)),
then we're going to return. Now careful, return
what, true or false? You can't just say return out of a method that returns a boolean.
Now, let's think about what the most sensible failure case is. If I ask the question
of a method, is the Barrel moving and there is no barrel pointer,
if we've got a choice between true and false, assuming we're not returning a richer
error like an enum, then I'm going to give it false in this case, because how can
the barrel be moving if the Barrel pointer's not set? OK you could argue
if it was anymore fringe than this, I would suggest you don't return a bool but you
return an enum, that gives a meaningful piece of information back. So your options would
be yes it's moving, no it's not moving, or don't ask me I can't even look through the Barrel pointer,
right now mate, which might be a slightly longer enum state than we need but you get the idea.
So with that protection in place, let's dive in! Auto,
I'm going to say BarrelForward, a very thin
variable here, it's just for self documentation, and we're going to look through the Barrel pointer,
which we protected. GetForwardVector(), which I'm pretty sure we've
used before. OK, so what are we going to return from this method? We're pretty much ready to
return, we're ready to return,
pseudocode it. We're going to return the boolean that is not
the "vectors are equal". So if
the forward direction and the
AimDirection, which is where? Let's go find it. AimDirection here! If
they're equal, then the Barrel is not
moving. If they're not equal the Barrel is moving, so it's the inversion of whether they're equal.
So I'm going to say if I BarrelForward.Equals.
And now, you can find out about this method, by the way, this dot Equals. It's here.
I've put it in the resources of the lecture for you, and it tells you what it does, it does a comparison with a
Tolerance, as I said, to
what? Well to this AimDirection. We need to promote that, in a second. I'm going to give it 0.01
for no particular reason, apart from it's a small number, which means that they look equal enough to be
good enough for me. The only thing is that AimDirection is out of scope now. Of course, it's not
inside this method, and it no longer needs to be just a local variable inside
this AimAt() method. We can take the auto off, which
turns it from an initialization and declaration simultaniously into a
nothing, because it doesn't know anything about AimDirection. And that's simple, we move AimDirection
into an FVector local
member of the class, comsa. OK,
so we have an AimDirection to compare to towards now. When VisualStudio catches up, all these
red squigglies will go away and we should be in good condition. So that's basically
the crux of IsBarrel, the way I'm doing it. So let's go ahead and compile
and see what we get out of this now! By the way, make sure you've
switched your chevron around here, in the question in
TickComponent. Is the time since the LastFireTime
less than the ReloadTimeInSeconds, not greater than in this case O.K., otherwise
you won't be in the Reloading state. So that's an important note there. Also
if you don't like FPlatformTime, and you probably shouldn't like FPlatformTime, I'm showing it to you as
an alternative. You can use GetWorld GetTimeSeconds, that will work
just as well if not better. So I'm going to leave it until
we actually need to make a change back to GetWorld GetTimeSeconds, but just a note for you.
OK let's play the game and see what happens! It's red and I can't fire, that's good! After 3 seconds,
what happens? Well we get a big glitch and then OK
nothing! It's not working! So what's wrong? Let's have a look at the stack trace.
Ooh, lots of stuff's going wrong here! So we've got something moaning about the
color and opacity, which is a Blueprint variable
that we have, if you remember, on the UI. So let's go
and look at that. While we've got these errors, let's deal with them one at a time. So on the
UI here we read under the PlayerUI
a Blueprint variable, in the graph which is here, which is the BP Aiming Component
Reference. Let's turn that into a string and then print it.
Oh no, we don't need to, because we
know that that is being set, because it is actually setting a color. So let's not necessarily
do that but note the following, the BP Aiming Component Reference
Blueprint variable here is currently private. Let's make that public by
clicking the little eye there, because it's being set from one blueprint and read from another.
So make that public and Compile! That should get rid of
this error about trying to access that Blueprint variable. Now we've
got a projectile Blueprint ensure failure on the TankAimingComponent
line... What line? I love these line numbers. 100!
So on line 100 we are not having a
ProjectileBlueprint available. That is probably because the AI tank is firing
too early. So have prevented it from firing at the beginning?
Yes we have, so it's not that. Let's have a look!
Let's recompile and have a look and see how it's behaving now.
Play! The AI tanks, when are they firing? They're firing after...
Yep, and I can fire after 3 seconds! Let's just see if my crosshair goes amber. Yeah
and then green! Actually it's working! So because I've had some ensure problems
and because we know that the ensures only work once per compilation
cycle or once per opening of the Editor, I'm actually going to close the Editor,
and then reopen it just to ensure that
we don't have any problems after that, because I don't want to ignore these ensures. It's
easy to look past them, when you're trying to get something done, and to not deal with them. So now
I'm reopen to make sure. Now I'm waiting a few seconds.
You see it goes green when the barrel is moving, it's amber, and when I fire it goes red
for 3 seconds. That looks good! I'm getting no errors in the Console
here, so that is a lot better. Let me show you the code I've added in SourceControl, briefly.
And remember, you can always look this up by going to the GitHub repository for the
course, and we're good to go!
So what has happened in this video, that's wrong? We haven't moved the
Initialize, that's just source control getting confused about the changes. We have switched
the chevron around, the comparison around, in this FPlatformTime time.
We've written this code here to do with the Barrel moving states.
Then, of course, we've written the entire IsBarrel moving method, which was these three lines
there. The header file changes are just the required things
to make all that work. So great, it's good news, we actually have aiming working,
which is quite satisfying, and it's much nicer now that you know
when you can and can't fire. I'm just going to get my controller out and have a play
and have a quick think about what's the least fun thing about this. And I think the least
fun thing now is this slightly ridiculous moving
metrics, which is where the tank's physics is a bit sluggish, because it
skids sideways so much that I can't really control it. That's actually starting to become annoying
now, so is the fact that they're bouncing off the ground like that!
Both of those things are somewhat annoying, so that's what we're going to fix next, but at least we
have a crosshair that gives us some affordance, as they call it, as to when we can
and can't fire and why we can or can't fire. So I look forward to seeing you in the next
video!
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1:Unreal/Section4/BT79 Are Two Floats Equal.srt