Hey and welcome to Programmatic Sideways
Friction! What we're going to be doing in this video is to
apply some friction sideways. so that as I turn I can actually turn
without slipping sideways. Pretty cool hey! Let's do it!
By the way. the AI tanks will have to do the same thing. of course. because they use the same control API as we do.
So just before we start this one. I want to fix a bug. If I open. and I'm
not going to. my TankPlayerController blueprint. it's actually going to cause a hard crash.
If you attach the debugger and find out why. I'll show you why. and let's
just mitigate this issues for now. so that you don't have this
hanging over you. Look in your TankPlayerController.cpp code.
and then. if we have a look at where we aim towards the
crosshair. we are assuming here that we actually have a possessed
pawn right now. So what we want to say is. if not (!GetPawn...
And I don't mind doing this again. it's a very inlineable. very optimizable
operation. If not (!GetPawn()) then I simply want to return.
and then. this is .for example.
"if not possessing". Now we don't use an ensure here. because
at runtime we may not be
possessing a tank. with the PlayerController. maybe our tank's died or something. So it's
perfectly reasonable to just exit if we're not possessing. If you
do that. just add that line of code there to your TankPlayerController and we recompile.
Then. that will make sure that. at times like this. like
right now. if I click play...  Sorry. if I try and open this Tank
PlayerController. because we're not possessing a tank right now as a
player it would crash. but now it won't crash. because that protection is in place.
o.k.. and aiming will still be working. which is good. I'm just going to check for this
green and then amber. OK!
Now let's move on and make this friction work! So what' happening at the moment is. the tank
is sliding sideways. because there's no reason for the Physics Engine
to apply any sort of asymmetric friction; friction is the same forward. backwards. left. and
right. What we want to do is apply a sideways force that is
exactly the right amount of force to stop the tank moving sideways at all.
Well tanks don't really do moving sideways. apart from perhaps on some very slippery
terrain. so it's this type of movement we want to stop. How are we going to do that? Well
let's go into our TankTrack.cpp
and take a look! We're firstly going to need a constructor and a
tick. because in order to make it tick you have to put the constructor in place.
So let's just quickly do that. UTankTrack TankTrack is what we do
for the constructor definition. UTankTrack.
strange naming with the constructors here. And then. we need this
BeginPlay boolean. What was it? Let's look in the TankAimingComponent!
PrimaryComponentTick.bCanEverTick = true. which we've
done before. Perfect! So that is now provided that we have a
constructor declared. which I like to do it in the private section. it works.
as they say. because of Unreal magic. UTank
Track() is the name of the method. the same as the class name. That's
how we do constructors! OK fantastic! Now how am I going to get the ticking working? Well what
type of class is this? It's a Static Mesh Component. Let's just have a look
in the class hierarchy and find out what a Static
MeshComponent is. A StaticMeshComponent is a type of
Mesh Component. is a type of PrimitiveComponent. is a SceneComponent. finally is an
ActorComponent. So because it is also a child of ActorComponent. just like
our TankAimingComponent was. if you remember. we can use the
same signature as we had in the TankAimingComponent. So
here it is. we just need to modify it slightly for the new class.
So I'm going to put that in. UTankTrack.
get rid of all the code.
Now what else do I need? Void. I need no t's
in there. no override on the end. That's great. so that's nearly there!
I better just check its log that it's working. (LogTemp.
Warning. TEXT... Getting bored of typing this.
("Track ticking"))
OK. It doesn't matter that I spelled it wrong. in this case. because it's going to be
a very temporary message. Let's put this ticking
here. inside the declaration with an override.
It's just moving code around and getting the ticking
working again. And then. we take all this stuff off the front here. The
class name. virtual. needs to go in. and let's just test with ticking.
So sorry about a couple of minutes worth of housekeeping. in order to make that work.
but it's good to revise how to put the ticking back and hopefully you
stopped and did that yourself. So sometimes. when you're watching these videos. if you think
I could do that. I don't need to sit and watch. And don't wait for me to tell you to do a challenge
yourself. just do it yourself. There you go. tank tickling or whatever it says!
That's good! So we are ticking. that's fantastic! Alright. so
what are we going to do. when we're ticking? How are we going to apply a sideways force? Well the general recipe. I'll help you with.
is as follows. We need to "// Calculate the
slippage speed". not velocity. speed
it's just a number. which is the sideways component of the speed
and we use a cross product for that. Then. we "// Work out
the required acceleration
this frame to correct". So if we're
moving sideways at 10 centimeters a second. then this frame in this Delta
Time. we're going to need a certain amount of acceleration to fix that velocity back down to 0 sideways.
Then. we "// Calculate
and apply sideways
force". Remember (F = m a). we have the mass of the tank.
we have the acceleration just above. we've just calculated it. so we apply a sideways
force. So let's start off with calculating the slippage
speed. I'm going to use auto. because I like it. SlippageSpeed =...
Well what is the Slippage
Speed? Let's have a look. I'm going to challenge you to make it! It's the component of the speed in the tank
right direction. we're just choosing that as a sideways direction. If there's no
Slippage. there should be 0. and if it's sliding entirely sideways. the SlippageSpeed will be the
same as the speed of the tank. In general. use the cosign of the angle
between the velocity of the tank. whichever direction it's actually going in.
and the sideways right vector. So if it is
going perfectly sideways. the cosign between those two angles is one. because the
cosign of 0 is 1. and you get the full
speed. If it's going forward. then the angle is 90 degrees. cosign of
90 is 0 so you get a 0 OK. And here's a hint for you!
Well it's not really a hint. it's a strong suggestion. Us FVector::DotProduct() between the
velocity of the tank or the component. you may
want to use GetComponentVelocity. and the tank right vector.
and there's a GetRightVector() method. So have a go! Just work out this SlippageSpeed.
make sure you understand what you're doing. and I'll see you in a moment.
OK welcome back! So this
SlippageSpeed is going to be the FVector static method
called DotProduct(). Between the what? Well
we can (GetRightVector()). Before
we go any further with that. let's just check in our tank blueprint
that the tank track has a forward
vector. the same as the Tank in X. The red
arrow on the Tank itself. or on say the... No I need to look
at the Tank itself. Well this is in the frame of the Tank. X is
forward. Let's just check that the track has that same forward. It does! OK
that's good! So then. we are getting the RightVector of the component. which is the Tank
Track. and we're going to cross product that with
the... Or DotProduct with it rather. and it doesn't matter which order we do a DotProduct
in with the GetComponentVelocity.
which is going to tell us the velocity of this component itself
which is the track. And hopefully. unless the tank is falling apart. then
the ComponentVelocity will be the same as the Tank
Velocity. and we're not going to be dealing with the destruction of the tank in this section. OK. so that
is the SlippageSpeed! Now we need to work out the required acceleration.
I don't need that comment. but we do need the acceleration. So auto.
I'm going to call it Correction or Correcting. CorrectionAcceleration
= what? Well
acceleration is speed over time. isn't it?
So meters per second. per second. Acceleration is speed over time. 0 to 60.
Speed is 60 over time. it tells you how quickly you're getting to 60.
So we're going to take this SlippageSpeed
and we're going to divide it by the DeltaTime.
which is available here as a parameter. and that tells
us how much acceleration we need in this frame. Now which direction is that acceleration in?
Well we need an acceleration. which is actually
a vector. so we multiply it by this GetRightVector again.
You could store that as a variable. local
variable. if you want to. We're nearly there. but we don't want to apply the acceleration
in the direction that we're slipping. we want to apply it in the opposite
direction to what we're slipping in. OK so we put a minus in here.
the opposite direction to that. that we're slipping in. OK
so that's the "acceleration to this frame to correct"! And then.
we're going to "// Calculate and apply a sideways" friction. and I don't need
the word for. which is (F = m a). So how do we work out the sideways friction?
Well I think I'll do it in two stages. I'm going to make a Correction
Force. What is that equal to? Well force is
mass times acceleration. so we need to GetTankRoot.
So how do we get the TankRootComponent. We are a
tank track. I need to get the mass from this Tank at the top here.
If you remember. it's this Tank... Sorry. this Tank here that actually
has a mass on it in kilos. This guy here. it's a Static Mesh Component
which is the root of this hierarchy. How do I get
that from the Tank track? Well let's
try doing that before we even try and work out the CorrectionForce. We can say auto.
Then we can say. well how are we going to get this tank root? Well we need to Get
the Owner for a start. What does that do? That goes up and gets this guy here.
from the Track. So once we've got the owner we look
through that pointer. provided that we can find an owner. of course.
We may want to check that. but to be honest. the tank is precomposed. I'm pretty safe
leaving that for the moment. Then. we Get the Root Component.
I've done this type of thing before. which is where we go down and find the TankRootComponent
there. And let's see what type that is. if I just GetOwner() GetRoot
Component(). Let's see what we end up with! Provided I have my semicolons in the right
place. let's just see what comes out of here!
Once it catches up. we'll see what this auto... Ah. I haven't given it a name. of
course. so I'm going to call it TankRoot.
auto TankRoot is GetOwner() GetRootComponent(). What comes out of that?
It is a USceneComponent pointer.
which is this guy here.
Now let's look at the class
hierarchy again!
SceneComponent is a type of ActorComponent.
And then. where does StaticMeshComponent comes into this? A StaticMesh
Component is a specialization of a SceneComponent. but we need
the StaticMeshComponent in order to actually get
from the Tank. the mass. Because if we look on the tank blueprint.
it is the fact that it's a StaticMesh and this
Physics property that is giving us a mass. So what we need to do with the
TankRoot is. we need to Cast it to a UStaticMeshComponent....
...
...in order to be able to get the properties that we want from it. So we cast to
the UStaticMeshComponent. once we go
and find this object here. we go get it as a StaticMeshComponent. Alright
that allows us to simply talk about the Tank
Root. Then. we can just say GetMass().
like that. it's a method that's provided for us. If we multiply
that Mass by the CorrectionAcceleration. that we've worked out. mass times
acceleration is nearly force. The only thing is. we need to divide by two.
because there are "// Two tracks".
OK so that is the
CorrectionForce. now we need to do is apply it! So we already have this TankRoot thing.
and you'll find that when you look through the pointer of the TankRoot. we can
just AddForce(). That's why we had to cast it. it gives us all these
methods and it's the (CorrectionForce) that we add.
So a bit physicsy for you there. but what we've done is
worked out the SlippageSpeed. worked out the required acceleration. and calculated an implied and a sideways friction.
precisely as we pseudocoded. Let's go ahead and compile
this and see if it works! By the way. I'll Compile. then I'll give you the
by the way. By the way. this TankRoot. we could go and
cache that state. We could do that at BeginPlay(). then we
could protect against it and check it. but
why cache it. at the moment? Until the Performance Profiler tells us there's a performance problem. let's not bother
cacheing it! Let's just focus on simple physics. OK using the left stick here. Ah.
that is looking a lot better! Now the very cool thing about the architecture
that we've setup is. watch the AI tanks now. Apart from these bugs. with them hitting the
ground. notice that they then have to move. One of them is not moving. actually. so let
me refresh the guy who's not moving. I think that's him. By refreshing him.
I needn't just drop a new blueprint in the game. But watch how they move.
they have to move according to the same physics. because they're using the same API as
I am. Oh dear. we have this significant ground problem. so that's going to have to be
a thing we look at very shortly now. But what I want you to notice is that
all the tanks now have sideways friction. totally different movement for all of us.
So that is pretty awesome! So congratulations on getting that far with the sideways
friction. and I will see you in the next video!
=======
Hey and welcome to Programmatic Sideways
Friction! What we're going to be doing in this video is to
apply some friction sideways, so that as I turn I can actually turn
without slipping sideways. Pretty cool hey! Let's do it!
By the way, the AI tanks will have to do the same thing, of course, because they use the same control API as we do.
So just before we start this one, I want to fix a bug. If I open, and I'm
not going to, my TankPlayerController blueprint, it's actually going to cause a hard crash.
If you attach the debugger and find out why, I'll show you why, and let's
just mitigate this issues for now, so that you don't have this
hanging over you. Look in your TankPlayerController.cpp code,
and then, if we have a look at where we aim towards the
crosshair, we are assuming here that we actually have a possessed
pawn right now. So what we want to say is, if not (!GetPawn...
And I don't mind doing this again, it's a very inlineable, very optimizable
operation. If not (!GetPawn()) then I simply want to return,
and then, this is ,for example,
"if not possessing". Now we don't use an ensure here, because
at runtime we may not be
possessing a tank, with the PlayerController, maybe our tank's died or something. So it's
perfectly reasonable to just exit if we're not possessing. If you
do that, just add that line of code there to your TankPlayerController and we recompile.
Then, that will make sure that, at times like this, like
right now, if I click play...  Sorry, if I try and open this Tank
PlayerController, because we're not possessing a tank right now as a
player it would crash, but now it won't crash, because that protection is in place.
o.k., and aiming will still be working, which is good. I'm just going to check for this
green and then amber. OK!
Now let's move on and make this friction work! So what' happening at the moment is, the tank
is sliding sideways, because there's no reason for the Physics Engine
to apply any sort of asymmetric friction; friction is the same forward, backwards, left, and
right. What we want to do is apply a sideways force that is
exactly the right amount of force to stop the tank moving sideways at all.
Well tanks don't really do moving sideways, apart from perhaps on some very slippery
terrain, so it's this type of movement we want to stop. How are we going to do that? Well
let's go into our TankTrack.cpp
and take a look! We're firstly going to need a constructor and a
tick, because in order to make it tick you have to put the constructor in place.
So let's just quickly do that, UTankTrack TankTrack is what we do
for the constructor definition. UTankTrack,
strange naming with the constructors here. And then, we need this
BeginPlay boolean. What was it? Let's look in the TankAimingComponent!
PrimaryComponentTick.bCanEverTick = true, which we've
done before. Perfect! So that is now provided that we have a
constructor declared, which I like to do it in the private section, it works,
as they say, because of Unreal magic. UTank
Track() is the name of the method, the same as the class name. That's
how we do constructors! OK fantastic! Now how am I going to get the ticking working? Well what
type of class is this? It's a Static Mesh Component. Let's just have a look
in the class hierarchy and find out what a Static
MeshComponent is. A StaticMeshComponent is a type of
Mesh Component, is a type of PrimitiveComponent, is a SceneComponent, finally is an
ActorComponent. So because it is also a child of ActorComponent, just like
our TankAimingComponent was, if you remember, we can use the
same signature as we had in the TankAimingComponent. So
here it is, we just need to modify it slightly for the new class.
So I'm going to put that in, UTankTrack,
get rid of all the code.
Now what else do I need? Void. I need no t's
in there, no override on the end. That's great, so that's nearly there!
I better just check its log that it's working. (LogTemp,
Warning, TEXT... Getting bored of typing this.
("Track ticking"))
OK. It doesn't matter that I spelled it wrong, in this case, because it's going to be
a very temporary message. Let's put this ticking
here, inside the declaration with an override.
It's just moving code around and getting the ticking
working again. And then, we take all this stuff off the front here. The
class name, virtual, needs to go in, and let's just test with ticking.
So sorry about a couple of minutes worth of housekeeping, in order to make that work,
but it's good to revise how to put the ticking back and hopefully you
stopped and did that yourself. So sometimes, when you're watching these videos, if you think
I could do that, I don't need to sit and watch. And don't wait for me to tell you to do a challenge
yourself, just do it yourself. There you go, tank tickling or whatever it says!
That's good! So we are ticking, that's fantastic! Alright, so
what are we going to do, when we're ticking? How are we going to apply a sideways force? Well the general recipe, I'll help you with,
is as follows. We need to "// Calculate the
slippage speed", not velocity, speed
it's just a number, which is the sideways component of the speed
and we use a cross product for that. Then, we "// Work out
the required acceleration
this frame to correct". So if we're
moving sideways at 10 centimeters a second, then this frame in this Delta
Time, we're going to need a certain amount of acceleration to fix that velocity back down to 0 sideways.
Then, we "// Calculate
and apply sideways
force". Remember (F = m a), we have the mass of the tank,
we have the acceleration just above, we've just calculated it, so we apply a sideways
force. So let's start off with calculating the slippage
speed. I'm going to use auto, because I like it. SlippageSpeed =...
Well what is the Slippage
Speed? Let's have a look, I'm going to challenge you to make it! It's the component of the speed in the tank
right direction, we're just choosing that as a sideways direction. If there's no
Slippage, there should be 0, and if it's sliding entirely sideways, the SlippageSpeed will be the
same as the speed of the tank. In general, use the cosign of the angle
between the velocity of the tank, whichever direction it's actually going in,
and the sideways right vector. So if it is
going perfectly sideways, the cosign between those two angles is one, because the
cosign of 0 is 1, and you get the full
speed. If it's going forward, then the angle is 90 degrees, cosign of
90 is 0 so you get a 0 OK. And here's a hint for you!
Well it's not really a hint, it's a strong suggestion. Us FVector::DotProduct() between the
velocity of the tank or the component, you may
want to use GetComponentVelocity, and the tank right vector,
and there's a GetRightVector() method. So have a go! Just work out this SlippageSpeed,
make sure you understand what you're doing, and I'll see you in a moment.
OK welcome back! So this
SlippageSpeed is going to be the FVector static method
called DotProduct(). Between the what? Well
we can (GetRightVector()). Before
we go any further with that, let's just check in our tank blueprint
that the tank track has a forward
vector, the same as the Tank in X. The red
arrow on the Tank itself, or on say the... No I need to look
at the Tank itself. Well this is in the frame of the Tank, X is
forward. Let's just check that the track has that same forward. It does! OK
that's good! So then, we are getting the RightVector of the component, which is the Tank
Track, and we're going to cross product that with
the... Or DotProduct with it rather, and it doesn't matter which order we do a DotProduct
in with the GetComponentVelocity,
which is going to tell us the velocity of this component itself
which is the track. And hopefully, unless the tank is falling apart, then
the ComponentVelocity will be the same as the Tank
Velocity, and we're not going to be dealing with the destruction of the tank in this section. OK, so that
is the SlippageSpeed! Now we need to work out the required acceleration.
I don't need that comment, but we do need the acceleration. So auto,
I'm going to call it Correction or Correcting. CorrectionAcceleration
= what? Well
acceleration is speed over time, isn't it?
So meters per second, per second. Acceleration is speed over time, 0 to 60.
Speed is 60 over time, it tells you how quickly you're getting to 60.
So we're going to take this SlippageSpeed
and we're going to divide it by the DeltaTime,
which is available here as a parameter, and that tells
us how much acceleration we need in this frame. Now which direction is that acceleration in?
Well we need an acceleration, which is actually
a vector, so we multiply it by this GetRightVector again.
You could store that as a variable, local
variable, if you want to. We're nearly there, but we don't want to apply the acceleration
in the direction that we're slipping, we want to apply it in the opposite
direction to what we're slipping in. OK so we put a minus in here,
the opposite direction to that, that we're slipping in. OK
so that's the "acceleration to this frame to correct"! And then,
we're going to "// Calculate and apply a sideways" friction, and I don't need
the word for, which is (F = m a). So how do we work out the sideways friction?
Well I think I'll do it in two stages. I'm going to make a Correction
Force. What is that equal to? Well force is
mass times acceleration, so we need to GetTankRoot.
So how do we get the TankRootComponent. We are a
tank track. I need to get the mass from this Tank at the top here.
If you remember, it's this Tank... Sorry, this Tank here that actually
has a mass on it in kilos. This guy here, it's a Static Mesh Component
which is the root of this hierarchy. How do I get
that from the Tank track? Well let's
try doing that before we even try and work out the CorrectionForce. We can say auto.
Then we can say, well how are we going to get this tank root? Well we need to Get
the Owner for a start. What does that do? That goes up and gets this guy here,
from the Track. So once we've got the owner we look
through that pointer, provided that we can find an owner, of course.
We may want to check that, but to be honest, the tank is precomposed, I'm pretty safe
leaving that for the moment. Then, we Get the Root Component.
I've done this type of thing before, which is where we go down and find the TankRootComponent
there. And let's see what type that is, if I just GetOwner() GetRoot
Component(). Let's see what we end up with! Provided I have my semicolons in the right
place, let's just see what comes out of here!
Once it catches up, we'll see what this auto... Ah, I haven't given it a name, of
course, so I'm going to call it TankRoot.
auto TankRoot is GetOwner() GetRootComponent(). What comes out of that?
It is a USceneComponent pointer,
which is this guy here.
Now let's look at the class
hierarchy again!
SceneComponent is a type of ActorComponent.
And then, where does StaticMeshComponent comes into this? A StaticMesh
Component is a specialization of a SceneComponent, but we need
the StaticMeshComponent in order to actually get
from the Tank, the mass. Because if we look on the tank blueprint,
it is the fact that it's a StaticMesh and this
Physics property that is giving us a mass. So what we need to do with the
TankRoot is, we need to Cast it to a UStaticMeshComponent,...
...
...in order to be able to get the properties that we want from it. So we cast to
the UStaticMeshComponent, once we go
and find this object here, we go get it as a StaticMeshComponent. Alright
that allows us to simply talk about the Tank
Root. Then, we can just say GetMass(),
like that, it's a method that's provided for us. If we multiply
that Mass by the CorrectionAcceleration, that we've worked out, mass times
acceleration is nearly force. The only thing is, we need to divide by two,
because there are "// Two tracks".
OK so that is the
CorrectionForce, now we need to do is apply it! So we already have this TankRoot thing,
and you'll find that when you look through the pointer of the TankRoot, we can
just AddForce(). That's why we had to cast it, it gives us all these
methods and it's the (CorrectionForce) that we add.
So a bit physicsy for you there, but what we've done is
worked out the SlippageSpeed, worked out the required acceleration, and calculated an implied and a sideways friction,
precisely as we pseudocoded. Let's go ahead and compile
this and see if it works! By the way, I'll Compile, then I'll give you the
by the way. By the way, this TankRoot, we could go and
cache that state. We could do that at BeginPlay(), then we
could protect against it and check it, but
why cache it, at the moment? Until the Performance Profiler tells us there's a performance problem, let's not bother
cacheing it! Let's just focus on simple physics. OK using the left stick here. Ah,
that is looking a lot better! Now the very cool thing about the architecture
that we've setup is, watch the AI tanks now. Apart from these bugs, with them hitting the
ground, notice that they then have to move. One of them is not moving, actually, so let
me refresh the guy who's not moving. I think that's him. By refreshing him,
I needn't just drop a new blueprint in the game. But watch how they move,
they have to move according to the same physics, because they're using the same API as
I am. Oh dear, we have this significant ground problem, so that's going to have to be
a thing we look at very shortly now. But what I want you to notice is that
all the tanks now have sideways friction, totally different movement for all of us.
So that is pretty awesome! So congratulations on getting that far with the sideways
friction, and I will see you in the next video!
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1:Unreal/Section4/BT80 Programmatic Sideways Friction.srt