Welcome to OnComponent
Hit Event in 4.12! What we're going to do here is intercept a hit
event between the tracks and the ground. so that we can in future use
it to prevent the tank from trying to apply a force. when it's in the air. So let's have a look at it!
So we're doing much better! The tank isn't sliding sideways now. but notice this.
if I drive the tank off the ground. look when it's in the air it goes nuts!
Why is it going so nuts? That's because we're still applying a driving force.
even though we're not in contact with the ground. That's kind of crazy! So the mission
here is to stop applying a force. unless we're in contact with the ground. Now. lets
use Blueprint to mock this up. initially. The first thing we need to do for this to work
is. both of the Left and Right Tracks need to have. under the Collision section
of the tank blueprint. the Simulation Generates Hit Events
checkbox ticked. Without that. they will not generate any Hit Events to detect.
Now let's just go to one of the tracks. You don't need to do this bit. I'm going to undo this bit of
blueprint. Follow me if you like. I'm going to click the event. Now. by the way. if you
select both tracks you won't get the Events list. so you have to select one track or the other.
When you select one or the other you get the Events list. At the bottom of the Details tab click plus.
and then. we can just print straight off this and
just see what we're trying to do in C++. here in Blueprint first.
So we could just say OnGround. we could even say Left track on ground.
On ground. there you go! So let's compile and play!
Provided those Simulation Generates Hit Events checkboxes
are set... There you go. we can see that the Left Track is indeed on the ground and it's logging
away. Cool! So that's very easy in Blueprint. but we are
all grown up and we don't want to be using Blueprint. we want to be using C++. So I'm going to
get rid of that and play the game and there they go! So
how do you do it in C++. how do we get access to this On Hit event?
Well there's a bit of controversy over this. right now. with version
4.12. If you try searching searching the web for "oncomponenthit unreal 4.12".
you'll find that people are really not sure how to do it. and that's because
they've changed stuff and they haven't documented what they've changed. Bless them. I'm sure they will at
some point but right now it's not clear. So how do you find out
what you should be doing here to register this. well we've got the source code. that's
the saving grace. So if you go OnComponentHit. which is the event which
we found the name out of from the blueprint. what we can do there
is we can right-click it and go to the definition. Yet again. we're diving into the source code.
this time of the primitive component. and it has this event.
which is of type FComponentHitSignature. Let's go to the definition of that.
Now I'm not necessarily expecting you guys to be able to do this. but the point is.
I want to give you an awareness of how we. with a lot of help from Sam. so me and Sam
found out how to get this signature. So you get here and you see a
macro. and if you look at that macro it's a bit odd. because we have commas between the
types and the actual names of these variables. Ignore the first
bit. We have a UPrimitiveComponent pointer
called HitComponent. We have an AActor pointer called OtherActor. we have a UPrimitiveComponent
pointer called OtherComp. How that translates to how you should actually use it is
as follows. I've written a slide for you. This is how to register for OnHit() Events.
in C++. in Unreal 4.12. [Laughs] OK.
Firstly. we register the delegate at BeginPlay(); we're going to need to put our BeginPlay back in.
and we use that syntax. OnComponentHit.AddDynamic(this.
and then the
delegate name of the method. So it's ampersand. forward
address of UTankTrack::On
Hit);. That tells it where to go and find the method. when this event gets triggered.
Then. you use this signature for the delegate itself.
[Laughs] It looks nasty but it's the thing I found in the source code. right. without all the commas.
It's OnHit(UPrimitiveComponent pointer HitComponent. AActor pointer
OtherActor. and so on. So you write an OnHit() method called that.
but what is important is that you make it a private UFUNCTION. that way the OnHit event will actually work.
OK. so what I'm going to do is just challenge you to actually do this. I want you to
register for OnHit(). inside C++. Use the instructions on the previous slide.
I'll even leave them up for the challenge. if I remember. Ensure that
both tracks have the following set in Blueprint: The Collision Simulation
Generates Hit Events. otherwise it will all go terribly wrong. and then. test that it works with
a log entry. And then. when you've done it and it works. arms in the air and
celebrate being one of the first people in Unreal 4.12 to get that working. So I'm just going to
dive back now and leave that on the screen. which is your recipe. Try and dig in. try
and work out how it works. I know it'll be ambiguous to some of you and very clear to others. but
a whole range of abilities on this course. So go ahead. pause the video. and get that puppy
working now!
OK welcome back! I'm actually going to use some of this
stuff straight off my slide. Why would I retype it? That would be nuts! So I'll come out
into the slide deck. then I'm going to go to
the... Well I need BeginPlay() back firstly. don't I? So we know how to do that don't we?
We've done this a hundred times. It's a load of fun. isn't it? Begin
Play(). There we go! So that almost brings BeginPlay()
back. but because it's C++. and we love C++ don't we. we have to go
over into the header file and type virtual. because that's what it is in the
parent class. We have to type void. because that's what comes back. we have to type BeginPlay(). because that's
the name of the method. and we have to type override. because we want to make sure
that we are overriding a method in the parent class. with exactly that signature.
Perfect! Now we have BeginPlay(). and we can say OnComponentHit
.AddDynamic. By the way. it won't complete the AddDynamic properly.
because something about the way the state of the source code.
at the moment. is preventing that from working. But this will work. OnComponentHit.Add
Dynamic. that's what we want. So that's the first bit of the recipe. and BeginPlay(). we
subscribe to this event. OK what's the next bit of the recipe?
A bit old OnHit() event. Now I didn't tell you whether it should be void
or what it should be. I didn't even write void for BeginPlay(). There you go!
So it should be void and it needs a class name.
and then. we have all that stuff. which I've pasted in
which you can get from the slides or from my repo. So
no semicolon but a pair of squigglies. and inside the squigglies. I'm just going to
simply say UE_LOG(LogTemp. Warning.
TEXT. And then we're just going to say ("I'm hit.
I'm hit!")) exclamation mark. because I'm very immature! OK so
then. once we've got that. then we need to go ahead and
declare this as well. inside our header file. of course.
So how are we going to do that? Well we go to the header file. Go to the private section. I'm going to do it
after BeginPlay() and probably after Tick. I like to keep BeginPlay() and Tick together.
Paste in the method. take away the class name.
put a semicolon on the end. and finally...
Where's the semicolon? I can't see my keyboard. the microphone is in the way. And this needs to be a
UFUNCTION(). because of Unreal magic. OK
great! Let's go ahead and compile this and see where we are! While
it compiles. I will show you. confidently. what I've done here in the
source control. I've added the BeginPlay() back in. I've added in that
signature which I shared with you. which we found from the source code as a UFUNCTION. and
then. in the TankTrack.cpp. I have
registered... That's a bit weird. it's got confused.
What have I done? Have I done something silly? Yes I think I've left something silly in the
constructor. Looking at SourceControl. of course I have. I shouldn't be saying OnComponentHit in the
constructor. So let's refresh the source control. and what I
have done here. without the... I need to save that file.
There you go. let it refresh. Good! So in BeginPlay() we
register for the event. and then. we use that same method
and then we simply print something out. Anyway. did it compile? It won't have done. because
I left some code in the constructor that I shouldn't have left. So now. hopefully
it will compile. By the way. I'd like to know in the discussions. which means over on
www.community.gamedev.tv/unreal. what you think about
me showing you the code i've just written in source control. while we wait for compilation. Is that
helpful or does it stink. Just let me know. that would be really helpful. Or perhaps
it would stink! OK. so here we go! The tracks are on the ground and we have lots of "I'm
hit. I'm hit!". I'm hits. which is cool! We have now got collision events actually triggering off inside C++!
But I would say that's a pretty good outcome for this lecture. so
there is your recipe. left on the screen. for how we use this OnHit() events. And in the next
video. we'll get on and actually make the tank not apply force. when it is on
the ground. So see you in there!
=======
Welcome to OnComponent
Hit Event in 4.12! What we're going to do here is intercept a hit
event between the tracks and the ground, so that we can in future use
it to prevent the tank from trying to apply a force, when it's in the air. So let's have a look at it!
So we're doing much better! The tank isn't sliding sideways now, but notice this,
if I drive the tank off the ground, look when it's in the air it goes nuts!
Why is it going so nuts? That's because we're still applying a driving force,
even though we're not in contact with the ground. That's kind of crazy! So the mission
here is to stop applying a force, unless we're in contact with the ground. Now, lets
use Blueprint to mock this up, initially. The first thing we need to do for this to work
is, both of the Left and Right Tracks need to have, under the Collision section
of the tank blueprint, the Simulation Generates Hit Events
checkbox ticked. Without that, they will not generate any Hit Events to detect.
Now let's just go to one of the tracks. You don't need to do this bit, I'm going to undo this bit of
blueprint. Follow me if you like. I'm going to click the event. Now, by the way, if you
select both tracks you won't get the Events list, so you have to select one track or the other.
When you select one or the other you get the Events list. At the bottom of the Details tab click plus,
and then, we can just print straight off this and
just see what we're trying to do in C++, here in Blueprint first.
So we could just say OnGround, we could even say Left track on ground.
On ground, there you go! So let's compile and play!
Provided those Simulation Generates Hit Events checkboxes
are set... There you go, we can see that the Left Track is indeed on the ground and it's logging
away. Cool! So that's very easy in Blueprint, but we are
all grown up and we don't want to be using Blueprint, we want to be using C++. So I'm going to
get rid of that and play the game and there they go! So
how do you do it in C++, how do we get access to this On Hit event?
Well there's a bit of controversy over this, right now, with version
4.12. If you try searching searching the web for "oncomponenthit unreal 4.12",
you'll find that people are really not sure how to do it, and that's because
they've changed stuff and they haven't documented what they've changed. Bless them. I'm sure they will at
some point but right now it's not clear. So how do you find out
what you should be doing here to register this. well we've got the source code, that's
the saving grace. So if you go OnComponentHit, which is the event which
we found the name out of from the blueprint, what we can do there
is we can right-click it and go to the definition. Yet again, we're diving into the source code,
this time of the primitive component, and it has this event,
which is of type FComponentHitSignature. Let's go to the definition of that.
Now I'm not necessarily expecting you guys to be able to do this, but the point is,
I want to give you an awareness of how we, with a lot of help from Sam, so me and Sam
found out how to get this signature. So you get here and you see a
macro, and if you look at that macro it's a bit odd, because we have commas between the
types and the actual names of these variables. Ignore the first
bit. We have a UPrimitiveComponent pointer
called HitComponent. We have an AActor pointer called OtherActor, we have a UPrimitiveComponent
pointer called OtherComp. How that translates to how you should actually use it is
as follows. I've written a slide for you. This is how to register for OnHit() Events,
in C++, in Unreal 4.12. [Laughs] OK.
Firstly, we register the delegate at BeginPlay(); we're going to need to put our BeginPlay back in,
and we use that syntax. OnComponentHit.AddDynamic(this,
and then the
delegate name of the method. So it's ampersand, forward
address of UTankTrack::On
Hit);. That tells it where to go and find the method, when this event gets triggered.
Then, you use this signature for the delegate itself.
[Laughs] It looks nasty but it's the thing I found in the source code, right, without all the commas.
It's OnHit(UPrimitiveComponent pointer HitComponent, AActor pointer
OtherActor, and so on. So you write an OnHit() method called that,
but what is important is that you make it a private UFUNCTION, that way the OnHit event will actually work.
OK, so what I'm going to do is just challenge you to actually do this. I want you to
register for OnHit(), inside C++. Use the instructions on the previous slide,
I'll even leave them up for the challenge, if I remember. Ensure that
both tracks have the following set in Blueprint: The Collision Simulation
Generates Hit Events, otherwise it will all go terribly wrong, and then, test that it works with
a log entry. And then, when you've done it and it works, arms in the air and
celebrate being one of the first people in Unreal 4.12 to get that working. So I'm just going to
dive back now and leave that on the screen, which is your recipe. Try and dig in, try
and work out how it works. I know it'll be ambiguous to some of you and very clear to others, but
a whole range of abilities on this course. So go ahead, pause the video, and get that puppy
working now!
OK welcome back! I'm actually going to use some of this
stuff straight off my slide. Why would I retype it? That would be nuts! So I'll come out
into the slide deck, then I'm going to go to
the... Well I need BeginPlay() back firstly, don't I? So we know how to do that don't we?
We've done this a hundred times. It's a load of fun, isn't it? Begin
Play(). There we go! So that almost brings BeginPlay()
back, but because it's C++, and we love C++ don't we, we have to go
over into the header file and type virtual, because that's what it is in the
parent class. We have to type void, because that's what comes back, we have to type BeginPlay(), because that's
the name of the method, and we have to type override, because we want to make sure
that we are overriding a method in the parent class, with exactly that signature.
Perfect! Now we have BeginPlay(), and we can say OnComponentHit
.AddDynamic. By the way, it won't complete the AddDynamic properly,
because something about the way the state of the source code,
at the moment, is preventing that from working. But this will work, OnComponentHit.Add
Dynamic, that's what we want. So that's the first bit of the recipe, and BeginPlay(), we
subscribe to this event. OK what's the next bit of the recipe?
A bit old OnHit() event. Now I didn't tell you whether it should be void
or what it should be. I didn't even write void for BeginPlay(). There you go!
So it should be void and it needs a class name,
and then, we have all that stuff, which I've pasted in
which you can get from the slides or from my repo. So
no semicolon but a pair of squigglies, and inside the squigglies, I'm just going to
simply say UE_LOG(LogTemp, Warning,
TEXT. And then we're just going to say ("I'm hit,
I'm hit!")) exclamation mark, because I'm very immature! OK so
then, once we've got that, then we need to go ahead and
declare this as well, inside our header file, of course.
So how are we going to do that? Well we go to the header file. Go to the private section, I'm going to do it
after BeginPlay() and probably after Tick, I like to keep BeginPlay() and Tick together.
Paste in the method, take away the class name,
put a semicolon on the end, and finally...
Where's the semicolon? I can't see my keyboard, the microphone is in the way. And this needs to be a
UFUNCTION(), because of Unreal magic. OK
great! Let's go ahead and compile this and see where we are! While
it compiles, I will show you, confidently, what I've done here in the
source control. I've added the BeginPlay() back in, I've added in that
signature which I shared with you, which we found from the source code as a UFUNCTION, and
then, in the TankTrack.cpp, I have
registered... That's a bit weird, it's got confused.
What have I done? Have I done something silly? Yes I think I've left something silly in the
constructor. Looking at SourceControl, of course I have, I shouldn't be saying OnComponentHit in the
constructor. So let's refresh the source control, and what I
have done here, without the... I need to save that file.
There you go, let it refresh. Good! So in BeginPlay() we
register for the event, and then, we use that same method
and then we simply print something out. Anyway, did it compile? It won't have done, because
I left some code in the constructor that I shouldn't have left. So now, hopefully
it will compile. By the way, I'd like to know in the discussions, which means over on
www.community.gamedev.tv/unreal, what you think about
me showing you the code i've just written in source control, while we wait for compilation. Is that
helpful or does it stink. Just let me know, that would be really helpful. Or perhaps
it would stink! OK, so here we go! The tracks are on the ground and we have lots of "I'm
hit, I'm hit!", I'm hits, which is cool! We have now got collision events actually triggering off inside C++!
But I would say that's a pretty good outcome for this lecture, so
there is your recipe, left on the screen, for how we use this OnHit() events. And in the next
video, we'll get on and actually make the tank not apply force, when it is on
the ground. So see you in there!
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1:Unreal/Section4/BT81 OnComponentHit Event in 4.12.srt