So welcome to Avoiding Boolean Flags!
We'll talk about why it's called that in the middle of the lecture. but for now. what I want to tell you
is that. by the end of the video. your tank and the AI tanks will be
not applying forces. unless they are in contact with the ground. And they'll
be moving a lot more sensibly. much more like a tank and none of this funny flying. So see you in there!
OK. so we'll get to why this video is called what it is a little bit later on. but for now.
the first thing I'm going to do is remove the AI tanks from the
scene. so remove both of those. So the World Outliner may be the most reliable place. rather than
hunting around in the 3D View. Then. the next thing I'm going to do is
just do a little bit of tweaking to my tank's physics. I'm removing those AI tanks. by the way. just
because we're focusing on our movement right now. we can put some new AI tanks in
later. So I want to go to the tank blueprint and observe
a couple of things. In fact. let's just show you this in the world first. Notice that if I move
along. I'm pushing the throttle. if I let go of the throttle I keep going at the same speed. seemingly
forever. That's rubbish and a tank is going to slow down! So the way you sort this out is. you go to
your tank blueprint. to the Tank root (Static Mesh Component) there.
scroll down. While you're scrolling down. make sure your Collision simulation generates
events is on. Mine didn't persist from the last video. for some reason. so I'll just save that
now. And it's under here. Linear Damping. Play with your figures
of Linear Damping. I'm going to choose 0.5. I tend to do... Well let's
see what 0.5 is like. before I say I'm going to choose it. So I accelerate away
and I let go of the throttle now and it comes to a halt in...
Yeah. I think that's a reasonable amount of time! But pick your own Linear Damping. What
Linear Damping is. is a force that works in opposition to the Linear Motion. It
is a force that works backwards. at a factor that depends on both
the tank's speed but also on this Linear Damping factor. Now let's look at
Angular Damping. At the moment. if we go hurtling off something. we have two
fundamental problems. when we're in the air. Not that we're going to do too much flying in tanks. because you can't
fly a tank fool. according to the A Team! But one of those problems is that
this happens. forces are still applied when it's in the air. we're going to fix that. and the other one is it
spins far too fast for a tank. So I'm going to give it a fair amount of Angular Damping.
0.8 Angular Damping. Rotations aren't completely properly
handled in these engines. The Intermediate Axis Theorem. if you want to look it up.
isn't built in really properly. but Angular Damping will give us
a nice effect. where the thing is a little bit harder to rotate than
it looks like it was. So if I put enough Angular Damping in look what happens as we're in the air.
it's a little bit better. everything's a little bit more mellow. So that's what I'm going to do. On the
tank blueprint. 0.5. 0.8 slows things down. I'm going to save this blueprint right now.
In fact. I'm going to Save All. so we never lose anything again. And now. we're going to turn
our attention to how we are going to decide whether we're
grounded or not and then how we're going to architect this class. Now don't use a
boolean flag. A boolean flag is when you're temped to say. ooh I'm going to set some
flag called IsGrounded. Just don't do that. the only time you want to use a boolean
is when the thing you're talking about really is true or false. like whether a button
is depressed or not. or something like that. But not when you're using
it to ask a question at one time. like am I grounded? So you could be
tempted to go. oh on hit. let's set a flag to say I'm grounded. and then. later
you read that flag. Well hang on. that's a bit nuts isn't it. because how
do you know that you're still grounded. when you come to read the flag later?
Why not just ask the question at the right time? But to do
that. you've got to architect his class a little bit differently. so what I'm going to suggest is that we don't have this
class ticking at all and that we just do everything on OnHit.
So OnHit gets called every frame anyway. and you saw that in the
logs up here. or every frame
that attracts our hitting something. it gets called right. So what makes sense.
from a pseudocode point of view. is just simply this. What we do OnHit is.
we "// Drive the tracks". and then. we "// Apply
a sideways force" and that's probably about it.
So let's start that process! The sideways force. let's
deal with that. as it's right in front of us. That code I've just highlighted in TickComponent is purely
about applying a sideways force. and we can't see that. so it's worth extracting it into
its own method. for self documentation purposes and so it can be called easily from On
Hit. So highlight that lot! In VisualStudio you've got quick actions. Right-click at the top
and then Extract Function. You can call it ApplySideways
Force. Now when you do this. notice that it's
noticing that you need the DeltaTime passed in there
OK. So we'll roll with that for a moment. OK
so what's happening is that TickComponent is now calling
ApplySidewaysForce. so that the behavior will be identical to what it was before. but we
actually don't want to call it from Tick. we want to call it straight from OnHit.
because OnHit's getting called every frame anyway. OK well that's all
we're doing from TickComponent. so guess what? We can get rid of TickComponent. we can
turn off ticking in the constructor. and. of course. we can remove
the TickComponent override. in the header file. Let's try
all that. before we go any further. So that's good news. because we
stopped our thing ticking. which is cool! Let me show you the uncommitted changes.
while we're here. I'm hearing that you like that. so that's good news. That's
what I've changed in the Tank.cpp and the Tank.h.
it's fairly obvious I've just removed that thing. OK cool!
So VisualStudio is popping up. Let's just play the game. make sure it still works! It should work
in exactly the same way. should the compile have succeeded. Delta
Time is an "undeclared identifier". OK fine.
So what happened is the Tick event had a Delta
Time inside it previously. remember it was one of it's parameters. and now we don't have it
available. so that's actually changed the signature of ApplySidewaysForce. Take the
DeltaTime out of it altogether. and we are actually just going to
cache... Well we don't even need to cache the DeltaTime. we can just. where we used
DeltaTime here let's just go get it. Let's just say. immediately before
that. auto DeltaTime = GetWorld().
Whenever you use GetWorld ask yourself if you really need to but.
in this case. it is a global piece of information the DeltaTime. it is WorldScale.
so it's fine to reach up to that global scope. GetDeltaTimeSeconds
or DeltaSeconds rather. So just do that. just get it just
before you need it. In fact. I'm going to move this comment up to the top of this method.
Then that's it. ApplySidewaysFriction doesn't need to take in a DeltaTime.
It works out the required acceleration. using the DeltaTime
and applies the SidewaysForce. Does that make sense? OK let's try it to see if it...
You know. let's not cry for how much sense it makes until we've
[Laughs] actually got it compiling. So this time I'll wait for it to compile.
before I show you the code. just because
you love staring at the Compiling C++ thing. It looks a bit like Knight Rider doesn't it?
Kit from Knight Rider. that little thing. OK. so we're refactoring here. so hopefully
we're close to compilation all the time. and look. it works the same! Does it? Am I slipping
sideways? No I''m not. So that's cool. yeah we've made good progress there!
I'll just quickly show you the code changes. for those of you who are interested. In the Tank.cpp. this is
what I've changed so far. It's a bit hard to read. but obviously the red is where I've deleted and
the green is where I've added. OK. so on here
we're applying a sideways force every frame. we've got rid of ticking. and it's
pretty good progress. How about this SetThrottle malarkey? Well
remember that that SetThrottle gets called four times per frame.
twice from IntendMoveForward and try twice from IntendTurnRight.
So we need to consume this throttle a little in a slightly
more interesting way. because you could be intending to move forward and turn right at the same
time. In fact. it happens whenever you're using the left thumb-stick on the controller. because
both of those inputs are kind of mixed together. So we want to make sure that we can't
get to a value of more than 1 in total. a total throttle of 1.
So let's think about what's going on here! This stuff inside
SetThrottle. at the moment. isn't setting the throttle at all really. is it? If you think about what it's actually
doing. we can extract this method. it's actually driving the
track. and it's taking a
throttle. So let's roll with that for a second! SetThrottle.
should SetThrottle just call DriveTrack with a (Throttle)? That is a completely
useless piece of refactoring. apart from DriveTrack is arguably a better
name than SetThrottle. right. Oh. by the way. for those none VisualStudio people.
when I do that extract function it is actually adding in all of my
header file things that I need for me. so that's kind of it. but if you
don't have that then you're going to need to do it manually. Anyway. when we set the throttle.
what I actually want to do is I want to cache this Throttle state. I want to keep the Throttle state.
Bear with me a second. let's show you why. So what we do is we just go float Current
Throttle. and I'm just going to say = 0. because I want
a sensible default. We put that as a member variable. The Drive
Track therefore no longer needs to take a throttle in at all. so we can get rid of that in its
signature. When it asks about a throttle.
it's going to use the CurrentThrottle. so DriveTrack's good to
go now. When we set a throttle what we want to do is this. we want to say that the CurrentThrottle
= the CurrentThrottle plus. not
+= in this case because I want to break it down further.
The CurrentThrottle is whatever CurrentThrottle was previously. plus the Throttle we're adding in.
but we don't want this to exceed 1. so we use a MathF
or FMath rather::Clamp
on that. And we restrict the range to
-1 to 1.
Now we want to be explicit that we want a floating point value out of this. not
an integer value out of this. so we're going to just put a float annotation here. in between the
word Clamp and the open brackets.
So hopefully that makes sense what we're doing. We're making sure that this CurrentThrottle member variable.
regardless of whether for MovementComponent. we are setting the
intention to move forward and to turn right at the same time. It's always going to end up
between -1 and +1. OK let's see how this behaves now!
And if it works it's all good news! Then. all we need to do is go over to the
AI tanks and make sure that they are playing the same game. by dropping them back in the scene.
It's a good idea to refresh them occasionally anyway. if we're making lots of changes to them. because you
can't be 110% sure that something didn't happen. Remember that the constructor
applies. runs on those tanks only when you drag them into the scene. so you can't be
100% sure that they're still going to work after major changes. So what's going
on? No movement at all! So I need to just work out what I've done
wrong there. Hop back into the code.
and of course. what I haven't done is ever called this DriveTrack method.
So we're setting a throttle. we extracted DriveTrack() out. but I deleted the call
to DriveTrack(). So where I've commented DriveTrack(). I'm just going to say DriveTrack().
It should be Track. because we are in single
track. if that makes sense. The other thing we should do while we're here is. it's all very well
setting this throttle but the tanks going to... Well let's just show you! I was going to say. the tank's going to continue to
roll forward isn't it. because we never set the throttle back to 0? So one thing
I'm thinking. while it compiles. we want to be doing is here we want to "//. reset
throttle". which is going to be trivial. but let me show you the effect of you not
resetting the throttle first. So I'm using the left stick on my controller here and I'm moving
around and it seems to be working fine. the question is. when we leave the ground.
Now. in the air you see there's no forces going on! Previously.
that tank would have flown but it's not. When it's not in the air there are no
forces. Much much much more like it! Now we are doing movement
the hard way with these tanks. of course we are. because there's a lot more learning in doing it this way than me
just saying to you. oh open up a new project in Unreal. use the four wheel vehicle.
then oh and the section's over. You're not going to learn anything from that. so doing things the
hard way. like training with a massive backpack on in the army. often gives you a lot
more growth. So let's reset this throttle. that's really trivial. Once we've used it.
we're just going to say CurrentThrottle = 0. Sorry. I never did show
you the problem with not doing that. so let me do that before I
go away. I've let go of the stick now. I'm not touching any controls and the tank
is still going! Why is it not slowing down. because of Linear Damping? It's nothing to do with that! The
fact is that. that current throttle member variable is still pinned at whatever value
it was at. OK. That's the problem we're seeing there. So if you set CurrentThrottle to 0.
we are golden. Let's take a look!
Then. all that remains is I dump in the two AI tanks and I
revel in the fact that they must behave. very similarly to the way my tank behaves. and
I'm going to say it again because they're using the same movement API. So I'm going to push
the throttle forward. then I'm going to let go of it. and the tank comes to a halt under the Linear
Damping. Bonzer! And then. I'm going to drop an AI tank or
two into the scene and just F11 it and make
sure that they can actually move now. And you'll find that they're moving much more
naturally. you see they've got sideways friction. they've got damping. They're still bouncing off these weird
imperfections in the terrain. What that is. is that the colliders of our tracks
are sometimes disappearing. but what I think this is that our colliders from our tracks
are sometimes disappearing into the floor and then popping back out. I haven't confirmed that yet
but it's not a dramatic problem. it's like we're hitting pebbles or something. so I'm not too
worried about it. and the point is that you're getting lots and lots and lots of different ways of using
Unreal here. So congratulations on getting that far. the tanks are working much better!
Remember you can always go to GitHub. my GitHub. in order to find
the code changes. I'll put a link in the resources. And I'll see you in the next lecture!
=======
So welcome to Avoiding Boolean Flags!
We'll talk about why it's called that in the middle of the lecture, but for now, what I want to tell you
is that, by the end of the video, your tank and the AI tanks will be
not applying forces, unless they are in contact with the ground. And they'll
be moving a lot more sensibly, much more like a tank and none of this funny flying. So see you in there!
OK, so we'll get to why this video is called what it is a little bit later on, but for now,
the first thing I'm going to do is remove the AI tanks from the
scene, so remove both of those. So the World Outliner may be the most reliable place, rather than
hunting around in the 3D View. Then, the next thing I'm going to do is
just do a little bit of tweaking to my tank's physics. I'm removing those AI tanks, by the way, just
because we're focusing on our movement right now, we can put some new AI tanks in
later. So I want to go to the tank blueprint and observe
a couple of things. In fact, let's just show you this in the world first. Notice that if I move
along, I'm pushing the throttle, if I let go of the throttle I keep going at the same speed, seemingly
forever. That's rubbish and a tank is going to slow down! So the way you sort this out is, you go to
your tank blueprint, to the Tank root (Static Mesh Component) there,
scroll down. While you're scrolling down, make sure your Collision simulation generates
events is on. Mine didn't persist from the last video, for some reason, so I'll just save that
now. And it's under here, Linear Damping. Play with your figures
of Linear Damping. I'm going to choose 0.5, I tend to do... Well let's
see what 0.5 is like, before I say I'm going to choose it. So I accelerate away
and I let go of the throttle now and it comes to a halt in...
Yeah, I think that's a reasonable amount of time! But pick your own Linear Damping. What
Linear Damping is, is a force that works in opposition to the Linear Motion. It
is a force that works backwards, at a factor that depends on both
the tank's speed but also on this Linear Damping factor. Now let's look at
Angular Damping. At the moment, if we go hurtling off something, we have two
fundamental problems, when we're in the air. Not that we're going to do too much flying in tanks, because you can't
fly a tank fool, according to the A Team! But one of those problems is that
this happens, forces are still applied when it's in the air, we're going to fix that, and the other one is it
spins far too fast for a tank. So I'm going to give it a fair amount of Angular Damping,
0.8 Angular Damping. Rotations aren't completely properly
handled in these engines. The Intermediate Axis Theorem, if you want to look it up,
isn't built in really properly, but Angular Damping will give us
a nice effect, where the thing is a little bit harder to rotate than
it looks like it was. So if I put enough Angular Damping in look what happens as we're in the air,
it's a little bit better, everything's a little bit more mellow. So that's what I'm going to do. On the
tank blueprint, 0.5, 0.8 slows things down. I'm going to save this blueprint right now.
In fact, I'm going to Save All, so we never lose anything again. And now, we're going to turn
our attention to how we are going to decide whether we're
grounded or not and then how we're going to architect this class. Now don't use a
boolean flag. A boolean flag is when you're temped to say, ooh I'm going to set some
flag called IsGrounded. Just don't do that, the only time you want to use a boolean
is when the thing you're talking about really is true or false, like whether a button
is depressed or not, or something like that. But not when you're using
it to ask a question at one time, like am I grounded? So you could be
tempted to go, oh on hit, let's set a flag to say I'm grounded, and then, later
you read that flag. Well hang on, that's a bit nuts isn't it, because how
do you know that you're still grounded, when you come to read the flag later?
Why not just ask the question at the right time? But to do
that, you've got to architect his class a little bit differently, so what I'm going to suggest is that we don't have this
class ticking at all and that we just do everything on OnHit.
So OnHit gets called every frame anyway, and you saw that in the
logs up here, or every frame
that attracts our hitting something, it gets called right. So what makes sense,
from a pseudocode point of view, is just simply this. What we do OnHit is,
we "// Drive the tracks", and then, we "// Apply
a sideways force" and that's probably about it.
So let's start that process! The sideways force, let's
deal with that, as it's right in front of us. That code I've just highlighted in TickComponent is purely
about applying a sideways force, and we can't see that, so it's worth extracting it into
its own method, for self documentation purposes and so it can be called easily from On
Hit. So highlight that lot! In VisualStudio you've got quick actions. Right-click at the top
and then Extract Function. You can call it ApplySideways
Force. Now when you do this, notice that it's
noticing that you need the DeltaTime passed in there
OK. So we'll roll with that for a moment. OK
so what's happening is that TickComponent is now calling
ApplySidewaysForce, so that the behavior will be identical to what it was before, but we
actually don't want to call it from Tick, we want to call it straight from OnHit,
because OnHit's getting called every frame anyway. OK well that's all
we're doing from TickComponent, so guess what? We can get rid of TickComponent, we can
turn off ticking in the constructor, and, of course, we can remove
the TickComponent override, in the header file. Let's try
all that, before we go any further. So that's good news, because we
stopped our thing ticking, which is cool! Let me show you the uncommitted changes,
while we're here. I'm hearing that you like that, so that's good news. That's
what I've changed in the Tank.cpp and the Tank.h,
it's fairly obvious I've just removed that thing. OK cool!
So VisualStudio is popping up. Let's just play the game, make sure it still works! It should work
in exactly the same way, should the compile have succeeded. Delta
Time is an "undeclared identifier". OK fine.
So what happened is the Tick event had a Delta
Time inside it previously, remember it was one of it's parameters, and now we don't have it
available, so that's actually changed the signature of ApplySidewaysForce. Take the
DeltaTime out of it altogether, and we are actually just going to
cache... Well we don't even need to cache the DeltaTime, we can just, where we used
DeltaTime here let's just go get it. Let's just say, immediately before
that, auto DeltaTime = GetWorld().
Whenever you use GetWorld ask yourself if you really need to but,
in this case, it is a global piece of information the DeltaTime, it is WorldScale,
so it's fine to reach up to that global scope, GetDeltaTimeSeconds
or DeltaSeconds rather. So just do that, just get it just
before you need it. In fact, I'm going to move this comment up to the top of this method.
Then that's it, ApplySidewaysFriction doesn't need to take in a DeltaTime.
It works out the required acceleration, using the DeltaTime
and applies the SidewaysForce. Does that make sense? OK let's try it to see if it...
You know, let's not cry for how much sense it makes until we've
[Laughs] actually got it compiling. So this time I'll wait for it to compile,
before I show you the code, just because
you love staring at the Compiling C++ thing. It looks a bit like Knight Rider doesn't it?
Kit from Knight Rider, that little thing. OK, so we're refactoring here, so hopefully
we're close to compilation all the time, and look, it works the same! Does it? Am I slipping
sideways? No I''m not. So that's cool, yeah we've made good progress there!
I'll just quickly show you the code changes, for those of you who are interested. In the Tank.cpp, this is
what I've changed so far. It's a bit hard to read, but obviously the red is where I've deleted and
the green is where I've added. OK, so on here
we're applying a sideways force every frame, we've got rid of ticking, and it's
pretty good progress. How about this SetThrottle malarkey? Well
remember that that SetThrottle gets called four times per frame,
twice from IntendMoveForward and try twice from IntendTurnRight.
So we need to consume this throttle a little in a slightly
more interesting way, because you could be intending to move forward and turn right at the same
time. In fact, it happens whenever you're using the left thumb-stick on the controller, because
both of those inputs are kind of mixed together. So we want to make sure that we can't
get to a value of more than 1 in total, a total throttle of 1.
So let's think about what's going on here! This stuff inside
SetThrottle, at the moment, isn't setting the throttle at all really, is it? If you think about what it's actually
doing, we can extract this method. it's actually driving the
track, and it's taking a
throttle. So let's roll with that for a second! SetThrottle,
should SetThrottle just call DriveTrack with a (Throttle)? That is a completely
useless piece of refactoring, apart from DriveTrack is arguably a better
name than SetThrottle, right. Oh, by the way, for those none VisualStudio people,
when I do that extract function it is actually adding in all of my
header file things that I need for me, so that's kind of it, but if you
don't have that then you're going to need to do it manually. Anyway, when we set the throttle,
what I actually want to do is I want to cache this Throttle state, I want to keep the Throttle state.
Bear with me a second, let's show you why. So what we do is we just go float Current
Throttle, and I'm just going to say = 0, because I want
a sensible default. We put that as a member variable. The Drive
Track therefore no longer needs to take a throttle in at all, so we can get rid of that in its
signature. When it asks about a throttle,
it's going to use the CurrentThrottle, so DriveTrack's good to
go now. When we set a throttle what we want to do is this, we want to say that the CurrentThrottle
= the CurrentThrottle plus, not
+= in this case because I want to break it down further.
The CurrentThrottle is whatever CurrentThrottle was previously, plus the Throttle we're adding in,
but we don't want this to exceed 1, so we use a MathF
or FMath rather::Clamp
on that. And we restrict the range to
-1 to 1.
Now we want to be explicit that we want a floating point value out of this, not
an integer value out of this, so we're going to just put a float annotation here, in between the
word Clamp and the open brackets.
So hopefully that makes sense what we're doing. We're making sure that this CurrentThrottle member variable,
regardless of whether for MovementComponent, we are setting the
intention to move forward and to turn right at the same time. It's always going to end up
between -1 and +1. OK let's see how this behaves now!
And if it works it's all good news! Then, all we need to do is go over to the
AI tanks and make sure that they are playing the same game, by dropping them back in the scene.
It's a good idea to refresh them occasionally anyway, if we're making lots of changes to them, because you
can't be 110% sure that something didn't happen. Remember that the constructor
applies, runs on those tanks only when you drag them into the scene, so you can't be
100% sure that they're still going to work after major changes. So what's going
on? No movement at all! So I need to just work out what I've done
wrong there. Hop back into the code,
and of course, what I haven't done is ever called this DriveTrack method.
So we're setting a throttle, we extracted DriveTrack() out, but I deleted the call
to DriveTrack(). So where I've commented DriveTrack(), I'm just going to say DriveTrack().
It should be Track, because we are in single
track, if that makes sense. The other thing we should do while we're here is, it's all very well
setting this throttle but the tanks going to... Well let's just show you! I was going to say, the tank's going to continue to
roll forward isn't it, because we never set the throttle back to 0? So one thing
I'm thinking, while it compiles, we want to be doing is here we want to "//. reset
throttle", which is going to be trivial, but let me show you the effect of you not
resetting the throttle first. So I'm using the left stick on my controller here and I'm moving
around and it seems to be working fine, the question is, when we leave the ground.
Now, in the air you see there's no forces going on! Previously,
that tank would have flown but it's not. When it's not in the air there are no
forces. Much much much more like it! Now we are doing movement
the hard way with these tanks, of course we are, because there's a lot more learning in doing it this way than me
just saying to you, oh open up a new project in Unreal, use the four wheel vehicle,
then oh and the section's over. You're not going to learn anything from that, so doing things the
hard way, like training with a massive backpack on in the army, often gives you a lot
more growth. So let's reset this throttle, that's really trivial. Once we've used it,
we're just going to say CurrentThrottle = 0. Sorry, I never did show
you the problem with not doing that, so let me do that before I
go away. I've let go of the stick now, I'm not touching any controls and the tank
is still going! Why is it not slowing down, because of Linear Damping? It's nothing to do with that! The
fact is that, that current throttle member variable is still pinned at whatever value
it was at, OK. That's the problem we're seeing there. So if you set CurrentThrottle to 0,
we are golden. Let's take a look!
Then, all that remains is I dump in the two AI tanks and I
revel in the fact that they must behave, very similarly to the way my tank behaves, and
I'm going to say it again because they're using the same movement API. So I'm going to push
the throttle forward, then I'm going to let go of it, and the tank comes to a halt under the Linear
Damping. Bonzer! And then, I'm going to drop an AI tank or
two into the scene and just F11 it and make
sure that they can actually move now. And you'll find that they're moving much more
naturally, you see they've got sideways friction, they've got damping. They're still bouncing off these weird
imperfections in the terrain. What that is, is that the colliders of our tracks
are sometimes disappearing, but what I think this is that our colliders from our tracks
are sometimes disappearing into the floor and then popping back out. I haven't confirmed that yet
but it's not a dramatic problem, it's like we're hitting pebbles or something, so I'm not too
worried about it, and the point is that you're getting lots and lots and lots of different ways of using
Unreal here. So congratulations on getting that far, the tanks are working much better!
Remember you can always go to GitHub, my GitHub, in order to find
the code changes, I'll put a link in the resources. And I'll see you in the next lecture!
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1:Unreal/Section4/BT82 Avoiding Boolean Flags.srt