So welcome to Improving
Tank Aiming! The purpose of this video is to just make sure that our tank always takes the short
route. So we'll end up with our tank on the hill with a literal glass ceiling in the sky to
help us put some pressure on the aiming system. and us and the AI tanks.
by the end of it. should be aiming more directly. no barrels going around the
wrong way. So I'll see you in there!
So let's look at improving this aim! Now these
two AI tanks. I'm not going to delete them this time because you may have placed them very carefully.
What it is about them that we don't want. when we're trying to do this
aiming testing. is we don't want them shooting at us. So we can just select them
and then. under their Details. Pawn section. you can say Auto Possess AI
Disabled. And the effect that will have is that the AI tanks
just don't aim at us. they're just sitting ducks ready for us to shoot at them. I can't
resist shooting at this guy with my crazy beach ball projectile! There you go! OK
great! So now we can stand and look much more carefully at our aiming. So
what's wrong with the aiming? Well you've noticed. probably. that it does some strange things.
Sometimes it goes the long way around. but also look what happens if I point at the sky.
Well firstly. we need to be careful when we look at this. This
is only moving the barrel. when we get a solution to the
aiming. and it hits something in the world. if you remember how the AimingComponent works.
So that we can focus on one thing at a time. I'm just going to
go to the tank blueprint and turn up the Launch Speed
to say 20.000.
and just test that that is enough to get the projectile even right over to the other
side of the world. So yeah. it's finding a solution even on that hillside there.
So now we are saying that. OK it's only aiming now
when it finds something to hit. but look what happens if we aim at the sky! You see it's
slewing around crazily! So what's going on there? Why is it trying to aim. even
though we're not hitting anything? If we go to Show... Sorry! To the
Lit button here and down to Visibility Collision. you'll see there is
nothing to hit out there. it is just a sky. So
what's going on? There's something wrong with the code in the TankPlayerController. because that's
the thing that tells it where to aim. So I'm interested in whether this GetSight
RayHitLocation thing. which is the boolean that determines whether we
aim or not. I'm interested in what that is every frame. so I'm going to just factor it
out of here. I'm just going to say auto or bool. It is going to be a bool. so
let's just do that this time. Bool GetSightRayHitLocation.
And I better give it a name. b
GotHitLocation
= that. OK. now I've factored it out so I can log it. So I'll pop it
back into the brackets. So far we've done nothing. we've just moved that out. but what this does mean
now is. that before we even go into the if statement we can now log this. Now how do you log
a boolean? I wonder if you know? What do you think? What do you think I'm going to type?
Any idea? OK. well a boolean's
internally stored as an integer. so one of the easiest ways of doing that is
to use %i for integer. If you were to go to "printf0
C++". something like that. then
in the printf reference you will get this here. "signed decimal
integer". I'll pop this in the lecture resources for you. that link. OK. so
an easy way to get the answer out of a bool is to just say
%i. Then. we can pop the boolean in.
and we can log that every frame. It's going to be quite instructive. let's have a look!
What I'm hoping will happen is it will say. yes I've got a hit. when I'm aiming at anything
like a tank. the ground. or even
well not when I hit the sky [Laughs] basically. So the tank or the ground. anything
where the player. the Visibility Collision. when we go to
this button and click there. anywhere that's visible I should be getting  1. And then. when I go up
there. I should be getting 0. So let's see if that's the case. and just clear
the log.
Not sure I am yet.
Yeah. so we're not. we're not getting 0. It's not saying I can't hit anything.
even though it's aiming at the sky. So what's wrong? Well let's go look at the code!
What's the method that it calls? It is calling GetSightRay
HitLocation. Let's look at GetSightRayHitLocation. Look. by default. if it
can't get a LookDirection it's returning true. Well that's wrong. it should be returning false.
And the other problem with it is that. if this
thing here fails we should also return false. but this thing here is a boolean.
so we want to return that. So our two simple changes are. we return false by default
and we return the result of this GetLookVectorHitLocation. that way
we will generally get false and we'll only get true if we actually hit something that is
visible. So let me recompile! And as I say. what I'm hoping now is that when I aim at anything
that's not gray. in this visibility collision view. that we get a
0 being logged out and that the aiming will stop.
So let's have a look up at the sky. Yeah. 0 gets logged out. and then. down at the ground
or a tank and up at the sky. Great! OK so that's
good news! That's much better! Now to test that a little bit further and give us the
ability to aim right up in the air. a little trick would be. you could put a glass ceilling
in here. I'll just show you how to do that! And that will allow us to aim right up. to really
test the movement of the barrel. So you could pop a cube in the scene. fairly high.
I'm going to make sure the padlocks are undone and scale it by 1.000.
1.000. 10. And if I come
down there it is. it's all big and black. I'm going to put it up a bit higher so there's a gap
between it and the mountains. and then. from the starter pack. I'm just going to assign a
glass material to it. So by putting a glass. literal
glass ceiling in here... Something's gone funny! That's because I changed.
I chose the wrong thing. Glass. there you go!
And what's happened to the scaling?
Hah. you know what I did? I
changed the Static Mesh in my hurry. so what you've actually got is. you've got a
cube as your Static Mesh and your materials should be Glass. Cool!
Alright. so let's have a look! If I now aim there. between the glass and
the mountain I get 0 logged out. and when I aim at the glass I get 1. The other benefit
of this is. it means we can actually test what happens if we aim really high in the sky. What
happens if I'm aiming there or there or up here
or there. You know. and is our aiming behaving
itself? Let's try going up on the mountain top. for a minute. I'll get the Xbox
controller going and just make sure now that we have pretty much a full
sphere of places that we can aim. that the aiming is behaving
itself. So it's important that aiming behaves. even when the tank's on a slope like this.
I'm going to just aim at the glass ceiling. fire. make sure it hits that point on the glass
ceiling. It does appear to. Let's aim behind me. I want to make sure that the aiming
always takes the shortest route. as well. from where we are to where we want
to be. So maybe it's better go to even further up this hill. so I can
really. from the top of the hill. get a huge almost like a sphere of different places
that you can aim. You want to put pressure on your aiming system. because you can be pretty sure that you're player will.
at some point. Ah look. that's going to wrong way! Did you see that? It's like. what
are you doing barrel or turret rather? You could have gone much shorter
distance! So this is our other problem with the aiming. Let me just move the
Player Start up here. because I think this would be a cool place for the Player Start.
right on top of the hill. So if I just grab it. move it
in that plane. move it up to the top of the hill. test that. Yeah we land
on top of the hill and don't fall off. Cool! So how then are we going to fix that
problem with the aiming? Well that's going to be your challenge. Let me just get you to the right place.
It's in the TankAimingComponent. our problem. and if you remember what we do. we work out
the difference between the barrel and the aim. and then. we just do a
Rotate by an amount of Yaw. What we need to do is protect that and say. well it depends
how much Yaw we're trying to do. If it's more than 180 degrees. then go the opposite
way. That's the hint. that's basically what we're doing. So I want you to make your turret take the short
route. Use a simple if() statement. Rotate so you always take the short route.
and test it player and AI tanks working again. Go ahead. pause the video. and see if
you can make that take the short route now!
OK welcome back! So I think this is relatively simple.
You can log to the Yaws if you want. to save time. I'm just not going to bother.
I'm simply going to say. if this (DeltaRotator.Yaw)
is less than 180 degrees...
So it turns out there's still a bug in this code. actually. but I'm going to fix that in a
few lectures time. If you want to fix it now. just change (DeltaRotator.Yaw)
for FMath::abs(DeltaRotator.Yaw). like
the annotations at the bottom of the screen. or leave your code like this. observe the bug which is that it
doesn't aim properly when you are changing from either
side of -X in the landscape space.
So if you point your aim down towards -X. behind where
my tank typically has been. which is why I didn't spot it. then the aim will go around the
wrong way. and we'll fix that in a few lectures time.
And you can always play around with the sign of these things. if you're not sure which way it should be.
If it's less than 180 degrees then do what we always did. otherwise
what I want to do is simply rotate in the opposite direction. So that's
pretty meaningful. You just say minus. like that.
OK and I think I'll make a comment here to say. "// Always
yaw the shortest way".
That's pretty simple. right! So just added a simple if case
in there. Let's see if that works. So we'll spawn on top of the hill in a minute. And what we're looking
to do is to make sure that we never end up with the aiming going in a
crazy haphazard opposite direction. I'll also. just for fun. in a moment.
re-enable the AI tanks. but first. let's make sure our aiming behaves. so it's aiming at the
sky. aiming at there. That's difficult to say. because it's so close to
us. but there and then I'd expect it to go left. Yeah. that to
me looks like it's always taking the shortest route now. So if you find any
use cases where it doesn't. let me know. but that's looking a lot better. I'm just going to re-enable
the AI on these enemy tanks here. So you select them
and you say Auto Possess AI. Placed in World. So they have been placed in the world. the AI
will get possessed. I'm going to grab the Xbox controller. dive
down the hill. and of course. we're falling
over which is always quite fun. And are they aiming properly? It doesn't really matter if I fall
over! It's fine if we get hit! You know. in a moment. obviously we're going to change
these projectiles. so they don't send the tank flying so much. But right now. it's actually quite
useful to be hit around a little bit and do some crazy stuff. because again it introduces really weird
conditions in the game that you wouldn't expect and allows us to say. well you know. is
this aiming working or isn't it working? So I don't mind being upside down. I don't mind
all that mess. I just want to drive around and make sure that the aiming
works. but I'm fairly convinced it does. so I'm going to get rid of this unecessary
log entry in here. just by searching the whole project. actually. for "UE_LOG".
And just ask myself. what logs do I really want?
Well I don't want this one anymore. I can leave this as a boolean. that won't slow things down very much.
And that's it. that's all we have! In fact. while I'm here. it's reminded me to look for any "TODO's" in the
project. We'll have to do that when we next look at the AI. We'll look at
the AI shortly. about the acceptance radius. and limiting the AI's firing
rate. Yep good! OK. so that is it. we have better aiming than we
had before! I quite like starting on top of the hill. so I think I'm going to do that. and
well done getting this far! Hopefully your barrels are aiming in the shortest direction.
and [Laughs] it's crazy these projectiles. And it's all a bit of fun. so I'll see
you in the next video!