Hey. and welcome to Tweaking Tank AI!
What we're going to do in this video is to simply prevent the tanks
from firing. the AI tanks from firing. until they're locked. And we're also
going to prevent them from getting any closer than about 80 meters away.
so that they get to about 80 meters and then blow us out the water. [Laughs] OK! See you soon!
OK so let's get into improving a few things about this aiming. The
first thing you'll notice is that these AI tanks. they
fire off their weapons before they're actually locked. so let's start by
sorting that out. So ohh. it's gone a bit funny hasn't it?!
Oh. you know what I've done there. by the way. oh I've hit the
top-left key on the keyboard. above the Tab under the Escape and that
brings up the game console. which you may be familiar with from some Unreal game.
OK. so what we want to do then is. in the TankAIController
and the .cpp. instead of just firing.
what we want to do in pseudocode is say if... And then.
what is the state? The AimingComponent header file. Yeah.
if Aiming or Locked only is what we want. so let's just pseudocode that
in the tank... "// If aiming or locked"
then fire is what we want to do. OK. so how are we going to do that? Well we need to
be able to get this state from the AimingComponent
and. at the moment. we don't have a way doing that. Now don't just make this FiringState
public. that's naughty. because that would allow other classes to set the FiringState. and as
your project gets bigger that means you're likely to end up doing that by mistake. What we want to do is make
a nice safe void... Ah. not void! Very easy to
type void. isn't it? We want a method that returns the FiringState. so the return
type is EFiringState. and then. it's GetFiringState()
and then const because we don't want it changing any of the member variables. we're
just getting the FiringState. Let's go ahead and implement that. I'm going to use VisualStudio's
Create Definition tool. but if you're in Xcode then it's very easy to
just go and write this over in the TankAimingComponent.cpp file.
So I'm just going to make sure that it's done it right. It kind of [Laughs] hasn't. it's
saying return an EFiringState() as a method. That's a bit weird. and it's not
EFiringState. it's FiringState. Remember the member variable in question
in the header file here is FiringState. so the implementation...
This is confusing for you Xcode guys. by the way. We're looking into the TankAiming
Conponent.cpp here. we can't just go to the TankAimingComponent. Here it is. there's a getter! In fact.
I'm going to move that getter further up the class. because I think it should be
probably. something like. after. it doesn't really matter. after Tick. something
like that. OK. so it's a very simple const method
that returns the FiringState. Now that we've got that getter method.
in the TankAIController. we can ask this question. "// if aim or locked".
We can actually ask it in code. if (Aiming
Component. because that's the thing that knows. GetFiringState()
== EFiringState
:: because it's a static.
In this case. it's an enum but it's known at compile time. that's when you use your colon
colons. If it's Locked. that's the only time. actually. we want
this AI tank to fire. and we'll worry about limiting the firing rate later.
Does that make sense? Let's have a go! We're simply saying to the AI
tanks. don't fire until you're locked. you crazy fools! Now let's see if they
actually get locked. This is going to depend somewhat on the
AcceptanceRadius. that we have in the TankAimingComponent. Do you remember this
here? This AcceptanceRadius is very small. It may be that they never quite get locked. but
let's see what happens. I'm going to go F11. go down the hill a little bit.
to where I can see them. Boom! Yeah oh. they definitely got
locked. [Laughs] O.K. No worries about them getting locked! But what they are doing
is getting. I think. too close. They're kind of crazy cheeky close. right now!
So are they aiming the right way? Let's just check that. They do appear to be.
Is this guy going to shoot me? He's not locked.
He doesn't want to think that he's locked either. You know why this probably is? It's probably because they're
trying to aim at the bottom half of... Remember that the only thing they can aim at. at the moment. is the
tank route i.e. it's origin. and they probably couldn't quite
get their barrels low enough but the point is. they shouldn't be getting that close in the first place.
So that's what we're going to tackle now. in the second half of the video. So.
so far. as a recap. what we have done is we have
written a getter and then implemented it. which was super simple on the TankAimingComponent and
then. just said to the AI Controller. only fire when locked. Very very simple. it
reads almost like English. Now we're going to look at the AcceptanceRadius. So
not that but in the... Where is the AcceptanceRadius? It'll be in the Tank
AIController. We have an AcceptanceRadius here.
If you go to the header file of the TankAIController.
remember the AcceptanceRadius is how close the tank AI can get. Well what I want to
do is. I want to expose this to a blueprint. but we don't even have a blueprint for it. at the moment.
so you're going to do it. Here's your challenge! I want you to make a blueprint of the TankAI
Controller class. See if you can remember how to do that. over in the Editor. Then. I want you
to expose AcceptanceRadius as EditAnywhere.
at least for now. You could make it edit default only. but let's go EditAnywhere to start
with. You'll see why. Code your default AcceptanceRadius. once you find it. So
explore it in the Editor. You may want to depossess the tank. play around with some AcceptanceRadiuses. see
how many meters. Remember that it's got two extra 0's on it. so 7.000 would mean
70 meters. And then. put the default back into C++. place your AI
tanks in the world. and remember that if you do place your AI tanks for your
player outside the Navmesh. then you may need to refresh your Navmesh.
Currently. my Navmesh is only a subset of the whole terrain. so I'll probably expand that out as well.
because if you go off the Navmesh. things will stop moving. OK. so pause the video and have a go at that
challenge now!
OK guys. let's get this done! This will be
a bit of fun. sort of. OK. so how do we do it? We go to the C++
Classes folder. of our Content browser.  We go find
ourselves the Tank AI Controller. right-click it. and then. say Create Blueprint class based on
Tank AIController. There it is! So I'm going to call it TankAIController_
BP. because that's how we like to name things and create it. There it is!
Now. just straight away. I'm going to put it in the Blueprints folder. just to keep the other one that's in there
company and to be tidy. So here it is! It doesn't do anything. it doesn't need to do anything
yet. but we are going to expose a property. So let's go ahead and do that! I'm going to move. of
course. this AcceptanceRadius. into the protected section of the class. Why?
Because the blueprint is a... Hold on. I can't talk and type at the same
time. I can usually but I can't right now. The blueprint
is a child class of the C++ class. In fact. you can
see that in the blueprint. It says Parent Class is the Tank AIController. So
that's exactly what protected means. it means the children can read it. So let's make this a
UPROPERTY(EditAnywhere) for now.
And then. I'm going to go
category = "Setup" in strings. And
I'm going to make a note. straight away. that "// Consider DefaultsEdit
Only". EditDefaultsOnly. If I actually put the word
exactly like that. then I could always copy and paste it later. That's the handy thing about writing the actual
code there. but you wouldn't normally write full coding comments. The whole point of comments
is that you can use English. But in this case. if I'm saying I might change this code for this
code. then it make sense to put it so that I could copy and paste it later. OK
so that's now exposed. Let's go have a little compile and
watch the TankAIController blueprint. as we do so. And what I'm
hoping will happen. I could collapse some of these categories down. is a Setup category will magically
appear in here. and we will be. there you go. able to set an Acceptance
Radius. So let's try an AcceptanceRadius of 150
meters. Compile. play. I love how fast you can compile blueprints. of course.
And let's make ourselves larger and see
how far away that is. Now they're not
moving. Yeah. they're coming towards us. I don't know. difficult to say! Difficult to
say. when they're shooting the daylights out of us like this. So why don't we
make it nearly impossible for them to shoot us. just temporarily. or we could even
take the TankAimingComponent off. The problem with that is. it's a little bit
tricky to do. So what's the easiest way of disabling this thing?
Well one thing would be to give them a pitiful launch speed of maybe 10 but remember what you
had first. I think it was 20.000. So
OK. let's try again! The point here is that I want to be able to see how
close they can get. and I can't do that all the time that they are shooting
me. So what you can do with this Edit...
Hmm. it doesn't seem to be holding there? They seem to be pretty close. so let's just
depossess with F8. click on this tank... Although. remember
it's not the tank that's controlling this. it's AIController. which must be that
one. That AIController went for the left tank and that one for the right tank. the AIController hasn't moved
in the world. But if you look at the AIController. then you can see the Acceptance
Radius. down there. is 3.000 on that one. So what you're going to have to do
is to tweak these things. actually. at runtime. So let's try
150.000. Then. I can repossess my tank. get back into
it. and then. drive off and see at what point does that tank.
whose AIController I just edited. start chasing us.
Keep going.
It doesn't seem to be chasing me
at all. What's wrong with him? Oh yes he is. there he is! OK. so the point is. that's too far away!
So I can go F8. I can click on this. I can pause the game even. click on the
controller in question. that one there. Try 80
meters. 8000.
and then. I could resume the game and see if 80 meters
looks reasonable. Now remember. they won't necessarily stop exactly where you ask them to.
because they are going to overshoot. right. especially if they're going that fast.
So another way of seeing is. I move away from him and see when he starts moving.
Is this a reasonable place for the tank to get to? Yeah. that's
probably about right for the enemy tank. We want it to stop around there and
shoot at us. Cool! So we have our value. that's how we discovered our value!
So it's not 150 meters but it's
80 meters. So now we can make things simpler again. We can go back to the C++. we can
code this in here. 80 meters. I will change it to EditDefault
Only and recompile. And then. what you'll
find will happen with EditDefaultOnly is that the actual instance of the
AIController will no longer have that value on it. and the only place that you'll be able to
change it is in a sensible place. which is the TankAIController's AcceptanceRadius over here.
OK. so let's have a look!
In fact. we've still got that as 150. so that's going to override the blueprint.
so I'm going to set it to 80 in here as well. The point of the C++ value
is that. if we make a new TankAIController blueprint.
then that's the value it's going to default to. so we want to
put the value in here that we want. right. So C++
determines what the default in this box is. and then. this box determines what actually
happens in the game play. if that makes sense. So 80 meters is what we're going for.
And we'll just save everything.
play the game. make sure it's OK. and then. hopefully we
have made the improvements we want to. which is that they don't fire until they're locked
and that they stop about 80 meters away. Cool! I just need to re-enable the
tank's firing. So instead of being at a launch at 4.000.
let's put it back to 10 meters per second. Let's put it back under the
TankAimingComponent of the tank blueprint. to 4.000.
which is 40 meters a second which is about 100 miles an hour. It's pretty slow.
actually. for a projectile. of course. but that's fine for now. while we're still using these beach balls. We'll
create our projectiles shortly. Let's just see how this is! Can I shoot them? It's difficult
actually. Ahh. I missed. of course. because the projectile's so slow. but they can certainly shoot me.
and they don't crowd me. they don't get too close. So I'm much happier with that. and I
will see you in the next video! If you're
still with me. then I just want to leave the code changes on the screen for you. That is the Tank
AIController C++. The AimingComponent is just
the getter. and remember you can always go to GitHub to get the code state. So
I will see you soon!
=======
Hey, and welcome to Tweaking Tank AI!
What we're going to do in this video is to simply prevent the tanks
from firing, the AI tanks from firing, until they're locked. And we're also
going to prevent them from getting any closer than about 80 meters away,
so that they get to about 80 meters and then blow us out the water. [Laughs] OK! See you soon!
OK so let's get into improving a few things about this aiming. The
first thing you'll notice is that these AI tanks, they
fire off their weapons before they're actually locked, so let's start by
sorting that out. So ohh, it's gone a bit funny hasn't it?!
Oh, you know what I've done there, by the way, oh I've hit the
top-left key on the keyboard, above the Tab under the Escape and that
brings up the game console, which you may be familiar with from some Unreal game.
OK, so what we want to do then is, in the TankAIController
and the .cpp, instead of just firing,
what we want to do in pseudocode is say if... And then,
what is the state? The AimingComponent header file. Yeah,
if Aiming or Locked only is what we want, so let's just pseudocode that
in the tank... "// If aiming or locked"
then fire is what we want to do. OK, so how are we going to do that? Well we need to
be able to get this state from the AimingComponent
and, at the moment, we don't have a way doing that. Now don't just make this FiringState
public, that's naughty, because that would allow other classes to set the FiringState, and as
your project gets bigger that means you're likely to end up doing that by mistake. What we want to do is make
a nice safe void... Ah, not void! Very easy to
type void, isn't it? We want a method that returns the FiringState, so the return
type is EFiringState, and then, it's GetFiringState()
and then const because we don't want it changing any of the member variables, we're
just getting the FiringState. Let's go ahead and implement that. I'm going to use VisualStudio's
Create Definition tool, but if you're in Xcode then it's very easy to
just go and write this over in the TankAimingComponent.cpp file.
So I'm just going to make sure that it's done it right. It kind of [Laughs] hasn't, it's
saying return an EFiringState() as a method. That's a bit weird, and it's not
EFiringState, it's FiringState. Remember the member variable in question
in the header file here is FiringState, so the implementation...
This is confusing for you Xcode guys, by the way. We're looking into the TankAiming
Conponent.cpp here, we can't just go to the TankAimingComponent. Here it is, there's a getter! In fact,
I'm going to move that getter further up the class, because I think it should be
probably, something like, after, it doesn't really matter, after Tick, something
like that. OK, so it's a very simple const method
that returns the FiringState. Now that we've got that getter method,
in the TankAIController, we can ask this question, "// if aim or locked".
We can actually ask it in code, if (Aiming
Component, because that's the thing that knows. GetFiringState()
== EFiringState
:: because it's a static.
In this case, it's an enum but it's known at compile time. that's when you use your colon
colons. If it's Locked, that's the only time, actually, we want
this AI tank to fire, and we'll worry about limiting the firing rate later.
Does that make sense? Let's have a go! We're simply saying to the AI
tanks, don't fire until you're locked, you crazy fools! Now let's see if they
actually get locked. This is going to depend somewhat on the
AcceptanceRadius, that we have in the TankAimingComponent. Do you remember this
here? This AcceptanceRadius is very small. It may be that they never quite get locked, but
let's see what happens. I'm going to go F11, go down the hill a little bit,
to where I can see them. Boom! Yeah oh, they definitely got
locked. [Laughs] O.K. No worries about them getting locked! But what they are doing
is getting, I think, too close. They're kind of crazy cheeky close, right now!
So are they aiming the right way? Let's just check that. They do appear to be.
Is this guy going to shoot me? He's not locked.
He doesn't want to think that he's locked either. You know why this probably is? It's probably because they're
trying to aim at the bottom half of... Remember that the only thing they can aim at, at the moment, is the
tank route i.e. it's origin, and they probably couldn't quite
get their barrels low enough but the point is, they shouldn't be getting that close in the first place.
So that's what we're going to tackle now, in the second half of the video. So,
so far, as a recap, what we have done is we have
written a getter and then implemented it, which was super simple on the TankAimingComponent and
then, just said to the AI Controller, only fire when locked. Very very simple, it
reads almost like English. Now we're going to look at the AcceptanceRadius. So
not that but in the... Where is the AcceptanceRadius? It'll be in the Tank
AIController. We have an AcceptanceRadius here.
If you go to the header file of the TankAIController,
remember the AcceptanceRadius is how close the tank AI can get. Well what I want to
do is, I want to expose this to a blueprint, but we don't even have a blueprint for it, at the moment,
so you're going to do it. Here's your challenge! I want you to make a blueprint of the TankAI
Controller class. See if you can remember how to do that, over in the Editor. Then, I want you
to expose AcceptanceRadius as EditAnywhere,
at least for now. You could make it edit default only, but let's go EditAnywhere to start
with. You'll see why. Code your default AcceptanceRadius, once you find it. So
explore it in the Editor. You may want to depossess the tank, play around with some AcceptanceRadiuses, see
how many meters. Remember that it's got two extra 0's on it, so 7,000 would mean
70 meters. And then, put the default back into C++, place your AI
tanks in the world, and remember that if you do place your AI tanks for your
player outside the Navmesh, then you may need to refresh your Navmesh.
Currently, my Navmesh is only a subset of the whole terrain, so I'll probably expand that out as well,
because if you go off the Navmesh, things will stop moving. OK, so pause the video and have a go at that
challenge now!
OK guys, let's get this done! This will be
a bit of fun, sort of. OK, so how do we do it? We go to the C++
Classes folder, of our Content browser.  We go find
ourselves the Tank AI Controller, right-click it, and then, say Create Blueprint class based on
Tank AIController. There it is! So I'm going to call it TankAIController_
BP, because that's how we like to name things and create it. There it is!
Now, just straight away, I'm going to put it in the Blueprints folder, just to keep the other one that's in there
company and to be tidy. So here it is! It doesn't do anything, it doesn't need to do anything
yet, but we are going to expose a property. So let's go ahead and do that! I'm going to move, of
course, this AcceptanceRadius, into the protected section of the class. Why?
Because the blueprint is a... Hold on, I can't talk and type at the same
time. I can usually but I can't right now. The blueprint
is a child class of the C++ class. In fact, you can
see that in the blueprint. It says Parent Class is the Tank AIController. So
that's exactly what protected means, it means the children can read it. So let's make this a
UPROPERTY(EditAnywhere) for now.
And then, I'm going to go
category = "Setup" in strings. And
I'm going to make a note, straight away, that "// Consider DefaultsEdit
Only". EditDefaultsOnly. If I actually put the word
exactly like that, then I could always copy and paste it later. That's the handy thing about writing the actual
code there, but you wouldn't normally write full coding comments. The whole point of comments
is that you can use English. But in this case, if I'm saying I might change this code for this
code, then it make sense to put it so that I could copy and paste it later. OK
so that's now exposed. Let's go have a little compile and
watch the TankAIController blueprint, as we do so. And what I'm
hoping will happen, I could collapse some of these categories down, is a Setup category will magically
appear in here, and we will be, there you go, able to set an Acceptance
Radius. So let's try an AcceptanceRadius of 150
meters. Compile, play. I love how fast you can compile blueprints, of course.
And let's make ourselves larger and see
how far away that is. Now they're not
moving. Yeah, they're coming towards us. I don't know, difficult to say! Difficult to
say, when they're shooting the daylights out of us like this. So why don't we
make it nearly impossible for them to shoot us, just temporarily, or we could even
take the TankAimingComponent off. The problem with that is, it's a little bit
tricky to do. So what's the easiest way of disabling this thing?
Well one thing would be to give them a pitiful launch speed of maybe 10 but remember what you
had first. I think it was 20,000. So
OK, let's try again! The point here is that I want to be able to see how
close they can get, and I can't do that all the time that they are shooting
me. So what you can do with this Edit...
Hmm, it doesn't seem to be holding there? They seem to be pretty close, so let's just
depossess with F8, click on this tank... Although, remember
it's not the tank that's controlling this, it's AIController, which must be that
one. That AIController went for the left tank and that one for the right tank. the AIController hasn't moved
in the world. But if you look at the AIController, then you can see the Acceptance
Radius, down there, is 3,000 on that one. So what you're going to have to do
is to tweak these things, actually, at runtime. So let's try
150,000. Then, I can repossess my tank, get back into
it, and then, drive off and see at what point does that tank,
whose AIController I just edited, start chasing us.
Keep going.
It doesn't seem to be chasing me
at all. What's wrong with him? Oh yes he is, there he is! OK, so the point is, that's too far away!
So I can go F8, I can click on this, I can pause the game even, click on the
controller in question, that one there. Try 80
meters, 8000,
and then, I could resume the game and see if 80 meters
looks reasonable. Now remember, they won't necessarily stop exactly where you ask them to,
because they are going to overshoot, right, especially if they're going that fast.
So another way of seeing is, I move away from him and see when he starts moving.
Is this a reasonable place for the tank to get to? Yeah, that's
probably about right for the enemy tank. We want it to stop around there and
shoot at us. Cool! So we have our value, that's how we discovered our value!
So it's not 150 meters but it's
80 meters. So now we can make things simpler again. We can go back to the C++, we can
code this in here, 80 meters. I will change it to EditDefault
Only and recompile. And then, what you'll
find will happen with EditDefaultOnly is that the actual instance of the
AIController will no longer have that value on it, and the only place that you'll be able to
change it is in a sensible place, which is the TankAIController's AcceptanceRadius over here.
OK, so let's have a look!
In fact, we've still got that as 150, so that's going to override the blueprint,
so I'm going to set it to 80 in here as well. The point of the C++ value
is that, if we make a new TankAIController blueprint,
then that's the value it's going to default to, so we want to
put the value in here that we want, right. So C++
determines what the default in this box is, and then, this box determines what actually
happens in the game play, if that makes sense. So 80 meters is what we're going for.
And we'll just save everything,
play the game, make sure it's OK, and then, hopefully we
have made the improvements we want to, which is that they don't fire until they're locked
and that they stop about 80 meters away. Cool! I just need to re-enable the
tank's firing. So instead of being at a launch at 4,000,
let's put it back to 10 meters per second. Let's put it back under the
TankAimingComponent of the tank blueprint, to 4,000,
which is 40 meters a second which is about 100 miles an hour. It's pretty slow,
actually, for a projectile, of course, but that's fine for now, while we're still using these beach balls. We'll
create our projectiles shortly. Let's just see how this is! Can I shoot them? It's difficult
actually. Ahh, I missed, of course, because the projectile's so slow, but they can certainly shoot me,
and they don't crowd me, they don't get too close. So I'm much happier with that, and I
will see you in the next video! If you're
still with me, then I just want to leave the code changes on the screen for you. That is the Tank
AIController C++. The AimingComponent is just
the getter, and remember you can always go to GitHub to get the code state. So
I will see you soon!
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1:Unreal/Section4/BT84 Tweaking Tank AI.srt