So welcome to Making
an Ammo Display! In this video we'll be doing exactly that. and by the end of it we'll have a little
ammo display up there. number 3. and when we cannot fire anymore. our crosshair
or reticle will go gray. So I'll see you in there!
Hello and welcome back! So let's just take a look at what we're going to
be doing. We want a ammo display. but just before we start. notice that
neither of those AI tanks are currently aiming at me. Yet as I drive a little bit
closer. the guy on the left starts aiming. then hopefully the
guy on the right starts aiming. There we go! So what could that be? What's the most likely
reason they're not aiming at me. at this stage. Well. if you think about it. I seem to be
just outside a radius don't I. one starts aiming and then the other. Well the
problem. of course. is that the velocity that they can
fire at is not high enough. I'm going to increase the Launch Speed to 8.000
or 80 meters a second or nearly 200 miles an hour.
over on the TankAimingComponent in the tank blueprint. Now. when we
start the game. we should find they both aim at us. because they both have an aiming solution. and we
are basically in range. Perfect! Alright. so we want a
piece of display text. Why don't we make the display text first. create the pane.
hey just for fun! So what I mean by that is. create a problem to
solve. The problem will be. we have no way of updating the display text. but at least we'll have the display
text. So let's grab the text. drop it onto our UI.
make it a little bit bigger. I'm going to use
a 96 font. That's a bit leery. let's try 72.
OK that's fine! There's no border around it. so it doesn't really matter how
I aligned the text in there. at this stage at least. but I think centered
may be better. Now I'm just going to put a default number in of
3 or even XX like that. just so I can help
see what's going on in terms of alignment. and then. what I want to do
is think very quickly. with any new item. about what the anchor point is.
And in the case of this piece of text. we want it anchored to
probably the top-right of the screen would make sense.
So let's compile and just have a look at that. If we play. then it's a fixed distance from the top-
right of this viewport. but remember that we are currently playing
in the selected viewport. You see when you say
Play Mode. Selected Viewport. so if we play now it's still anchored to the top-right.
So that's cool! If you want to see what it would be like. in a stand alone instance.
you can go to the drop-down up here. near the play button. and say Standalone
Game. If you do that. it'll ask you to save everything. no harm in that.
and it'll open a whole new process and play the game in a nice 16 x 9
window or however we've got our game configured. and then. it'll show you that the ammo
display works there. too. Cool! So the ammo display is anchored to the top-right.
Now what we're going to need is a getter. So under the Content section of the
text-box. that we've put in. we want to go ahead and create a
binding from that and we get some blueprint. Alright
cool! So look. I've done enough. I want you to do that rest of this. So I'm going to give you
a challenge. Make an ammo display. Get an ammo
display working. Basically. we want it counting down. it should count down each time you fire.
As a bonus. make the crosshair go gray. when you're completely out of ammo.
and a tip for you. if you do add a new enum state. for example. out of ammo.
you're going to need to restart the Editor in the current version of Unreal. in order for that
enum state to show in your blueprint because of a bug. OK
pause the video. see if you can get ammo display working in it's entirety now.
Hey hey hey. welcome back! So in order for this to work. we're going to need to go
ahead and open a couple of files. of course. and it's mainly going to
be the TankAimingComponent. And let's look at the TankAiming
Component header file. So I'm going to make myself and OutOfAmmo
enum state. while I'm there. because well we
want to keep track of that. I'm also. at the bottom of the TankAimingComponent.h.
going to make an integer RoundsLeft. and I'm going to make a
default of 3. So we start with 3 rounds. unless
we're told anything else. Now. we're going to need a getter. so don't make it
public. Make yourself an integer Get
RoundsLeft(). It doesn't need any parameters.
const method like that. so that any class can
ask the AimingComponent how many rounds it's got left. That seems perfectly reasonable to me.
I'm going to create a definition. using Visual
Studio's tool. "A definition for the symbol 'GetRoundLeft' "...
It's not going to work. so I'll just go do it myself. Not a problem. I'll put it under
Tick. I think. So it's going to be
int. the class name.
::GetRoundsLeft() const to match
the signature. and then. we're just going to return
RoundsLeft. comsa! Very simple! OK
let's just compile this! We want to stay close to compilation. i.e.
close to a game that is ready to compile. and then. we have ourselves a
RoundsLeft variable. But we're going to need to expose this guy to
blueprint aren't we. otherwise we're not going to be able to read it. Here in the PlayerUI.
where I went over to the Designer and
bound this. created a binding. what happened is in the graph here it
created a whole new Event Graph called Get Text 0. Well let's give that a more meaningful
name. over on the My Blueprint tab. Let's rename it to
Get_Rounds_Left or something like that.
so it's a bit more meaningful. And what we're going to want here is. we're going to want to be able to get the
BP_Aiming Component Reference. and from this. we're going to want to be able to Get Rounds
Left. We can't right now. Why not? Well because this is not a UPROPERTY.
And in fact. it's going to be the same UPROPERTY as Fire().
so I'll just use that one there. It's going to be a BlueprintCallable. Firing category.
GetRoundsLeft() OK. So that's cool! Let's go
ahead and compile our code. and then. we will have here.
in the graph. specifically the GetRoundsLeft
Event Graph of the PlayerUI blueprint. we will have the ability to
call GetRoundsLeft. on the PlayerUI blueprint
reference that we have. Once we get that. we need to take the
value. and what do we do with it? We're going to turn it into a string.
Once it's a string. you'll notice that this is a one color and this text
here is slightly differently. They've made them a similar color. which is cool. but they're not exactly
the same. One is an internationalizer or. as they call it. a localizable
text and this is a string. but it turns out. if you drag the two together. it'll
put the required string to localizable
text node in for you. So that's pretty cool! So there's your blueprint.
like that! You can line these up all day. and there are various tools to distribute
and line these things up. if you care about that. Alignment. Align
Center. middle like that or whatever. however you like it. but
the point is that's the logic. So that is now getting the
rounds left. Let's see if it is! Let's play the game! Not in Stand Alone. I'm going to go back to the Viewport.
just because I can see it. There you go. XX! Now. it's
not working. Why not? GetRoundLeft. let's compile
it. It's because it's not compiling! So it's saying that we have a
"Invalid option value 'Reloading' in Select". and we have
an error here. OK this error probably is because we have changed
or I changed the enum. and this enum is not up to date with the
enum that I changed. So let me try just deleting this guy.
there that's probably my best bet and coming off and going Select.
No I've still not go the fourth enum state. so this is the bug I was telling you about.
Let's close Unreal altogether.
Now something's linked to... I just want to make sure I'm not going to lose anything.
It's the PlayerUI Blueprint. That's OK. we don't mind losing a bit of that. because that's what we're working
on anyway. So I'm not going to save the PlayerUI Blueprint.
This is a bug in Unreal. it's known about. at the moment. and I did say you need to
restart the Editor. if you are going to be able to get that new enum state. So
back into the PlayerUI Blueprint! Let's see what we lost. in terms of the Graph.
All of it! [Laughs] OK. but at least
here. in this section we still now have
a four element enum. OK. so sorry
about the bug on Unreal's behalf. but that's what it is. you do need to restart to fix it. So I'm
going to get rid of that comment. Now notice. on Out Of Ammo. we can actually
directly set the color. so I'm going to set it to gray. Now I wonder if that would.
if it were a bit darker. I wonder if that would work on the others. Well I think it would. If we break this
link. then you'll see that locked is defaulting to black. I can go to the previous
green. select the hex color. put it in here.
And why am I doing this? Just because it's simpler. we're reducing the number of nodes. Break the Link.
get the hex color.
do that. final one.
get the hex color. and
off we go! Now I do want to thank the student that mentioned this. on the forum.
By the way. we can get rid of these nodes. I don't remember the students name. but we can always go and have a look!
No harm in seeing our community forums. so you can do
searches in here. I think it's "cleaner". I think that was a word that I remember in it.
Cleaner Color Selection Node. and yeah. Jonas_J! Thank you very much for showing that that's
possible. It shows that if you do contribute in the forum that I do listen and
build it into later videos. So there you go! We now have the colors
directly in there. much neater. much tidier. much happier Ben. hopefully
much happier students and that's that! Now. of course. it lost
all of our other stuff that we did. didn't it? So if we go to the Designer.
it lost all of this binding information. so let's just do that again. We recreate
the binding. we go get our Aiming Component Reference.
we drag off it. we go and Get the Rounds
Left. like so.
we turn it To a String. and sometimes you just have to
redo your work with a smile and not worry about it. Try not to swear. try not to
curse. try not to get into any sort of victim mentality about it. it happens to all of us. If you want to
use a powerful tool like this. that's cutting edge and constantly changing. we'll have some problems with it
sometimes. just deal with it. try not to get stressed. Just smile and carry
on. if you get stressed and angry about it. it's only you that it's going to effect at the end of the day.
You might want to report a bug. you might want to do something proactive. but
please don't fill yourself up with stress. Alright. so that's done! I've recreated
that. I've saved everything. Let's go back and see if it works! Three! Now I'm going to fire!
Three. OK good! So this is exactly what I
expect. is that it doesn't count down yet. Why not? Because when we fire.
in the TankAimingComponent. we need to say RoundsLeft
-- which is a shortcut for RoundsLeft. = RoundsLeft - 1.
Let's just check that that change worked. but I'm pretty confident it will do.
And while that compiles. as a check. let's think about when
we want to fire. Do we only want to be able to fire when reloading? Well let's look at the states.
Here they are! No we want to be able to fire
when we are aiming or locked. What we were saying is.
fire when we're not reloading. but now that means. fire when we're
Aiming. Locked. or OutOfAmmo. and we don't want to be able to fire when we're OutOfAmmo. we only want Aiming
and Locked. So I'm going to change the logic around completely. Did this compile? Yes!
I'm going to change the logic around completely to fire if the EFiringState
is Locked. for the AI Tanks. or
the EFiringState
is Aiming. so that we can fire
if we want to. before we get Locked. Does that make sense? So we can now
fire in Locked or Aiming. very explicit. it's positive rather than negative.
I prefer that. I'm just going to back indent there. So let's have a look!
We should now only be able to fire at the right time. basically.
Apart from. we never set the
OutOfAmmo state. did we?
We have this OutOfAmmo state. it never gets set. but when we'll be setting states. we're setting them
here. in the TickComponent. So it's all very well that we decrement.
right now. Three. two.
etc.. but we're going to go below 0 if we're not careful. So what we want to do is put another if
statement at the top. Now be careful. if you're putting another if at the top of an if. remember to put your
else first. Now we can come in and put the new condition.
if (RoundsLeft is less than or equal to 0... Why
less than or equal to? Just in case we ever ended up in negative rounds. how would we handle
the case of being negative rounds? Well we would still. if we had negative rounds.
be in FiringState of OutOfAmmo. for sure
right. You could just say equals and put an ensure statement up here.
to make sure you never to negative. but it's not that consequential if we go negative at the
moment. so this will do. OK cool! So every Tick.
we're setting OutOfAmmo. If we're not out of ammo. then we're Reloading. if we
have. you know. if it's been too little time since we last fire. If
we're not reloading and the barrel's moving. then we're Aiming. otherwise we're Locked.
So that's the logic of it. Let's see if this works! It should work
for both of us. is what I'm hoping now. because the architecture we have means
us and the AI tanks all have to follow the same rules. So if I Alt P
to play. when I'm here. in a nice full screen and I'm going to fire as I go down the hill.
I have two rounds. I have a red reticle. goes amber. I can
fire again. I have one round. it goes amber. I fire again. it
goes gray. I cannot fire anymore. That's good! Now let's
just check that the AI tanks also fun out of ammo and don't cause any problems.
and I think that they've both had all their rounds. Ah. so
I'm feeling very safe now. apart from I've flipped. I really need to
sort that issue out. I think that's a self collision issue. by the way. and we'll fix it shortly.
OK it seems to be working. it seems to be working absolutely fine! Maybe we have an
ensure that's gone off though. I did see... Yeah. we had a Projectile
Blueprint ensure fire off. I'm not sure why. in this case.
I don't see any reason why we would have had something
not be able to find a projectile. Let's just check the TankAiming
Component has it's projectile bluepri?nt. OK I'm going to put that down to a 1 off. but I'm going to keep an
eye on that. if that happens again. I don't see any fundamental reason
why that should have happened. OK fantastic. we now have much better aiming.
so I will see you in the next video!