So hey and welcome to Using the Reference Viewer! The purpose of this video actually is
to delete our starter content from our project altogether
and to bring the Starter Content folder out of the .gitignore,
so that we have all of our starter content type material
tracked by source control, when we do choose to use it. So we simply won't have start content at all
at the end, and everything in our content will be properly tracked by source control,
paving the way for us to use projectiles properly, being sure that we're
starting from the actual starter content without any modifications. So I'll see you in there!
So our mission here is to get rid of the Starter Content folder, because it's
not currently tracked under source control. Remember in our .gitignore we were
ingoring it, and therefore, any changes we make to it are not being tracked and that's dangerous.
I, in particular, have caused a problem, if I just show you. If
we look in the Starter Content and then we go to particles, this
P_Explosion that comes in the starter content, don't worry about how it works
for now. But I have edited it offline between videos, and I have
added an extra Smoke emitter and that's going to cause problems.
So that's symptomatic of an overall issue that we're not tracking changes in starter
content. Now we've chosen not to because starter content is large. If you have a
look at StarterContent's properties, you'll see that it's 600 megabytes.
We don't want to put all that under source control, especially as I if I use TreeSize.
You'll see that most of it is textures and most of these we never use. So the skill
I want to show you is using the Reference Viewer and using Unreal's Reference Checking
to work out how we can delete stuff and move stuff, without losing any
references, anything important. So let's see the process for
doing that. If we just try and... Firstly, let's backup this
StarterContent, before we do anything else. So I'd suggest you close Unreal, go to your
file system, go find your BattleTank folder, and go into
Content, StarterContent, right-click it, send it to a .zip file,
and pop it on your Desktop. I've already done that to save time. And just
take it completely out of the folder OK, and that way you've got a backup of your StarterContent, because
remember it's not being tracked under source control. That should make you a little bit nervous.
I'm going to close VisualStudio, because it's nothing to do with this video, and let's go back
into Unreal, which is somewhere around here.
Here we go! Perfect! So what I'm going to do is get you going on this, show you the
ideas, a couple of tips and tricks, and then, I'm going to leave it to you to go and manage, to delete your starter content
folder. So now that we have a backup, we can just try and delete it. Right-click on StarterContent,
in the Content browser, and Delete. It's not just going to delete it. I know that the
ceiling of the sky uses a cube and that the grass is painted on the
landscape and there's dirt on the hills, and you may have used other starter content stuff as
well, but this system will now go ahead and check for references and dependencies
and it'll warn us before it deletes anything, which is quite cool! There you go! So if
we start with this, Metal_Rust. I happen to know that that's used by this
Mortar. So this is the asset that's using the referenced assets,
and then, the referenced asset, in this case, is the rust. The flat land is going to be
using grass and gravel, and then, we've got glass on the ceiling
and we have a cube as well on that ceiling.
And then, I'm not seeing much else in the list. No I think that's it! Well we can get rid of the glass
and the cube very easily, because that is all about this sky
glass here. We don't need that. If I just delete that from the scene completely,
then we should have solved at least those reference issues. Let's go ahead and
rerun the delete. Before you rerun the delete, you want to be saving everything, just
to make sure that it's caught up with you. So go ahead and rerun the delete, and this time it
should find less things that are dependent on the StarterContent
folder, that's what it's looking for. It's ignoring self references within the Starter
Content Folder. For instance, if a particle system requires a texture
and they're both in the StarterContent. That won't be reported here, that's a good thing, that keeps it simple
for us. OK, so what do we have now? We have
Rust, Grass, and Gravel, it seems like they're the only things. Yeah!
And between them, they're used on the Mortar, the FlatLand, and the BattleGround.
Let's start with the Mortar, and I'll leave you to do the landscape texture
or the landscape or roughness thing and then the BattleGround itself. The general
principle is this, let's look at the Rust, for a start!
Let's find "rust" within the StarterContent. M_Metal_Rust, there it is! If you
right-click it and say Reference Viewer, it will show you
not only what depends on rust, so the Mortar and the Starter map, don't
care about the Starter map, but the Mortar depends on Rust. And then Rust, what does that
depend on? All these things on the right here, there's up to 15 it's rendering, you can choose that here.
So the Rust itself depends on all
these things. Some of these are in the starter content. These three, the MacroVariation,
which makes the rust look different over a larger scale, the color of the rust itself, and then, the normal
map, which gives it bumpiness, are all in the StarterContent. So
if you want to get all of these out, as well as the asset itself, you right-click and say Find
in Content Browser. And you go back to your Content Browser and it will have highlighted
these textures that Rust depends on. Now you can move those
into the Mortar folder. We'd also better move Rust
itself. Where is Rust itself? It seems not to be here, but that's probably because I'm looking in the
wrong folder. There you go, Rust is in the Materials folder. Let's move over to the
Mortar, too. Great! Now if we go back to the
Starter Content and look for Rust, it seems to have all gone, which is good news! It's all inside
the Mortar folder, along with all the other bits. OK, so if we do a Save
All, and then, we go ahead and
try and delete the StarterContent, we should be working through the list now and
getting rid of things that depend on starter content. Ultimately, as I said, what we'll do once we've
managed to get rid of starter content is remove it from source control and live a happy life, with
everything in our project properly tracked, apart from all the derived files, of course.
So let's just let this search finish, and then I'll throw you into a challenge!
So what have we got? We've just got Grass and Gravel
now. The Mortar still seems to be dependent upon something.
Could it be this reference further down the list? Let's have a look! Metal_Rust!
OK, let's just deal with these object redirectors. So there is
one more thing left. Let me show you what happened. When we
moved the Rust material, from the StarterContent's
Materials folder into the Mortar, this guy here, look what it did. You can't
see it unless you go to Filters, Other Filters,
and then show Redirectors,
they're like aliases. If you do that you'll find, through a search maybe
use this, that we have a Rust Redirector in the Materials folder.
And that was just Unreal's way of making sure that there's a bridge, over to the Rust's
new location, in case it's needed, but we're trying to get rid of the StarterContent
folder. So we can get rid of that redirector like this, right-click the Materials folder and Fix
Up Redirectors. It says that it "Finds references to all redirectors in the selected
folders and resaves them if possible", and "deletes any redirectors
that had all their references fixed." Perfect, so we do that! Now,
there are not redirectors, which means that if we now try and delete
starter content... This is a pretty common gotcha, that there redirectors
can confuse you, and you may not be able to see the redirectors, but remember you turn on the Filters,
Other, Show Redirectors, and then, you get to see those aliases.
Now we're going to do a search again, and we should
only have two assets that depend on anything in there, those two. And it's the Grass and
Gravel and anything that the Grass and Gravel require that we need to
move out now. And guess what, who's going to do that? You are! So make sure
you've backed up your folder as a .zip file, try deleting your starter content, move all referenced
assets out or delete relevant objects, and then eventually delete the Starter
Content folder, close and reopen the Editor, and test everything works,
and then, when you've done that, share your nice new tidy folder structure, as an image
or some other how, in our discussions over on the community site and I'll see you in a minute.
OK welcome back! So I am going to just observe this. I think it's Grass and Gravel
are the only things left, so I'm going to go and find Grass and Gravel
inside the StarterContent. Let's start with the Grass! M
_Ground_Grass. There are actually three things. Now the
Ground_Grass is the thing in question, I think, or was it the texture?
Hmm, good question, I will just go back and have a look. I don't remember
which type of grass it was. If these searches take a long time, you could
always use something like SnagIt, a screen capture tool, to grab
the result of the search, and then, go in one big pass through, deal with everything
and then only run the search infrequently, because it's quite a slow dependency search.
So I could come here with SnagIt, I have a keyboard shortcut for that.
And have I got SnagIt open somewhere? I should have.
And I can come and snapshot that, and then I can see exactly that it's T_Ground
_Gras and T_Ground_Gravel, it's the textures. So we start
from T_Ground_Grass. We look at the Reference Viewer for that and we see
what it depends on. Well ostensibly it doesn't depend on anything. That's interesting!
So I should...
T_Ground_Grass_D, I'm not trusting that entirely. What are the references
for the others? Grass, yeah Grass depends on all
this stuff, you see, in the StarterContent. If you're going to use
Grass, which we have been doing as a material on our
landscape we're going to need to take all this stuff with it, the Perlin_Noise, the MacroVariation, and all that.
So again, we can find it in the Content Browser, move all this stuff into the BattleGround
folder, and then, I'm going to go back to my
screenshot, if I can find it in here, and see what else we had. We also had
the Gravel, so I'm going to look for Gravel.
T_Ground_Gravel, I'm going to look at its references.
Let's try the other one.
Yeah, I think most of them have gone across, so I just
need to move both bits that relate to the Gravel into
the BattleGround folder. And that should be
pretty much it! Let's go ahead and save everything, rerun the deletion
script, and see if we've got all
our dependencies out of the StarterContent folder. It'll be a big sigh of relief when we have, we can
finally finally get rid of it, close Unreal, remove it from source control,
and we'll be happy happy bunnies in the safety of no more mess-ups, due to changes
in starter content. So we still have some things,
both on the FlatLand asset. What have we got? T_Ground_Gravel_D. OK, it's just object
redirectors. All of these problems now are redirectors, so we can right-
click, fix up redirectors in folder. I think that will do it recursively,
through the subfolders, I think I saw it do it just then. So now, if I delete the
starter content, finally with the redirectors gone, we should be in a
position where we have not starter content and all of our stuff is nicely
put away with the assets that need them, like the Rust with the Mortar,
etc. Now you may want to separate your assets out differently, as your project gets bigger,
but this is a great start! Yeah, this is the thing we want to get to, Pending Deleted
Assets. So let's delete all that! So I'm loading
everything, deleting it, and no more folder that's
talking about starter content. Great! I'm going to get rid of this filter. I'm going
to do what I suggested you do, which is close and then reopen the Editor.
Then, I've got a tiny bit of source control work to do and then we are done!
So I reopen the Editor. Now has starter content come back? It has!
So what i'm going to do is, just close the Editor, go to Content, and delete off the disk
the StarterContent folder, and then, reload Unreal.
You need to do that with Unreal closed,
and there, it is no longer there. It's all very well it no longer being there. Don't
celebrate yet, make sure that your game runs. [Laughs] I deleted a folder! Oh, I broke my game!
Not so clever. So everything appears to be OK, and we've done it quite
carefully. That's good news! So close Unreal, close VisualStudio.
Let's open up our .gitignore file. Now there are two .gitignore files in my project,
anyway one's at the root here of the project, and that has in it
a couple of things, it has BattleTank.VC.VC.opendb and
the .vs folder, so let's keep that on the left. And if I go
into BattleTank, I've got another .gitignore, which is the one we're going to keep, which has all this stuff in it.
But it doesn't have the BattleTank.VC.VC.opendb, so I'm going to move that
into there, and I'm going to move the .vs/, so we ignore
everything in the hidden .vs folder, like that. I'm going to save this
.gitignore on the right, so I've just added those things. I'm also going to get rid of the
StarterContent removal at the bottom. So what we're doing in our main
.gitignore is, we're consolidating two .gitignore files together, and we are
making it start tracking starter content and we're putting these things in,
so that we can delete this other .gitignore. Let's just
save it all, and I'll show you the changes, because .gitignores themselves, of course, are subject
to version control. Let's have a look at what the changes are, after I stage all this.
The following things are 10
megabytes or larger. That's OK I'm going to live with that, I don't think they're too huge.
I'm going to stage the .gitignore, and then, you can see the changes I made to the
.gitignore. The one in
the BattleTank folder has just had these two things added to it
and the StarterContent taken out, and the .gitignore, that's in the top level here, I'm going to
delete because I don't need it. I only want one .gitignore. Some instances you
want more than one, in this case I don't. So when this catch's up, it should notice that I
deleted the other .gitignore. There it is! Stage that deletion and we're good to
go! So we've deleted a .gitignore, moved a bunch of assets. They look like pluses
in here, because they've come under folders that are now tracked by source control.
We've modified that main .gitignore and we are in a good
position here. So let's go ahead, commit our work, and carry on with
starter content properly tracked under source control!