So welcome to Introducing Particles
Systems! In this video we are actually going to get as far as this,
which is that we can get our tank, we can fire, and look it leaves
smoke and everything. How cool is that! See you in there!
OK guys, so we want to make a particle system. Now that we don't have
the starter content imported, let me show you a neat trick for getting
starter content across, without bringing all of it across. So go
ahead into the EPIC Games Launcher or just to
your BattleGround project and make a
new project. We're going to make a whole new Blank Unreal project With Starter Content.
I'm just going to call the project StarterContent,
and the idea is that once we have an empty StarterContent
project, which you can see forming itself here in the Editor... By the way, with the Settings
I used it doesn't need to be a C++ project, it just needs to be Blank project With Starter Content,
that's all it needs to be. Now, when it opens, if you've got a VR device, it's
going to start trying to open all your VR devices, which is going to be a hassle.
So just go to your Plugins, turn off all or any plugins that relate to
VR, that are causing those things to start when you start the project
and just restart it. Then, you can close your Oculus and
your vive and whatever else your lucky enough to have. I have to have those for work, of course.
Aren't I hard cut done by? So here we go, we have a Starter Content
project. Now what we can do in here is, we can go around, son't change anything in here
because that is just a bit of a, you know... ?Well to be honest
you could enforce that you can't change anything in here, by making
this particular Starter Content folder read only. Let's go ahead and
do that, actually. So if you go as far as there, we can go and find
in Explorer the Starter Content folder, maybe go up one.
What I'm going to do is right-click it, go to Properties, and just make all of
it Read Only, turn it into a tick, including the sub-folders.
And now, what that means is that if I'm in the Starter Content project, absent mindedly, and I
go and try and change something like this Explosion, some parameter on here, it doesn't matter
what these things are at the moment, then it won't let me save it. If you get this box
it's because it won't let you save, because the file is not writable
OK, and you can't even make it writable because it's made
non-writable by the operating system. OK but what we can do in this
project is browse things, and go, OK well maybe this is good for the muzzle flash, it's
a good starting point for the muzzle flash. So let's
move this into our project! So let's see how to do that! You right-click it,
Asset Actions, and Migrate. So in your Starter
Conent project, if you made one, if you haven't take a breath for a moment to go off and
make yourself a Starter Content project, it's a useful tool to have. Then,
go find the particle system you want, which we're going to be using P_Explosion, right-
click it, Asset Actions, Migrate. Then, it'll say well
do you want to save what you change? Well no, because we don't want to save what we change, we want the one from
the starter pack. It then tells you all the stuff that it's going to bring with it, all these textures and
materials. You just say OK. Then, the first time it's a little laborious,
because you have to drill through and find where you want to put it. So in my case, it's Documents,
repos, Unreal, BattleTank, BattleTank,
and it's the Content folder you want to point it to, of your project OK,
it's important! Once you've found that project and you say OK, it does a very quick migration.
Then, close the StarterContent folder, you don't need to save anything.
The whole project even, close the whole project. It didn't matter whether you have your Battle Tank project
open or not, at that time, it will work, but don't have two Unreal projects open at the same
time, because you'll probably find yourself doing things in one project, when you're meant to be doing
them in another. OK. So now, look what we've got over here! We
have StarterContent back! Why? Haven't I gone around in circles? Well I have
and if we look at source control it should have picked up the fact that we've added StarterContent but there's
not much, there's only a little handful of things in here now, OK,
and that's the key, is that we've only got what we need for this P_Explosion
particle effect. Now in terms of how you want to organize your assets,
you could move the Explosion into the Projectile, if you want to.
I'm even going to rename it, I'm just going to hit F2 to rename that, and I'm
going to call it whatever we called it in the code, actually. I think we called it Launch
Blast? Yeah, I won't look it up, I'm pretty sure it was LaunchBlast.
LaunchBlast, there you go! So now I have a particle effect, in Projectile,
called LaunchBlast, and it's dependencies are sitting in the StarterContent folder.
Now it's entirely up to you if you want to move these textures and materials into the
Projectile, to have all of the Projectile assets together. There are so many of them, I'm not going to
bother. I'm going to allow myself to have a thin, very minimal, source
control tracked StarterContent folder now OK, because that's
how things end up by default, and if we import other assets they might want to reference these
as well. But I will move the actual MuzzleBlast into the Projectile, just to say to me, well
these are the things that constitute the Projectile. If I want to see the dependencies of
the MuzzleBlast, I can always go to the Reference Viewer and see what else it needs. Cool!
So let's finally get in and actually modify
this and look at and understand this particle effect! You want to make sure that you can
change things, that you can click Save in here, in the beginning, and that it hasn't brought over any read only
properties. It hasn't! Now I'm going to talk you through the overview of
how this particle system thing works! So you have a Viewport, if you don't have any other windows,
I mentioned, just click the Window menu and bring them up. That is showing you a
simulation of how this particle effect is going to look. If you don't like the background color, you
click in the Viewport, in the toolbar click Background Color, and then, maybe
turn it into something like a light sky, because that's what we're go?ing to be seeing it against, mainly.
There you go, so I've changed the background color! The rest of this stuff in this toolbar,
well we're not going to use that often, possibly Restart Sim just to go back to the beginning of the
Simulation, in a longer simulation a longer effect, but otherwise, I'm not going to be using
that toolbar much. Let's hide the tab. Viewport, what else can we do in
Viewport? Well a whole bunch of stuff on the left, under View, we're not going to use at the moment, but time
can be handy. You can slow this thing down to 10%, click Restart, and then, you
can really carefully look at say the beginning of the simulation. So that's what you
can do under Time. I'm going to leave mine at 100%. Then, let's move right. We have
Emitters. Now what's Emitters all about? Well this effect is built up from
a whole bunch of things. You can turn them on and off with the ticks, so if you just
wanted to turn off say the Shockwave, then you'd turn that off
and then you get the same effect without the Shockwave. If you want to look at the Shockwave only,
you hit S for Solo, and it turns everything else off, apart from the Shockwave.
You can also add the fireball. You can have Solo, S for single, but you can
have many singles. So why would you have both the ability to have many singles and
checkboxes? Well imagine you had 30 emitters and you wanted to see only 2 of them,
you would do that just by going click click, and you don't have to un-tick 28 things off to the
right. Imagine, on the other hand, you wanted to see 29 of the
30, of course, the way to do that would just be to unselect the one you don't want. So that gives you quite
a lot of flexibility. So the other thing we have here in the middle is a button, which changes the
render mode, the Emitter Render Mode, for how it displays for
debugging. But let's not worry about that one for now, we leave that on what looks like some 10 pin bowling, although it looks less
than 10, it's 6 pin bowling [Laughs], and if you click it you can see down here in details
what the render mode is. But let's not worry about that for now, we just don't need it.
So Details, what does that tell you? Well it depends on what you're selected on. Each Emitter will
have a different set of details. When you click in the actual top of it it'll go orange,
and if you click down into these, what we call modules like Required, Spawn,
Lifetime, Initial Size, each of those will have a bunch of properties, as well.
They all have a Required, that tells you what material it's using if any. For example,
Smoke is created by using a material that is
spawned into the world many times and it's a transparent material, and it tells you
where it's being emitted from and how it's aligned to this camera
or not. Basically, these things generally are pointing straight to the camera, they're little pieces of
transparent cellophane or cardboard, if you like, in real terms. They're just
tranSparent textures that are rendered facing the camera and they give these effects.
You can also choose whether this stuff happens in local or global space, that will become important
in a moment. All of these effects I think, I haven't looked through them all, are in
local space, as you click through the Required
section. The Sparks aren't actually, so the Sparks are staying in the world. As you click on this Required
module, everything but the Sparks and the Shockwave
are in local space, so they'll go with the projectile. Let's
see that! If we watch carefully as we fire it... Ah, well
actually [Laughs] we're missing a trick here, you need to go to your Projectile blueprint.
You need to make the Full Blueprint Editor on your LaunchBlast.
Of course, we need to choose the particle system under the Details tab, under the
Particles, Template, which is the LaunchBlast. Compile that!
Now let's take a look at the particle system. F11 for full screen,
and then, let's take a look at it coming out. OK, so you can actually just
see, if you're sharp, that the particles, the sparks,
stay where they are in the world and everything else like
the smoke goes along with the actual
cannon ball or with the projectile, OK. So that's the difference between world
space and local space. There's smoke coming out of the projectile in the world. Look we could fire it,
hit F8, and then... Probably easier with our thing up.
Let's just fire once more. Possess, fire, F8, Pause.
Now we could go to that projectile in the world space.
But what we want to happen in the projectile is, we want it to be leaving smoke
behind it, so how are we going to do that? Well the final thing we need to
look at is this Curve Editor. I want you to remove all curves, that won't change the
behavior of the particle effect, try it! Right-click inside one of these curves,
down here, Remove All Curves, and it just means it's plotting nothing but the
particle effect has been unaffected by that. So this Smoke
Emitter here has a Lifetime property or module
on it. You can add new modules by right-clicking up here and then
adding these modules. There's tons of an amazing amount of stuff you can with particle systems!
If you click the little Plot icon, next to Lifetime, it will plot it down here.
You can click Fit to fit it to the graph, and you can use the mouse wheel to
go in and out. What's this red and green dot. Well firstly, you can turn that
lifetime plot on and off. You may have several different factors that you've added with a little yellow
dot here, and then, the green and red correspond to something. In this
case, what do they correspond to? Well look in the Details tab. We have a
Uniform Distribution, which means that this smoke will last somewhere
between 2 and 3 seconds. You can change that by dragging
the 3 up or dragging this up here to say 9 seconds.
And now what that means, if we watch this carefully, is that the smoke part of
this will now last somewhere between 3 and 9 seconds, different
every time OK. Or 2 and 9 seconds rather. I'm going to reset
that to 2 to 3, but that gives some variability. So the general
deal with particle systems, have a look on Wikipedia, "wiki particle
systems". Just have a look at that, it gives you a pretty good
overview of what they're like. It talks about the fuzzy phenomenon and the spawning
of things and the fact that you normally are using a
variable amount of time that things last for, etc.
Have a look at that, I'll put that in the resources of this lecture for you OK.
So what we're going to do to leave a smoke trail is, I'm going to start
with the same smoke. So right-click on your Smoke and Duplicate the Emitter.
Now you've got two called Smoke, so let's right-click. I'm going to choose the right-hand one.
They're the same so it doesn't matter. Rename it to Smoke Trail.
So now we've got a Smoke Trail to work on. Now the thing that's going to make
it different, firstly, is click the Required module of the Smoke Trail,
go into the Details tab, and then, go to where it talks about Using
Local Space. No, let's go World Space! So let's see the effect of that. We've
turned off Local Space on the Smoke Trail. Play the game, we fire.
What do we get? Well we get smoke that's staying attached to the projectile, but we also get
smoke that stays just outside the barrel but we only get one lump of smoke. What
we want is for that projectile to be continuously emitting smoke.
So how do you do that? Well you go to the Spawn module there.
Under Spawn you go and look, and we're going to make a Constant Spawn
Rate, and we're going to have it or we could have a range if you want it, it doesn't really matter. I'm going to
go with Constant and let's just try spawning at say 30,
30 per second OK. so put a Spawn Rate against the Smoke
Trail emitter of 30 per second. Save that, maximize
your screen, fire. Ah look at that, that's looking better! It's
lifetime's too short, because the smoke is, I would say, running out too early, so I'm just
going to fix that, and then, I'm going to challenge you to go ahead and make things how you want them. So click
on Lifetime. We've got somewhere between 2 and 3 seconds, let's just make it a constant
30 seconds. Then, in code, we can disable this once
it hits something. So I've made the Lifetime 30 seconds.
Let's have a look! Ah, it looks pretty
cool, apart from the color has gone a bit funny now.
So that's probably because we have a Color Over Lifetime.
If you have a look here, we have Color Over Lifetime,
and you can plot that by clicking the little graph. It will bring the curves down here. If you've got curves you
don't want, Remove All Curves. Never any harm in doing that, it doesn't change the properties a
bit. And if you click Color Over Lifetime, which is the one we're interested in, you can turn off Alpha
Over Lifetime with that yellow dot. And if we just plot Color Over Lifetime, you
can see the red, green, and blue. How do I know that's what it is? Well just
from experience but you could also come in here and look, and if you drill down
far enough, eventually you will see what these things
actually mean, In Values, Out Values, etc. And
you can see what effect this Color Over Lifetime is going to have. I want
it to, if anything, not change very much over its life, so I'm just going to reduce that
change. Oh, OK
so I think what we've got here is we've got... I don't even need, I don't think, Color Over Lifetime.
Let's just turn it off, you can temporarily turn it off there.
That's fine! But now it doesn't have a color, so we need
to maybe make it a constant Color Over Lifetime.
So simplify the Color Over Lifetime massively,
make it just a constant black. Let's try that!
That's better but it's taking a while to
grow, it's growing too slowly. So that's the size over
lifetime. So if I Remove All the Curves, Plot size over lifetime,
have a look at that, I could fit it, and the problem I'm finding is that it's not
growing fast enough, so I just drag that to the left. And hopefully
you get the idea. Let's have a look! So it's black constant...
[Strange Cannon Noise] No something's still... Ah, you know what it probably is, it's probably Transparency
Over Lifetime! So if we Plot Color Over Life, one of the things we'll
end up with, if we turn the others off, is Alpha Over Life. Let's plot that! And indeed,
Alpha Over Life is taking a while to go up,
and actually, we don't even want it changing like that. We probably just want a Constant
Alpha Over Life. And let's just try fully opaque, see
how that looks. That looks better to me! OK
there's a thousand handles you can pull here, but to be honest, that's good enough.
It's fine that the thing stopped smoking. What I want you to do now is, I want you to go ahead
and setup and share your smoke. Tweak the parameters to your taste.
Get creative with the color, the size etc. Don't worry about it disappearing from the
side view, let me just show you that. If we look at the smoke
trail, from a sufficiently wide camera view, it will just disappear. You see how it
disappears there, we'll sort that out in the next lecture. That is a known problem, don't try and
fix or fix it if you want, but I'm going to tell you, in the next lecture, how to fix it.
And then, share with the community, there's a link in the resources to our community site,
your smoke effect. I'd love to see it! Get a bit creative with color size, etc., and have
fun! Nothing else to do in this video, so the video will end now. And I'll see you in the
next one, where we'll sort out the camera issue! But please, make your smoke cool, then share it with
the community!