So welcome to Particle Bounding
Boxes! What we're going to be doing, in this video, is getting rid of the horrible problem where our smoke
trails disappear, when you look at them at a sideways angle, and make sure that they
show all the way around like this. So let's go and see how that's done!
So this should be a relatively simple and short video. What we're going to be
doing is, looking at the fact that it if you fire a lot of these smoke
effects into the scene and then rotate your camera watch what happens. You see them disappearing. They're
still there in the world, but as I rotate the camera, at about 45
degrees off the camera, they disappear. That's not much fun, that looks kind of
silly, so what are we going to do about that. Well firstly, what's the root cause of it? Let's
go into the Tank Particle System, for a start.
I'm sorry, the Projectile Particle System, the Launch Blast Particle
System. Let's go into that! And if you scroll your Emitters
across and then click in the black space, just to make sure we're on the properties of
the Particle System itself, not any of the particular emitters.
If you scroll down here, I'll give a bit more space. Then one of the things you'll
see is that under the Bounds section, Use Fixed Relative Bounding, and in
fact, you can visualize these bounds, this zone in which the
particle systems are displayed, by clicking on this Bounds button
here. And you can even click the down arrow and say, Set Fixed
Bounds and that will show you, if you've got the bounds on, the zone in
which, provided that both the camera and the particle system are in that area,
then they will render. And if you see here, it actually
tells you the values. The problem is that, in our game, when we start moving the camera off
to the side, like this, we are getting outside of these bounding
boxes. Now it's not entirely intuitive how that's happening, it does look more
like it's a problem to do with billboarding, i.e. to do with these textures
facing the camera, but it isn't that, that's what I call a red herring. It is just
about the bounding box sizes. What it turns out we need, because we have a particle system
that spans a very large scale in our game, because
the same particle system is leaving smoke over a very long distance in the game.
In those circumstance and in those circumstances only, you don't want to Use
Fixed Bounding Boxes, you want to turn that setting off. And what
that will do is, it will recalculate the bounding boxes every frame. Now that will have a performance
hit, it may or may not be noticeable in your system. We'll test that in a minute, in fact, it's going to be
part of your challenge. But if you turn off this Use Fixed Relative Bounding Boxes,
it's going to, as I say, calculate the visibility requirements every
single frame. Now, It's going to warn you that you have a particle system
with no bounding box and it contains a GPU Emitter. What's a GPU Emitter?
The Sparks are the GPU Emitter, they're very subtle, they'er hardly
any part of the effect, and we can actually just remove that altogether. You
can see that it's a GPU Emitter, because it says GPU Sprites here. What that is,
by the way, is if you right-click in the Emitter it's the TypeData is of
type ?GPU Sprites, and this means that this particular effect is
rendered on the GPU and it's rendered on the GPU using an optimization based
on scene depth, because GPU's basically can only do things
in parallel. And one way to make these types of GPU
sprites very fast is to allow the GPU to do it, and different calls
on the GPU can do different parts of the scene but it can only do that if it's all based on scene
depth and that messes up when we start coming to this wide angle. You can see it's already
fixed, because I've toggled that setting, I can go all the way around now. So
what we're not allowed to do is have variable bounding boxes and a GPU emitter, but we don't
need the Sparks, so I'm going to go ahead and just delete the emitter altogether.
So right-click on your Sparks, delete it altogether. It'll hardly make any difference to the
visual appearance of your smoke trails, but it will stop
the warning and make sure we don't get serious performance glitches. So there it is,
that is the problem solved! So what I want you to do is, remember that you can go to Show
FPS here, from this down arrow at the top-left of your viewport,
and I want you to do the following. I want you to go ahead and test your performance impact. Measure your
Frames Per Second, with 20 smoke trails visible.
Turn on dynamic bounding boxes, like I just did. Measure again, see
if there's a change in the FPS, and share your results with the community. If you don't get any change and
you don't get anything interesting at 20 smoke trails, then maybe turn it up to 100 if you
can click that fast, 100 rounds in the tank. And just see if you can detect
how much difference it's making on your system, and then, share with us over on the community site, community.gamedev.tv,
what sort of impact this is having, this change in settings, on your
machine. I'll be very interested to see!
OK welcome back! So there is a small
resolution to this challenge. I'm just going to turn on my FPS. I am going to
do what I suggested you do, which is you go down... In fact, I'm going to collapse these other guys down.
So I can quickly get to this, I'm going to Use a Fixed Bounding Box, which should be of higher performance,
because it does not need to recalculate anything every frame. I'm going to fire off 20
of these guys, make sure they're all on the screen, and I'm just capped at 120
frames a second. So I'm on a, what am I on? An Intel i7
4 gigahertz quad core, with a GTX 980 (Graphics Card). So that's
the performance benchmark there. I'm going to suggest
that it's capped at 120 frames per second, therefore I'm not going to see any
change. So I'm going to need more projectiles, I'm going to go to 200 projectiles, and
I'm even going to turn down my minimum reload time.
I'm not even sure I can click a mouse that fast, but it'll allow me to launch these really fast. But let's put a
lot of these guys in the scene, see if I can get the frame rate to drop.
It's pretty stubbornly sitting there at 120. You don't want to go too fast, sideways
with the camera, because then they're not rendering, but it isn't effecting my frame rates.
On my system the answer here is that it doesn't [Laughs] really make any difference how many of these
things are on the screen, it's not dropping the frame rate.
So now let's try going into using dynamic bounding boxes with
that many particles. Let's see if we now get a drop in frame rate! I'll even up the screen
resolution, by going to full screen. No, you see, even with these
dynamic bounding boxes, provided I don't accidentally click on Explorer, I've got full
three dimensional view of these things, and yet I'm still...
I know as long as I keep my mouse in the game window, I'm still not getting a drop in frame rate.
So on my system, anyway, it makes absolutely no difference, which is a very
cursory proof to me that that's absolutely fine to be using in this game.
In this instance, we can use dynamic bounding boxes and still tolerate the performance hit that we're
getting. So I'll be interested to see how it works for you! That's all I've really got to say on this
video. That is a solution to a common problem. I have also in your slides...
By the way, I've given you a slide that shows you how to do this, it's on the next slide there.
It says, click here to make sure that you are in the general particle system properties. Go down
to Bounds and click that. OK fantastic! Well done and I'll see you in the next video!