So welcome to the strangely named Using FAttachmentTransform
Rules! It sounds boring. it's called that just because it comes up well on Google search
for our sales page. but what we're doing is using a new API
and more importantly creating an impact blast! Look that. pretty cool! OK. see you in the video!
So let's work on this impact blast then! I'm going to use the same
particle effect as the launch blast. so I'm just going to duplicate it and just
call it ImpactBlast. It's going to be very
similar to that. Of course. all the dependencies of the ImpactBlast will
already be here. because it has the same dependencies
as the LaunchBlast. So if I save that ImpactBlast
and go into it. it should work. we should have no problems with it. And if we look at the Reference
Viewer now. after having saved it. you'll see it's picked up all of these
references. so we're reusing these things. which is good. OK cool!
So ImpactBlast. what's that going to look like then. Well. It's up to you to customize
it how you want. I'm not going to go through that too much. but before we do that.
let's just get it working from a coding point of view. so we can see it in situation.
rather than in isolation. So what do we want? We want on our Projectile
a new type of component. called an Impact
Blast. and that's almost identical to the LaunchBlast. so I'm not going to insult you by asking you to do it.
It's so much like the LaunchBlast that we literally copy this stuff.
Call it ImpactBlast in two different places.
actually over here as well. ImpactBlast
for the name. and of course. we
need to declare ImpactBlast. which I'll go and do in the header file right now. It's going to be
just like a LaunchBlast. same details so it's literally really
simple. The only difference is with the ImpactBlast. of course. is that we don't
want it to be activated at the start. So with the LaunchBlast we
have not said AutoActivate is false. so it is activated by default and that's
right. because we spawn the projectile into the world and it starts off with that particle effect.
But what we're going to want with the Impact
Blast is. we want it to be AutoActivate false. we don't want it to be
activated at the start. Alright. the other thing about this class here is
that we say a PrimaryActorTick.bCanEverTick = true. The projectile actually
doesn't need to tick. so we can say false here. because if you look
down you'll see that we don't use the Tick here at all. I'll leave the BeginPlay() in case we
need it but that's it. By the way. while we're talking about Auto Activate. you see that the Projectile
Movement does not activate. that's correct as well; we don't want the projectile to
move until we actually call the LaunchProjectile() method.
OK. so that's all working fine! Let me go ahead
and make sure that ImpactBlast is in the header file. because it's not saying that it is.
and of course. it isn't because I just copied.
OK. so ImpactBlast goes there. these lines get copied. Launch
Blast changed for ImpactBlast. and we make it non-auto-activating.
Let's go ahead. see if that compiles. and when it does compile or if it does
compile. what we should see is. of course. inside the
Projectile Blueprint. we should see on the left-hand side a LaunchBlast and
a ImpactBlast next to each other. Also. we want to be attaching to (Root Component). Yeah
we did that by default. because I just copied. I said let's have the same paradigm
as the launch blast. so copying code. So what have I done. I done a boo boo somewhere?
"The function is deprecated. use AttachToComponent instead".
"update your code". OK. on Projectile line (19) it
doesn't like AttachTo(RootComponent) and AttachToComponent.
It's funny that it didn't complain about that before. they're just warnings here.
and then. we have a linker error. OK so what's
happening here is quite interesting. We would have had these warnings before. but we weren't looking
at them. OK. so I'm not going to fix them. we'll come back to them. Let's just make
a note in the code that we need a TODO. "// TODO
update to Attach... Well "update
to new API". OK so we've actioned this. in that we've put a TODO.
but the thing is that the reason we have a failure of actual compilation
here is because we have unresolved externals. which always means that we have a mish
or nearly always means that we have a mismatch.
between the declaration of something in the header file and the implementation
in the other file; and what that is. actually. is
Tick. it's because I never took Tick out of the header file. So those
errors can be a little bit strange. Now let's go and compile again. because there's useful learning
in here. which is that when it compiles again. the compilation
will succeed. probably now hopefully. if I've done it right. The compilation
will succeed and we will miss those warnings. so I'm just going to make sure that you're
aware of how you can get to and check for those warnings. You see. compilation
successful. it hasn't told us anything's wrong here. but if we go to Window.
Developer Tools. and then. Message Log.
I think we should dock our message log here in future. because look. if we
come down here and have a look. we've got Compiler Log. Now let's read the Compiler Log.
There you go. the warning is there against the
Compile Log. and it's saying that we shouldn't use AttachTo. please use
AttachToComponent instead. OK well let's go and do that right away. but. the point here.
the general point is that a compilation succeeding does not mean there are no warnings. and warnings should still
be fixed. I'm just going to try changing to AttachTo
Component. like that. and we'll just check the. you know.
the documentation for AttachToComponent. at least the inline documentation here. I think
that's going to work OK. I won't remove the TODO till it's working. Let's try recompiling!
And this time. we'll keep an eye on the message log rather
than the output log. the Compiler Log here. And this will still tell us when
our... Here you go! It "does not take 1
arguments". OK. so you can't just do a straight transposition of one to the other. we actually
need to take a second to read that a lot more carefully and see what the
deal is. with regards to what it wants. So it wants a USceneComponent pointer
which I believe that the Root Component is. but it also wants an FAttachmentTransformRules.
So let's look at what this second parameter is. it wants an FAttachment
TransformRules. So it appears that this new AttachToComponent method just
wants us to be a little bit more explicit about how we attach. If you go to Google
and search for that. you'll have FAttachmentTransformRules. I've also
linked to this in the course resources. And what we're going to want to do
here is to provide a KeepRelativeTransform. What we're saying
there is that we want the ImpactBlast to go with the Projectile.
at least for now. We may decide to change that policy later. but that's where we're going to
start in both cases. So if we look... Sorry I'm flicking all over the
place. If we look at the documentation. it's just KeepRelativeTransform is
what we want OK. so it's a static. Alright. let's go ahead
and have a look at how that's going to work. So in the code we are simply going
to say FAttachmentTransformRules:: take the static off it. Keep
RelativeTransform and that should do it. Let's do that for both.
And by the same argument. I won't remove the TODO.
until it compiles without warnings. Let's go back and compile! So
from now on you've got this tool of the Message Log. an even better way to be compiling. because not only
do you catch errors but you catch warnings. Better than just looking at the
output log. OK the compile's complete. we've got no issues at all. If we want to look at our
Output Log. at the bottom. that's also pretty normal. So that's all good news!
Alright. let's give ourselves some more room. I will just show you the
code changes. I made a lot of changes in that lecture. just if this helps you. and then. we'll move onto the
next bit. So we stopped at ticking. and then we did this stuff that you
can see in here. We removed the Tick but the bulk of it is just this green
in there. OK. in the header file. we simply declared and removed the Tick function.
OK cool. so that's a recap of where we are! We are about
8 minutes into the video. so we've got time for some more. Great! So now
what we want to do is to actually customize this
ImpactBlast to be how we want it and to activate it when we
actually get a hit. So what I want you to do is revise a few lectures ago. I want you
register a component OnHit() event delegate. What a mouthful but we did
do it a few videos ago. Use the LaunchBlast arrow
Deactivate() method. in order to turn off
the LaunchBlast. the one that's leaving the smoke trail. when
the collider hits something. we turn off the LaunchBlast. Add an Impact
Blast particle effect to the projectile. We've already done most of that. we probably haven't
actually wired up. in the blueprint. the impact blast. We've done most of it.
Activate that on impact. and you activate it using a very similar line to the
LaunchBlast Deactivate(). I guess you could imagine what it is. And then. share your
explosion with the community and I'll see you in a minute!
OK welcome back! So the first thing. I don't think
we've done is gone into this ImpactBlast and actually assigned the Impact
Blast to the component. So that's done now. if we
compile and play that. well then it crashes! Let's just try again. No
I don't think there's any particular reason it would have crashed there. I don't think we've done any naughties.
not protecting components. Again. my general policy is if it crashes once.
don't worry. You might want to run the debugger now. in case it crashes a second time. I'm not going
to. I'm just going to reattach the ImpactBlast. compile that. and you see it's
absolutely fine. Let's just have a look! We have a LaunchBlast and an ImpactBlast
doing basically the same thing. so you can't really tell. It looks like we've just got two particle effects on top of
each other. It doesn't look a lot different. OK let's go to the code and think about
what we're going to do! Several videos ago we did an OnComponent  hit event.
so why don't we just go find that! "OnComponent
Hit. and we can go to the entire project and
go find that. OK. so what we needed to do in BeginPlay(). when we did this
on the TankTrack. is we needed to add a dynamic delegate.
So well that's the first thing I've found. let's do that on BeginPlay() of the Projectile.
Let's just model what we've done before. it worked before. let's do it again. OK let's keep going!
So OnComponentHit. OK so the next thing we need to know
is where the definition of the OnHitEvent is inside this TankTrack.
So there it is. OnHit. and it's got this massive signature.
so let's just go take it. I'm going to put.
after LaunchProjectile I'm going to put OnHit like that. put some
squigglies. and the only thing you need to be aware of. of course. is changing from your Projectile
to your TankTrack to your Projectile. OK let's keep going! If we've got a
none hit here in the TankTrack.cpp. then we must have some
declaration of that. so let's go see how we did that before. We made it a UFUNCTION().
and let's just copy that straight into the Projectile. Let's
think about the protection. It was private. so let's just try private again.
And there's no reason for it to be anything but private either. It's a method.
so I like it to go at the top. I don't know why. they just seem like they should go at the
top. it doesn't matter at all. OK so hopefully that's it! We just put an
OnHit here. we have defined it here. Well we're not doing
anything yet. I think what would probably make sense to do here is to go
to the LaunchBlast and deactivate it.
so... I gave you that in the slide. didn't I? I said
LaunchBlast Deactivate().
So we're going to do that OnHit. as an indication that we have hit
something. and let's see if that is working and if the collisions are actually happening.
Let's compile! Again. I don't know why I've gotten rid of my Message Log. so I'm going to bring
it back. dock it down here. and start looking
at the message log. The part of the Message Log you want is the Compile Log
there. you'll get nothing out of it until the compiler is finished. Ooh. " 'OnComponent
Hit' : undeclared identifier" on line (33).
And the problem here is that I'm trying to run OnComponentHit
or access OnComponentHit on a projectile. which
actually. if you think about it. is not a component at all. it is an
actor. So what we need to do is. we need to do the OnComponentHit. we need you to register
that against the CollisionMesh OnComponent
Hit. OK so that was the dark side of all that copying
was that. obviously. it didn't think about what we're doing with the On
ComponentHit. Because we're not a component. we need to get into the scope of the component we're talking about.
Let's see if that'll compile!
UTankTrack is not a class or namespace. And the other dark side. of course.
of the copying and pasting is I didn't change that UTankTrack to AProjectile there.
Now let's go ahead and compile again! So you can see that copying and pasting clearly saves you a load
of time but it also has. as I say. has a darker side. which is that you end up
bringing stuff in which can cause you some issues. So it's up to you how much copying and
pasting you do vs. writing original code. I thought I'd show you that approach. So
it's compiled which is great! Now let's just play the game! Not really necessarily going to be able to
see that that... Yes we can. we can see that that particle effect has stopped. You can particularly
see it. if you temporarily get rid of the impact blast. just
un-assign it. We can just clear that here.
Compile the blueprint. play the game. and then.
if we just go into the world with F8 and move over to the site
of these...
...these cannon ball things. You can see that there's no smoke coming out of them. they are deactivated now.
OK so that is what's going on! They are deactivated. those components
on them are deactivated. You could click into. of course. the actual thing. and
you could look and look at the LaunchBlast and then you could probably go into the Details
and even confirm that it's deactivated.
if it's exposed.
No it's not. whether it's actually activated
right now is not exposed as a parameter. but you can see it's not activated. So that
process of deactivating it on landing. deactivating the LaunchBlast
on landing has worked. and it will no longer emit a launch trail. So video's got
quite long. I think what we need to do is stop there. for the moment. and just
take track on how far we've got. What have you got? Add an ImpactBlast
to the projectile. activate it. No we can do that. we can activate
that ImpactBlast in the last couple of minutes. Let's just do that. So back to the Projectile Blueprint!
ImpactBlast. reassign the Particle System.
I'm just going to do something to the ParticleSystem that makes it super obvious.
like take the Initial Size of the FireBall. plot just
the Initial Size of the FireBall on the graph. Go and say.
what's the size range? I'm going to zoom right out and just make it much bigger.
like that.
Actually. it's going to be easier just to look and say. well these are uniform vectors they have
X. Y. Z. so let's just ramp up the maximum possible
size and the minimum possible size in X.
Y. and Z. It can be asymmetric for now. And what that should do is. when
we get an impact blast... Whoah there it is! So. we're starting with the
ImpactBlast activated. we don't want that. we want to make sure that AutoActivate
is turned off. Now. you go to
the Projectile. ImpactBlast.
we then search for "auto" activate and it's on. It wants to be off.
And it should have been made the default of in the C++. I thought
we did that. so let's go and have a look. where we add the ImpactBlast.
AutoActivate = false. Ahh look. I've copied again!
Wow! I am doing lost of copy and paste boo boos right now!
That is why the ImpactBlast did not AutoActivate false!
So let's just recompile. Now. when you do this recompilation. the
setting that you have against this ImpactBlast component. the fact I've said
not AutoActivate in Blueprint is still overriding what's happening in the C++.
It's just that the little arrow will go away. because it's now at the new
default value. So let's just watch this. see what happens!
It's nearly there. what we haven't done is reactivated this on
impact. So where we see our OnHit we inactivate the LaunchBlast
and we Activate()
the ImpactBlast. Let's compile that!
And it's pretty simple and meaningful. all of this. I like it. I like the way the code's coming together.
So a few little mistakes and hiccups for me. in this video. but again I'm leaving
those in. because my general feedback from you guys is that's better. it's more realistic. it's
more live and uncut. It's more like the journey you guys are probably having.
so hopefully you like that. Boom! Look at that! That's enough for this
video! Congratulations! I want you to snapshot your beautiful impacts and things
and share them in the community! And I'll see you in the next video!
=======
So welcome to the strangely named Using FAttachmentTransform
Rules! It sounds boring, it's called that just because it comes up well on Google search
for our sales page, but what we're doing is using a new API
and more importantly creating an impact blast! Look that, pretty cool! OK, see you in the video!
So let's work on this impact blast then! I'm going to use the same
particle effect as the launch blast, so I'm just going to duplicate it and just
call it ImpactBlast. It's going to be very
similar to that. Of course, all the dependencies of the ImpactBlast will
already be here, because it has the same dependencies
as the LaunchBlast. So if I save that ImpactBlast
and go into it, it should work, we should have no problems with it. And if we look at the Reference
Viewer now, after having saved it, you'll see it's picked up all of these
references, so we're reusing these things, which is good. OK cool!
So ImpactBlast, what's that going to look like then. Well, It's up to you to customize
it how you want, I'm not going to go through that too much, but before we do that,
let's just get it working from a coding point of view, so we can see it in situation,
rather than in isolation. So what do we want? We want on our Projectile
a new type of component, called an Impact
Blast, and that's almost identical to the LaunchBlast, so I'm not going to insult you by asking you to do it.
It's so much like the LaunchBlast that we literally copy this stuff.
Call it ImpactBlast in two different places,
actually over here as well, ImpactBlast
for the name, and of course, we
need to declare ImpactBlast, which I'll go and do in the header file right now. It's going to be
just like a LaunchBlast, same details so it's literally really
simple. The only difference is with the ImpactBlast, of course, is that we don't
want it to be activated at the start. So with the LaunchBlast we
have not said AutoActivate is false, so it is activated by default and that's
right, because we spawn the projectile into the world and it starts off with that particle effect.
But what we're going to want with the Impact
Blast is, we want it to be AutoActivate false, we don't want it to be
activated at the start. Alright, the other thing about this class here is
that we say a PrimaryActorTick.bCanEverTick = true. The projectile actually
doesn't need to tick, so we can say false here, because if you look
down you'll see that we don't use the Tick here at all. I'll leave the BeginPlay() in case we
need it but that's it. By the way, while we're talking about Auto Activate, you see that the Projectile
Movement does not activate, that's correct as well; we don't want the projectile to
move until we actually call the LaunchProjectile() method.
OK, so that's all working fine! Let me go ahead
and make sure that ImpactBlast is in the header file, because it's not saying that it is,
and of course, it isn't because I just copied.
OK, so ImpactBlast goes there, these lines get copied, Launch
Blast changed for ImpactBlast, and we make it non-auto-activating.
Let's go ahead, see if that compiles, and when it does compile or if it does
compile, what we should see is, of course, inside the
Projectile Blueprint, we should see on the left-hand side a LaunchBlast and
a ImpactBlast next to each other. Also, we want to be attaching to (Root Component). Yeah
we did that by default, because I just copied, I said let's have the same paradigm
as the launch blast, so copying code. So what have I done, I done a boo boo somewhere?
"The function is deprecated, use AttachToComponent instead",
"update your code". OK, on Projectile line (19) it
doesn't like AttachTo(RootComponent) and AttachToComponent.
It's funny that it didn't complain about that before, they're just warnings here,
and then, we have a linker error. OK so what's
happening here is quite interesting. We would have had these warnings before, but we weren't looking
at them. OK, so I'm not going to fix them, we'll come back to them. Let's just make
a note in the code that we need a TODO. "// TODO
update to Attach... Well "update
to new API". OK so we've actioned this, in that we've put a TODO,
but the thing is that the reason we have a failure of actual compilation
here is because we have unresolved externals, which always means that we have a mish
or nearly always means that we have a mismatch,
between the declaration of something in the header file and the implementation
in the other file; and what that is, actually, is
Tick, it's because I never took Tick out of the header file. So those
errors can be a little bit strange. Now let's go and compile again, because there's useful learning
in here, which is that when it compiles again, the compilation
will succeed, probably now hopefully, if I've done it right. The compilation
will succeed and we will miss those warnings, so I'm just going to make sure that you're
aware of how you can get to and check for those warnings. You see, compilation
successful, it hasn't told us anything's wrong here, but if we go to Window,
Developer Tools, and then, Message Log.
I think we should dock our message log here in future, because look, if we
come down here and have a look, we've got Compiler Log. Now let's read the Compiler Log.
There you go, the warning is there against the
Compile Log, and it's saying that we shouldn't use AttachTo, please use
AttachToComponent instead. OK well let's go and do that right away, but, the point here,
the general point is that a compilation succeeding does not mean there are no warnings, and warnings should still
be fixed. I'm just going to try changing to AttachTo
Component, like that, and we'll just check the, you know,
the documentation for AttachToComponent, at least the inline documentation here. I think
that's going to work OK. I won't remove the TODO till it's working. Let's try recompiling!
And this time, we'll keep an eye on the message log rather
than the output log, the Compiler Log here. And this will still tell us when
our... Here you go! It "does not take 1
arguments". OK, so you can't just do a straight transposition of one to the other, we actually
need to take a second to read that a lot more carefully and see what the
deal is, with regards to what it wants. So it wants a USceneComponent pointer
which I believe that the Root Component is, but it also wants an FAttachmentTransformRules.
So let's look at what this second parameter is, it wants an FAttachment
TransformRules. So it appears that this new AttachToComponent method just
wants us to be a little bit more explicit about how we attach. If you go to Google
and search for that, you'll have FAttachmentTransformRules. I've also
linked to this in the course resources. And what we're going to want to do
here is to provide a KeepRelativeTransform. What we're saying
there is that we want the ImpactBlast to go with the Projectile,
at least for now. We may decide to change that policy later, but that's where we're going to
start in both cases. So if we look... Sorry I'm flicking all over the
place. If we look at the documentation, it's just KeepRelativeTransform is
what we want OK, so it's a static. Alright, let's go ahead
and have a look at how that's going to work. So in the code we are simply going
to say FAttachmentTransformRules:: take the static off it, Keep
RelativeTransform and that should do it. Let's do that for both.
And by the same argument, I won't remove the TODO,
until it compiles without warnings. Let's go back and compile! So
from now on you've got this tool of the Message Log, an even better way to be compiling, because not only
do you catch errors but you catch warnings. Better than just looking at the
output log. OK the compile's complete, we've got no issues at all. If we want to look at our
Output Log, at the bottom, that's also pretty normal. So that's all good news!
Alright, let's give ourselves some more room. I will just show you the
code changes, I made a lot of changes in that lecture, just if this helps you, and then, we'll move onto the
next bit. So we stopped at ticking, and then we did this stuff that you
can see in here. We removed the Tick but the bulk of it is just this green
in there. OK, in the header file, we simply declared and removed the Tick function.
OK cool, so that's a recap of where we are! We are about
8 minutes into the video, so we've got time for some more. Great! So now
what we want to do is to actually customize this
ImpactBlast to be how we want it and to activate it when we
actually get a hit. So what I want you to do is revise a few lectures ago. I want you
register a component OnHit() event delegate. What a mouthful but we did
do it a few videos ago. Use the LaunchBlast arrow
Deactivate() method, in order to turn off
the LaunchBlast, the one that's leaving the smoke trail, when
the collider hits something, we turn off the LaunchBlast. Add an Impact
Blast particle effect to the projectile. We've already done most of that, we probably haven't
actually wired up, in the blueprint, the impact blast. We've done most of it.
Activate that on impact, and you activate it using a very similar line to the
LaunchBlast Deactivate(), I guess you could imagine what it is. And then, share your
explosion with the community and I'll see you in a minute!
OK welcome back! So the first thing, I don't think
we've done is gone into this ImpactBlast and actually assigned the Impact
Blast to the component. So that's done now, if we
compile and play that, well then it crashes! Let's just try again. No
I don't think there's any particular reason it would have crashed there. I don't think we've done any naughties,
not protecting components. Again, my general policy is if it crashes once,
don't worry. You might want to run the debugger now, in case it crashes a second time. I'm not going
to, I'm just going to reattach the ImpactBlast, compile that, and you see it's
absolutely fine. Let's just have a look! We have a LaunchBlast and an ImpactBlast
doing basically the same thing, so you can't really tell. It looks like we've just got two particle effects on top of
each other. It doesn't look a lot different. OK let's go to the code and think about
what we're going to do! Several videos ago we did an OnComponent  hit event,
so why don't we just go find that! "OnComponent
Hit, and we can go to the entire project and
go find that. OK, so what we needed to do in BeginPlay(), when we did this
on the TankTrack, is we needed to add a dynamic delegate.
So well that's the first thing I've found, let's do that on BeginPlay() of the Projectile.
Let's just model what we've done before, it worked before, let's do it again. OK let's keep going!
So OnComponentHit, OK so the next thing we need to know
is where the definition of the OnHitEvent is inside this TankTrack.
So there it is, OnHit, and it's got this massive signature,
so let's just go take it. I'm going to put,
after LaunchProjectile I'm going to put OnHit like that, put some
squigglies, and the only thing you need to be aware of, of course, is changing from your Projectile
to your TankTrack to your Projectile. OK let's keep going! If we've got a
none hit here in the TankTrack.cpp, then we must have some
declaration of that, so let's go see how we did that before. We made it a UFUNCTION(),
and let's just copy that straight into the Projectile. Let's
think about the protection. It was private, so let's just try private again.
And there's no reason for it to be anything but private either. It's a method,
so I like it to go at the top. I don't know why, they just seem like they should go at the
top, it doesn't matter at all. OK so hopefully that's it! We just put an
OnHit here, we have defined it here. Well we're not doing
anything yet. I think what would probably make sense to do here is to go
to the LaunchBlast and deactivate it,
so... I gave you that in the slide, didn't I? I said
LaunchBlast Deactivate().
So we're going to do that OnHit, as an indication that we have hit
something, and let's see if that is working and if the collisions are actually happening.
Let's compile! Again, I don't know why I've gotten rid of my Message Log, so I'm going to bring
it back, dock it down here, and start looking
at the message log. The part of the Message Log you want is the Compile Log
there, you'll get nothing out of it until the compiler is finished. Ooh, " 'OnComponent
Hit' : undeclared identifier" on line (33).
And the problem here is that I'm trying to run OnComponentHit
or access OnComponentHit on a projectile, which
actually, if you think about it, is not a component at all, it is an
actor. So what we need to do is, we need to do the OnComponentHit, we need you to register
that against the CollisionMesh OnComponent
Hit. OK so that was the dark side of all that copying
was that, obviously, it didn't think about what we're doing with the On
ComponentHit. Because we're not a component, we need to get into the scope of the component we're talking about.
Let's see if that'll compile!
UTankTrack is not a class or namespace. And the other dark side, of course,
of the copying and pasting is I didn't change that UTankTrack to AProjectile there.
Now let's go ahead and compile again! So you can see that copying and pasting clearly saves you a load
of time but it also has, as I say, has a darker side, which is that you end up
bringing stuff in which can cause you some issues. So it's up to you how much copying and
pasting you do vs. writing original code. I thought I'd show you that approach. So
it's compiled which is great! Now let's just play the game! Not really necessarily going to be able to
see that that... Yes we can, we can see that that particle effect has stopped. You can particularly
see it, if you temporarily get rid of the impact blast, just
un-assign it. We can just clear that here.
Compile the blueprint, play the game, and then,
if we just go into the world with F8 and move over to the site
of these...
...these cannon ball things. You can see that there's no smoke coming out of them, they are deactivated now.
OK so that is what's going on! They are deactivated, those components
on them are deactivated. You could click into, of course, the actual thing, and
you could look and look at the LaunchBlast and then you could probably go into the Details
and even confirm that it's deactivated,
if it's exposed.
No it's not, whether it's actually activated
right now is not exposed as a parameter, but you can see it's not activated. So that
process of deactivating it on landing, deactivating the LaunchBlast
on landing has worked, and it will no longer emit a launch trail. So video's got
quite long. I think what we need to do is stop there, for the moment, and just
take track on how far we've got. What have you got? Add an ImpactBlast
to the projectile, activate it. No we can do that, we can activate
that ImpactBlast in the last couple of minutes. Let's just do that. So back to the Projectile Blueprint!
ImpactBlast, reassign the Particle System.
I'm just going to do something to the ParticleSystem that makes it super obvious,
like take the Initial Size of the FireBall, plot just
the Initial Size of the FireBall on the graph. Go and say,
what's the size range? I'm going to zoom right out and just make it much bigger,
like that.
Actually, it's going to be easier just to look and say, well these are uniform vectors they have
X, Y, Z, so let's just ramp up the maximum possible
size and the minimum possible size in X,
Y, and Z. It can be asymmetric for now. And what that should do is, when
we get an impact blast... Whoah there it is! So, we're starting with the
ImpactBlast activated, we don't want that, we want to make sure that AutoActivate
is turned off. Now, you go to
the Projectile, ImpactBlast,
we then search for "auto" activate and it's on. It wants to be off.
And it should have been made the default of in the C++. I thought
we did that, so let's go and have a look, where we add the ImpactBlast.
AutoActivate = false. Ahh look, I've copied again!
Wow! I am doing lost of copy and paste boo boos right now!
That is why the ImpactBlast did not AutoActivate false!
So let's just recompile. Now, when you do this recompilation, the
setting that you have against this ImpactBlast component, the fact I've said
not AutoActivate in Blueprint is still overriding what's happening in the C++.
It's just that the little arrow will go away, because it's now at the new
default value. So let's just watch this, see what happens!
It's nearly there, what we haven't done is reactivated this on
impact. So where we see our OnHit we inactivate the LaunchBlast
and we Activate()
the ImpactBlast. Let's compile that!
And it's pretty simple and meaningful, all of this. I like it, I like the way the code's coming together.
So a few little mistakes and hiccups for me, in this video, but again I'm leaving
those in, because my general feedback from you guys is that's better, it's more realistic, it's
more live and uncut. It's more like the journey you guys are probably having,
so hopefully you like that. Boom! Look at that! That's enough for this
video! Congratulations! I want you to snapshot your beautiful impacts and things
and share them in the community! And I'll see you in the next video!
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1:Unreal/Section4/BT91 Using FAttachmentTransformRules.srt