Hey so I'm calling this video
Radial Forces & Caching! It'll be pretty clear why. by the end of it. and
by the end of it you'll have this result. is that you can have
the other tank fire a projectile at you or vice versa. of course. And you will knock each other for 6. So I'll see you in there!
So let's take stock and ask that question. what's least fun about this game? Well
being able to fire that often and having 200 rounds is a bit crazy on a tank.
So I'm going to go to the TankAimingComponent to give myself a 2 second reload
time and 20 rounds. just to make that more sensible. Alright. let's
put an enemy tank back in the scene and play the game. I'll depossess
and use F11 and F8 to depossess and then F11 to go full
screen. OK what happens when the explosion hits us? OK. well it's OK.
Firstly. the tank isn't moving. let's make that our first focus. We've also got
these balls stacking up and that's no good. and also we want
to turn off the brown balls and we want to get rid of this smoke. But let's focus on
adding a force. so that we actually knock my tank out of
the way. So how are we going to do that? Well let's go and look at the projectile and
see. in the blueprint. what we have if we search for components
that relate to force. And we have this thing here called a Radial Force. "Used
to emit a Radial Force or impulse that can effect physics objects and or destructible
objects." Well I think we all get a sense of what a force is. it's something that causes an acceleration.
But what is an impulse? Well you can go on Wikipedia and look up an impulse.
You'll get a bit of math. It tells you that it's the integral of F dt. which means it is the
area under the force time graph. If you do a
Google Image search for "impulse force graph". you'll see that you've got an idea of seconds or
milliseconds and then an amount of force. An explosion would be something like this.
A force would rapidly rise. while the air pressure rises. and then it would drop off.
And what an impulse is is it's the area under that curve.
So what this add radial force. as an impulse allows you to
do is do exactly that. add a fixed impulse. It could be 100
million newtons for 1 second or it could be 10 times
smaller force for 10 times longer or 10 times bigger force for 10 times less time. as
long as the area. as long as the multiple of those two is equivalent.
OK. So the way we're
going to add that is as we've added all the other things in the Projectile. Let's go to the Projectile
header file. and let's make ourselves the appropriate type to start with.
So let's barrow the code for the. well let's barrow the annotation
UPROPERTY. and then. it's going to be a
U. let's see if we can find it. URadialForceComponent. That was easy to find. it has the same name
as in the blueprint. It's a pointer. I'm going to call it
an ExplosionForce.
and we're going to be good boys and girls and
initialize it to the null pointer like that. Fantastic! Alright. so we now have a local variable to store the
ExplosionForce! Now let's go and actually add the ExplosionForce
as a default subobject. So ExplosionForce = Create
DefaultSubobject URadial
ForceComponent.
And then. let's just give it a simple name. (FName)
with a capital N. and I'm just going to call it
("Explosion Force")). So let's not bother with AttachTo
Component. for the moment. We've done it with the LaunchBlast. we haven't done it with ProjectileMovement. we have
done it with the ImpactBlast. Let's see if it's necessary. So let's go ahead and
compile our code and take a look at the Projectile Blueprint.
when we do so. and see what happens. In fact. while I'm compiling my code. let's be
nice to you and show you my code changes. That's the header file code changes there.
and the C++ code changes are there. Remember you can always go to github.com/Ben
Tristem. navigate to Unreal. find the section. and get
the code. Alright. so how is that compiled? And that's the question. it looks like
it may have done. Compile succeeded! I'm just going to
Save All. I've got a lot of stars here. I don't like stars. stars mean unsaved work that could get lost if
Unreal crashed. Would it crash? But in case it does! Now let's look at the
Projectile! ExplosionForce. there we go! CollisionMesh. Launch
Blast. ImpactBlast. ExplosionForce. and ProjectileMovement
are all sitting there. OK great! So
there's the ExplosionForce! Now how do we know how much ExplosionForce to set on this?
Well to start we need a Radius. 2 meters. OK. Maybe we'll go to 5 meters. our
tanks are 7 meters long. And then. this talks about the Falloff. so it's a constant
falloff. in this case. after 5 meters there is no force. So there's going to be a 5 meter blast
area. Now how much Impulse Strength do we need? Well remember
what the definition is. it's the force times the time. It's more subtle than that.
because it's actually an integral under a curve. but let's imagine it's a constant force. for a minute.
a square curve like this one down here. How would we even get an
idea as to how much impulse we need to give here. Well one very easy
way to get an idea is to go look at the tracks. and see how much force we have Driving
Force-wise. We have 1. 2. 3. 4. 5. 6. 0's
and a 40. so we have 40 million Newtons. So how
about. with our Projectile Impulse here. we imagine
that we apply. I don't know. 100 million Newtons. the same
force as both tank tracks driving plus a bit. and
we apply that for say 1 second. the duration of the explosion. then we get 100 million.
Let's try it. because it's 100 Million times 1 second. So 100.
1. 2. 3. 4. 5. 6. OK there you go!
Let's try that as a starting Impulse Strength. Now Unreal crashed!
Luckily I'd saved everything. so we shouldn't lose any work. Again.
a single crash like that not that unusual. when you're changing blueprints.
Let's go and restore everything. have a look
over here at the ExplosionForce. turn the Radius back.
and then. set this guy back to 100 Million.
trying not to curse. because of the crash.
OK fantastic. let's compile that! Now let's play the game!
So I've applied this explosion force as
on the object. but we need to code for that explosion force to actually do
something. So the way that you do that is you come into
where the actual hit happens here. and you say ExplosionForce.
and then you go through the arrow pointer.
and you FireImpulse. There's no parameters on that. but you just fire the impulse that's
been setup in the component. In our case. I've overridden that in
Blueprint. Let's just try going ahead and recompiling!
Then. we should get a force firing off. when
the explosion. component. hits the tank. So
let's go and see if that works or if it doesn't work.
So it fires. it hits. but the tank's not
moving. OK. so we could doubt the size of our impulse.
It would be very reasonable to doubt that impulse and say it should be bigger. but it's not
actually the size of the impulse that's causing the problem. I'm actually leading you down a path here
on purpose. There is a problem already here on the screen. but
it's going to lead to some very interesting debugging attitude and behavior. So
what I'm going to do now is turn up that Radius to say
1.000 meters. so 1.00000. If I turn up the
Radius to 1.000. it shouldn't need to be 1.000. but look at this.
I think it will work now! Then. you're going to have
a challenge to work out why. Hmm.
now the tank goes flying backwards! OK now let's look at that a little bit more carefully.
If I just get into the tank here and move. If I
can move before he shoots me again. I just... Look at this! What's quite
interesting is me and the other tank are both heading backwards. when that
Impulse Force goes off. So what is going on here? And that's your job.
that's your job is to work out what is going on. in this case. Let me get you to the
challenge slide. Find the bug. basically. is what you need to do.
because it's a really interesting bug. It's not actually a bug. as such. we're just
slightly misusing the engine but it is important. So why is this behavior happening? Try
inspecting the projectile at runtime. Pause the game. depossess. inspect the projectile.
look at all its components. particularly the ExplosionForce one. see
if you can find out what's going wrong. If you can. write a single line of code; it's a line
we've already written in the C++ files.
and see if you can solve the problem. Share the solution and your approach to the problem. in the discussions.
Spend a little bit of time scratching your head. because this is the sort of thing you might come across in your own
use of the engine. and I want you to be prepared. both in terms of the skills
to debug but also in terms of the attitude. Take a positive attitude to this. say I can
solve this! This is solvable! So go ahead. pause the video. and take a look now!
OK welcome back!
So let's just play the game. F8 to depossess.
I'm going to move to the side. When the projectile is in flight I'm going to pause it. I'm going to
click on it. Let's take a look at it! What's funny about this projectile? Well
there it is in the world. sitting and doing its thing. Let's just look through the
components. fine. Now. ExplosionForce. look where the
projectile itself is. Look at the location in the world. you can see the
indicator there and the CollsionMesh and the  LaunchBlast and the ImpactBlast.
all going along with it. But where's the ExplosionForce? Err. there it is!
It's at the root of the game. it's a... Well I don't know
actually if it is exactly at the root. but that probably is actually
relative to the tank. Yeah. that's probably at 0. 0. 0 position in the world. If
you want to be sure. of course. you can come to Modes. you can add yourself a
cube to the world. I would scale it 10. 10. 10. or you
could have just used the padlock to do that. Reset it to the origin. Actually yeah.
you can see it is. So the ExplosionForce is ending up at the world's
origin. Why is that? Let me show you another thing that's weird about
the ExplosionForce. Look at the ImpactBlast and the LaunchBlast. I did
that around the wrong way but you get the idea. Look at its Transform. it has a Location. Rotation. and Scale. Look at
the Transform on the ExplosionForce. it only has a Scale.
no Rotation or Location. It's knocked
out. to use a technical term. Now. this is why. congratulations if you
found this. because we didn't bother to AttachedToComponent.
OK so I'm going to grab that line. In fact. we don't need to update to the new
API. because we've done that. We do need to Attach. if we don't Attach it will look
like it is attached to the CollisionMesh but it ain't working. so we
need to put this AttachToComponent line in. OK. And because I've done it
there. I'm also going to do it on the... Actually. we don't need it on the ProjectileMovement.
because if you look at the ProjectileMovement it sits differently. it doesn't
sit as a child of the CollisionMesh. It doesn't need to go along with the CollisionMesh. it can just
stay in the world with the ProjectileLaunch. So we don't need to bother with that. but we certainly do
with this ExplosionForce. So let's go ahead. compile
the code. Then. I'll Save All as
well. I can do that now. I want to get rid of my stars. stars are a bad thing. and as I say. it's work that could easily
get lost. And isn't that an interesting strange bug right. that
the only symptom was that that transform wasn't working. Let's have a look here! Explosion
Force now. ExplosionForce now. actually. still
doesn't have a sensible looking transform. and this is now probably because of caching.
Unreal Engine tends to cache things. often for performance. too much for it's own good
I would say. and you can end up with these types of problems. where that
change should've made it work properly but it isn't. So let's take a look .
now if that's helped. If it hasn't. we have to do what? What do we do if this hasn't helped?
We have to refresh the intermediate files. don't we?
So look. that hasn't helped! I can recompile the blueprint.
I'm definitely... Ah OK. another problem! I said I'm
definitely attaching the right component. That's easy to do. you barrow the code but you
use the wrong thing. OK. so that can give you a problem as well. it needs to be the
ExplosionForce that attaches. That was my fault. in this case. but that's a different
issue. right. The reason it didn't attach is
because I used the wrong variable name there. which you could have done the first
time around. by the way. You may have done that. had you just automatically come in
and copied that line. This is the problem with copying and pasting lines. but it doesn't
remove from the underlying problem that if you
don't attach. either by using the wrong variable name here or by not having
the line altogether. like we didn't have in the beginning. Then. it looks like it's attached
but it doesn't act like it's attached. OK. so now
this is interesting. If we recompile now. looking at the explosion force.
if I've written this code properly. AttachToComponent. you would hope
that when I look at this ExplosionForceComponent that it has its
Transform working. It doesn't! Let's try reclosing and reloading
Unreal. Does that do it? It
may not do it. So we're going around this cycle twice here. because I want to
bring home the fact that not only do we have to attach
these things but it can also cache the state. Look now it's back. just by
closing and reloading Unreal. You see how
difficult to diagnose that can be. Now that this ExplosionForce has a reasonable looking
Transform. I suspect we'll be able to turn the Radius back down to 5 meters.
because now the Explosion force won't be acting from the middle of
the world anymore. It'll be... Ooh. what's going on with my camera? Hang on a second.
OK that's better!
I suspect it won't be acting from the middle of the world anymore but it'll be acting where
we want it to. So that missed me and that hit me sideways.
You see what's happening there? Great! So very interesting problem.
It's showing you the problems with caching in Unreal. so remember some things are cached.
Even though I changed that variable name back and recompiled. it
still didn't have the correct transform. And yes. you need. when
you actually want your hierarchy to look like this. you absolutely have to AttachTo.
otherwise it will look like it's attached and it won't be. The thing to watch out for
is that all of your components have proper. that this is a proper
Transform for the root component. but any subcomponents need to
also. apart from just having a scale. have to have a relative Location and
Rotation. compared to that root component. So flick through them. keep your eye here.
on the right-hand side of the screen under the Transform OK. Really valuable stuff. that'll get you out of
lots of trouble in the future. in Unreal. So I'm just going to close the engine right now. Actually I
won't close it. but I'll leave it there. save everything. and I will see you in the next video!