So welcome to using GetTimerManager()! We're going to
go and get the TimerManager from the world. in this video. and what we're going to do.
by the end of it. is just have the projectiles that both myself and the enemy tank fire.
Rather than just accumulating in the scene. they're going to destroy themselves after
10 seconds or a reasonable amount of time. So let's get in and make that happen!
OK guys. so let's take a look at these projectiles in action! I'm
going to fire at the enemy tank a few times. and then. I'm going to depossess
and just observe a few things. Firstly. the projectiles are not being
destroyed. which can mean it's a difficult bug to reproduce. but it can mean
the projectiles can actually hit each other in the air. And we can kind of stop the enemy tank
firing. by cluttering the area with
projectiles. As I say. it's a hard problem to reproduce. But what i'm trying to do is
end up with a projectile effectively stuck to the barrel of the other
tank. and then. he can't fire and I can't fire. It's not happening to
me now. It is a tricky one to reproduce. but we don't want these things hanging around in the world
anyway. So what are we going to do about that? Well we have these Collision Meshes.
these brown Collision Meshes. on. Just turning them invisible wouldn't get rid of the problem.
that the projectiles are still sitting around in
the world. even though we may not want them. There you go. I did it in the end! If I depossess
now. let's go look at what's happened! You see the two
projectiles have caught each other in mid air. [Laughs] Now we just get all of the projectiles piling on top
of each other. It looks kind of crazy doesn't it? OK. so what we want to do.
in the C++ code. is when when we actually hit something. we
want to destroy the Collision Mesh. but before we just blindly destroy it. if you
look at the Projectile. remember that it's the root component. Let's get in the habit of
thinking about whether or not we're destroying the root component. If we are let's set
something else first. So I'm going to set the ImpactBlast as the root component. then
destroy the Collision Mesh in the code. OK so it's not super difficult. Set
RootComponent(ImpactBlast). There you go!
And I'll put these as kind of a pair. and then. we're going to
Destroy...
Sorry we need to go to the CollisionMesh. and it's a function on there called
DestroyComponent(). Great! OK
let's have a go at that! Let's see what that looks like! Recompile. and what we should have is.
because the Collision Meshes have actually been destroyed immediately on impact. this situation
should then be impossible. and if it is. then we can
even turn off the Collision Meshes. I don't think we're going to need them anymore. these brown
Collision Meshes. So now. obviously just firing it a few times does
not prove that the bug has gone away. but I think we can reason that the bug must have gone
away. because the Collision Meshes are destroyed immediately on impact.
OK that's cool! Now I don't like these black puffs of smoke that are hanging
around. after the projectile is destroyed. so I'm just going to go and look at the Projectile Blueprint.
Actually. I'll look at the ImpactBlast
Particle Effect. I think what it is. is that my my ImpactBlast has
still got a SmokeTrail Emitter. I don't like that. so I'm going to delete my Smoke TrailEmitter from
the ImpactBlast. and that should stop that funny business
about them hanging around. Let's just take a look. how this
looks now. Yeah. we've got a little
puff there. but that's OK. what we haven't got is those black smoke trails hanging around. OK.
So continually. as you go through this. play with the parameters of your
ImpactBlast and your LaunchBlast and get things how you want them. But what we've got now
is another problem with these projectiles. which is that if we look on the right-hand side. in the World Outliner.
every time we fire a projectile. they may well have their Collision Meshes
destroyed but they still exist in the world. And after not much game play. we'd have a
massive number of projectiles. projectile BP 7. BP9. BP10.
And this is a memory leak. this is creating things without destroying them. We're not tidying up
after ourselves. eventually the game would crash. It might take a while but we need to tidy
it up. So we need to come up with a scheme for destroying our projectiles. so let's just
discuss the possible schemes. One is to use a Projectile Destroy Timer. We're going
to use that one. it's very simple. and the projectile becomes self-responsible. What
we do is we set a timer. and then. when that timer elapses. it just destroys the projectile. it just
destroys itself. The problem. the con. is that it's not very performant if you have
hundreds of projectiles with all these timers going. So you could do something else. you could
Spawn an Explosion Effect. at the impact site. and destroy the
projectile. So the projectile disappears and a explosion.
a new object. starts. It's more physical. the projectile has gone. you could argue. once it's
exploded. and the explosion remains behind. It's more complex to do
this and it could. of course. slow down just when you don't want it. i.e. just when explosions are
going off you're destroying and spawning objects. not necessarily the most performant thing to be doing.
Finally. if you had a natural limit to the number of projectiles
in the world. say you took the number of tanks and then worked out how many times a second
they could fire and how long the projectiles live. you could say. OK we can't have more
than 100 in the world at a time. naturally. So let's just have a pool of 100
projectiles. for example. and then. when a projectile lands you could
disable it and so it effectively disappears and isn't active anymore.
And then. next time a projectile is needed. you pick the oldest
projectile from a pool. and you pluck it. put it in a barrel. and reactivate
it. So the projectiles never actually get instantiated and de-instantiated. but you just have a
fixed number of them that are moved around in a circular fashion in what we call a ring buffer.
in the world. So there's an option for you. We're going to do with the first one. a simple
Projectile Destroy Timer. So how do we do that? Well when we hit.
I'm just going to help you get the method. then I'm going to help you implement it. We need to go to the world.
because the world has in it the TimerManager. so we Get the TimerManager.
Now that we have the world's TimerManager. we
can call a SetTimer() method on it. Now. SetTimer's a bit minging. in that it
has a whole lot of different overloads. We're going to go for overload number 6 here.
mainly because it does everything we need. plus it actually has some
minimal form of documentation on it. We've done things like this before.
You're going to need to make yourself an FTimerHandle. just call it
Timer or TimerHandle. Immediately above the class is going to be
just this. it is just the projectile. We're going to need a
Delegate method. which is a huge. look at that massive parameter
name there. but it is a simple Delegate method OnTimerExpire or something. which
you'll write. And then. we won't loop. this timer isn't going to loop. it's going to go once.
Alright. so that gives you enough of a clue to do this challenge. Make the projectiles
self-destroy. I want you to use that method. Set a Blueprint editable
DestroyDelay. so we don't have to keep recompiling. when we play with our DestroyDelay. Write
a a simple delegate method. In that delegate method. just use the Destroy() method
to destroy the projectile. test that it works. and then. go over to the community.gamedev.tv
and comment on the whole approach and which one you chose. So go ahead.
do that challenge. and I'll see you in a minute!
OK welcome back! So let's get this timer thing going! So
what do we need? We need a timer. so we're going to go FTimerHandle.
Unfortunately. we're just going to throw this away. but it's an out parameter and
we must provide it. So there's the timer! We're going to ignore what it
says here. because this is overload number 2. we want number 6.
so we could go to get to 6 there. So what does it need next? Well it needs a reference
to ourselves. this. this projectile. Then. we need to tell it the delegate
method. so we're going to call it an ampersand AProjectile. or
actually. rather than writing it here. why don't I go write the method now. void
AProjectile::
OnTimer
Expire(). And I might as well even just write it. we simply just
say Destroy(). which will by default destroy the
current projectile. Great! So now the reason I did that is. I can just copy
AProjectile::OnTimerExpire(). Remember to put your ampersand. &. address of operator in front. that's
how you do it when you specify delegates. Destroy
Delay. which we have not defined yet. and false. OK.
I'll make is a slightly longer line there. but it does all fit on one line.
Alright. so we need to go and do a couple of things. Firstly. we need to declare this OnTimer
Expire. I'm going to use the Quick Actions to create a declaration of it in the header file.
I'm going to pop over to the header file. make sure that it's in sensible place. I think it is.
That's fine. And then. I'm also going to
declare a timer delay. so it's going to be
a float and it's going to be a Destroy
Delay. and I'll make it a default of 10 seconds
or something like that. I better make it a UPROPERTY. so we can
Edit it. (EditDefaults
Only). because I think we only want to be able to edit
on the archetype. not on individual projectiles. Category
= "Setup" will do fine. OK. so we have a Destroy
Delay. 10 point maybe we need there. and
yeah we're. I think. good to go! So that's the code I've written. just that.
a delegate and a couple of declarations. Let's go ahead and see if that'll compile! And then.
crucially. what we do is we fire back and forth at each other and what we're hoping is that projectiles will delete
themselves out of the list. and we will not end up with an infinitely
growing list of projectiles. Of course. the first one won't delete for 10 seconds but that's quite normal
and expected. and we'll go from there. it'll be fun. Good!
OK. so I'm going to leave myself in this smaller view here. because I want to be able to see
the World Outliner. And I can see now projectile BP1.
BP2. BP3. BP4. and I'm firing continuously. BP5. 6. 7.
Now what we should see in a minute is (Deleted Actor). There you go. briefly you saw (Deleted
Actor). I'm going to stop firing right now. so that the overall firing rate is lower
than the destruction rate. because previously. between me and the other tank. we were
firing faster than this. And now. you see the projectile pool is just down to the number of projectiles
that the enemy tank is responsible for. So you can see that the
hierarchy. or the World Outliner rather. is keep itself tidy now.
We are destroying what we are creating and that's good news! I'll show you the code we've done
in this lecture. and then. I'll see you in the next lecture. We made these declarations here. Of
course. this UPROPERTY allows us to go to the Projectile Blueprint.
to the top of it there. and then. we go to Destroy Delay. and we can
change that if we want to. The other thing we did is. we popped in
and did this implementation here. which I'll just leave on the screen. And I will see you in the next video!
=======
So welcome to using GetTimerManager()! We're going to
go and get the TimerManager from the world, in this video, and what we're going to do,
by the end of it, is just have the projectiles that both myself and the enemy tank fire.
Rather than just accumulating in the scene, they're going to destroy themselves after
10 seconds or a reasonable amount of time. So let's get in and make that happen!
OK guys, so let's take a look at these projectiles in action! I'm
going to fire at the enemy tank a few times, and then, I'm going to depossess
and just observe a few things. Firstly, the projectiles are not being
destroyed, which can mean it's a difficult bug to reproduce, but it can mean
the projectiles can actually hit each other in the air. And we can kind of stop the enemy tank
firing, by cluttering the area with
projectiles. As I say, it's a hard problem to reproduce. But what i'm trying to do is
end up with a projectile effectively stuck to the barrel of the other
tank, and then, he can't fire and I can't fire. It's not happening to
me now. It is a tricky one to reproduce, but we don't want these things hanging around in the world
anyway. So what are we going to do about that? Well we have these Collision Meshes,
these brown Collision Meshes, on. Just turning them invisible wouldn't get rid of the problem,
that the projectiles are still sitting around in
the world, even though we may not want them. There you go, I did it in the end! If I depossess
now, let's go look at what's happened! You see the two
projectiles have caught each other in mid air. [Laughs] Now we just get all of the projectiles piling on top
of each other. It looks kind of crazy doesn't it? OK, so what we want to do,
in the C++ code, is when when we actually hit something, we
want to destroy the Collision Mesh, but before we just blindly destroy it, if you
look at the Projectile, remember that it's the root component. Let's get in the habit of
thinking about whether or not we're destroying the root component. If we are let's set
something else first. So I'm going to set the ImpactBlast as the root component, then
destroy the Collision Mesh in the code. OK so it's not super difficult. Set
RootComponent(ImpactBlast). There you go!
And I'll put these as kind of a pair, and then, we're going to
Destroy...
Sorry we need to go to the CollisionMesh, and it's a function on there called
DestroyComponent(). Great! OK
let's have a go at that! Let's see what that looks like! Recompile, and what we should have is,
because the Collision Meshes have actually been destroyed immediately on impact, this situation
should then be impossible, and if it is, then we can
even turn off the Collision Meshes. I don't think we're going to need them anymore, these brown
Collision Meshes. So now, obviously just firing it a few times does
not prove that the bug has gone away, but I think we can reason that the bug must have gone
away, because the Collision Meshes are destroyed immediately on impact.
OK that's cool! Now I don't like these black puffs of smoke that are hanging
around, after the projectile is destroyed, so I'm just going to go and look at the Projectile Blueprint.
Actually, I'll look at the ImpactBlast
Particle Effect. I think what it is, is that my my ImpactBlast has
still got a SmokeTrail Emitter. I don't like that, so I'm going to delete my Smoke TrailEmitter from
the ImpactBlast, and that should stop that funny business
about them hanging around. Let's just take a look, how this
looks now. Yeah, we've got a little
puff there, but that's OK, what we haven't got is those black smoke trails hanging around. OK.
So continually, as you go through this, play with the parameters of your
ImpactBlast and your LaunchBlast and get things how you want them. But what we've got now
is another problem with these projectiles, which is that if we look on the right-hand side, in the World Outliner,
every time we fire a projectile, they may well have their Collision Meshes
destroyed but they still exist in the world. And after not much game play, we'd have a
massive number of projectiles, projectile BP 7, BP9, BP10.
And this is a memory leak, this is creating things without destroying them. We're not tidying up
after ourselves, eventually the game would crash. It might take a while but we need to tidy
it up. So we need to come up with a scheme for destroying our projectiles, so let's just
discuss the possible schemes. One is to use a Projectile Destroy Timer. We're going
to use that one, it's very simple, and the projectile becomes self-responsible. What
we do is we set a timer, and then, when that timer elapses, it just destroys the projectile, it just
destroys itself. The problem, the con, is that it's not very performant if you have
hundreds of projectiles with all these timers going. So you could do something else, you could
Spawn an Explosion Effect, at the impact site, and destroy the
projectile. So the projectile disappears and a explosion,
a new object, starts. It's more physical, the projectile has gone, you could argue, once it's
exploded, and the explosion remains behind. It's more complex to do
this and it could, of course, slow down just when you don't want it, i.e. just when explosions are
going off you're destroying and spawning objects, not necessarily the most performant thing to be doing.
Finally, if you had a natural limit to the number of projectiles
in the world, say you took the number of tanks and then worked out how many times a second
they could fire and how long the projectiles live, you could say, OK we can't have more
than 100 in the world at a time, naturally. So let's just have a pool of 100
projectiles, for example, and then, when a projectile lands you could
disable it and so it effectively disappears and isn't active anymore.
And then, next time a projectile is needed, you pick the oldest
projectile from a pool, and you pluck it, put it in a barrel, and reactivate
it. So the projectiles never actually get instantiated and de-instantiated, but you just have a
fixed number of them that are moved around in a circular fashion in what we call a ring buffer,
in the world. So there's an option for you. We're going to do with the first one, a simple
Projectile Destroy Timer. So how do we do that? Well when we hit,
I'm just going to help you get the method, then I'm going to help you implement it. We need to go to the world,
because the world has in it the TimerManager, so we Get the TimerManager.
Now that we have the world's TimerManager, we
can call a SetTimer() method on it. Now, SetTimer's a bit minging, in that it
has a whole lot of different overloads. We're going to go for overload number 6 here,
mainly because it does everything we need, plus it actually has some
minimal form of documentation on it. We've done things like this before.
You're going to need to make yourself an FTimerHandle, just call it
Timer or TimerHandle. Immediately above the class is going to be
just this, it is just the projectile. We're going to need a
Delegate method, which is a huge, look at that massive parameter
name there, but it is a simple Delegate method OnTimerExpire or something, which
you'll write. And then, we won't loop, this timer isn't going to loop, it's going to go once.
Alright, so that gives you enough of a clue to do this challenge. Make the projectiles
self-destroy. I want you to use that method. Set a Blueprint editable
DestroyDelay, so we don't have to keep recompiling, when we play with our DestroyDelay. Write
a a simple delegate method. In that delegate method, just use the Destroy() method
to destroy the projectile, test that it works, and then, go over to the community.gamedev.tv
and comment on the whole approach and which one you chose. So go ahead,
do that challenge, and I'll see you in a minute!
OK welcome back! So let's get this timer thing going! So
what do we need? We need a timer, so we're going to go FTimerHandle.
Unfortunately, we're just going to throw this away, but it's an out parameter and
we must provide it. So there's the timer! We're going to ignore what it
says here, because this is overload number 2, we want number 6,
so we could go to get to 6 there. So what does it need next? Well it needs a reference
to ourselves, this, this projectile. Then, we need to tell it the delegate
method, so we're going to call it an ampersand AProjectile, or
actually, rather than writing it here, why don't I go write the method now. void
AProjectile::
OnTimer
Expire(). And I might as well even just write it, we simply just
say Destroy(), which will by default destroy the
current projectile. Great! So now the reason I did that is, I can just copy
AProjectile::OnTimerExpire(). Remember to put your ampersand, &, address of operator in front, that's
how you do it when you specify delegates. Destroy
Delay, which we have not defined yet, and false. OK,
I'll make is a slightly longer line there, but it does all fit on one line.
Alright, so we need to go and do a couple of things. Firstly, we need to declare this OnTimer
Expire. I'm going to use the Quick Actions to create a declaration of it in the header file.
I'm going to pop over to the header file, make sure that it's in sensible place. I think it is.
That's fine. And then, I'm also going to
declare a timer delay, so it's going to be
a float and it's going to be a Destroy
Delay, and I'll make it a default of 10 seconds
or something like that. I better make it a UPROPERTY, so we can
Edit it. (EditDefaults
Only), because I think we only want to be able to edit
on the archetype, not on individual projectiles. Category
= "Setup" will do fine. OK, so we have a Destroy
Delay, 10 point maybe we need there, and
yeah we're, I think, good to go! So that's the code I've written, just that,
a delegate and a couple of declarations. Let's go ahead and see if that'll compile! And then,
crucially, what we do is we fire back and forth at each other and what we're hoping is that projectiles will delete
themselves out of the list, and we will not end up with an infinitely
growing list of projectiles. Of course, the first one won't delete for 10 seconds but that's quite normal
and expected, and we'll go from there, it'll be fun. Good!
OK, so I'm going to leave myself in this smaller view here, because I want to be able to see
the World Outliner. And I can see now projectile BP1,
BP2, BP3, BP4, and I'm firing continuously, BP5, 6, 7.
Now what we should see in a minute is (Deleted Actor). There you go, briefly you saw (Deleted
Actor). I'm going to stop firing right now, so that the overall firing rate is lower
than the destruction rate, because previously, between me and the other tank, we were
firing faster than this. And now, you see the projectile pool is just down to the number of projectiles
that the enemy tank is responsible for. So you can see that the
hierarchy, or the World Outliner rather, is keep itself tidy now.
We are destroying what we are creating and that's good news! I'll show you the code we've done
in this lecture, and then, I'll see you in the next lecture. We made these declarations here. Of
course, this UPROPERTY allows us to go to the Projectile Blueprint,
to the top of it there, and then, we go to Destroy Delay, and we can
change that if we want to. The other thing we did is, we popped in
and did this implementation here, which I'll just leave on the screen. And I will see you in the next video!
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1:Unreal/Section4/BT93 Using GetTimerManager().srt