Hey and welcome to
The Observer Pattern! Instead of telling you what it's all about. I'm going to immediately tell you what it's all about!
So before I even tell you what these delegates or dynamic multicast
delegates are. let me just show you how we're going to use them. to give you some context. On our
tank we're going to have a property called OnDeath. that we can
say Broadcast. So we're going to Broadcast the fact that the tank
has died. That's going to go into the Unreal Engine. it's going to work some magic.
and then. the TankPlayerController and the TankAIController can
subscribe to receive this and they will then be able to process it.
For example. the PlayerController over here can then say.
OK I'm going to go into spectate mode and the AIController can stop
trying to control the tank. given that the tank is now defunct. OK. so that's generally
how it's going to work. The broadcaster here. the tank. does not care who
is listening. which observers are on the right-hand side. that's the general
principal. the general pattern. So in your resources I've given you
a few links. I would suggest that you take a moment to go and read them now.
as soon as I've introduced them. I'll tell you when. Read about Delegates and find out rougtly what
Delegates are. Don't get mad. just have an overview of this. spend a couple of minutes. Then. read about Dynamic
Delegates. There's not much difference. it tells you the difference here. And then.
look about Multi-cast Delegates. and there are again some
slight differences with Multi-cast Delegates. And we're going to be using Dynamic Multi-cast
Delegates. all of these layers on top of each other. this thing here. And
the reason is. that it's the most flexible and versatile and the most reusable. and
I would start with that. in general. and you can move backwards to simpler delegates when
performance dictates you need to or when some other constraint dictates you need to.
But there are a lot of boulders to navigate in Unreal. when it comes to these things.
because there's various combinations that are not possible on Actors or Components
or exposable in Blueprint or not. etc. So I'm giving you one
reliable recipe for getting these things working. So we just need
to write a little bit of code on the tank and a little bit of code on the AIController
and PlayerController to make this work. O.K.. so this is
the steps of setting up Dynamic Multi-cast Delegates. DMCD's. If you haven't already
stopped and red the Unreal docs. those first three docs I showed you about Delegates.
Dynamic Delegates. and Multi-cast Delegates. please stop the video and do that now.
OK. so this is how we're going
to do it. On the tank. for example. or on the
broadcasting type. we DECLARE_DYNAMIC_MULTICAST_DELEGATE with some SubjectName.
We just say F and then we give it a name. You then
Declare a property of type FSubjectName. called On
SomethingHappened. I'll give you concrete examples in a minute. And then. you broadcast
OnSomethingHappened.BroadCast(). So in the case of the tank. this could just be FTank
Delegate. FtankdelegateOnDeath
OnDeath.BroadCast(). You get the idea?
On the receiver. we need to declare a UFunction.
it won't work properly otherwise. And then. you have to declare a DelegateMethod(). This is the method on
the receiver. on the AIController. etc. that will handle
the delegate when it gets called. and for example. you would say void OnTank
Death(). And then. to register to listen you do this. you find the
BroadcastingInstance. i.e. the possessed tank. in our case.
and then. you say OnSomethingHappen. i.e. OnTankDeath.Add
UniqueDynamic this. i.e. the TankPlayerController. the AI
Controller. whatever. and then the class for the class we're in the PlayerController. the AIController.
the ListenerClass. And then you tell it the address of. this is an ampersand operator.
address of operator. You're saying. go find in memory the delegate
method. i.e. the OnTankDeath(). which we declared here. So what this guy
does is it binds. it's the binding; It's saying this is where you need to go to find
how to do that. But the question is. when do we register? Well I'm gong to help you with that bit. I'm not going to
leave you to work that on your own. that would be a tad mean. I'm at least going to do it
on the AIController for you. otherwise I'm being nasty.
So if we look at the AIController header file. it's a type of AController which
in turn inherits and inherits again. and what we can do here is
we can override something called SetPawn. So virtual
void SetPawn(). and then. it takes it
in (APawn pointer InPawn).
And then. I'm going to override it. override the superclass. Now this gets
called when the Pawn is possessed. OK. so when the TankAIController gets
possessed. this method gets called. Let's now go and implement that
SetPawn and I'll show you why. because that's where
we are going to do the binding. This binding that I've showed you down here. this is where we're going to
put that code OK. and it's not fair for me to make you work out that that's where we should
be doing it. because you'll find it just won't work if we try and do it at a different time. Or at least it won't
work reliably. we can't be sure that at BeginPlay() we have possessed yet.
So we SetPawn
(APawn pointer
InPawn). and then. we're ready to go and
implement the method. The first thing we need to do is call the super class. right. We're
overriding here. so we want to call Super::SetPawn
(InPawn). We don't know what the game engine's doing in the super class. We've
overridden. if we don't call Super then this whole thing won't get called on this object
and that's no good! OK. so we've called Super! Now. the next thing we need to do
is we need to only do what we're going to do next. if we have an
(InPawn). So one way to do that. we'll just say. if (InPawn). and then. we'll go
into a block of code. OK. if we don't have one. we don't even want to proceed.
Then. what we're going to do is we're going to work out what the Possessed
Tank is. and that is the In
Pawn. that's coming in. So the Pawn that this AIController is
possessing but we need to cast it to ATank. Now we can't
cast it to ATank. of course. without this class knowing something about
ATank and that's fair enough. We are implementing a
delegate that relates to ATank's OnDeath event. so we need to
include "Tank.h". That is quite normal. If you want to know why.
then we can go up here and say
why we've imported it. "// So we can implement
OnDeath". OK. So now that we've #included
"Tank.h". then this Cast down here should work. Then. we probably want an
ensure statement. so we say if not
(!ensure(possessedTank)).
Don't worry. you'll get a chance to do all of this for yourself on the other side. on the TankPlayerController.
If not PossessedTank return. because by this stage we really
ought to have a (PossessedTank) successfully cast from the Pawn.
And then. it's where we're going to "// Subscribe
our local method". which we haven't
written yet. "to the tank's death event". And
you're going to do that OK. so I'll put a TODO in. Alright.
so this is where you do it. As I said. it wouldn't be very fair for me to expect you to work that out. Let me recap why we're
doing it on SetPawn. Because constructor is too early. BeginPlay() may
race. By racing what I mean is that. we
may or may not have possessed at BeginPlay(). and we don't want to take that
risk. We want to explicitly only do this once the SetPawn gets called.
OK. so that's the structure for you! Right now. given that layout.
what I'd like you to do is to go ahead and setup the whole delegate system. as much as you
can. For beginners this may be a bit much. For advanced people. you may get it done.
Use the crib-sheet on the previous slide. I'll leave that up in a minute.
Register the TankPlayerController and the TankAIController. to receive OnDeath.
By the way. if you want to reduce the scope of this challenge. just forget the TankPlayerController.
just do the TankAIController. that I've already started. At least get the TankAIController
done. Now you want to receive that event. from their possessed tank. like I've already setup for you.
and then. log to prove that we're getting the message. OK. so we just want
a log entry when our tank dies. When the AI tank dies. you may have a bit of fun trying to kill the AI
tank. as a minimum. and you want to log to say. OK cool. it's dead!
And if you want the extra challenge. then go ahead and do the same for the PlayerController. So pause
the video and see if you can get that working now! I'm going to leave up on the screen this
recipe for you.
OK welcome back! So given our recipe there. let's go ahead
and see what we need to do. So on the tank. we
need to firstly underneath here... Hopefully
you found this in the documentation above the class. We need to DECLARE_
DYNAMIC_MULTICAST. and unfortunately you get no help
here. from the auto-complete. DELEGATE. And I'm just going to call it
(FTankDelegate). that's the type. and you
do. unfortunately. need a semicolon; we never know with these things but in this case we do need
one. OK. now it's going to be a public thing here. and
it's going to be of type FTankDelegate. and then. it's going to be On
Death. OK. so this OnDeath here is something that
we can actually. in the C++ class. call. we can broadcast on.
OnDeath.Broadcast(). instead of logging out to say the tank's dead.
we just say Broadcast OnDeath and then let all the listeners
or observers decide what they're going to do with that.
OK. so we say OnDeath.Broadcast(). Let's make sure the code compiles to this stage.
and while it's compiling. I'll show you what has changed
on the Tank. Just that. OnDeath.Broadcast(). in place of the log message.
and on the tank header file. above the class. we have declared DYNAMIC_
MULTICAST_DELEGATE and the type and then FTankDelegate OnDeath. OK. so that has
compiled. but of course. at this moment. we are not going to know whether it's working.
So to know whether it's working. we're going to need to go into the TankAIController.
and then. we're going to need to subscribe our local method. So how do we do that? Well let's
go back to your recipe! We've done this. we've done this. and we've even done that. so we're now below the
line. We need a DelegateMethod(). a UFUNCtION() DelegateMethod(). so let's do
that to start with! So it's going to be a private method. Remember I said it has to be a UFUNCTION().
if I can spell it right.
in order for it to work. And then. what name do we give it? Well what does it say in the
recipe? We call it the DelegateMethod().
I mean that's what I've called it. but OnTankDeath is one thing you could do. I'm going to say
OnPossess. to be really clear. TankDeath. So our
local method is going to be OnPossessedTankDeath(). OK.
and that is what's going to get called. We have to have a method here. so
let's make this OnPossessedTankDeath() directly below the SetPawn. I think. so we can see it.
And then. to turn that into a definition we just need to.
of course. put the class name in front and some squigglies.
OK. so now we have somewhere in memory that we can
go. i.e. here. in order to use
or in order to handle the Delegate. when it gets called. So how do we do this? We say
BroadcastingInstance OnSomethingHappened. So the BroadcastingInstance I set you
up with. that's the PossessedTank.
OK. so we have the Broadcasting
Instance. Now. once the auto-complete's there. if we look through the BroadcastingInstance pointer
and type on. we should have an OnDeath.  You see with all these other
engine things. OnActorOverlap. we've got OnDeath! Ah. that's pretty
cool! So PossessedTank OnDeath. then what do you do? BroadcastingInstance OnSomethingHappened
.AddUniqueDynamic. Now warning. the system is
not going to give you AddUniqueDynamic. unfortunately. as an auto-complete. you're going to have to type it yourself.
AddUniqueDynamic() on this. and then. we need the function name. So we just put a
ampersand in front of this stuff here.
OK. and that has now subscribed
us! It said OK. here's the instance. it's got this OnDeath delegate that gets
called. We're going to add a UniqueDynamicRegistration for it.
and we're going to handle it. using this method here. So to finish off. all
we need to do is log. to say that we're receiving this.
Just say ("Received") like that! OK. let's see
if that works! I'll get it compiling! I'll remind you. while we're compiling.
of what we've done! We've made on OnPossessedTankDeath(). UFUNCTION() method
here! We've done our subscription
so I can get rid of the TODO here. where we tell the possessed tank
where to go to handle the death event. and then. we're just logging to say received. OK.
so now what's got to happen. firstly. is I need to open the tank blueprint.
Save let's compile. It might crash.
It's crashed because we've made a fairly fundamental change to the tank blueprint. and sometimes
that causes crashes in the engine. so that's not uncommon.
So let's reopen the tank blueprint. I'm just going to make sure it does compile.
I'm not going to play the game! So the
tank didn't appear to be aiming there. Let's go look at the tank blueprint and just make sure
that it still has an AI class. and indeed. it does not have an AI
class. So let's reset the the TankAIController there. Compile. and Save the
blueprint. and let's just play again! And I'm hoping that he'll now aim at me.
which he does appear to be doing. One strategy for just destroying the enemy tank is to get
so close he can't find an aim solution and then he won't fire. because he's too
keen to be precise. You need to be close enough that you can hit him. of
course. but not so close that he can fire at you. And then. what you can do. at this stage. is
keep firing at the enemy tank until it's dead. watching its health bar
go down and its jitter. making any notes about any changes to your effects
you want to make. at this point. and now we want to keep an eye on the Output Log. There we go!
"Received!" Fantastic! So we actually have that
event system working. and there's no reason we can't just go straight ahead and do exactly the same thing
on the PlayerControlledTank now. But let's do that in another video. because this one's plenty long enough!
So hopefully this diagram makes a little more sense now. You've had an
overview of how this works. a fantastically useful general system. You can use it.
for example. for achievements in your game. you know. when you get those unlocks pop up on your
console or even your Steam achievements. That can be done like this. there's a lot of things that can be done like
this. Please go and read Game Programming Patterns. as linked in the resources.
this Observer Pattern. Have a browse through this. don't
expect yourself to necessarily to understand all of it but it's a pretty good overview.
and I will see you in the next video!