Welcome to Finishing Off Part 2! In this video we are
going to make our ground undulate a little bit more like this, so it's a bit more interesting,
up and down all over the place. And we will introduce a
new mortar type, which one of our students Robert Woo has provided for us.
You can see it proudly sitting on the top of the hill there, much more attractive than the one I provided.
We'll also make sure that that mortar can be fired into oblivion if we
hit it, which I didn't, and we will be
generally tidying up and finishing off our work. So I will see you in there!
OK, so we've knocked off three of our pick and mix challenge, let's look at the next
one! Use the noise landscape function to undulate... Oh,
there's an example of me working too hard for try and make something fit on one line
of slide. So let's go and take a look at the Landscaping
Tool [Laugh] and then Click on the Sculpt Tool. So
you go to Modes, Landscape, Sculpt, Sculpt Tool, and you get
to Noise eventually. Now let's just do a little test. What I want to do is
make this landscape less flat. OK, so that is clearly
too much undulation, so I'm going to turn the Tool Strength down
to 0.02, quite low really. Noise Mode, Both directions,
it's going to raise and lower the terrain. Noise scale, that's the
size of the perlin noise filter. Let's just try a few different things. So this is a 15
NoiseScale there, if you look at what it's done to the terrain, and then, if I go to half
way up, let's just take a sample here, very different
wave length, basically, of undulation. And if I went really big,
then I'd think we'd find that you'd hardly even see the undulations. Alright, well I
think that, given those three, I'd like the one in the middle the best. So I'm just going to undo,
go to the middle somewhere, and then, I might just make the brush a little smaller,
and then, I think I'm just going to give the landscape
some noisy treatment. Let's go ahead and do it. So do the same with yours, just
make it noisy. You'll see these component divisions just come up in the land, as
you do this. I actually may need a little bit more strength. Let's have a look at see what it looks like
down at the ground level. No I think it's OK, it's just giving a natural
kind of slightly slightly undulating feel to it. I think I'll go to
0.03, bearing in mind that's a 50% increase in the
Strength. That should be enough! And actually, why am I messing around with such a small
brush? Let's just go to the biggest brush we can get our grubby mitts on! OK
there you go! Oh, that's too much!
Now look, you can spend a lot more time than I'm going to,
because watching me do this is not the most amount of fun you'll have ever had,
but the idea is to introduce a little bit of undulation, a little
bit of change and uncertainty in the landscape, so that we're not driving around
on a flat plane. And try not to get too many
artifacts of the tool in there like that, so if you have the tool too strong when you
click around on it, you're going to get these artifacts come in. Let's
try this, this looks a bit more crazy to me. OK, remember you need
to come out of the Landscaping Mode, or it just doesn't work properly.
I'm grabbing my controller, that's what the clutter was, and here we go! There is a tank down in the
valley there, let's boost him! Oh I can't, because he's below my
aim capability! Who's going to reload first? He is! Uh oh,
I'm in trouble! OK, but look you get the idea straight away. It's much more interesting
when you've got this undulating landscape. So that's what I want you to do, is
one of the things, is go and make your landscape undulate. Now, the other thing I notice
about my landscape, I think I'm going to go to a top view, is that if we look
for the NavMeshBoundsVolume it's too small, so let's just make that larger.
So NavMeshBoundsVolume there, and with the appropriate
place, you should be able to drag it. If you can't drag it like that, just go to its Details and
just change its X and Y size up appropriately. So let's just reset its
position there, and then, just make it bigger
than the landscape.
And that's great! OK, so now if we go back to the Perspective and
hit P for Show and what that will do
is show Navigation. P hits show Navigation like that, in a single fell
swoop. So how's that looking? Well the problem actually is
that the NavMeshBoundsVolume is not deep enough now. You see that the AI tanks will never be able to get
into the bottom of these holes, so we do need to go and reselect the NavMeshBoundsVolume.
You need to pay attention to the three dimensionality of it, and we do need to make it deeper.
So I'm going to make it quite a lot deeper, and now, we need to
probably have a look from one of the sides and say, well how's that looking?
Well it's looking OK, I would say. It needs to be lower, as an offset.
There you go, now it goes into the bottom of all the holes and crevices in the ground!
Now let's let the calculation recalculate. And it
should be able to get, apart from the very steepest bits of slope, which is fine, it should now
give us the situation where your AI tank can get from any part of a landscape
to any other part, perhaps apart from these deepest crevices like this one here.
So that should be fine! Let it finish calculating your navigation, and that part of
the challenge is done! Of course, mine is very very rough and ready, but you get the
idea. The NavMeshBoundsVolume needs to extend in three dimensions into
the areas where you want that tank to be able to go. Probably not right to the top of your biggest hills,
probably, yes, down to the bottom of your deepest valleys,
and that is kind of what you're looking for. And you can always verify things in like a Left View
or a side view, etc. So give yourself a little bit more
Z height, if you need to, play around with it
till eventually it fills in to where you want it to be. Bear in mind, in the Left View here, you
don't get to see everything necessary, so you may need it higher in Z than
you think you do, in order to get the ground level in. OK
cool! So that's going through calculating one final time and then that
will be done! So while that's calculating, let's go look at the next thing! Make the AutoMortars damageable. OK,
so when it comes to mortars, our students have provided some mortars for us. If you look
against this lecture, in the resources, we have a Student AutoMortar as a .zip file.
In there, I'm going to use Robert Wu's. The other guy's will also work. They're different styles
for you, but they will maybe need some changes to the import settings, I'll show you
as we go through. So if I grab Robert Wu's pack here, I'm probably just going
to export this .zip first, actually, because if we don't it may not
drag into Unreal properly. So there you go, that's exported! Robert Wu, and there's some
.fbx's. So I think what I'll do is just grab the
base, for a start, and just drop it into the Mortar folder in Unreal here,
something like that. That brings up an import dialog. I'm going to leave
the Import Rotation and Translation the same, but you may need to change that for the other models.
Import All and there we go, we have a different base to the mortar.
So now, if you go into the Mortar Blueprint, go to the Body, you can now
come in and say, well OK let's go find Robert's base, and there it is!
OK that's cool! So that's done that bit and now we have that base,
and of course, you're going to need to go to the base and create a socket
in it. Now I'm going to do this by eye, it's called Dome, the socket,
or was it turret? I don't remember but we'll change it if it's not right. Then, you move that up
to the middle of the base like that and Save.
OK cool, so next bit! We need to go down to the Dome
and we switch that out. Now, of course, Robert's dome isn't imported, so we just go find
both the turret and the barrel, the turret being the dome,
and you drag them into the Mortar folder.
I Import All and then, we've got those
models now! Now, on our mortar, we can go to the Dome and we can switch that out for
very fancy looking triple gun dome thing there.
There you go! And we had got the socket name right and it does look like it's sitting
about right, possibly a tiny bit low, but I think we'll roll with that!
OK, and then the Barrel, finally! So now, we need to go find Robert's
altogether superior triple set of barrels, somewhere in here.
There you go! And then, of course, on the Dome itself, we need to go to the model,
we need to go and create ourselves
a socket called Barrel.
I'm not entirely sure where that socket needs to be in Robert's model, so I'm going to try just
somewhere like this. I'm not sure,
has Robert provided any instructions? Let's have a look! No, not a text file. So it is helpful, by the
way, if you're making models, like I think John did, to make a read me which talks about the attachement
points. But that doesn't matter, we can look at these attachment points. I'm super grateful for everybody's
work, it really doesn't matter. And there you can see that,
actually, it's the left-hand barrel socket I need to be aiming at, plus I need to be a little bit farther
forward. So remember, that when you do this, you can when you're
specifying a barrel here, on your socket manager, you can choose a
preview mesh, and that' makes a lot of sense. So let's go choose that preview mesh there.
Now it's much more easy for me to position that barrel, much more
precisely, because I can see the result without having to flip back and forth
to the blueprint as a whole.
OK, so if I now just go for something like that, I can even preview in here
the idea, well I can preview certainly over on the Mortar,
the idea of rotating these barrels. Now this Barrel socket
has changed, so we need to just reparent the socket there. While I'm at it, I might
as well make sure that that's correct. Cool! Now let's just rotate these guys,
and they're pretty close, I would say. Fantastic! So what else do we need to check? We need to check that
the AimingComponent still has a projectile, which it doesn't. And we should
be good to go, it's all facing down positive X. Let's try it! Let's drop
without P. I'm going to hit P to get rid of that in the scene. Let's drop Robert's into
the scene. I'm just going to work out where the Player Start is, so it's quite close to us,
and let's drop one of Robert's Mortars right here. End Key remember,
snaps things to the ground level. Let's play the game!
Now I didn't save, so the Mortar blue, if it does crash here, which it shouldn't
with all our ensure assertions, but if it does crash, I'll lose something in the Mortar Blueprint. That's
OK. I don't like how long that took to run, so I'm just going to see if there's an ensure
that's failed. Indeed there is, there's a PossessedTank
ensure that's failed. So I'll just get rid of the tank in the scene
and just focus purely on the Mortar, for now. Clear this
Log, play again. OK let's have a look! Is this mortar...
Ah, look how good that looks! Thank you very much, Robert, that looks pretty
awesome! So the final thing is, it's kind of hitting itself, and this is way beyond
your challenge, call of duty, by the way. Of course, I'm doing a load more here, and the
reason it's hitting itself is that the Barrel, we don't have a
projectile socket on it yet.
So it needs a proper Projectile socket on, I'll move that
to the middle barrel and slightly ahead of the barrels,
and that should sort of the firing. Let's have a go!
It's looking really sharp, as far as I'm concerned, that Mortar.
Boom! And it can hit us! Awesome! So finally, to make that thing
damageable, all we need to do is go to the Mortar, to the Body of the
Mortar, simulate some physics. I'm going to give it a massive, I don't know, this looks like
about a 10 ton to 10000 barrel to me. Give it
some Linear and Angular Damping, if you like. Leave Gravity
off, because it's just going to sit on the ground, and that should be enough, just those changes there.
You can see what I've changed, by the way, by where the little yellow resets are. They're the things
that I've changed, it helps you guide your eye. OK, so let's just save
everything, play the game, and see what
happens if I shoot now, this mortar. Well firstly, it's not
doing so well. He's had a bit of a problem there, so let's just see if
he just may have been colliding with the ground. Let's try again, moved it up a little bit.
That's better! And if I shoot this guy, what happens!
Well let's see! Boom, now he goes absolutely flying
off! Well that's not damage to such, but he has gone
completely disappearing. I think he may be too heavy. If he was lighter than that,
he'd disappear at even higher speed. So you might be asking now, well why don't I just
implement damage ability in the same way as we did on the tank? Well we could but I don't
think it's really necessary, because I want to show you the feature of Unreal that if this
mortar goes flying off to a sufficient distance, like imagine it was only 100 kilos
when we hit it, then see what happens. I want you to see that it actually does
clear up objects for you, when they get to an unreasonably large distance
away in the world and there's not chance of them coming back. Let's see that in action!
So I'm now going to try again, try and get a nice direct hit on this mortar.
I think is quite funny that it then goes absolutely boosting off. If
you then depossess and then go
and inspect, by going to the World Outliner, that mortar if you can find it somewhere
in here, you can always do a search by the way, you'll see that that mortar
is still flying away and the reason
it's stopped and hanging in the air here is because of the Linear Damping.
So if we are to get rid of Linear Damping on the mortar altogether...
We could even get rid of Angular Damping, actually. There's no reason this thing should
just go flying off wildly. I was only putting those in out of habit, because real things have
those. Now let's just hit it again! Boom! And that goes
absolutely flying, up into the air, [Laughs] very funny!
Now what happens to it? Let's track it! Let's go to F8 to
depossess. The World Outliner, let's go find that mortar! Ah, it just got deleted! Too late!
Oh no it didn't, that was a different object. Here you go! Now here's the mortar.
If you look at it's details it's miles and miles away, now let's look at this location.
It's just moving further and further away from us,
and what you'll find, if you wait a little while is that that mortar will actually get to a threshold where
it's completely deleted. It's already out of range, it already can't find an aim solution.
It's not really causing us a performance problem right now, because it's so
far away that it's not going to be rendering, it won't be able to find an aim solution,
so we're just waiting for that mortar to get to a point where it gets deleted now. So I'm going to just
use that as the very basic solution to making the mortars damageable.
What I'd like you to do later, once you've done the next section of the course, and
maybe even further content than that, is to loop back here and think about creating some sort of
damageable interface, that could apply to both the mortar and the tank, but that's a little bit
beyond the scope of this section. So that's how I'm going to do it and that makes the mortar
disreputable and ejectable and not damageable as such, but we can
certainly get it out of here so it doesn't do us anymore harm. Just boost it completely out
of the world, that's a lot of fun! So the final challenge was to look through the Unreal coding
standards and make sure we're complying with it. I think that, in general, we're doing very well up to
the point that it talks about Comments, at least, which is all I wanted you to get
to, just up to here, not even going into Const correctness. The only thing is,
it does talk a fair amount about bools and what we need to do about bools and how you name
boolean methods, but unfortunately, the engine itself breaks those
rules. So in methods like this, if we just search
for "bool" GetSightRayHitLocation, it's not obvious
that the bool is saying yes I've succeeded or no I've failed. But if
you look at the methods that surround that, that the engine actually uses they go like this,
they behave like this, and they don't use the B prefix, and they don't start
with is. So what the coding standard says is that
properties that are boolean should start with b, lower case b,
it's the only variables that do start with lowercase, and methods should start with the word is,
but with this case, we're breaking the rule with these HitLocation and  hit vectors, because I
think it reads a little bit better and, as I say, they break the rule in the engine themselves.
So everywhere else I think we're doing OK. IsBarrelMoving is an
is question, bHaveAimSolution in a property here starts with a b.
So in general I think we've fairly well complied with the coding standards, there's probably one or two little things
that don't, but you know the point is to get 95% the way there and I think we've
done that. So well done, that game's shaped up really nicely, and
I will, in the next video, challenge you to come
back here and continue to improve and develop this game, once you've learned some more tools
from the next section!