Phew!! That was a long section wasn't it?! Well congratulations
on getting to the end of it! I've needed to keep this section within 100 videos
for various technical reasons. to do with the way we produce videos. But actually. it's just
about exactly the right time to finish this section but not to finish the development
of the game. Let me explain what I mean by that. When you do the
next section. I'm going to want you to come back and continue to add to Battle Tank.
and I'm going to want you to do the same thing with Building Escape. which I'll talk you through in a moment.
So firstly. let's just recap what we've done in Battle Tank! We've worked on
landscapes. terrain. you saw a trick for making low poly terrain. We've talked
about NavMesh Bounds Volumes. we've talked about making noise
in the land and raising and lowering terrain. a whole bunch of stuff like that.
We've look at the AI system or at least had a little glance into that. and we've already
modified the AI system. intercepting that RequestDirectMove call there.
so that the tanks. driven by the AI. have to move just like our
player tanks do. which makes things super fair. If you just let the AI drive it. on its own.
these tanks move around in a really kind of robotic rigid sort of way. which is not
great. You've learned User Interface for the first time. so please go back
to Building Escape and add some User Interface. You've learned a lot more about C++ and
Blueprint and what goes where. right. Hopefully you feel now that you know when
to do things in C++. basically most of the time. and when it's appropriate
to be using Blueprint. when you're referencing assets or when you're doing something that's very visual
by nature or UI related. And finally. you've learned a whole ton more
C++. Congratulations on that! It's a tough language. it's a tough engine. you've done
really really well! And hopefully you've even had a whiff of game architecture. you understand
a little bit more about what it takes to put a more complex game together. So what I'd
like you to do now. as a final challenge is. just before you go into the next section.
go and dust off Building Escape for me. And I've got a few little notes over there. as to what
I'd like you to do. So number 1. consider putting your project under version control.
Get setup under Git. now that you've got some idea how to make that work. Add a
Start Menu to at least Building Escape. so you don't just dive into the game like
that. Create at least one new puzzle. using something you've learned in this section.
I don't mind what it is. whether it's the line tracing or whether its
something to do with AI. i don't mind. but make another puzzle and show us what you've made
over in the community.gamedev.tv forum. And we'd love to see how you've
improved Building Escape. it feels great to go back to those old projects and improve them.
Add some landscape around the room. the rooms just sitting there. floating in mid air. Why not
put a landscape around it this time?! And consider a projectile based
puzzle. I'm saying. add another puzzle. One of those things you could do is use projectiles. maybe have to
hit a switch on the wall. something like that. and maybe you could even make some improvements
to the overall code and architecture of the game. So please go back.
spend a little while. As long as you've like. I don't mind if you spend half an hour or half a
month going back and improving Building Escape. but that will really cement your learning. because
it's easy. kind of easy to follow through Battle Tank just doing what
I do. like monkey say monkey do. And that's great! I'm sure you're
doing the challenges. I really hope you are. but even going through and doing the challenges
is not quite the same as completely reapplying that knowledge to a previous
[Ooh. I'm wanted]. to a previous  project. So. I hope
you've enjoyed the section. Go improve Building Escape. and then. I'll see you in the
next section!