Hi and welcome to Zombie Runner! So.
this game is a little bit more of a Sandbox Game. it's not a complete game.
I'm just showing you the essence of what you're going to need to create a First
Person Shooter. The reason for that is. we've already covered Menu Systems
and a lot of other things. by this stage in the course. and I want to focus on
the things that are different about this type of game. So. we're going to be looking at
Pathfinding. We're going to have an animated third person character.
running around. chasing you. We're going to be looking at terrain and environments for the
first time and various other useful tools! So. dive into
the section. and I'll see you at the end!