I am so excited about this zombie game that I need to put a dampener on it! This is
like the game developers equivalent of a
cold shower! So, just before we dive in,
I am going to read the Unity 5.1 Change
Log, so we're going to be talking about unity 5.1
features in this video. So, what I want to
do is make sure you have unity 5.1 or
later installed, briefly talk about
what was new in Unity 5.1, and why we're
using it in this section. So, let's just
take a little look. This is also a bit of
a lesson in how to read change logs. So, here we go. This is Unity telling us about what's in
a later version. Every time a new version
of Unity comes out, I think it's worth
you taking a quick look at the release
notes. This is how I read release notes.
I flick over them first.
Literally overview first, and general
process of overview, in view, review is
a good idea. Bear in mind, when you overview like this, your brain is going to pick out
the big things like the graphics far more
readily than that awkward little line in there
somewhere, that makes a massive
difference to your projects. So, know
that when you do an overview you are
getting a very biased overview of what
you're looking at, because it's going to be
weighted by the graphical and hence
informational density. And then, I do a
in view, so overview, in view, review.
So then, I look through and see what's
the general point. So, there's a multiplayer
networking feature! Fantastic! We'll use
that! That saves us from using services
like pars, hopefully, if it works well? Pars is fantastic, it does let you create
online scoreboards and cloud-based data
sharing, but let's give Unity's Multiplayer
Networking System a go, if it will
support what we need it to do. So, some
new network components, some improvements to the Oculus Rift, although still haven't got
support for the Mac at the time of
recording. A new HDR color picker. That's cool,
High Dynamic Range! So, some new stuff to do with text compression, and other stuff
like that. So there are Community Analytics improvements here, so once your game is
out there, you're going to be able to,
provided your users allow you to, track some
more interesting things. which is
going to be great. You'll notice that
when you start Unity 5.1 a couple of
things happen, and number one, it's
obviously talking to the server. You
can see that bar going across the top
there. It still will work offline, I'm
confident of that. In fact, let me show
you what the experience is if we are offline. I'm just going quit Unity.
I'm going to callously pull out my network
cable, you can't see that I've done that,
but I have done that. And then, I'm going
to reopen Unity now, and this will fail
to talk to the server and it'll say
work offline. So, there's a difference.
That's fine but just note that it's
different. I'm plugged back in. The other
thing you'll notice when you try and open a previous project, even though you're
previous project may have been in a
previous version of Unity 5, it
will still want to do a rebuild, which. is going to take a few minutes or a few seconds
depending on the size of your project. So, take a back up before that. Of course, this
project, Zombie Runner, has absolutely nothing in it. I just have an empty project.
So, there's that. It's always worth
reading the backwards compatibility
breaking changes, so there are a few
changes to the Animator. You'll see more
of that later, so if you're upgrading a
previous project, particularly say Glitch
Garden, you may well find you need to
make some minor tweaks to the animations,
to make them work. We haven't been using Hinge Joints, Motor Springs, et cetera, yet, so
this stuff shouldn't hurt you too much. Stuff under the physics and the Xbox One is irrelevant,
right now. Then, you can just look at say
the changes in general, lots of stuff to
the Animator, GI so on so on so on. Ok, cool!
Some improvements! Now, there's one improvement that caught my eye and its for the reason I
mentioned earlier, it's a big graphic
amongst a load of text, but it is
actually useful. You can now add motion
constraints to 2D rigid bodies. What does that mean?
Well, in something like Block Breaker, previously it would have been a pain to make the paddles stay in
a fixed Y position without jeopardizing the physics of the paddle. Now, if you wanted the paddle
to stay in a fixed Y position but to be
free, otherwise as a rigid body, you could
click this fixed Y position button, which is a new constraint. It has always been there for 3D
objects, but now, it's available for 2D.
That just caught my eye.
If you want to go back and play with the implications of that for Block Breaker...
Umm, lots of fixes. It's worth reading if you've got something you know is broken or if you've been
waiting for a fix. And some known issues.
It's always worth an eye over the known issues, as well.
Ok! So, that's it really. That's what is in
Unity 5.1. Why are we upgrading to Unity 5.1 now?
Just because it's the latest version, and we always like to use the latest and
greatest stuff. We may use its networking
features later in this project, but for
now, that's it. What I want you to do is
create yourself a new Unity project. You
know how to do that, by now. Call it Zombie Runner, and then, we're in the
same place and on the same page; we just have a completely blank Unity project. We're ready to
roll up our sleeves and create something
brand new and fresh.
So, I look forward to working with you.