Welcome back! In this video. we're going to be creating a terrain. So. we'll first
have you go and read the game design document. Then. I'll show you how to set up a
terrain. talk you through some settings.
and then. make your own. So. go read
the GDD first. you'll get a feel for where
we're headed. Write down your own ideas
about what you want to do in this game.
and then. share your ideas in the
discussion. So. pause the video. go find the
game design document. which is at the beginning of the
section. take a look come up with some ideas of your own that you want to include.
challenge yourself. and see you in a
second. So. over in Unity I have a blank
Zombie Runner project here. with
absolutely nothing going on. So. the first
thing to do is create a 3D object.
terrain. Fantastic! There it is. a big white
blob in your scene. There it is in the
hierarchy. and there it is in your assets.
So. that's absolutely wicked! So. when we
first set this terrain up. firstly.
there's not really enough space to work
with it in my windows here. so I'm going to
remove a few panes. You're welcome to do
the same if you like. I'm going to get rid of
the project. the console. and
the hierarchy. and then. save this
layout. which is in a slightly different
place in Unity 5.1. I'm going to save it as Terrain. Terrain Editing. there you go. or just terrain.
whatever. So. there you've got a much bigger layout. so I can see what I'm doing.
Now. the way I'm moving around this terrain. in case you haven't noticed Fly
Through Mode is as follows. you go into
the Scene View. right click the mouse
button or hold down both fingers on a Mac
Trackpad. and then. you can use A to go
left D to go right. Standard first person
controls. In fact. you can see it in the
middle of screen there. it's indicating with the little icon next to the
eye. And then. W goes forward S goes
backwards. and then. E and Q go up and
down. if you're lucky. And then. Shift makes everything go faster. Sometimes you
might find the E and Q. I'm finding that
it sometimes is acting on my terrain
settings over here. But generally. your Fly
Through Mode is a fairly reliable way of
moving around. in the game mode. while you're holding down the right mouse button. Cool! So. I've
accidentally tweaked the terrain there. It
doesn't matter if you do that. we can
always replace and fix the terrain later.
So. first thing is to decide on how big a
terrain you're going to want. This one is
500 by 500 World Units. and you can
see that by going into the Inspector. clicking on the little cog on the right hand
side. under Terrain where I'm pointing
now. and then. scrolling down to where it says
Resolution. Terrain Width. Terrain Length; it's 500 by 500 meters. When I've called for at least
600 by 600 and I've chosen that size.
because it's not much bigger than the
default. And yet. at normal running speed
of one of our characters it gives us a
whole minute of movement across this
terrain. if we were to get down there and
have a character controller. which you'll
meet later. run across this terrain. it would take
about a minute to get across.
Now. if you have a very fast machine or lots of memory. so more than say
8 gig of RAM and a pretty fast
machine. a quad-core or beyond then. you
might want to go up on this terrain size.
If you have a particularly slow machine.
you may want to go down. because you'll notice with terrain already. you see it's doing stuff in the
background. now. It's doing various
things that we don't need to worry about at the moment.
It's doing some clustering. invisibility
calculations. This is basically to do with
how Unity is going to reveal the terrain
to us. as we move across. It doesn't look
much like a terrain at the moment. it's rather boring
right. It's just a flat space. but pick
yourself a size. and that is something
that you do need to get right now.
because if you draw features on this
terrain. and then. you resize the terrain later. then everything will get stretched.
And it doesn't have to be square by the
way; it doesn't have to be 600 by 600. I'm just going
to go with a simple 600 by 600 to save
myself work. but if you want a more
adventurous world and you like to think
you're going to like creating worlds. feel free
to make this big... bigger. So. the first thing we're going to want to do is put some sort of
texture to this terrain. This plain white
is just. too. boring. So. click the middle
setting. for the moment. which is the
Paint Texture setting. and we're going to
need to go and get ourselves a texture.
Now. the place to get that is from the Asset
Packs. You want the Environment Asset Pack. so go to Assets. Import Package Environment.
Now. if for any reason you don't have that
Environment Asset Pack. you're going to need
to go and get it from the Unity store.
but you probably checked it when you
installed Unity. so you probably have
this pack. Import Package Environment.
So. it's going to decompress the package. pop up with a dialogue something like this.
I think we may as well take the whole lot.
If you do want to save some space.
on your project then. you could look a bit
more critically at this. and say well what do I
want? Do I need Cross-Platform Input? Not really. Do I need Environment? Yes. it's
all about environment. Do I need utility
stuff? No. not really at the moment. So. you
could if you wish. just take actually the
Environment Section by expanding out
your windows like this and just taking
environment. I'm going to do that. because
it's going to be smaller and quicker. But
again. if you're not worried about size
just import the whole lot. So. here we go!
It's bringing in some Standard Assets.
which are going to be really handy for getting a basic bit of terrain off the ground. So. let that happen.
You might be wondering what these other
things on here are. while we wait. These are
brushes. they're just different shapes with.
which you can paint on the canvas of your
terrains. And then. you've got a brush size.
which is that blue blur you see there.
That tells you how big a brush you're using.
and so that varies how large your
brushes are. And then. the opacity here tells
you how quickly you paint. so that tells
you if it's very high then. you
immediately go to fully opaque terrain textures.
And if it's very low then. you have to put a very transparent texture on. until you
go over the space lots of times. we'll see
that in a bit. And I'll talk about the difference
between opacity and target strength. but now that my import has imported. lets add a texture.
Now. you get two options. several options actually. You have the Tile Size of the
textures and the Default. if you're using your own terrains. Let's leave
that as default. Then. you have the option
for an Albedo and a Normal Map. so we're
going to go for the Albedo. And let's
look for something like grass. Grass Hill
Albedo. for example there. Ok! So. there we are. we have an Albedo Darkness
tile. And if we add that to our list then.
it's the first texture in our list of
brushes. and it automatically applies that to the entire terrain. So. if you
come down and then. have a little look
around... I'm just going to zoom in. It looks incredibly
tiled. but when you get up close it kind of
looks ok. It looks a bit repetitive.
But we're going to break this up a lot. But at
least we have a terrain we can see
better than the plain boring terrain.
that we had before. So. that is how you
get the base texture on there. You can add as many layers of textures as you want. so
if you then go back in here. and then
look down. you've got... a lot of these to
do with trees and stuff. but the other
thing you've got is Grass Rocky Albedo.
So. let's have some of that and add that to
the list. and let's also add the mud one. Ok.
Now. with the mud. you also notice if you put mud in the search. that you get a
Normal Map available. as well. So. let's do
that. let's select the Muddy Albedo.
but let's also select a Muddy Normal Map.
Now. let's see what that does briefly.
So. say you were to click over on this mud texture. because it's loaded with not
only a texture but a Normal Map. look
what happens when I make something muddy.
I choose Mud. by clicking on it there. I then. pick myself a brush. and I'll make
the size of it smaller. like this. so it's
reasonable. Now. the Opacity tells you how opaque
the texture that you paint actually
is. but it tells you how quickly it puts
the paint down. So. if I have a very low
Opacity then. it puts the paint down very
slowly. and I have to keep going over the
same area again and again. If I have a very
high Opacity. it immediately goes to
the Target Strength. and the Target
Strength tells you how transparent the texture is when you've
finished. So look. if I put a target strength
of 1 and an Opacity of 100. it
immediately goes to 100% mud. Wheres if I had a low Opacity and a high
Target Strength... And what it would do is
it would eventually go to
100% mud. if I rub in enough. So. I
actually like having a bit of a low
Opacity. it gives a more natural feel. and then. you can kind of brush on your muddy
areas. like this. Now. the mud will look
different to other stuff. a little bit.
Because it has a Normal Map. it may. to
your eye. look a little bit 3D. and
that's the purpose of a Normal Map. We
won't go into the details. right now. but
it should give it a kind of 3D look. Let's see  by turning off the
Normal Map. for a moment. There you go. look at the mud. now. it looks very flat. Now. go back
to the texture. and add the Normal Map. Can you see the difference? Let me move this out of the way.
I can. it makes it look really much more 3D.
While you're here. you could search the
Standard Asset Pack for normal. see whatever Normal Maps you have. but you'll find that for
ground stuff. rather than trees use only
the mud. Ok. So. just give it a more 3D effect.
So. that is how you paint your textures
on the land.
The other thing I want to show you.
before I let you loose creating your own
land is how to raise and lower the
terrain. So. bear in mind that. right now.
the terrain is the lowest height it can
get. So. if you try and hold down Shift
and click. you cannot lower the terrain.
but you can raise it. Ok and you have a
similar kind of setting here. with Opacity and brush size. So. you can raise
up the terrain where you want your hills. Now. if you want the whole terrain up. so
that you can dig valleys. and I do
suggest that you do this so that you
can actually dig down a little bit.
this is how you do it. You use the next
setting along. which is Paint Height. Now. what Paint Height lets you do. is say you
put in a target height of 50 and a very
high Opacity in a big brush. Then. you
paint and then. it stops; It caps it at
50. So. you could paint the whole texture like
this. or you could just say flatten to 50. and I actually think that 50 is probably a good place to be.
That means we can make holes that are up to 50 meters deep. That's pretty caverness. but
that's fine. So. I'm going to suggest that
you go to Paint Height. choose a height of 50 and
flatten your terrain. And that's just
going to determine how deep you can dig
into the terrain. when you go to the
Raise Lower Button and hold down Shift.
You're going to able to create cavities that are up to 50 meters deep.
Ok so. creating the shape and then
texturing kind of go hand-in-hand.
So. imagine I've textured this bit here.
What would I want? Well. the standard
thing would be. you'd kind of grab
yourself a rocky texture for the edges
here. Now. that brush is too big. and the
Opacity is so the Target Strength is too
high and the Opacity is too high. So. I
could start brushing a rocky texture
onto the sides of a hill like this. to
give it more of a kind of. more of a
rocky feel. You see. I'm doing is really
rough for now. because I'm going to challenge you to make your own terrain. in a minute.
And then. what you might want to do in your depressions. not your depression.
is to paint some mud. maybe in the bottom
of your dips. Yes. and maybe a rocky surface
on the vertical surfaces and some mud in
the bottom. If you've still got remnants of
something like that. and you can't get rid of
it. that's because you need a Target Strength
of 1. so that you completely overwrite any
underlying textures.
They're all slightly opaque unless you have a Target Strength of 1. The other thing of course you can do is.
make yourself some mountains. So. I
suggest you do that and that's that.
Now. what I would like you to do is make
hills all the way around the outside. Now. the
reason being is that when you're down on the ground. one of the tricks that
games use. so that you can't tell that
there's an edge to the world is that
they raise up the ages of all the world. Let me just do this over here. for
a second. And you just need to do it enough that when you're down at eye height.
which is about two meters off the ground. that you can't any longer see the end
of the game world. So. this is really
rough. just to show you the idea. If I had
hills all the way along there... you want them all the way around the outside of your terrain.
And look what happens when I get down to eye height. Watch the edge of the world and the
horizon there. See if you've got
sufficient height. You can't see the edge
of the world. it looks like it's going on
forever. now. Yeah. especially if you've got
terrain up here and over here.
Cool hey! So. what I want you to do is to
create your own to terrain. Now. remember in
the GDD you know what's going on. you want to be able to run away from
these zombies. You can't have overhangs.
remember. that's one of the limitations of
Unity's Terrain system. is that it's
impossible to make something above
something else. It's a pure height map.
every part of this is just at a particular
height. but go ahead and make yourself
your own terrain focusing on raising and
lowering. flattening if necessary.
Smooth Height. if you're wondering. just
smooths things out if they're looking too jagged.
And then. use this paint texture to paint on
some broccoli texture. which remember you load
through edit textures. And some mud. maybe in the bottom of your pits and just randomly
where you want it and just standard
grass in other places. So. if I want to
get rid of this nasty patch here. I go 100%
grassy texture. and you see I can tidy up.
Ok. so that's your challenge! Make this
terrain your own. make it interesting!
It doesn't really matter how it is. just
make sure it's got some dips and some
various hills and things like that. Remember. you're going to have zombies
running at you from all different places. We
want places for them to spawn. We want places
for you to spawn. We want places for the
helicopter to be able to land. So. go ahead
and set up your own terrain. and have a
lot of fun with it now. using these
first four terrain tools. that you've
just learnt about. There's your challenge slide.
Fantastic! How did you get on with your
terrain? What were your challenges? I would
really like you now to zoom out of your terrain. Once you've made it to this stage.
even if it's the most basic terrain. then
take a screenshot. and save that
screenshot and put it over in the
discussions for us. That would be
fantastic if you could do that. If you
don't know how to save your screen shot.
well. there's lots of programs to do that. Most systems. Mac and PC. allow you to do it
built into the system. or you can use a
fantastic system like Snag It here or
one of many other free tools. But let's
get you saving your screenshot and
sticking it in the discussion. so that we
can see the shape of your terrain.
So. it should just be shaped and basically
textured. We'll worry about trees and
other features a little bit later. and I
shall do my terrain in the next video.