So now. we're equipped with an
inescapable terrain and a first person
controller to explore it with. Let's start
placing trees and details. In this video...
How to place trees on your terrain. how to
paint grass details. about grass
and billboards. and the performance impact of grass. So. let's get
into the terrain. double click on it
maybe. dive in. and start taking a look at
a couple more of these terrain settings.
So. we've already covered raising and
lowering. Painting Height and the fact
that's very similar. but it clamps the
height to whatever you choose here. You
can also flatten your entire terrain in one
button. if you want. Dangerous! [Laughs] Smoothing Height. which we haven't done. but
that just smooths out bumps in the terrain. which you may want to do at some point. Can be
quite nice to smooth the mesh out. Painting textures. we've already talked about.
You can have different textures. you can add them on top of each other.
I haven't textured up my terrain very much
yet. but you might well have already done
yours or be in the process of it. I might want to kind of paint these mountains. like this.
Slap it on. Ben. don't worry about the style! So. you get the idea.
Yep. so that was the painting. So. new stuff! Place trees! So. notice if
you click Place Trees that it says: "No trees defined." You need to Edit Trees and
Add a Tree. Now. it's going to ask you for a tree prefab. so provided you've got the
Environment Package installed. you should have some prefabs. What should we go for. for a
zombie theme? I'm going to go for broadleaf trees. mainly. in this game.
That's a mobile one though. so Conifer Desktop or Broadleaf Mobile? Which one should
we go for? I'm going to go for Conifer Desktop. There you go. And you can add that. and it just adds
it to the list of trees here. Ok. Then.
what you can do is go and find
yourself a bit of terrain. You choose
your Brush Size and you choose your Tree
Density. You can randomize the tree
height. Let me make this Inspector bigger.  You can
randomize the tree height here. and you can choose a range in which you randomize it.
You can lock the width and height. which kind of keeps them in proportion. You can
choose a color variation there. if you
want.
and you can just start painting trees. Look at that! Pretty cool. hey! I mean I've gone a bit
nuts. but that's the idea. You can just
start painting trees down on the terrain.
It takes a little while to do it and to compute it. but once they're down they're down.
Ok and that's pretty cool. as long as
you're still on the tree at all. Oh. gone a bit nuts there.
You can also Mass Place Trees. and
if you click on Mass Place Trees what
that's going to do is it's going to just
place. into the whole terrain. maybe
1.000 trees. Let's do that.
not keeping the existing trees. There you go. we have a forrest. [Laughs] Now. your performance is going to
really start to suffer. but at least. if you get
yourself down into the game view. look at this
we're really... Oops. excuse that.  We're really starting to get some of Unity's leverage now. Look at this! I mean
Ok. it's all of it one type of tree and the performance might suffer. but look at all the work
that's being done for us by this engine here. Pretty awesome. Ok.
So. actually I quite like the idea of
Mass Placing Trees. I think 1.000
may be too many. so I'm going to do an undo here. and get rid of those thousand trees.
But I am going to mass place. myself. say 200 trees. not keeping the existing.
because that's just a quick way of getting
a load of trees down. Now. you might say
well. what happens if I've got trees like on the top of the hill here. and I
want to get rid of the trees.
Well. it says "Hold down shift to erase trees". So. if you see trees somewhere you
don't want them. you can hold down Shift. get yourself into a position where you
can see the trees. hold down Shift. and
you can delete that type of tree. Ok so.
you can either mass place trees. like
I've just done and distribute them
around the terrain. or you can place them
individually by kind of painting them
as we have been or you can do some
combination of the two. And I'm not sure what tree is in
the bottom of the pond here. so let's get rid of them.
But let's just preview this from the
standpoint of the first person and
maximize. Ok. this will do. I mean you could spend a lot of time
making this prettier. but at least I have
some trees in the terrain. To reason the
terrain. [Laughs About Misspoken Words] What I'm wanting to do is show you the principle of placing trees.
If you want more types of trees you're welcome. and you can go across here. I'm not sure the palm
trees make the most sense. You could have a Broadleaf Desktop like that. and you
add it. Now. you suddenly have a second
type of tree there. and we could then. for
instance. Mass Place those broadly. So. we could have say 50 broadleafs. keeping
the existing trees. and then. when you go
into your world you'll find that you
have a mix now of broadleaf trees and those conifers. Ok so. it's pretty cool! So. we have
a mix of trees. I'm going to stick with that
for now.
Now. the second thing I want to show you.
in this part of the tutorial. is we go
over to the painting details. Now. you may be wondering about these brushes.
They're just different shape brushes.
Why you'd want a star shaped brush. I
don't know. but when it comes to painting
grass then. painting grass with something
like the one I've got selected there. at the
bottom right. makes sense. So. you might want
that brush. Add a grass texture. Now.
when you add grass texture. this dialogue
will pop up. You can choose the little
dot there. type grass in the search.
and which one shall we have? Let's have this guy here. Ok. And then. you can leave
all the details as they are. but
before you click Add. just notice
Billboard. And what Billboard does for you is as follows. It means that the grass. and you
may have noticed this in games. it means
the grass will always face you. That's what that's going
to do. Ok. So. if we go to scene view. start placing down some grass. Now. this brush that I've
chosen is quite good for placing down
grass. but be quite conservative with
the grass. Oops. hang on. I've come off onto terrain hiring. Ok.
Now. if you start painting and you think you can't see the grass.
that's because of your draw distance. and
it's Unity optimizing for the draw
distance. So. you're going to need to be
quite close to the grass. in order to
better see it. Now. you can change the draw distances...  Oops. be careful. because
sometimes it'll automatically click across to a Paint Height. instead of details.
Now. you can change how far into the distance Unity is rendering the detail. and it's
going to depend on how high you are off the ground and how much performance hit want.
But if you want to change it. you go to Terrain Settings. and you'll see Detail Distance here.
And if I turn it down. my world of detail
comes in. and if I turn it up. it goes out.
Ok. So. it's up to you. Depends how fast your machine is. how fast the target platform.
I'm going to make a draw distance of maybe 100 meters. Ok. So that's that. now back on
these Billboard business. If I come down
and look at this grass you'll find that.
whichever direction you look at it
from it always looks the same. It's a
Billboard that's always facing you. and you can't get around it and that's fine.
That's much better for performance. but it's just a bit weird so be aware of that.
Alright. so here I am back in the world. I'm in an area with no grass. right now.
So. I'm going to zoom right out and just make sure there's a little bit of grass
everywhere. Now. it's going to be difficult to know where you're painting
the grass from this distance. because of
the draw distance because
it includes the Z distance. So. if you're a Y distance rather. if you're up in the air then. it's
going to include that distance. and you
won't be able to see it even from the air.
Let me put my character here. FPS
Controller. Game Object... Move to View. There you go.
So. that was Game Object. Move to View.
and when I click Play.
my guy will be. kind of stuck in the ground by the looks of it. Let's zoom out a bit. Let's lift him up and across.
Ok. let's try him then. So. if you lose track of your game guy. of your GameObject then. just remember where the
middle of your terrain is. Maybe 200 by
200 by... ah sorry. 200 by say 55
height by 200. Try that and then. let's
see where we end up in the terrain now.
We just need to move ourselves; we'll go
find the grassy bit. So. what are the
coordinates of the grassy bit? Well. into
Scene View. go look at the grassy bit.
wherever it is. Here we are in the grassy
bit. Now. what are the coordinates
of where we are in the grassy bit here?
Well. one way to find out is you put an empty GameObject in the scene like that. and
you query to see where it is. Well. it's been created under the ground. but it's at
530 by 58. Ok. So. if I go to my FPS Controller and set it to
530 by 58. and then. play the game. he ends up here in the grassy bit. And he's got
that Draw Distance Limit on him. and you can see the grass
unfolding unfortunately but he's looking
pretty good. I think this guy might be a
little bit too tall for his own good actually. that's not really helping. So. in
the camera. which is attached to the FPS
Controller. instead of having a Y
position of the camera of 7 you could set that down to maybe 2 meters.
And let's see how that looks. that's a bit better. We're a bit closer to the ground. and the impact of that draw
distance is less noticeable. So. that's how you draw trees. that's how you draw features. Go ahead and knock
yourself out and detail up your own terrain now. and add some detail to your terrain.
Ensure it runs Ok regularly. by going
into the game view. Be subtle. think about
the game play. and enjoy putting
detail in your terrain. and when you're finished.
we'd love to see a snapshot in the
discussions.