Hey hey. welcome back! So. we're going to be adding a water table. and you are in for a treat.
because Unity 5 comes with beautiful water shaders built in. for free now! So. let's
take a look! We're going to be using Unity 5's wonderful water prefab to create a water
table in your terrain. Water table
meaning a height in the terrain below
which there is water. although you'll see
that it's just a surface. but let's take
a look. Dig down to create some water hazards. paint some mud under the water
surface even. and previewing the water from the ground. So. let's dive
into Unity and take a look at this. Under your Standard Assets under Environment.
if you've imported the package. which I
hope you have by now. you should
have Water and Water Basic. Go for Water Water. that's the folder we're looking for.
Standard Assets. Environment. Water. Water. and get a prefab. and we're going to go for
WaterProDaytime. I think for now. They look very similar. by the way. If you drag
that WaterProDaytime into the scene
and double click it. you'll see that it's
made a little circle. but it'll have made a
circle in completely the wrong place.
So. how high do we want this. for a start? Well. maybe 5 meters below our ground.
so in my case that's at 45. So. that's looking a little bit better. Now. we need to move it
into the middle of the terrain. So.
remember you can click the Y arrow to
look at the world from above. and then.
move it roughly to the middle of your
terrain. Look at your settings. remind
yourself how big your terrain is. if
necessary go to Terrain Settings 600 by
600. Ok. So. your water. and I'm just going to call
it Water Table. should be at 300 by 45 by
300. in my case. And if we use
the Transform Tool. we can confirm there
that it is right in the middle of the
terrain. Cool! So. the problem with it now is it's too small. So. what size does it need to be?
Well. if we want it to go out to these corners over here then. it's
going to need to have a radius of at
least 300. so 300 by 300.
I'm sorry. the Y direction doesn't matter. because it's just a flat circle. but 300 is going
to get to the edge here but it's not
going to get to the edges here. So. let's
do a little calculation. How are we going to find out how big it needs to be to
go to the edge? Well. it's going to be the
square root of 2. isn't it. If you're any good at
math. you'll know that it's going to be
the square root of 2. which is 1.4
times the 300. So. 425 will do. If we make a scale 425. in both directions.
X and Z.  Boom! Now. we have a water
table that is just as big as our terrain.
It just about touches the edges of the
terrain. and wherever the terrain is lower
than that. it will intercept the water
table. So. let's go right down to the
FPS Controller and have a quick look
around. to start with.
Now. if you've got any low-lying areas. like this big hole I'm heading over towards at breakneck speed
over here. then. you're going to be in for a treat in a minute. because we're going to get Unity 5's wonderful
water shader in our face. Look at that! And without even making any changes to the settings. it's already not looking half bad.
Look at that! How cool is that? And you can look back at the Sun and have lots of fun. Now. we're going to
improve the lighting. we're going to do all sorts of things. but I just wanted to show you how nice the
water shader actually is in here. So. what that's done is it's put a water circle underneath the
entire terrain. at a fixed height. Now.
anywhere that you decide to go and drop
the height of the terrain. now the water
will appear. which is what I meant by a
water table. So. you might want to create
some water hazards. some water areas. where
your zombies are going to attack you.
and you don't want them to get across the
water. So. as you drop the terrain. it will
automatically now create water
effectively. You're going to end up with some trees. So. remember you go to trees. and you hold
down Shift and you just delete trees
like that. Ok. And then. your FPS controller you may
want to move across into say the middle.
Where is the middle? 300 by 300.
Let's see where we end up. probably in
the water. Now. we're stuck underwater. Now. when
you're underwater. it doesn't look like you're under water. because it's just not how the renderer
works. And later on. we're going to put some colliders in. so that if we actually end
up in the water we die. but in the meanwhile. I just want to show you how cool this looks. hey. Really coming
together nicely. Now. there are some settings on your Water Table Prefab. let's look at it. It has a Water Plane Mesh.
which is slightly different to a Normal Mesh. It has some materials here. it also has a
Water Script. and you can choose whether
it's Reflective. Refractive.
or Simple. So. if you go reflective then. it only reflects off the surface.
I kind of prefer that actually. and I'm
probably going to leave mine reflective.
But if you do want to better see under the
surface. you can make refractive water. which is
even more complicated. Now. that will
reflect off the surface. but it will also
show into the water. It's up to you which one of those two you use. I've never seen water quite
this clear. so I think I'm going to just
go with reflective. The other benefit of
going with reflective is. if you're with
refractive then. you have to start going
in and painting under the water.
otherwise it looks silly. So. if we go to
this area here. it looks silly for there to be grass growing under the water.
You could of course go to your terrain. your Paint Tool. get your muddy widget here.
Maybe a smaller brush. and you could paint mud under the water surface. diligently in
all of your ponds. Now. if you've got the
patience for that. well then I commend you.
and that would be great and it would look a lot better. But if you look in there. it's still ridiculously clear water
isn't it? So. unless you've got a setting in the water for how clear the water is. I would suggest
you just go Reflective water. It's entirely up to you.
Alright and then. you can choose various other things. which I don't think
we need to be messing around with now.
You've also got some options under
WaterProDaytime here. which we can look at. but It's best off if we can see the game view.
So. I'm going to unmaximize on play. click play. go to the water's edge like so. Now. I can mess
around with the Water Scale. and that changes the Wave Scale of the water. In fact. I recommend
a slightly lower Wave Scale. So remember. if you make these changes in
Play Mode it's going to forget them when
you get out. And unfortunately. being a
shader you can't copy these things. so you're just going to need to remember them. So you've
got your reflection distortion here.
which is changing how much it's distorting
those trees. You see. if I put it down to 0.
you see how kind of glassy it is.
So. that's cool! Refraction Distortion is not going to make any difference here. because we've got a
purely reflective shader. Alright so.
that's the shader. which is the thing
which is responsible for choosing how
that surface of the water looks.
The water is actually just flat. and the
shader is very cleverly making it look
like it's not flat. So. play with the
properties of your water yourself. and
get your water looking how you would
like it to look.