Hey hey! In this video. we're going to awesome-ify you're scene lighting. So. I'm going to show you
how to move your scene view to your
character view. how to add fog to your
scene. add a lens flare to the sun. and
then add a flare layer to the FPS Controller Camera.
That was Chinese for camera. Ok fantastic! So. let's get on with all of that. Firstly. let's
imagine that you want to work on the sun and the lighting. and that you want to do it
by standing here and looking in between these two trees. And you get yourself to this position and you go.
well that's a cool place! Of course. if you stop playing or even move the mouse. you're going to lose
this position. So. Control or Command + Shift + P. to pause the game. and then you've got
this locked. Then. what you can do is. you
can go to your FPS Controller Camera
like that. Then. you can go to Game Object.
Once you're in the Scene View. you can go to GameObject.
Align View to Selected. Ok. And then. that
means that the Scene View is now the
same as that game view. as you left it. So.
that's a pretty handy tool for you. Ok. Let's
look at adding some fog to the scene.
to make this more ominous. In the Window
Menu under Lighting. now you've got a load
of scene lighting options in Unity 5.
Now. it's asking for the sun. If you don't select a sun then. it would assume the
brightest directional light you have is the
sun. but you may as well give it the sun
while you're there. It's only used for Procedural Sky Boxes. but I'm just setting it as I go past. The bit
we're looking at is fog. down here. so click Fog. I'm going to use Exponential
Fog. You can play with these differences.
it's a question of how fast the fog
comes on. as you go away from the camera. I'm going to go with Exponential Fog. of
the strength .02. Ok. Then. if you look
at that. inside the Game View. you can see
we have a foggy landscape.
Fantastic! So. what I want to do next to
improve the lighting is to add a lens
flare effect. Remember we're going to be
wearing a helmet. so we want to make it
feel like we're kind of looking through
a lens. So. you need two things for that.
you need to go to your Directional Light.
and then. add a lens flare. ok. to the
light itself. Now. when you go and try and select a flare. there is none.
and that's because it's in another asset
package. And the asset package you need
is the Effects Package. so import package
effects. Now. we only really need the lens
flare. but we don't know what the
dependencies are. So. I think that I'm
just going to go in and import the whole lot.
Now. your project might be getting rather
large by now. but hopefully you've got the space for it. This is the disadvantage of just
importing things willy nilly. but it does
speed things up and allow us to get
access to all of the cool fun bits on
Unity. So. now back on your Directional
Light. When you choose Lens Flare now. you'll have the option for a 50 millimeter zoom.
A flare. small. the sun. etc. Now. before we choose it. let me show you something. In the Scene
View. you've got this little preview
option here. and at the moment it's
showing flares. And you want to make sure there's a tick box in there. Your game camera will not
show the flare. even when you've added it. yet. So. let's go to the Directional Light and
add in a flare. Now. you need to make it
directional. so click directional. Ahh. there it  is!
Now. you can play with the brightness. Go really silly or you can go not so silly.
I'm going to make it quite strong. and you
can have different fade speeds. Well.
that has no affect. the way we're using
it. Ok. so I've got a brightness of say 1.5.
Directional Sunlight Flare. Now. do I want
sun. or do I want 50 millimetre zoom? I'm
going to go with the 50 millimetre zoom
here. because it has these extra light
camera effects. which is just a bit more fun.
Ok. so I've got a 50 millimetre zoom flare. it's a white flare. with a 1.5 brightness. Now.
you'll notice if you go to the Game View and play and try looking at the sun. you don't see the flare.
And the reason you don't see the flare
yet. is because the camera that you're looking
through on the FPS Controller does not
have a Flare Layer. It needs something
called a Flare Layer. for the camera to see it. It's got no settings Ok. but it's just a thing
that makes the camera process those flares in the scene.
Now. when you look at the sun. look at that. and isn't this why you got Unity out of the box. in the first place?
Not that it comes in a box. Maybe it should come in a box?
It would be much nicer if it came in a box! But look at that. the water. the sun flares. these camera effects. fog.
Ahh. what more do you want? You see. now you've done all of the hard
work of understanding how to script
behavior in Unity. We've got ourselves in
a position where we can start playing
with this stuff confidently. knowing that
when we need to go under the scenes.
behind the scenes rather and start
actually making behavior work properly
that we have the coding skills to do so.
So. well done getting yourself this far! Do
have a look at the other options in the
Lighting Panel. see if there's anything
else you want to change. But this stuff is
all quite detailed. like Maps and Precomputed Realtime Global Illumination. all this
type of stuff. Probably not stuff you
want to get yourself messing around with
right now. but just take a look for
inspiration. Take a look at the books if you like.
the little book. and do look up and see
what all this stuff means. at least on a
first pass. But the important thing that
you do right now. really is just tweak
your whole environment. Get it all how
you want it.
Remember it will change when you play
test the game. Adjust the height of your
terrain. your textures. your details. your trees. your water. your lights. etc.. and just have
fun with it. And I'll see you on the other
side.
Welcome back! So. I'm just going to have a
little tweak of my terrain and stuff now.
Make sure that this is going to be reasonably good to play. or at least make sure that it looks
like it is. So. I'm going to look at it
from above... zoom right out. Now. because I
can't see what the hell's going on. I'm
going to go to Window and Lighting
and turn fog back off again. at least for
now. And then. I'm going to be able to see my
terrain. One of the things I would like in my terrain is more depressed areas where we can
have water. to try and make life a
little bit harder for these zombies when
they come chasing us. So. I'm just going to
randomly cut into the terrain here. It's going to
be a bit strange. Ok. And then. you may
want to have many more mountainous areas.
I'm very very lean on mountainous
areas here. I might want to have some
sort of mountain range coming through. See I'm really just slapping it on here. and
I'm going to want you to spend a lot more
time doing this. The thing is. that I'm trying
to get the concepts across. and not all
of the... you know not spending absolutely
ages painting textures on here. etc. I do want to share a few general things with you.
One is. remember use your terrain editing layout. if you want extra space. Secondly.
as a general rule. when you're first
getting into terrains it's
useful to have this kind of half grassy
half rocky texture on any of your
vertical surfaces. with a reasonably
small brush. And then. what you can do is
you can just paint that on here. That one there. And you can just paint it on these rocky surfaces
quite roughly. And that can give quite a
useful effect. rather than having grass
just kind of disappearing up the sides
of everything. which looks really fake.
You can do it pretty quickly actually. you
can slap that on in a pretty organic way.
and just make these hills look a little
bit more natural. So. there's a tip for
you. if you're going around with your
terrain. paint this rocky texture on.
You also want to get the muddy
texture and put that into various
places. I need to raise the terrain up here a little bit. because I've got a feeling the character
may be able to almost get out of there. Now. I'm finding on my machine that it's often
selecting onto a different terrain tool. If you're finding that. just be aware
of which tool you're selected on there. And
it's pretty cool isn't it. this ability to
just modify the terrain? And you can
always dive into your first person
character and have a look around in that.
or you can use the Fly Through Controls.
which I'm using here. which I'm right
clicking and then using the
normal first person controls. WSAD. So. I can have a look at it from this guy's perspective. Obviously. I've got
some texturing to do over there still. So.
let's have a look.
Here you go. just got a few more bits of the terrain that need painting. Fill in these
mountainsides here. a little bit. so that
they're not too grassy. On the bits that
can't be grassy. I think I need some more mud. Need more
muddy muddy areas. so you could have suggested muddy pathways. whatever. You can see that I'm
not taking a lot of pride in my terrain
here. and that's because it's really
difficult. I think for me. to get great
concepts across whilst painting a
terrain in. Obviously. there are a lot of
considerations for how you make this
look natural and feel good. And I think
that I'm going to iterate on this terrain.
as I play the game and try and use things like mud to indicate maybe directions to
safe areas or dangerous areas and things
like that. I'm also starting to feel this
terrain is a bit small. but for the
purposes of teaching this section I
think it's going to be absolutely fine. Now.
remember you can place or remove
more trees. you can place or remove more
grass details. We have really not put
that much grass down on this terrain. so
I might paint a bit more. Remember. when
you're painting your grass that you're
not going to see it. unless you're within
the draw distance of the grass that we
talked about. Ok. there's not many of
these terrain settings you probably
want to be fiddling with. at the moment. You
could increase your terrain size. but it will
stretch all of your features. That's ok
let's just take a look at doing that. If
I go to say 1.000 by 1.000. you
see what it does. It stretches all the
features. and your water table will also get
stretched. Well. not get stretched. it will
stay where it is and needs to be moved
and resized. So. you could make your
terrain bigger. make all your hills a bit
smoother. it'll spread all your trees out.
That's fine. In fact. I'm going to do that.
I'm going to go up to 1.000 by 1.000. Then. I'm going to move my water table to 500 by 500. I'm going to
resize the water table. doing that same
calculation again. which is 500 times 1.42 = 710.
It needs to be in radius. like so. so it just reaches the edges. And then. I have a
slightly larger terrain. more spread out.
slightly smoother features. so that's
fine in this case. You can make a kind
of X and Y even scale change accepting that
it will just smooth out your terrain features. Ok. so I now have 1.000 by
1.000 terrain. which my machine still
seems to be coping with. And have a go
around with your character. Obviously your character's going to need to start in a
position that doesn't fall off the world. etc.
Later. we will deal with falling
through the world and all that sort of
business. So for now. enjoy getting your
character somewhere sensible. and then.
running around your own terrain. Here we go.
Little puddles. You see how quickly you can get something vaguely acceptable? But be careful about the
slopes in your terrain. you see my slope is too much here. In fact. my character is a bit wet. he can
only go up 10 degree slopes. I'm going to
give him 20 degree slopes. especially as he can't jump.
He's a bit crippled. otherwise. by his inability to move around the terrain. Ok that's cool! So. much bigger
terrain. 1.000 by 1.000 now. can't escape. plenty of different textures. We're well on the way.
Let's just check that lens flare. Still looking great!
There it is. Cool! Alright! Congratulations! Go ahead. make your terrain beautiful. Find some
nice places in it. maybe maximize your
screen. and take us some screenshots.
Make us all jealous. with how cool your
terrain is and how nice your lighting
and everything looks. Make mine look
really silly for me. I really would appreciate
that. Ok. Thanks very much guys. and I'll see you soon.