Hey. welcome back guys! So. we're going to get an Artificial Intelligence Agent in our
game now. We'll be setting up our Navmesh to do that. So. I'm going to be telling
you what a Navmesh is. We'll be
setting up our terrain Navmesh. We'll be
talking a little bit about baking
settings. This is not to do with cooking! [Laughs]
We will be baking our Navmesh. and you'll
preview it. to make sure that it suits
our terrain. So. let's go back over into
Unity. and take a little look at what we
need to do. We have a terrain. right. and
I've seen some fantastic different
terrains. in the discussions. please do
post yours if you haven't already.
Most of what I've seen is much better
than ours. but the key here really is. we're
going to need to adjust the terrain as we
go along. because we don't really know
how suitable it is. until we play the game.
So. don't worry if you're terrain doesn't look
amazing. You can improve it as you go along. but what we need to do is to have a zombie
chase us. I already want a zombie chasing us. Now. Unity has provided us a
very useful standard asset. In fact. go ahead and look under your Standard Assets Folder
under Characters now. and then. you'll
find Third Person Characters here. And if
you don't have this pack. go to Assets.
Import Package and Characters. Once you
finish that import. you should find
Third Person Character is an option.
and in there. you'll have lots of things.
which you are welcome to take a look at but one
of them is a Prefab Folder. And in the Prefab Folder. you'll have a Third Person
Controller. which we're not using here
because we have a first person game. from
the eyes of the player. but we do have an
AI Third Person Controller Prefab. So. you're
welcome to drop that now. into the scene.
Let's go ahead and do that. and I'm going to
set my position to say 255... 200. something like that. and let's see where that ends up putting it.
It's Ok. he's sitting just above the
ground. somewhere on the map. If that puts him
in the middle of a hill for you. then
move your AI
Third Person Controller. which I'm going
to rename to Zombie01. somewhere. where he's
just off the ground. so that he falls to the
ground. when you click play.
So. if you then click play. go back to the Scene View. and have a look at your zombie. You can double click on
him remember. You'll see that he's probably falling down a hill or something now or maybe just
standing there. He's a guy called Ethan. we're going to be using him as a placeholder zombie. Whether or not I
actually get around to making full zombies for this game. I think it's unlikely.
I'm trying to show you the elements of the game here. but there he is. And there's a few things going on with
him. and he needs in order to be able to
to navigate to me. he needs something
called a Navmesh. So. let me show you
this stage by stage. Firstly. on your
Third Person Controller. if you look down.
it's got several elements. a Transform
which tells it where it is. an Animator
which was responsible for his kind of
cool swaying action. a Rigidbody. which
gives him some physics. a Capsule
Collider. which allows him to go up and
down the slopes. a Navmesh Agent...
Hmm. interesting and we'll come back to that in a bit. and then. a couple of scripts. An AI
Character Controller Script and a Third
Person Character Script. Cool! So. there's an
overview of this guy. Now. one of the
things he has is a target. and if you drag
the First Person Controller into the
target. like that... So I've taken the First
Person Controller. from my Hierarchy. and
selected it as the target of this agent. If
you play the game now. and go to the
Scene View and look at the Agent. he's
not actually moving. He's not trying to
move towards us. despite the fact that
that's what we've told the system to do. We've said
chase me. and he is not chasing me right
now. So. the reason is. because there is no
Navmesh for him to follow. He does not
have a Navmesh. and there's actually a warning
along the bottom of the screen. saying
"Set destination can only be called on an
active agent that has been placed on a Navmesh". There is no Navmesh. So what
a Navmesh is. is a way of this Artificial Intelligence Agent
understanding enough about the world that it can actually navigate the
world. Alright. so we're going to set up our first Navmesh. right now. So. what you want to
do is click on the terrain. and we're going to open a new module. under Window. we have
Navigation. Now. for me that's over on the right. You can put it where you like. the
right hand side is reasonable. And if
you're not selected on the terrain. say
you're selected on a light. it's going to
say select a mesh renderer or a terrain
from the scene. Ok so. I've selected a terrain. Now. we can leave all these settings as
they are for the moment.
and just go to the Bake Tab. And what you
need to do with a Navmesh is. you
actually need to create it offline here. in this case. before you run the
game. and then bake the Navigation Mesh onto the terrain. So. let's see
what that actually means. Some basic
settings the Agent Radius. half a meter is
about right. Agent Height 2 meters
is about right. Maximum Slope 45 is
about right. Step Height 40 centimetres. that's the maximum step that the agent can go up.
that's about right. and we don't worry
about these advanced settings for now.
So. we should just click Bake. with those settings. It's going to take a little while. You can
see the progress. down on the bottom right. What it's doing now is it's exporting the terrain tiles. and
when it's finished doing that it's then going to start calculating the Navmesh. And then. in a
moment you'll see your whole terrain fill
up with some blue indications as to
where this guy can and can't go. Now. there are a lot more advanced things we can do with
Navmeshes. He can jump. he can drop. and he can even kind of go through a portal
to somewhere else. which is the Off Mesh Links. But for now. we're just focusing on
the real basics. which is the idea of a
simple Navmesh. and this could take
a while on your machine. it might be much quicker. I'm on a Quad Core i7 here on
a laptop. it could be much slower. So. that
might take you a while and when it's finished.
have a look around you're terrain. and
you will find that the blue areas are
where this guy is going to be able to
navigate to. Now. there's a limited draw
distance on these. so you may need to
get relatively close to see it in action.
And I'm using these First Person Control
Keys again W. S. A. D. while holding down the
right mouse button. and you can see the
areas of the terrain that he is able to navigate.
Cool hey! So. before we go any further. I want you to create your first Navmesh. Bake a
Navmesh into the terrain. preview it in your scene. adjust either the terrain or the
Navmesh settings. things like the
slope. until it's how you want it. And then.
share a screenshot of your baked Navmesh in the discussions. So. go ahead
pause the video and set up your Navmesh... your first version of your Navmesh now.
Cool welcome back! So. I'm going to stick
with what we've got here for the moment.
and just check it works before the end
of this video. And then. we'll go
from there. So. the way to check it works
is simply to play the game. and then go
to the Scene View and look at this zombie guy. Now. there he goes. he's running.
Now. he's doing some weird stuff. If we look at him. he's kind of doing mad jumping around.
but he is effectively running. Now. if he's
not behaving right. if he's doing jumps all
the time like this jump jump jump. holding his arms up in the air looking like a loony. then
the reason is you need to go to the
zombie. and you need to go to the
Inspector for the zombie and one of his
settings in the Third Person Character
Script is a Ground Check Distance. So. you want to change this Ground Check
Distance. it's a check on distance
between the character and the ground.
and you want to change it to something like 2 from 0.2. a nice big value. Now. let's look
at the guy; double click on the zombie... in the Scene View remember. and you'll get a
quick look at how he's running across
the terrain. Now. you can follow him around.
watching his Capsule Collider stay in
contact with the ground. Now. it's that
Capsule Collider. that capsule shaped inner collider that is going to stay in contact
with the ground mesh. and there he goes. he's running along the terrain after us.
Let's go into the game. and you can maximize. during play by the way. by just clicking
here and then Maximize. And let's look
around. I'm actually. for the first time.
feeling a little bit anxious. I know that
somewhere out there. there is a zombie running
across the terrain chasing me. So. let's
see if we can see him. And this is what I
want you to do. I want you to get to the point where the zombie actually chases you. Now.
in case you've missed a bit of this
video. while we wait for him to be
visible. where I showed you how to make
yourself the target. it's under the
zombie itself in the third person... Well
sorry. in the AI Character Controller Script
here. and the target. we make the target
the FPS controller us. and it
will continually chase us. Ok. so let's go back to the Scene View. find this zombie.
How's he doing? He's running along the terrain after us. So. back in Game View let's
maximize. Where is he coming from? Probably from the right. I'm not sure.
I'm slightly nervous that this guy is going to jump out on me in a minute.
and I don't know which direction from.
Now. I don't know if the scaling is going to be
right. when this zombie gets here. We may be far too big; he may be far too small.
We're going to worry about that in a
subsequent video. I just want to make sure
that he actually gets to me. because
that's a nice win. So. where is he
coming from? This is scary. Fun hey! For the first time. we are feeling a little bit
concerned. Oh. here he comes!
Oh. I'm not worried. look at that poxy little
zombie. He's tiny but he stops when he
gets to us and patiently stands there with
his arms by his side. Not quite the
effect we're looking for. but we clearly
have a scaling issue going on. So. what
we'll do in the next video is deal with the
relative scaling between you and the
zombie. because at the moment he's not at all scary. at that height. So. see you soon! [Laughs]
=======
Kind: captions
Language: en
Hey, welcome back guys! So, we're going to get an Artificial Intelligence Agent in our
game now. We'll be setting up our Navmesh to do that. So, I'm going to be telling
you what a Navmesh is. We'll be
setting up our terrain Navmesh. We'll be
talking a little bit about baking
settings. This is not to do with cooking! [Laughs]
We will be baking our Navmesh, and you'll
preview it, to make sure that it suits
our terrain. So, let's go back over into
Unity, and take a little look at what we
need to do. We have a terrain, right, and
I've seen some fantastic different
terrains, in the discussions, please do
post yours if you haven't already.
Most of what I've seen is much better
than ours, but the key here really is, we're
going to need to adjust the terrain as we
go along, because we don't really know
how suitable it is, until we play the game.
So, don't worry if you're terrain doesn't look
amazing. You can improve it as you go along, but what we need to do is to have a zombie
chase us. I already want a zombie chasing us. Now, Unity has provided us a
very useful standard asset. In fact, go ahead and look under your Standard Assets Folder
under Characters now, and then, you'll
find Third Person Characters here. And if
you don't have this pack, go to Assets,
Import Package and Characters. Once you
finish that import, you should find
Third Person Character is an option,
and in there, you'll have lots of things,
which you are welcome to take a look at but one
of them is a Prefab Folder. And in the Prefab Folder, you'll have a Third Person
Controller, which we're not using here
because we have a first person game, from
the eyes of the player, but we do have an
AI Third Person Controller Prefab. So, you're
welcome to drop that now, into the scene.
Let's go ahead and do that, and I'm going to
set my position to say 255... 200, something like that, and let's see where that ends up putting it.
It's Ok, he's sitting just above the
ground, somewhere on the map. If that puts him
in the middle of a hill for you, then
move your AI
Third Person Controller, which I'm going
to rename to Zombie01, somewhere, where he's
just off the ground, so that he falls to the
ground, when you click play.
So, if you then click play, go back to the Scene View, and have a look at your zombie. You can double click on
him remember. You'll see that he's probably falling down a hill or something now or maybe just
standing there. He's a guy called Ethan, we're going to be using him as a placeholder zombie. Whether or not I
actually get around to making full zombies for this game, I think it's unlikely.
I'm trying to show you the elements of the game here, but there he is. And there's a few things going on with
him, and he needs in order to be able to
to navigate to me, he needs something
called a Navmesh. So, let me show you
this stage by stage. Firstly, on your
Third Person Controller, if you look down,
it's got several elements, a Transform
which tells it where it is, an Animator
which was responsible for his kind of
cool swaying action, a Rigidbody, which
gives him some physics, a Capsule
Collider, which allows him to go up and
down the slopes, a Navmesh Agent...
Hmm, interesting and we'll come back to that in a bit, and then, a couple of scripts. An AI
Character Controller Script and a Third
Person Character Script. Cool! So, there's an
overview of this guy. Now, one of the
things he has is a target, and if you drag
the First Person Controller into the
target, like that... So I've taken the First
Person Controller, from my Hierarchy, and
selected it as the target of this agent. If
you play the game now, and go to the
Scene View and look at the Agent, he's
not actually moving. He's not trying to
move towards us, despite the fact that
that's what we've told the system to do. We've said
chase me, and he is not chasing me right
now. So, the reason is, because there is no
Navmesh for him to follow. He does not
have a Navmesh, and there's actually a warning
along the bottom of the screen, saying
"Set destination can only be called on an
active agent that has been placed on a Navmesh". There is no Navmesh. So what
a Navmesh is, is a way of this Artificial Intelligence Agent
understanding enough about the world that it can actually navigate the
world. Alright, so we're going to set up our first Navmesh, right now. So, what you want to
do is click on the terrain, and we're going to open a new module, under Window, we have
Navigation. Now, for me that's over on the right. You can put it where you like, the
right hand side is reasonable. And if
you're not selected on the terrain, say
you're selected on a light, it's going to
say select a mesh renderer or a terrain
from the scene. Ok so, I've selected a terrain. Now, we can leave all these settings as
they are for the moment,
and just go to the Bake Tab. And what you
need to do with a Navmesh is, you
actually need to create it offline here, in this case, before you run the
game, and then bake the Navigation Mesh onto the terrain. So, let's see
what that actually means. Some basic
settings the Agent Radius, half a meter is
about right. Agent Height 2 meters
is about right. Maximum Slope 45 is
about right. Step Height 40 centimetres, that's the maximum step that the agent can go up,
that's about right, and we don't worry
about these advanced settings for now.
So, we should just click Bake, with those settings. It's going to take a little while. You can
see the progress, down on the bottom right. What it's doing now is it's exporting the terrain tiles, and
when it's finished doing that it's then going to start calculating the Navmesh. And then, in a
moment you'll see your whole terrain fill
up with some blue indications as to
where this guy can and can't go. Now, there are a lot more advanced things we can do with
Navmeshes. He can jump, he can drop, and he can even kind of go through a portal
to somewhere else, which is the Off Mesh Links. But for now, we're just focusing on
the real basics, which is the idea of a
simple Navmesh, and this could take
a while on your machine, it might be much quicker. I'm on a Quad Core i7 here on
a laptop, it could be much slower. So, that
might take you a while and when it's finished,
have a look around you're terrain, and
you will find that the blue areas are
where this guy is going to be able to
navigate to. Now, there's a limited draw
distance on these, so you may need to
get relatively close to see it in action.
And I'm using these First Person Control
Keys again W, S, A, D, while holding down the
right mouse button, and you can see the
areas of the terrain that he is able to navigate.
Cool hey! So, before we go any further, I want you to create your first Navmesh. Bake a
Navmesh into the terrain, preview it in your scene, adjust either the terrain or the
Navmesh settings, things like the
slope, until it's how you want it. And then,
share a screenshot of your baked Navmesh in the discussions. So, go ahead
pause the video and set up your Navmesh... your first version of your Navmesh now.
Cool welcome back! So, I'm going to stick
with what we've got here for the moment,
and just check it works before the end
of this video. And then, we'll go
from there. So, the way to check it works
is simply to play the game, and then go
to the Scene View and look at this zombie guy. Now, there he goes, he's running.
Now, he's doing some weird stuff. If we look at him, he's kind of doing mad jumping around,
but he is effectively running. Now, if he's
not behaving right, if he's doing jumps all
the time like this jump jump jump, holding his arms up in the air looking like a loony, then
the reason is you need to go to the
zombie, and you need to go to the
Inspector for the zombie and one of his
settings in the Third Person Character
Script is a Ground Check Distance. So, you want to change this Ground Check
Distance, it's a check on distance
between the character and the ground,
and you want to change it to something like 2 from 0.2, a nice big value. Now, let's look
at the guy; double click on the zombie... in the Scene View remember, and you'll get a
quick look at how he's running across
the terrain. Now, you can follow him around,
watching his Capsule Collider stay in
contact with the ground. Now, it's that
Capsule Collider, that capsule shaped inner collider that is going to stay in contact
with the ground mesh, and there he goes, he's running along the terrain after us.
Let's go into the game, and you can maximize, during play by the way, by just clicking
here and then Maximize. And let's look
around, I'm actually, for the first time,
feeling a little bit anxious. I know that
somewhere out there, there is a zombie running
across the terrain chasing me. So, let's
see if we can see him. And this is what I
want you to do, I want you to get to the point where the zombie actually chases you. Now,
in case you've missed a bit of this
video, while we wait for him to be
visible, where I showed you how to make
yourself the target, it's under the
zombie itself in the third person... Well
sorry, in the AI Character Controller Script
here, and the target, we make the target
the FPS controller us, and it
will continually chase us. Ok, so let's go back to the Scene View, find this zombie.
How's he doing? He's running along the terrain after us. So, back in Game View let's
maximize. Where is he coming from? Probably from the right, I'm not sure.
I'm slightly nervous that this guy is going to jump out on me in a minute,
and I don't know which direction from.
Now, I don't know if the scaling is going to be
right, when this zombie gets here. We may be far too big; he may be far too small.
We're going to worry about that in a
subsequent video. I just want to make sure
that he actually gets to me, because
that's a nice win. So, where is he
coming from? This is scary. Fun hey! For the first time, we are feeling a little bit
concerned. Oh, here he comes!
Oh, I'm not worried, look at that poxy little
zombie. He's tiny but he stops when he
gets to us and patiently stands there with
his arms by his side. Not quite the
effect we're looking for, but we clearly
have a scaling issue going on. So, what
we'll do in the next video is deal with the
relative scaling between you and the
zombie, because at the moment he's not at all scary, at that height. So, see you soon! [Laughs]
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1:Unity/Section9/ZR11 Setting Up Your Navmesh.srt