Welcome back! In this video we're going to be scaling our characters. using a reference.
cube in our scene.  setting up your first
person character's eye height. and checking
character scale against the environment.
So. let's dive right on in.
So. here we go. Now. the issue that we had was that the first person controller
eye height is very very high. So. let's go
take a look. let's stick them both
somewhere sensible. I'm going to move both my first person controller and
my zombie somewhere fairly central. in
the middle of the terrain here. Let's just
check the first person controller sits
down Ok now. on the terrain. Yeah. there he is.
Now. given that he's at 474 368. I'm just
going to bring the zombie very close. So.
say 470 360. we'll put the zombie really
close to the first person. Let's have a look. Boom. there
we go. Now. if I look around. somewhere I should have a zombie... up next to me.
No. why not? Let's look at the scene. Um huh. there he is and there I am. He's so close. I can't even see him by the looks of it.
Let's take a look. There he is right down there. Ok. it's just that he's so much smaller. So. one of the
first things we need to do is sort this
out. Now. who's got the scale problem?
Is it the zombie? Is it us? Is it a
combination?
Well. one of the first things to do is
get an absolute reference in here.
So. wherever you've put your zombie and your first person in the scene. here they are.
Let's put a cube. a couple of cubes down on the ground. a 3D object cube.
By default that says cubic metre. which is
ideal. So. just move it down until it's
precisely on the ground. easiest just to
do that by eye. as soon as you see the geometry disappear
into the terrain around there. then it's
on the ground. And I'm going to duplicate
that and make myself another reference
cube. that is just above the first one.
I might just leave a tiny gap. so I can see
where the 1 metre mark is. Cool!
So. given those reference cubes. let's go back into the game. find the cubes.
Well. I'm far too big look. I'm towering over
that cube. Ethan is about the right
height actually. Cool! So. let's
get this fixed. Let's take a bit
more of a look at this first person
character. and try and understand why
his scale is so off. So. I'm going to start with the FPS Controller. I'm going to move it down to
ground level. and bring it over towards
me a little bit. Any way that you can work
with it. and maybe put its Capsule Collider close to the ground. So. what's
the deal with this FPS Controller. how
big is it. and where do you find that?
Well. there's lots of things on the FPS
Controller. It's quite a complex little
thing. but you'll see here that it's the
Character Controller itself here. this
bit that has a height. and if we adjust
the height the Capsule Collider goes
with it. You see that in the scene. And
it has a default height of 1.8 meters. which
is about right which means that when that
capsule is sitting on the ground. like
this. that the top of this capsule here is
at about 1.8 metres. Now. let's just
check that assumption. always check it against your reference cubes. You see
that is about right. he is about 1.8
metres. We set it to 2 metres of height.
and again sitting back on the ground and
you can see it's the same height as the
cubes. Alright so. that's good. that's
proving that this setting works fine.
So. what's going on with this camera? It's
miles in the air. Well. the camera is
childed. remember. to the FPS Controller.
and it has a funny position. If I could set
the position to 00 it would be right in
the middle of the FPS Controller. but now.
the camera is still the wrong. height isn't it. because it's at a height of what? What is
the height of the camera now? Just work
it out for me. If the FPS Controller is 1.8 metres high.
the camera must be... at the moment it is half way up the
controller. so it's at 0.9 of a
meter right. So. that's too low. So. that's
the problem we are having. is the camera
is just too low. So. how high do we want
the camera? Well. one way of sorting that
out is to bring the zombie into play.
So. you can use these particular widgets here. and maybe do a face-off
between the zombie and your character here and get yourself a scene where they can see
each other. And you can see that right now. in the Game View. if our camera was
rotated properly. which it's not really... Let's just change the camera rotation.
There's the camera. let's just change the rotation say to 0. Ok! Now. if we look in the Game View we're
kind of looking halfway up this guy's back
right now. Let's just pull myself
across until we're lined up with him.
looking at the camera preview. looking
halfway up his back. So. what I want to do
is just get the camera offset such that
we're kind of eye-to-eye or possibly the
zombie is a little bit bigger than us.
An easy way to do that is just to change the Y component of the camera. Make sure you're
not in play mode. of course. And I think
something like that will work. let's take
a look. Hmm. he's still a bit too tall. You could always spin your zombie around. by the way. so you're facing the
front of him. Something like that. let's try it. So. Let's move around and see how this zombie fairs.
You can run by holding down Shift.
to get away from him. Pretty good!
He's still not very scary at that height. so I
think I'm going to put my camera to a height
of say 0.4. and that makes the zombie
placeholder guy a little bit more kind of scary.
There you go. you've got that 1 metre
object in the scene or two 1 metre objects.
And you've got the zombie and this all feels a lot more sensible. down from this
height. So. what I want you to do now is
to do that for yourself. but also while
you're at it. check your zombie and
all your reference cubes against things
like the trees. Do they stack up against
the trees? So. if I move this guy over
towards this tree over here. is that
tree too big? I would say my trees probably are a
little bit too big actually. And also. the
other question is your terrain features.
You know take your zombie or your cubes and move them over to
a terrain feature. like a dip in the land.
like over here. and say to yourself: Well.
is this a sensible dip in the land?
Normally. if you use roughly the terrain
tools settings I did. you'll be about right. but if you are miles off and
these dips are far too big or the trees are far too big. you could scale your entire
terrain a little bit. If you have a
systemic error. you could just change the
entire terrain scale here. I would do it
the same in X and Y. so you don't create
distortions. otherwise you may need to
just go back and make a few tweaks to
your tree settings. for example.
So. you'd go back to the terrain. you'd go
back down to where we have trees. and you
may want to just mass place a new set of
trees. I do think these trees are a
little bit too high. so where this tree
height was here. I might want to just knock it down a
little bit. and then. mass place a load of
new trees. not keeping existing trees.
So. I might want to put 500 trees in without existing trees. and are they the
right height now? Well. they're better. they're much better. so I think I'm going to do that.
That's how you would change your trees
systematically. You change the height here.
you click Mass Place. you don't keep
existing trees. if you don't want to keep
existing trees. but be careful. because if
you lose them then of course...
all the hard work you may have done
of say taking trees out of the water and
things could get lost.
So. be careful if you're going to do it that
way. but if you want to spend the
time then go ahead and just remove
trees that are sitting in the water. Remember.
you do that with the Paint Trees Tool
while holding down Shift. So. you're going to need to
go back around the terrain and take any
ridiculous trees out. that sit say in
the water. And I think it's worth
spending the time to do that. just to tie
it all together and to get the scale
feeling about right. Now. it's quite easy to
end up selecting off the Tree Painting Tool. so just be a little
bit careful with that. And if you want to
maximize your Scene View. before you do
this. it makes quite a bit of sense. because then you can see what you're doing. So. I'm just going
to have a quick look around my terrain.
and say: Well. where do I really not want
trees? And then. make sure that I unpaint
trees from where it's done them in the
wrong place. Now. of course it's very lazy
just randomly painting trees like this.
but it does save us a lot of time. So.
there's something to be said for it. but
you know you get what you pay for. if you like. If you don't spend the time then.
you're not going to get the best effect
on your trees. Ok so. you get the idea.
That's what I want you to do now. is
go and get your terrain scale right.
the height features of your terrain and your trees and all the dips in the land.
compared to the characters. I'm going to delete my reference cubes. and then leave you with
a challenge slide as follows.
Get your character's eye height just right. check Zombie placeholder against the trees.
etc.. and share a photo of your
zombie or zombies if you want to duplicate
them. against some sort of backdrop maybe some pretty water and sun or something
like that. Let's get a zombie placeholder
group shot and stick it in the
discussions. So. go ahead get all your
scaling feeling right. and I will see you soon.
Cool! Welcome back! So. I've kind of already done the scaling. before I showed you this challenge.
So. remember to recap. you could rescale the entire terrain and see the affect that. that has. That's over in
the Terrain Settings here. so terrain. the
settings cog. and then. you change the
Terrain Width and the Terrain Length. If you want to do that. another way to do it is
to repaint all the trees that you've put
in on mass. Now. there's a recap of the way
that we do that. is that we go to the
Paint Trees Setting here. the Place Trees.
Then. you Mass Place Trees. after having changed the height. Now. you've got a range of
heights. it's random in this range from
Minimum to Maximum. and you can also just
drag the middle of it. So. you choose your
variability through the width and then the
mean of the height through the position of the slider. And then.
you Mass Place your trees. ditching the other ones. I wouldn't put more than 1.000
trees in a terrain. I think you might end up with performance
problems. but that just depends on your
computer. So. you just need to be thinking
about what it's going to be run on. So. that's it! We have a terrain and
directional light and a first person
controller and a water table. And we have
reasonably sensible scaling. so that now
when we play our game we're down here on
the floor. and somewhere there should be
a zombie trying to get me.
And remember. if you can't find your zombie. your single lone zombie then. go into Scene
View and double click. and you will then
be able to zoom out and see where he is in
the terrain. Turning on things like the
Transform Tool will help you to visualize
where he is. and there he is patiently
waiting for me there. And if I run away and
turn around and do some finger gymnastics. you can see him chasing me through the
world. and it's much more kind of
sensible now. It's much more like a
sensibly scaled world. So. there you go! I look forward to seeing you in the next video!