Hey hey welcome back! Let's talk about user input mapping or using input
mapping, even. So, we're going to be
talking about the Unity Input Manager.
We'll create an input for the view zoom and we'll default that to V. We'll create an input for call helicopter
and default it to H, and then, give both inputs basic placeholder behavior, as a default
of V and H, because the whole point of
Input Mapping, as you'll see, is that we
can allow the player to change
the key bindings, later. Although, we probably
won't go as far as doing that, it does make it possible.
OK cool! So, how do we do this? Well, the
first thing you need to do is go to
the Input Manager, which is Edit, Project
Settings, and then, Input here. Take a
look at my screen. Fantastic! So, that will give you an array of 18 default things, so
let's make that 20 so that we have two
new things. One is going to be View Zoom
or just Zoom, and we can give it a
descriptive name: Zoom the player's view
.. or something like that. Now, we don't need a negative on here. It's asking for
a descriptive name and a descriptive
negative, it's cut off, but that's what
it says. We don't have a negative of Zoom, it's just going to be a whole Z or
V to zoom in, and it's going to be let go
to zoom out, so we don't need a negative
button, but it's going to be V to zoom
the view. So, let's emphasize that there,
it could be Z, whatever you like.
OK, and the other one that we're going to have is helicopter, so Call Heli, like that,
Call the helicopter, and we're going to default that to H. So, in the Input Manager that's
what we've done, we've set up two more
elements of the array called Zoom and
Call Heli, with default keys of H and V, and
the names that you are going to need to refer to
in code are these things, Zoom and Call Heli. So, I'm going to help you through the first one, the zooming in,
and then, I'm going to ask you to use Input Mapping yourself, for the second one.
So, let's go just have a little bit of tidy up first here in Unity. I'm going to make
a folder for my scripts. I'm going to stick to this format, there's lots of ways you can organize your stuff.
There's actually a Game Folder here, that's
already been created for us, with the Navmesh, so
this time, I'm going to slightly break
the convention and put both the terrain
in the Game Scene and the game. Just for
fun, just as a different way of
doing things. Now, remember you can always search here and you can search by type here. So, if
you're looking for scenes, you can click
Scene, and it will show you all your
scenes here. OK, this will be from the
Standard Asset Pack, you can ignore that one. In fact,
you can even delete the Tessellation Sample, if you like. I'm going to do that.
Fantastic! Anyway, so we digress. Let's
think about how we're going to zoom in.
So again, I need that scene, so let's go to
the game Scene. In the Game Scene, we have
a player that has a camera, which I'm
going to rename to Eyes. OK, so I'm going to
put a script on him called Eyes. OK, so it's a new script. Notice how I just typed
the name of a script, that doesn't
exist, there, and it gives me a default,
New Script, Create and Add. So, that's pretty efficient, right. Of course, what it hasn't
done yet is put that into the Scripts Folder. Fine. So, let's go look at this
Eyes Script and think about how we're going to do that. I'll get you going, and then, I'm going to
challenge you to make that key do the
zoom. If you think you're confident stop
now and go ahead and do it, otherwise, I'm
going to help you through. So, we're going to
have a private camera called Eyes, so the
moment I've declared that, I want to go
back to Unity and say, well here it's
going to start, in a minute, asking me for
the Eyes, or is it? Why is it not asking me for the eyes?  Because I said private. Why did I
say private? Good question!
Well, there is only one camera in this
scene at the moment, and furthermore, the
camera is on the same component. So, why would we try and drag that in? You'd be
better off using GetComponent, so I
naturally went to private, and then, the
next thing that would make sense to do
is to say that, eyes = GetComponent &lt;Camera&gt; ();
on the same object, so you get the
camera and that's it. So then, the other
things that we're going to need is, we're going to need a private float default field of view,
which you're going to read at the start.
I'll leave that to you.
I'm going to want a private
bool called fade in. No no, to get that let's
just keep it simple, we're just going to
have a private float default field of
view and then, when we click a button, we're going to
zoom in. So, whatever field of view we set here, I want it to remember that, so
the designer can set your field of view,
but when you zoom in, I want it to go one
and a half times larger than it was
before. So, that's the idea.
So, when I say one and a half times larger,
of course, I mean one and a half times
more zoom, but that means a smaller field
of view. So look, let's challenge you to
do this. I think you can do it. We're going to
trigger from the zoom input. Look in the docs,
see if you can work out how to read that zoom input. Take a look for that, I think I've called it a capital
Z, but you get the idea. Whatever you've called it in the Input Manager,
When you push that key, change the field
of view of the Eyes to 1.5
times smaller field of view, so you're zooming in, and then, revert back when the key is
released. See if you can work that out, it's a
relatively simple bit of code, but there's a new method
you need to find. Go ahead, pause the video and see if you can make the zoom keys zoom your view.
Welcome back guys! OK, so how am I going to do this? Well, what I'm going to need to
do is, I'm going to, at the start, need to get
that default field of view, so that the
designer can change it. So, it's quite
common to go defaultFOV = eyes.fieldOfView; ...it's a
property. Ok fantastic! And then, what we want to do on every update, is we want to say if... This is the
method you need. if (Input.GetButton OK, and if that GetButton is ("Zoom" ) ... Now, let me
just check back in Unity. Is that what I
called it? Project Settings, Input, Zoom
here. Yes, it is. OK. If we get a zoom on
this frame, then we go eyes.fieldOfView = defaultFOV
that we read at the start, so that the designer can offset all of this stuff.
Divided by 1.5 is a float, so we're making it 1.5 times smaller; else if we're not reading
that key on this frame, we make the field
of view the default field of view, so it goes back when
you release the key. Does that make sense? Look for the key, set it, I'll release it.
So, here we are in Unity. We've set a field of view on the camera, I'm going to leave mine at 60. If we then play,
then we have compiler errors, so let's go have a look and see what the compiler errors are. So, I've
just done a boo-boo, and that's that I've missed a closing bracket. Fantastic! So, let's try again.
Fantastic! So, here I am looking around,
and I go V for the zoom. Ha, cunning hey! V works!
Every time I press the V key, it zooms in. And there he comes, Ethan's pegging at me, and I can see. Fantastic!
OK. And the benefit of this is that there
are methods that allow the player
to change these input bindings at playtime. It also allows your designer
to use the default buttons. Cool! So, what we're going to want to get you to do now, is using the Call Heli input,
I want you to trigger a sound, some sort of sound. I'm going to say something like
Rescue helicopter inbound, ETA five
minutes or something like that. And then, I'm
just going to play that sound, that's all I'm going to do, when I've hit that button. So, that is your challenge,
is to get the helicopter call behavior just
triggering.
Create a CallHeli input, which we've done, and trigger the sounds when pressed, pretty simple. You've also got to
decide where these scripts are going to go. OK, see you soon.
Hey hey, so we don't have a helicopter do we? We don't have a helicopter in the scene.
We don't have a helicopter prefab. We will
bring in a helicopter in a bit, but right
now, it's not the job we need to do. We
just need to think about what game
object, when there's no helicopter in the
scene, what game object is going to be
responsible for receiving this helicopter call. Well, there's a couple of ways
you could do this. You could have a game
manager, of some sort, that would instantiate
helicopter, or we're trying to keep it as
real as possible here, you could actually
just have a helicopter that's over the mountain somewhere and out of sight, because that's what's
really going to happen. So, that's what I'm
going to do, I'm going to make an empty
GameObject for now, completely empty. I'm going to call it the helicopter, and later,
we'll build this up to be the actual
helicopter. And I'm going to put it outside the game
world, just sitting down here somewhere.
Let's take a look at my Y position.
My Y position should probably be around 0, and there he is, just looks a bit funny,
I'm just trying to see where that is in
3D space. Ah that's why, you see I've just got myself a
perspective issue. It's over here. That's
absolutely fine, being over there. I just needed
to know where it was. So, that helicopter is hidden from view and any way, it's nothing,
it's just an empty transform, but crucially we now have a GameObject that we
can add the script to. So, I can now
simply say Helicopter. I can't type Helicopter, but I
can say Helicopter. [Laughs] There you go. So, there is the Helicopter Script. So, now the
Helicopter Script can actually listen
for that key press, right. Pretty cool!
So, what it can do every frame... In fact,
why don't we just barrow what we did in Eyes,
every frame we can say something like this. If we hear CallHeli, then there's probably a few
things we need to do, which we can sort
out in a future script, but I think
I'm going to want to do at least this. A private bool, inbound, or something like that,
or called = false, and when I call the heli, I'm going to want to
say called = true; and then, I'm also going to want to play a sound.
So, to meet the results of the challenge, you do need to trigger a sound. So, we're
going to need to publicly expose public
audio. Now what is it? AudioClip, so we'll have this
AudioClip patched in, but let's just check
that this key binding is working. So, I'm
just going to print "Helicopter called" to the console, for the moment, and set that
boolean. Let's just check that work. So, play the game, we can still zoom in with V,
we look at the console, and if I hit H now,
we get helicopter call. Now, we've got it called a lot
of times, but that is just because the key is just repeating, when it's held
down. OK, so you could use a different
method. I'm going to move the script across.
You could use a slightly different method,
which will help before we solve the
problem, along the way. Let's just say GetButtonDown. So, try now, you'll see that
GetButtonDown just responds a little
bit differently. So, you push it now, and
you just get one call. That's much better
right. You can still push it multiple times,
so let's suppress that, straight away. So, we don't want to respond more than once,
so if we push the Call Heli and not
called, then we do this. So, we should just do it
once, because we set call to true. Cool! So, let's try again. So now, H can only call a heli once. At first, we
sorted out the button repeat issue, and now we're sorting out the logic, so that we can call the helicopter,
just once. And however many times I'm pressing the H key, I'm pushing it frantically now, it only gets called once.
Fantastic! So, the helicopter now has a
state, which is that it's in a called state,
and that's absolutely fine. So, how are we
going to get this AudioClip on there?
Well, that is going to be the subject of the
next lecture, where we're going to deal
with actually putting in the 3D sound.
But this is good enough, that you have
the helicopter called, and it's in a called
state, so a slightly different result of
the challenge that I gave you. If you've gone ahead and gotten as far as the sound, well
done. If you're struggling with the sound,
well then I'm going to show you in the
next lecture, all about 3D sounds. So,
congratulations and see you soon!