Hey! So. we're going to look at Rigged Mechanim Animation. Now. what's that mean? We're going to
be introducing Unity's mechanim
system. it's Unity's animation system for
bipeds and humanoids and things. We'll
be exploring how Ethan is constructed
and finding the rigging and muscle tools.
within Ethan. so we can have a play
with how he moves. So. let's just take a look at Ethan over here. so click on your
zombie instance and in my case there it is. It's a little bit close to a tree for
my liking. so I'm just going to move it across and maybe down a bit. Ok. so what is this thing? I mean.
we've just dropped it in this
Third Person Character Controller.
it's all very well doing that. but the
problem is we don't really
understand how it works. And you may have already had the urge to modify Ethan's movement
or appearance. so we need to understand
how he works to do that. So. there is what
I call zombie 01. and let's just take a look at how this prefab has been composed.
So. we have an Animator. we've seen the animator before in Glitch Garden and
a Animation Controller. we may as well look at that Animation Controller. I'll probably put it
down here. which is where we've been used to seeing it. So. there's an Animation
Controller. down there. It's got some
differences. it's using something called a Blend Tree
in here. which is new to you. but
we'll look at that later in the course.
So. anyway he has an Animation Controller. He also has an avatar. and it's the Avatar really
we're going to be focusing on more during
this video. So. let's do that now. while we're
here. The Avatar. if you click on it and you have your Project Pane open.
it will go and find his avatar. right down in
the Third Person Character Models here.
and if you expand out Ethan. we'll just click Avatar over on the Inspector. on the right.
it'll go straight to Ethan's avatar. Now. fairly hidden inside Ethan's avatar is a button.
saying Configure Avatar. which you may as well go ahead and click. So. try and find that. And you can save
the scene. I've moved Ethan around a bit. that's fine. And look. you've got a whole new thing here. and this
is called a Rigging Tool. so let's look what's happened when I click that configure
button. It's dropped another Ethan clone
into the scene here. on the left hand
side. just temporarily while we play with
the skeleton. and if you expand that out. you'll
see that it's comprised of a body and some glasses. We'll talk about that in a
minute. but for this bit what's relevant is
the skeleton. And what Ethan consists
of is a set of bones. which are defined by a bunch of transforms. There you are you can
see the bones. And then. there's a
hierarchy of bones. from the hips.
connect to the spine and the leg. You know the hip joint connects to the leg joint. and the leg
joint connects to the knee joint. I'm sure there was a kids' rhyme
about that. So. we have a hierarchy of all
his bones drilling through and it's
very important they're arranged properly. And you can either click in the Inspector or on the
Scene View or actually on these little
green dots. and you'll see that for the
head you can click on the left hand. the
right hand. And if I had a bit more
vertical screen space. you'd see a lot
more of these bone definitions. And
what's happened here is. that when this
character was set up. all of these
transforms here define the bones. and
the outside is defined by the mesh
renderer. the skin mesh renderer. We'll look at that in a second. And this gives Unity
the ability to understand how this
humanoid character is rigged. i.e. how the bones
relate to all of these different positions.
Ok. so have a look at that. and that will be
part of your challenge. will be to have a
good look around at this stuff. And the
other fun thing is the Muscles Tab
here. and that puts the clone into a
different pose. And if you look at him here.
you'll see he's sitting in a slightly
awkward floaty pose. and what this does
is. it allows you to define. by the moving
groups of muscles like this or by moving
individual muscles like maybe the left
leg. the range of motion. Now. because
the animations for this guy have already
been defined. it's not actually going to
change very much. depending on the state and how the animation was set up. But if you're
animating him from a start. you might very well for a zombie. for example. want
to restrict the range of motion of his
legs. and the way you do that is. you drill down into a
particular muscle group. And you can
actually reduce the possible range of
motion. by changing one extreme. the
other extreme. and then. the offset by
moving the whole thing. And in fact. you can even see a little indicator here. right by his hip.
which gives you some indication of how
wide a range of motion we're dealing with.
So. if I was to restrict his leg motion.
right down and then. try and move it. you'll see that
we can stop it moving forward at all.
Alright. so it's a pretty cool system!
It understands basically. in summary. how
the bones are connected together. right
across the body and then. how the muscle movements are restricted. Pretty cool right!
Ok. I'm going to zoom all the way back. Now. I'm going to come out of this system. by clicking Done at
the bottom right of the Inspector. Go back
to the clone and keep working down him.
So. that's the avatar. and within the avatar.
we have access to that whole configure
avatar system. which is the muscle and bone system. Then. the rest of the Animator
is kind of as before. he's got a Rigidbody and a Capsule Collider. as you can see. and the
Navmesh Agent. which we've been
using to have him automatically move
himself from pathfinder and the
environment. And then. it's got a couple
of scripts on it. So. that is the essence of how he is put together. Now. the other thing I
want to show you about Ethan. in this short video. is the Fundamental Top Level
Construction. So. what I just showed you
is at the root of Ethan. and then. he has
a body here. Now. if we look at that body. it has something called a Skinned Mesh Renderer. If I turn it
off it clearly disappears. Now. a Skinned Mesh Renderer is different to a normal mesh
renderer. and the reason it's different is because it automatically helps to store the mesh.
when things like arms move or any
joint moves. So. if I look at his shoulder
there and then. go to his skeleton and
drill into. all the way through the spine
to the neck. it's quite counter-intuitive at times. and then. all the way up to the left
shoulder. for example. and get the Rotate
Tool. Look as I rotate his shoulder. look
carefully at the textures here in his chest.
you see they kind of distort. and that's because the Skinned Mesh Renderer is doing a lot
of work for us. So. the body has a special
type of mesh renderer. Basically. if you
were making a robot with hinge like joints. you wouldn't use a Skinned Mesh
Renderer. you would just use a normal mesh renderer.
When you're making something that has
clothing on the outside or skin on the
outside you want to use this very clever
component. which will do this type of
calculation for you. And it takes Ethan's body as a mesh. and it takes the root bone of
his skeleton. which is the hips. as
another parameter. Ok. so the other thing
it's got is a set of glasses. that's been
specified separately. that's also a
Skinned Mesh Renderer. Now. you may ask why would you want it to be a skinned
renderer for glasses? You don't have to. in this case. The benefit. of course. of it being
a skinned renderer is. if you were to expand Ethan's head out then. the glasses would
stretch with it. so they're kind of flexible
glasses. which is cool. And then. the
third object is a skeleton and you'll
notice it's just a hierarchy of transforms.
as we drill down it's just transforms on here. but these transforms define the bone
positions. rotations. and even scales. Ok.
so that is the purpose of this hierarchy.
is to completely define this guy's skeleton. which as I
said. if you go into the Mechanim System. is actually drawn for you. When. you zoom in. to the
clone that comes temporarily into the
scene. there you go. you can see he's got
an inner skeleton. Alright. now Unity can
actually what we call rig. which is
putting these bones to a skin for you.
provided that the thing that you have
created in your 3D tool is humanoid-ish and is standing in a t-pose
like this. But you will have had to
define all the bones as well. all
the positions and transforms of the bones. So. this is outside the scope of this
course. at the moment. but I just want to
show you how he's comprised so that Ethan no
longer is a complete mystery. We'll take a
look at his animations in a
separate video. Ok cool! Thanks for watching! I have a little challenge for you. of course as always.
which is I want you to save your project.
and then. have a good play with Ethan
yourself and his rigging. And try restricting some bone movements. see if you
can make him a little bit more zombie
like in the muscle system perhaps. and note
where you get stuck. what works what
doesn't work and just have a play and
then. you can revert yourself back to
whatever you saved. So. maybe zip up. save your project.
both the project and the scene. Zip up
the whole project folder perhaps.
or use Version Control to take a
snapshot. Have a good play! Break things!
You'll learn most by breaking things. and note where you get stuck. maybe write down your
questions. and I'll see you soon!
=======
Kind: captions
Language: en
Hey! So, we're going to look at Rigged Mechanim Animation. Now, what's that mean? We're going to
be introducing Unity's mechanim
system, it's Unity's animation system for
bipeds and humanoids and things. We'll
be exploring how Ethan is constructed
and finding the rigging and muscle tools,
within Ethan, so we can have a play
with how he moves. So, let's just take a look at Ethan over here, so click on your
zombie instance and in my case there it is. It's a little bit close to a tree for
my liking, so I'm just going to move it across and maybe down a bit. Ok, so what is this thing? I mean,
we've just dropped it in this
Third Person Character Controller,
it's all very well doing that, but the
problem is we don't really
understand how it works. And you may have already had the urge to modify Ethan's movement
or appearance, so we need to understand
how he works to do that. So, there is what
I call zombie 01, and let's just take a look at how this prefab has been composed.
So, we have an Animator, we've seen the animator before in Glitch Garden and
a Animation Controller, we may as well look at that Animation Controller. I'll probably put it
down here, which is where we've been used to seeing it. So, there's an Animation
Controller, down there. It's got some
differences, it's using something called a Blend Tree
in here, which is new to you, but
we'll look at that later in the course.
So, anyway he has an Animation Controller. He also has an avatar, and it's the Avatar really
we're going to be focusing on more during
this video. So, let's do that now, while we're
here. The Avatar, if you click on it and you have your Project Pane open,
it will go and find his avatar, right down in
the Third Person Character Models here,
and if you expand out Ethan, we'll just click Avatar over on the Inspector, on the right,
it'll go straight to Ethan's avatar. Now, fairly hidden inside Ethan's avatar is a button,
saying Configure Avatar, which you may as well go ahead and click. So, try and find that. And you can save
the scene, I've moved Ethan around a bit, that's fine. And look, you've got a whole new thing here, and this
is called a Rigging Tool, so let's look what's happened when I click that configure
button. It's dropped another Ethan clone
into the scene here, on the left hand
side, just temporarily while we play with
the skeleton, and if you expand that out, you'll
see that it's comprised of a body and some glasses. We'll talk about that in a
minute, but for this bit what's relevant is
the skeleton. And what Ethan consists
of is a set of bones, which are defined by a bunch of transforms. There you are you can
see the bones. And then, there's a
hierarchy of bones, from the hips,
connect to the spine and the leg. You know the hip joint connects to the leg joint, and the leg
joint connects to the knee joint. I'm sure there was a kids' rhyme
about that. So, we have a hierarchy of all
his bones drilling through and it's
very important they're arranged properly. And you can either click in the Inspector or on the
Scene View or actually on these little
green dots, and you'll see that for the
head you can click on the left hand, the
right hand. And if I had a bit more
vertical screen space, you'd see a lot
more of these bone definitions. And
what's happened here is, that when this
character was set up, all of these
transforms here define the bones, and
the outside is defined by the mesh
renderer, the skin mesh renderer. We'll look at that in a second. And this gives Unity
the ability to understand how this
humanoid character is rigged, i.e. how the bones
relate to all of these different positions.
Ok, so have a look at that, and that will be
part of your challenge, will be to have a
good look around at this stuff. And the
other fun thing is the Muscles Tab
here, and that puts the clone into a
different pose. And if you look at him here,
you'll see he's sitting in a slightly
awkward floaty pose, and what this does
is, it allows you to define, by the moving
groups of muscles like this or by moving
individual muscles like maybe the left
leg, the range of motion. Now, because
the animations for this guy have already
been defined, it's not actually going to
change very much, depending on the state and how the animation was set up. But if you're
animating him from a start, you might very well for a zombie, for example, want
to restrict the range of motion of his
legs, and the way you do that is, you drill down into a
particular muscle group. And you can
actually reduce the possible range of
motion, by changing one extreme, the
other extreme, and then, the offset by
moving the whole thing. And in fact, you can even see a little indicator here, right by his hip,
which gives you some indication of how
wide a range of motion we're dealing with.
So, if I was to restrict his leg motion,
right down and then, try and move it, you'll see that
we can stop it moving forward at all.
Alright, so it's a pretty cool system!
It understands basically, in summary, how
the bones are connected together, right
across the body and then, how the muscle movements are restricted. Pretty cool right!
Ok, I'm going to zoom all the way back. Now, I'm going to come out of this system, by clicking Done at
the bottom right of the Inspector. Go back
to the clone and keep working down him.
So, that's the avatar, and within the avatar,
we have access to that whole configure
avatar system, which is the muscle and bone system. Then, the rest of the Animator
is kind of as before, he's got a Rigidbody and a Capsule Collider, as you can see, and the
Navmesh Agent, which we've been
using to have him automatically move
himself from pathfinder and the
environment. And then, it's got a couple
of scripts on it. So, that is the essence of how he is put together. Now, the other thing I
want to show you about Ethan, in this short video, is the Fundamental Top Level
Construction. So, what I just showed you
is at the root of Ethan, and then, he has
a body here. Now, if we look at that body, it has something called a Skinned Mesh Renderer. If I turn it
off it clearly disappears. Now, a Skinned Mesh Renderer is different to a normal mesh
renderer, and the reason it's different is because it automatically helps to store the mesh,
when things like arms move or any
joint moves. So, if I look at his shoulder
there and then, go to his skeleton and
drill into, all the way through the spine
to the neck, it's quite counter-intuitive at times, and then, all the way up to the left
shoulder, for example, and get the Rotate
Tool. Look as I rotate his shoulder, look
carefully at the textures here in his chest,
you see they kind of distort, and that's because the Skinned Mesh Renderer is doing a lot
of work for us. So, the body has a special
type of mesh renderer. Basically, if you
were making a robot with hinge like joints, you wouldn't use a Skinned Mesh
Renderer, you would just use a normal mesh renderer.
When you're making something that has
clothing on the outside or skin on the
outside you want to use this very clever
component, which will do this type of
calculation for you. And it takes Ethan's body as a mesh, and it takes the root bone of
his skeleton, which is the hips, as
another parameter. Ok, so the other thing
it's got is a set of glasses, that's been
specified separately, that's also a
Skinned Mesh Renderer. Now, you may ask why would you want it to be a skinned
renderer for glasses? You don't have to, in this case. The benefit, of course, of it being
a skinned renderer is, if you were to expand Ethan's head out then, the glasses would
stretch with it, so they're kind of flexible
glasses, which is cool. And then, the
third object is a skeleton and you'll
notice it's just a hierarchy of transforms,
as we drill down it's just transforms on here, but these transforms define the bone
positions, rotations, and even scales. Ok,
so that is the purpose of this hierarchy,
is to completely define this guy's skeleton, which as I
said, if you go into the Mechanim System, is actually drawn for you. When, you zoom in, to the
clone that comes temporarily into the
scene, there you go, you can see he's got
an inner skeleton. Alright, now Unity can
actually what we call rig, which is
putting these bones to a skin for you,
provided that the thing that you have
created in your 3D tool is humanoid-ish and is standing in a t-pose
like this. But you will have had to
define all the bones as well, all
the positions and transforms of the bones. So, this is outside the scope of this
course, at the moment, but I just want to
show you how he's comprised so that Ethan no
longer is a complete mystery. We'll take a
look at his animations in a
separate video. Ok cool! Thanks for watching! I have a little challenge for you, of course as always,
which is I want you to save your project,
and then, have a good play with Ethan
yourself and his rigging. And try restricting some bone movements, see if you
can make him a little bit more zombie
like in the muscle system perhaps, and note
where you get stuck, what works what
doesn't work and just have a play and
then, you can revert yourself back to
whatever you saved. So, maybe zip up, save your project,
both the project and the scene. Zip up
the whole project folder perhaps,
or use Version Control to take a
snapshot. Have a good play! Break things!
You'll learn most by breaking things, and note where you get stuck, maybe write down your
questions, and I'll see you soon!
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1:Unity/Section9/ZR16 Rigged Mechanim Animation.srt