Hey guys welcome back! In this video
we'll be exploring humanoid animation a
little further. So, an overview of how Ethan is actually animated. We'll be
talking about re-targeting animations,
introducing blend trees, and while I'm there,
I'm going to tell you what Inverse Kinematics is, because you'll see a little IK button,
and I'm sure your curiosity will get the
better of you otherwise. So, let's
just take a look at how Ethan is actually animated. It all starts, of course,
with Ethan's third person animator controller, which is here in the Inspector, if you
click on Zombie, and then, click on
the Controller. So, there it is, let's...
I'm going to put it down on the bottom, I'm just more used to it there. You put it wherever you like.
And I'm going to take a look. It's got three
fundamental states, ignoring the entry
state here, which actually we could move these across couldn't we. And we wouldn't have to keep scrolling
around and giving you seasickness. So, you've got a grounded state, but it's actually got
a sub-state machine and then, an airborne
state and a crouching state. They've done
a lot of work for you Unity, in providing
this. Here you see this IK sticking up here,
Inverse Kinematics. I'll explain what that is in a bit. So, the overview is that he can be on the
ground, in the air, or crouching, and there are various transition criteria for this, to
do with parameters. OK, so what I want to
show you, really in this video, is
the preview down at the bottom here, that
you've got, now you've seen this
before and you've seen that you can click Preview. And this is previewing this transition, going
from crouching to grounding. I also want
to show you that when we go into an animation,
this is using something called a Blend Tree, and what this means is there's a whole bunch
of different animation states for Ethan here. He's got a whole load of different
things, and what you see with this Blend
Tree, at the top firstly, is a State Space.
It's a whole bunch of different animations he could be in. He's got about 20
animations, between walking left and
right and sharp walking, etc.
And they're all specified down here, and this X and Y position is just where it's plotted
on this graph above. OK, and this is how fast the animation is played.
And what the Blend Tree does for us is it
allows us to combine animations together,
so if I do a preview down here, you can
see that down here, this has selected the
Idle Animation, and another way of moving
between these is to move the parameters
that have been set up. So, this is how
far forward your stick would be pressed,
for example, on an Xbox controller, and then, this bit would represent how far left and
right your stick is being moved. So, you can either explore the state space here, or you can
actually just grab the red dot, up in the
Inspector, and move around. And this is
very much like you would see, when you
start moving your control around, as I
say. So, this is a fantastic system for
combining different animations together.
So, that is an introduction to Blend
Trees. It's simply a question of adding a
Blend Tree, adding in all the different
animations you want, putting them in
different positions on the diagram, and
then, letting Unity do the blending
between them for you. It's pretty cool
and pretty clever, and you can see
just how much work they have to do, to
acknowledge the fact that turning left
and turning right or walking left and walking right is different, doing that
in a sharp, rapid way. They have to do a
different animation for that, because of
the way the body sways, etc.
Now, we'll look at the actual animations in a second, before we do I just want to show
you how you can re-target animations. If
you click the Avatar, down here, you could
choose the Unity model, this dude here,
and he will take exactly the same motions.
One of the cool things about animations is,
you can put them on any humanoid
character, any character with the same
rigging, with the same bone structure,
you can put this same animation on, it could be an orc or a person. And you can go back
to Auto, and if it doesn't bring it up on
Auto, you can always just go to other, and
then, explicitly choose the game object
that you want to use, say Ethan here, for the
preview. OK, this thing here just turns on
and off this little access, which
shows you the direction he's facing. Now, the other thing I just wanted to introduce you to is Inverse
Kinematics. What's Inverse Kinematics? Well, it's often used on the feet.
For example, normally when you animate
you move forward down the Hierarchy, so
if we were to look at this zombie and zoom in to him, let's give myself some more
space right now, and then, maybe zoom right in to his shoulder... Now by the way, thank you to
Elijah for pointing out that, if you get
bored of clicking these little expansion
icons, you can hold down the Alt key on
your keyboard, I'm holding down Alt now, and
then click it and it'll do a full
expansion. And that would let us get to
his shoulder, for instance, a bit quicker, although you'd end up being vomited on by the Hierarchy.
And Forward Kinematics is this, it's when we move say an arm from this end, that's
Forward Kinematics. So, if I want to get the
hand to a certain position, I've got to move
the arm up, and then, I've got to go to the
forearm and move that and so on. It's great
for that type of movement, but how about he wants to put his hand on a wall and keep it
there or put his foot on the ground and
keep it there?
Well, Inverse Kinematics is doing
calculations to say, well actually I'm
going to specify where the end of the
limb is, say the hand, and then, I'm going
to want the computer to work out
backwards what the limits of motion of
the rest of the body are, if the hand
were say glued to a table or the foot was
glued to the floor. So, that's just an
overview of when you see IK,
Inverse Kinematics in here. That's what
it's talking about.
OK, and you can see it making a minor
change here with the feet. Again, a little bit beyond
the scope of this course to get into that
level of detail about animation. Maybe you want to
check out my Blender course, later on in
there, if you want to get into that
detail. Animation is a completely different art, and we've got to have a lot of
respect for the guys who are spending a
huge amount of time putting these
animations together. So, we've talked
about an overview of how Ethan is animated,
re-targeting animations, how you could apply these to different things. You've got an
overview of Blend Trees, by the way, there are also Blend Trees for his airborne state.
So, if we click into here, you can now see
that when airborne he can jump
off the left leg or the right leg, and one of
the easiest ways to see that is to look
at this. This is deciding how far through the
jump animation he is, and this guy is deciding
whether he has jumped off the left leg or the right leg. And then, by cycling the run
appropriately, he can do
realistic-looking jumps.  A lot of work hey! A lot of work, and there's a similar thing
for crouched animations. So, the final
thing really, I want to show you is just how
much work there is in the key framing of
this guy. If I bring up a separate window here,
click on Ethan, I'm going to go back to that
Animation Window. Look at this! It's nuts!
So, this is just for the idle animation. This is just the idle, it's got
all of these key frames. It's absolutely
crazy, it takes a huge amount of work, and
this is your Stand Quarter Right,
your Humanoid Jump Mid-Air, it's quite simple that one. But look at Idle, for example; look how many different
key-frames we've got, for how many
different body parts.
And then, you could go into the curves, as well, and see it diagrammatically. Now, that's not unusual for
animating a character. You know, Disney films would use something like that as well, with
even more. So yeah! It's impressive! It's an art form, in its own right!
Absolutely, it's a huge amount of work to
get it right, but Unity supports it, is
the bottom line here. It's really really
powerful, allowing you to animate, and
then, it'll blend between these
animations for you. So, back to Unity!  Anything
else to tell you? One more thing about
Ethan, his animation is augmented by a
Third Person Character Script here, and
you'll see it's also taking in some
additional parameters about how he
animates, Moving Turn Speed, Jump Power,
Gravity Multiplier. And if you go into that script, you'll better see how that works.
There's a variety of set up at the start here,
and then, he's doing things like the
move. He's modifying the way it moves, applying extra rotation, when he turns to give some
momentum. Scaling his capsule for
crouching, those sort of things, you need
to be thinking about. So, if he's going to be in a crouch state, then his Capsule Collider needs to
be smaller, and then, you need to decide
on things like can he stand, when he's in
low headroom. So, these are the sort of
things where you need to be casting a
sphere, for example, which we haven't
covered yet, but this is similar to
detecting collisions, to say: Look can I
stand up here or can I not stand up here? So, in
totality and in summary, to animate a
humanoid properly you need animation
state machines, you need sometimes a
variety of different transition criteria.
So, for example, going from grounded to...
Let's have a look at one of these, here you go. From airborne to grounded has multiple
criteria, it depends on whether he's on
the ground or whether or not he's jumping
down, or the down animation is at a certain parameter value. You're going to
need Blend Trees, in order to make
realistic blends between different
motions, otherwise your going to get very
unnatural looking animation, and then
finally, once you've set up thousands of
key-frames, literally thousands of
key-frames, over in your animator... By the
way, this animation only lasts about 2 seconds,
2.1 seconds I think it is. The final thing
you need to do, is to be modifying
the animations with script. Now, the great
thing is that for third person and for first
person, not that there's so much animation involved in the first person, but at least
for third person you can use Ethan as a
starting point, because we can re-target
this animation to a completely different
skin. If you decide to go over here and
look for, I don't know, zombie. I don't know if there are any free zombies in the Asset
Store, but of course if you do a search there and you find an appropriately rigged zombie, you
could pull that in and then, apply that
mesh and have the same animations going
on. So, you've got a little bit of ammunition now, to go off and customize
Ethan. If you do know how to 3D model, then do it. If you want to go and find or
even buy a good zombie, I mean there's
one here, but I can't recommend it in the
course, because it's paid for but it's
probably a good asset.
You probably want to go and look on the asset store, and if you want to either
buy or find yourself a good zombie great!
I'm trying to teach you the basic
principles here. We've had such great
results from people, in Bowl Master, making
their own games without too much
guidance, and I want to start weaning you
off me giving you every single asset and
every single idea about user interface, etc.
By the way, have you built your user interface for this game yet, because remember at the beginning,
I said if you don't build it early then
you won't build it at all?
Then, in Bowl Master, we stopped building UI or any significant menu system. And I
wonder how many of you are actually still
building your user interfaces, because just
because I've stopped doing it, to wean you off, you need to keep building menu systems.
So, enjoy customizing Ethan, and I'm going to continue with the logic of the game now, and we will come back
and add more information about animations, if you want it and you need it later on. OK, see you soon!