Hey welcome back! We're going to talk about simple day-night cycles here. give this place a
little bit more atmosphere and a bit more
variety. So. we're going to talk about
the Earth's orbit. We'll be coding a very simple day-night cycle and using a time scale
parameter. So. a physics lesson or astrophysics lesson for you. Remember that
the Earth goes around the Sun once a year. On the left hand side of the diagram you've got.
kind of June-ish. and on the right hand
side of the diagram you've got December-ish.
so that's how it works. It's summer in
the Northern Hemisphere in June-ish.
because the Sun is more overhead. and
then. in December-ish it's more
overhead in the Southern Hemisphere. So.
the Earth's axis is offset from
the vertical by about 22 1/2 degrees. if I remember right. and there's a
reference there in the notes. So. when is
the Sun directly overhead? Well. it's
only directly overhead between the Tropic of Cancer and Capricorn and midday. So. on
June 21st at the Tropic of Cancer its overhead. and then. as you come down to say 10 degrees
north then it's overhead at midday on two
days of the year. April the 16th and August the 27th.
So. in our game we're going to be somewhere between the Equator and the Tropic of
Cancer. and we're going to pick a day
when the Sun does pass straight overhead.
So. it's going to be something like April the 16th or 27th Ok.
just so that we don't have to worry
about the Sun passing lower in the sky than
overhead. but it's relatively easy to
modify your scripts to do that if you ever wanted to and
that would be a challenge to you. So. before we go in and actually send you to do this
challenge. let's look at how we're going to do it. It's actually pretty simple. because
we just take the Sun. which is a
directional light. and let's say I want it
to rise in the east and let's say I want the east to be positive X then. I would rotate it
270 in Y. And then. you'll notice
that if I play with the X rotation of the Sun here...
give myself a bit more space...
then. the Sun will set and rise. So. all we're
going to do to get it to go overhead is to
rotate it in X. So. however the designer leaves it we want it
to start. If they leave it there. we want it to start there in X and Y. and then. we
want to move its transform around using a script. And then... oh. I've left a
script there. And then. that script is
going to automatically just rotate the
directional light like this and will
provide a time scale. So. of course this is
all a challenge for you. Here we go! Write
DayNightcycle.cs. Write a script on the
directional light. Publicly expose a float time scale. this is the number of minutes per second.
that are going to pass. Try setting that to 60 an issue. that's pretty common for games. One second in
the game is one minute. and see the
effect. Have a go. pause the video! Write that
relatively simple script right now. and
I will see you when you're done. Hey Ok. let's
make this day-night cycle happen then. So. call it Daycycle. I'm going to tidy it into my
Scripts Folder and have a little edit. So. what do we need to publicly expose? Well. I
said that we needed to publicly expose
the timeScale; Ok. that's fine. or we could
even be more explicit. We could say
minutesPerSecond;
there you go. that's fine! Now. if you do
want to give the designer even more
information. do you remember the annotation we can put. so that we get a popup in the
inspector? ...or a Tooltip. Yep. it's Tooltip. and it takes in a string. "Set
a value... What do we say? It's the ("Number of minutes per second that pass.
try 60"); There's a hint there. Ok. and then. close the Tooltip. And then. do we
need anything else? Well. no because it's only the transform of the very directional light
itself. So. here's the script. sitting on the
directional light. In a moment. when I
build this script my minutes per second should come through. unless I've made a syntax
error. which I have. I've put my semicolon in the wrong place. I must have also done
something else. I've put a semicolon in. and I don't need one. So. with these Tooltips. you don't need a
semicolon on the end of the line with
these annotations. Ok! Now. the script
should build! There we go. minutes per
second. and if I hover over it. it says:
Number of minutes per second that passed. try 60. And over here. you can see
that they have a transform on the unit. and it's only the transform that we need to
manipulate. So. I'm going to default that to 60 in the inspector. and then. just get the
script done. We do need one other member variable though. we need a private Vector3...
or is it a Quaternion? It's actually a
Quaternion for the rotations.
startRotation and at the start we need to find startRotation simply equals... If I can find my equals key.
= transform.rotation; Now. if you look at
that on the Intellisense there. you can
see that it's saying that it's a
Quaternion. They're still mysterious to us.
Quaternions. but it doesn't matter. Like a
light bulb we don't necessarily have to
know how they work to use them. They are actually four vectors. i.e. four element
vectors of complex numbers. which is why I'm staunchly avoiding them. for you guys. [Laughs]
Aright. so what are we going to do each frame? Well. one of the easiest things to do is to say
transform.RotateAround
Look at that method. it's static there. Ok. it needs a point.
an axis. and an angle. So. the point is just where we are. (transform.position
The axis is going to be Vector3.forward
if you think about it. because it's X. positive X is Vector3.forward
And let's hope or wish that we had angleThisFrame. We don't have angleThisFrame yet. but I want to keep the
line nice and short. So now. I go and right
angleThisFrame
Now. what is the angleThisFrame? Well.
without the time scaling. it is Time.deltaTime
divided by 360 degrees isn't it. Does that make sense
to you? So. if the frame time was one
second then. we have to divide...
We'd say a 360th of a second is the angle that we want to pass through.
but we need to multiply all that up by
the time scale. or minutesPerSecond. I think we've
called it. Ok so. hopefully that relatively simple math makes sense to you. Let's go and try it.
We have 60 set. let's hit play. The Sun starts where we left it. and then. let's just watch the
shadows. watch the hills. There are no shadows yet. You can see the rotation of the
directional light up there. is doing
its thing. and in a minute we will have a
dawn! It'll be a glorious dawn in our zombie game! Hello. Ethan! He's come to meet us. staring
hopefully over at the east. Ok. look to speed this up I'm going to start the Sun just
a little bit higher. It's a little bit
painfully low there. so if I look into the
positive X direction. you can move the
Sun up. There you go. just sticking his little
head above the mountain there. So. let's
go look at it!
Where is the Sun? There! Now. look at these shadows! Ah cool! You see it. up it comes. and that is about right!
It is doing about a minute a second. The way that I can tell. normally is just by looking at say tree
shadows. It's roughly what they do in a
game. they seem pretty violent right now.
but that's just because it's so early in
the morning. Realities like this as well
actually have very long shadows. because of the big angular difference. They move a lot very
very early in the morning. But if we were
to move the Sun up quite a lot.
kind of more overhead and then play. and
now go look at a tree shadow. it'll only
be moving very subtly if we stand still and look at it. You see. and that's reasonable. Cool hey! So. we
now have a day-night cycle! So.
congratulations if you passed that
coding challenge yourself! A job well done for you. and hopefully you can now
go ahead and modify that if you want to.
You could as an extra challenge. I'm not
going to show you the solution. but you
could for example come in here and say
what's my latitude? You could do some
searching around the web and try and work out
how to put the whole lot in. you know
workout latitude. Also. you'd need the time
of year. and then. it could actually do
the day-night cycle for this particular
time of year. Very useful if you were say
designing yourself a house in Unity.
You could then put a script that simulates the Sun position. for your time of year.
So. pretty cool! I hope you've enjoyed that. and I'll see you soon!
=======
Kind: captions
Language: en
Hey welcome back! We're going to talk about simple day-night cycles here, give this place a
little bit more atmosphere and a bit more
variety. So, we're going to talk about
the Earth's orbit. We'll be coding a very simple day-night cycle and using a time scale
parameter. So, a physics lesson or astrophysics lesson for you. Remember that
the Earth goes around the Sun once a year. On the left hand side of the diagram you've got,
kind of June-ish, and on the right hand
side of the diagram you've got December-ish,
so that's how it works. It's summer in
the Northern Hemisphere in June-ish.
because the Sun is more overhead, and
then, in December-ish it's more
overhead in the Southern Hemisphere. So,
the Earth's axis is offset from
the vertical by about 22 1/2 degrees, if I remember right, and there's a
reference there in the notes. So, when is
the Sun directly overhead? Well, it's
only directly overhead between the Tropic of Cancer and Capricorn and midday. So, on
June 21st at the Tropic of Cancer its overhead, and then, as you come down to say 10 degrees
north then it's overhead at midday on two
days of the year, April the 16th and August the 27th.
So, in our game we're going to be somewhere between the Equator and the Tropic of
Cancer, and we're going to pick a day
when the Sun does pass straight overhead.
So, it's going to be something like April the 16th or 27th Ok,
just so that we don't have to worry
about the Sun passing lower in the sky than
overhead, but it's relatively easy to
modify your scripts to do that if you ever wanted to and
that would be a challenge to you. So, before we go in and actually send you to do this
challenge, let's look at how we're going to do it. It's actually pretty simple, because
we just take the Sun, which is a
directional light, and let's say I want it
to rise in the east and let's say I want the east to be positive X then, I would rotate it
270 in Y. And then, you'll notice
that if I play with the X rotation of the Sun here...
give myself a bit more space...
then, the Sun will set and rise. So, all we're
going to do to get it to go overhead is to
rotate it in X. So, however the designer leaves it we want it
to start. If they leave it there, we want it to start there in X and Y, and then, we
want to move its transform around using a script. And then... oh, I've left a
script there. And then, that script is
going to automatically just rotate the
directional light like this and will
provide a time scale. So, of course this is
all a challenge for you. Here we go! Write
DayNightcycle.cs. Write a script on the
directional light. Publicly expose a float time scale, this is the number of minutes per second,
that are going to pass. Try setting that to 60 an issue, that's pretty common for games. One second in
the game is one minute, and see the
effect. Have a go, pause the video! Write that
relatively simple script right now, and
I will see you when you're done. Hey Ok, let's
make this day-night cycle happen then. So, call it Daycycle, I'm going to tidy it into my
Scripts Folder and have a little edit. So, what do we need to publicly expose? Well, I
said that we needed to publicly expose
the timeScale; Ok, that's fine, or we could
even be more explicit. We could say
minutesPerSecond;
there you go, that's fine! Now, if you do
want to give the designer even more
information, do you remember the annotation we can put, so that we get a popup in the
inspector? ...or a Tooltip. Yep, it's Tooltip, and it takes in a string. "Set
a value... What do we say? It's the ("Number of minutes per second that pass,
try 60"); There's a hint there, Ok, and then, close the Tooltip. And then, do we
need anything else? Well, no because it's only the transform of the very directional light
itself. So, here's the script, sitting on the
directional light. In a moment, when I
build this script my minutes per second should come through, unless I've made a syntax
error, which I have. I've put my semicolon in the wrong place. I must have also done
something else. I've put a semicolon in, and I don't need one. So, with these Tooltips, you don't need a
semicolon on the end of the line with
these annotations. Ok! Now, the script
should build! There we go, minutes per
second, and if I hover over it, it says:
Number of minutes per second that passed, try 60. And over here, you can see
that they have a transform on the unit, and it's only the transform that we need to
manipulate. So, I'm going to default that to 60 in the inspector, and then, just get the
script done. We do need one other member variable though, we need a private Vector3...
or is it a Quaternion? It's actually a
Quaternion for the rotations.
startRotation and at the start we need to find startRotation simply equals... If I can find my equals key.
= transform.rotation; Now, if you look at
that on the Intellisense there, you can
see that it's saying that it's a
Quaternion. They're still mysterious to us,
Quaternions, but it doesn't matter. Like a
light bulb we don't necessarily have to
know how they work to use them. They are actually four vectors, i.e. four element
vectors of complex numbers, which is why I'm staunchly avoiding them, for you guys. [Laughs]
Aright, so what are we going to do each frame? Well, one of the easiest things to do is to say
transform.RotateAround
Look at that method, it's static there. Ok, it needs a point,
an axis, and an angle. So, the point is just where we are. (transform.position
The axis is going to be Vector3.forward
if you think about it, because it's X, positive X is Vector3.forward
And let's hope or wish that we had angleThisFrame. We don't have angleThisFrame yet, but I want to keep the
line nice and short. So now, I go and right
angleThisFrame
Now, what is the angleThisFrame? Well,
without the time scaling, it is Time.deltaTime
divided by 360 degrees isn't it. Does that make sense
to you? So, if the frame time was one
second then, we have to divide...
We'd say a 360th of a second is the angle that we want to pass through,
but we need to multiply all that up by
the time scale, or minutesPerSecond, I think we've
called it. Ok so, hopefully that relatively simple math makes sense to you. Let's go and try it.
We have 60 set, let's hit play. The Sun starts where we left it, and then, let's just watch the
shadows, watch the hills. There are no shadows yet. You can see the rotation of the
directional light up there, is doing
its thing, and in a minute we will have a
dawn! It'll be a glorious dawn in our zombie game! Hello, Ethan! He's come to meet us, staring
hopefully over at the east. Ok, look to speed this up I'm going to start the Sun just
a little bit higher. It's a little bit
painfully low there, so if I look into the
positive X direction, you can move the
Sun up. There you go, just sticking his little
head above the mountain there. So, let's
go look at it!
Where is the Sun? There! Now, look at these shadows! Ah cool! You see it, up it comes, and that is about right!
It is doing about a minute a second. The way that I can tell, normally is just by looking at say tree
shadows. It's roughly what they do in a
game, they seem pretty violent right now,
but that's just because it's so early in
the morning. Realities like this as well
actually have very long shadows, because of the big angular difference. They move a lot very
very early in the morning. But if we were
to move the Sun up quite a lot,
kind of more overhead and then play, and
now go look at a tree shadow, it'll only
be moving very subtly if we stand still and look at it. You see, and that's reasonable. Cool hey! So, we
now have a day-night cycle! So,
congratulations if you passed that
coding challenge yourself! A job well done for you, and hopefully you can now
go ahead and modify that if you want to.
You could as an extra challenge, I'm not
going to show you the solution, but you
could for example come in here and say
what's my latitude? You could do some
searching around the web and try and work out
how to put the whole lot in, you know
workout latitude. Also, you'd need the time
of year, and then, it could actually do
the day-night cycle for this particular
time of year. Very useful if you were say
designing yourself a house in Unity.
You could then put a script that simulates the Sun position, for your time of year.
So, pretty cool! I hope you've enjoyed that, and I'll see you soon!
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1:Unity/Section9/ZR18 Simple Day & Night Cycle.srt