Hey hey welcome back! So. we're going to be talking about searching for a clear area.
We're going to be helping the player look
for a suitable landing place. just talk about
which type of collider we need to detect a
clear area. we'll create a simple system for
it. and I'll talk a bit more about my growing
vision for the game as a whole. So. I think
what I'm going to end up doing in this game
is. have the player in the first scene. just
be falling from the air. probably looking
up. so that it doesn't give away the size
of the terrain. and possibly. at night. I'll
decide that later. anyway the idea is. you
kind of go splat. you hit the ground. it fades
to black. and then. you wake up. And when
you wake up. all your prompts are driven by
my innerVoice. So. I'm going to land on the
ground and say something like "Shit. the parachute must have not opened. Got to find a clear
flat space the size of a tennis court. to
call a HELO." or something a little more thought
out. And then. you'll go around. running aroundlooking for a sufficiently large. clear space
to land and helicopter. Now. how big a space
is that? Well. I'm a helicopter pilot myself.
and I think that a tennis court is good enough.
for a small helicopter. So. something like
18 by 30 meters. something like that should
be enough. Call it 18 by 30 or 18 by 40. don't
mind 20 by 40 meters. We like to have a bit
of a run in. it's not very safe to be doing
vertical landings. in case you have an engine
failure. especially in a single engine helicopter.
Anyway. I digress. So. what we want to do
is have some way of the player being able
to wonder around and find a clear area. So.
you can explore the different types of ways
of doing that. You can do ray casting. but
that's more complicated than we need. and
you haven't seen a ray cast yet. or you would
normally just reach for a collider. Now. you
may think you could use say a 2D Circle Collider.
but you can't. because you cannot prevent
a Circle Collider from being just purely in
the X Y plane. and we need something in the
X Z plane. And as you look through all the
different types of colliders. you'll find
that probably the only one that works sensibly
is a Box Collider. And anyway. it's the right
kind of shape. so I'm going to put a Box Collider
on the player. or am I? Let me think about
the architecture of this. Do I want to consider
the player to have a collider and possibly
cause a bit of confusion with the character
controller's collider. or rather the... Where
is it? Yeah. the Character Controller itself
has this Capsule Collider on it. It's actually
being controlled here. you see. Even though.
if you turn it off. it doesn't stop displaying.
the Character Controller comes bundled with
a Capsule Collider. So. I could put the box
collider on the player. that's find. or I
could be more explicit and create a new sub-object
of the player. called something like Clear
Area. centered on the player. Now. that could
have a Box Collider and just be a plain vanilla
thing. OK. so there it is. there is a box.
Now. I said 20 by 40 meters. I think it would
be easier for the player. if the 20 meters
extended out in front of them. so if we go
40 rather in the Z and 20 let's say in the
X. There you go. Now. depending on your terrain
you may need to mess around with that size
a bit. or mess around with you trees. but
that's a sort of size for me. where it won't
always fit. If I go and look from above. it's
certainly not going to fit everywhere. right.
but there will be places where he can find
a clear space. So. that's pretty good for
me. OK. so there we have. on the player. this
clear area box. Now. you want its transform
to be reset. it wants to be right at the root
of the player. There it is. Now. the other
thing we want to watch out for with it is
the grass. It's because it needs to not be
colliding with the grass. It should collide
with the trees. because the trees have colliders
on them. and the way to check that of course
is to go to Terrain. Settings. and then. down
here. you'll see Enable Tree Colliders. So.
we'll see that in a minute. when we inspect
the scripts. So. what we don't have is a way
of keeping it above the grass. so why don't
we put it at 1.5 meters off the ground. Something
like that. So. there's a Box Collider. just
floating. centered on the player. and of course
remember if you go into Game and turn Gizmos
on. at the top right here. you can actually.
in the Game View. see this Box. temporarily.
OK. now the player is not going to see this.
but we want to... Well. he could I suppose.
but we don't really need them to. We can use
sound prompts to tell them what they need
to be doing. but it's useful maybe for the
moment. So. that's it there's the collider
that you need. We can make it a trigger. and
it should collide with the terrain. if the
terrain comes up. which is good. because we
want to be landing on a flat area of ground.
Other things this box will collide with. include
the zombie. here. and the trees. which is
all fine. Now. we don't actually need a zombie
at the moment. We're going to instantiate
the zombie. after we've called the helicopter.
It's tempting just to delete the zombie from
here. but don't do that. because we spend
a lot of work and time on this zombie. Various
things like the Navmesh Agent Settings. we've
spend time tweaking. if you remember. and
various other things. Now. I know it's based
on a prefab at the moment. but if you look
at that prefab. it's here in the Standard
Assets.. and I don't want it to be based on
that prefab. I want it to be based on our
own new prefab. Let me show you a couple of
new things. I'm going to create a folder.
again. and I'm going to call it Prefab. just
for now. and then. in there I want to show
you that you can actually create a prefab
inside there. And I'm going to call it Zombie.
and it's just a blank prefab placeholder.
And then. you can drag your zombie from the
Hierarchy onto that Zombie Prefab placeholder.
and there he is and now you have a properly
prefabbed zombie. So. now I test that by dropping
a second zombie in the scene. and if you have
a look around in Game View. we should find
that Ethan is running over there from his
normal direction but also that there is another
zombie on the way. And their possibly stuck.
I'm not sure where that second zombie is.
so let's look in Scene View. He is stuck and
that is because he probably doesn't have a
target. but that's OK. we get the idea. He's
there. he's working. We could make him target
the player. and he should run off in our direction.
There we go. So the purpose of that is just
to make sure that. that prefab actually works
properly. and from somewhere we'll probably
see another zombie. running towards us. There
he is. The reason he's got a green outline
is. because we still have Gizmos turned on
in Game View. There you go. Cool. and there
he comes. OK! Fantastic! So. that prefab works.
and now we can comfortably delete both zombies
from the scene. Now. this is an edit of this
video. and previously I deleted the zombie
without thinking about that. so from now on.
for the rest of this video you won't see the
Prefabs Folder. and it'll come in. in the
next video. So. don't worry about that. and
now. I'm going to talk about my vision for
the game. What I'm going to do is have the
game that you land. you go: Ugh! It's night
time. you're lighting everything with a flare.
You look around for a suitable landing place.
you call the helicopter by firing up a flare
into the air. and then. all hell breaks loose.
OK. so that's the kind of plan. So. there
it is. there's the collider. What I want you
to do now. is a little challenge. I want you
to create a landing area detector. Use the
3D Box Collider. that we just put on. wait
for one clear second of no collisions. Well.
their actually strictly triggers. because
it's a Trigger Collider. And then. trigger
a sound file of your own. And my sound file
is going to go something like: This spot should
do. Something like that. Call this spot should
do. You know. I'll do my best Duke Nukem voice.
Cool! So. pause the video. and just try and
get that working now. OK. welcome back! So.
how are we going to make this work. Well.
we can put a script right here on the clear
area thing. and we can just call it clear
area. I guess. Clear Area Script. Create and
Add. Fantastic! OK. so how is the Clear Area
Script going to work? Well. it's going to
need a private float. which is timeSinceLastTrigger;
And it may as well start off as 0. as if it's
colliding immediately. Now. what components
is this guy going to need to look for? Not
a lot. I don't think. I think it's a question
of going like this: void OnTriggerEnter () And
we actually don't care what it collides with.
I don't think. at the moment. so we don't
necessarily need to pass... Excuse me. [Coughs]
We don't necessarily need to pass in any parameters
over here. So. when a trigger happens we go
timeSinceLastTrigger = 0) because we've just
triggered. OK. and then. on every update.
we can say timeSinceLastTrigger += the frame
time Time.deltaTime; And then. again every
Update. we can ask the question well. is it
time to declare that we have a suitable landing
area? So. before we go any farther. let's
just make some things public and look how
this works. at the moment. before we get too
abstract. So. we simply have a float there.
That should count up. until the triggers stop.
Let's make sure that. that actually works.
So. inspecting the clear area. it's been over
a second. and as soon as that collider intersepts
a tree there. well you see the first time
it touches a tree. it resets. but it doesn't
keep resetting. So. that's not the behavior
we want. and it's because of instead of OnTriggerEnter.
I want OnTriggerStay. Let's try again. So.
we start here. and the time is over a second.
because we're starting in a clear area. but
now it's staying under a second until we return
to a clear area. So. I'm just going to change
the default start position of my player. to
somewhere that is not a clear area. much more
in the trees. like over here and see how that
looks. Now. again watching the clear area
component. Oh. I do seem to be in a clear
area. that was unlucky. How did I manage that?
Really! He's not in a clear area. These trees
aren't triggering. for some reason. Let me
move a little bit further out. make sure there's
a tree in the box. OK. so the trees that are
on me are triggering now. Oh. I have noticed.
by the way. that my clear area has shifted.
Be careful what you drag. when you drag this
clear area around. Are you moving the player.
as a whole. or are you just moving its clear
area box? OK. be a little bit careful. you
want the clear area to stay centered on the
player. Cool! So. here we are in a clear area.
and there. we're not. So. I'm actually going
to make my box bigger. My clear area is clearly
not big enough. so I'm going to make it 30
meters wide by 40 meters long. It's obviously
not enough of a challenge. Here you go. So.
time since last trigger is staying below 1
second. and if I wonder around. and later
this will be under.. Ah. you go! You went
under a second. somewhere around here. And
the idea is that when you stay. in the clear
like this. for more than a second then. he
goes "This should do". So. let's make that
bit work. if (timeSinceLastTrigger is greater
than1 float then. what are we going to do?
Well. let's put a log entry out. OK. we found
a clear area. We can also play a sound clip.
so let me make sure that finding the clear
area works properly first. I'm looking at
the Console. wondering around. I'm going to
say something like "I need to find a clear
flat area to land to land a HELO." I go here.
and found clear area. and it keeps firing.
but that's OK. I don't think we really care
about that necessarily. We could put a boolean
flag or some sort of toggle in here. but it
depends what we do next. Now. we're just trying
to play a sound file. and we're done. So.
where is the sound file going to come off?
Well. good question. Let's take a look. and
see if we've already got a source. We have
already got an AudioSource on the player.
and the script is being driven by the Player
Script. So. let's go just take a look at the
Player Script. This doesn't currently find
his AudioSource. The AudioSource on the player
is currently being used only by the Character
Controller for the footstep sounds. So. it's
still going to be a voice in our head. so
it's definitely going to come on the player.
So. I think that we will use the player. and
I think we need to think about the architecture.
We need to think how are we going to tell
the player to think something. if he is going
to have a voice in his head regularly. how
are we going to tell him to think stuff? An
Enum may be a good idea here. but regardless
of the solution we come up with. we've gotten
to a point where we need to think a bit more
carefully about the architecture. So. I'm
not going to put the audio call in here. because
we know how to do it. we know that this is
being called. so we could easily put an audio
clip player in here. We need to think a little
bit carefully about where these audio clips
are stored. how we keep track of all the different
things the player could think and say to himself
in his head. etc. So. that will be the subject
of another video. Cool! Ah. at least we've
got this far. and we have a way of finding
clear areas. which is pretty cool. I like
it. it's just a Box Collider around the player.
with an OnTriggerStay. and it's high enough.
1.5 meters in my case off the ground. to not
get triggered by the grass and it gets triggered
by trees and it'll also get triggered by terrain
that's going up. Let's just show you that
quickly. If we head off to an area that's
clear of trees. but go down into a dip in
the terrain. this still wouldn't be a very
good helicopter landing area. right. and our
system detects that. It's pretty cool! Look!
That guy is not suitable. it keeps resetting
the time since last trigger. because the collider
is sitting in the terrain. even tough there
are no trees around. So. pretty cool system!
Congratulations. if you came up with it yourself!
And if you've made some improvements. And
And yeah. I look forward to seeing you in the
next video.