Hey welcome back! So, we're going to use a technique called an innerVoice, to guide the
player. So, we'll be using an innerVoice to guide the player around the scene, recording some
sound prompts, and triggering sound prompts at the right time. So, let's
start at the very beginning. Why are we here? What's going on? Well, we don't know.
We could use a lot of UI and we've learned about UI, but how about using sound. So, if we
click Play, what happens? Well firstly, we've
got a problem, which is that for some
reason, it's ignoring the trees that are within this collider, and it's calling the
helicopter, all automatically for us, far
too quickly. So, we have quite a nice
division of responsibility, the calling
of the helicopter is handled by
the Clear Area Script, we know that. So, in the Clear Area Script, I'm going to just add
another condition. I'm going to say that we
are going to send the found clear area
message upwards, if it's been more than a second of not colliding with any
trees or anything, but we also want the Time.realtimeSinceStartup
which is how long the game has been running, to be greater than, say 10 seconds. And what
that will do when we play, it will just
suppress that initial helicopter call,
for at least 10 seconds, by then, the
player is likely to have moved around, and
we'll have time to play our voice
prompts. OK, so back to the scripts, so
you know what to add. It's simply adding
this bit, which is making sure with 10
seconds have passed, you can choose a
different value of course. OK fine!
So, what I want to do, is at the very beginning of the game, I want to set
the scene a little bit. Now, you might want to make a fade up, you know a visual fade up.
There's lots of ways of doing that, there's lots of fancy things you can do, but I just
want to crack on and get the important
bits done for you. So, the player
itself is going to need access to various
different sound files. So, I'm going to make a little
section here for sound files, and let's have explicitly just write each one out. We could use
arrays, we could not even connect them to
the player, we could just find them based
on their name inside the assets, but I'm
just going to, for each one, just say I have an
AudioClip, and I'm going to have the first one as just, whatHappened; audio public AudioClip
whatHappened, which of course means that the player, when we look at his script
or her script, is going to be asking for a whatHappened.
OK, so let's go record what happened, just
for fun. Now, have some fun yourself, record
yourself an audio script for setting the scene, but I'm just going to make a fool of
myself now, by recording something in
a voice far deeper than I'm qualified to use.
And I'm just going to record something daft. So, have a few goes and see how it goes.
[He Says in a Character's Deep Voice] Ah, what the hell happened! I better call for some help!
Got to find an area about the size of a
tennis court and call a HELO! I think that sounds really stupid. Let's try it!
[The Recording Plays] Ah, what the hell happened! I better call for some help!
Got to find an area about the size of a
tennis court and call a HELO! [Ben Starts Talking] OK, well that'll do. So, I'm
just going to trim the sound there, and then, export the selection here in Audacity.
You can use your favorite sound program, or you can use Audacity as well, and I'm
just going to call this what happened.
And I'm going to save it as an .ogg file, because it's compatible with a lot of different
formats, a lot of different platforms,
should I say target platforms. Cool! So, there
it goes what happened? And of course, I'm going to put that in your start pack for
you, so by the time you watch this video,
we will have an Audio Folder inside your start pack.
So, here we go, audio and very simply just add it. Simple stuff right, but needs doing and no point in me
skipping over it. What happened? Here We go, boom! So, when is that going to play? Well that may as
well play, at the beginning. Now, be careful with these sound units on the player.
The player already has an AudioSource, but if we play the game and look at
that AudioSource, you'll notice it does
things like jump and footsteps.
That AudioSource is being handled or being used by the character controller,
first-person character controller, and
it's using these jump and land and other
sounds. So, we're going to need a new AudioSource. There's other ways of doing this, but
one of the easiest ways is just to add a
new AudioSource, to the player, and think
about whether it's 2D or 3D. Well, I think
it's 2D, because it's his innerVoice. OK, and
it doesn't currently have an AudioClip,
of any sort. We're going to pass audio clips into it.
So, the question of which AudioSource we
would grab, should we try and use this
second AudioSource, is quite an
interesting one, because
the first person controller, rather script here, already does the following
in the Start, it goes and finds a component of type AudioSource, but this
is kind of assuming there's just one. And
if we had a second AudioSource, which we
want to do, because we want footsteps to
play, as well as the innerVoice, then
how's this going to know which one to grab? How do we know that this is going to
address the correct AudioSource? Well, we don't, at the moment, so if you're going to use
off the shelf scripts, like this, it's fine,
and it brings you a lot of power, but the
dark side is, you sometimes need to
modify them. So, let's go ahead and do
that, let's change the First Person
Controller Script, for a start, so that we
can make sure that it grabs the right
AudioSource. Now, how do we
differentiate them? Well, let's take a
look at them. I would like them to be next
to each other, so I can move this
component up or not. It's going to lose the
prefab connection. Let me just look at
something. Look at your player, right click on
your player and look at the prefab. Where is it? It's still in the Standard  Asset,
you can see we've never prefabbed the player, all we've done is updated an existing FPS
Controller prefab. Not a particularly good
idea. Now, I think it's a good time to
make our own prefab of the player, so
drag your player down into your Prefabs Folder.
Now, you have this player, if you select Prefab, connected over here. That's fine, then you
will find that you should be able to move
your audio sources together, so a side
effect of just trying to move that up, was
realizing that the prefab is not
properly stored. OK, so now we have two
audio sources, on this player. How are we going to
distinguish between them? Well, let's use
the priority, the default priority here
is 128, for the one that came on
the prefab, for the footsteps. We'll leave
it at that, and then, we will put a much
higher priority, let's call it one, on the
innerVoice. The innerVoice AudioSource is really important. Now, we can't
label it any other way, but we could set
a priority of 1. So, now we have two audio
sources, one is a 3D AudioSource, making
the footsteps, and other players will be able to hear that,
and the second one is a 2D AudioSource, that only we hear, that is for the innerVoice.
We haven't arranged that only we hear it,
but there's only one player, so who cares
right. So, what the scripts are going to do is find all the AudioSource
components and then, use the priority to
distinguish between them. This is just one of many
different ways of doing it. Let's start by doing this, with the First Person
Controller Script, and then, I'll ask you to do it for the player. So, instead of going
GetComponent source, what we want to do is, we want to say temporarily, let's
have our self an AudioSource array, audio
sources, here in the First Person Controller.cs,
and that = GetComponents, that's with an S, of type AudioSource. OK, and
then... Oops, I'll get my brackets around the right way. So, there has returned to me an array of audio
sources, and then, we want to say foreach (AudioSource
I'm thinking of type AudioSource, so it is a capital, in audioSources), which is an array.
If audioSource... here you go, get the syntax right. So, for each audioSource variable, of type
AudioSource, in the audioSources array, if (audioSource.priority == 128)
then, we do this m_AudioSource = audioSource;
otherwise, we just simply do nothing. So, let's firstly check
that, that works. What this should be doing... You're allowed to convert the type in here, when
you build this. What this should be doing
is, still working just fine. We should be able to
hear our foot steps, and we can and that's fine. Let's inspect the player, have a little
look at his setup, and we have an AudioSource there, the top one there,
the Footstep 01 Footstep 02, toggling away, and our other audio sources doing absolutely
nothing at the moment. That's great! So, now what I want you to do is, I want you to
apply a similar idea across to the
players. So, in the Player Script, we
started thinking about the idea of
having an AudioSource. We have an AudioClip,
but what we haven't done yet is
determine the right AudioSource. So, what I want you to
do is go private AudioSource InnnerVoice; And then, in the Start, I want you to write a bit of code
that finds the correct AudioSource for
the innerVoice.
So, go ahead pause the video, and go and find the correct or innerVoice AudioSource,
right now. OK welcome back! So, I'm going to use the code that we had over here. You're allowed to copy and
paste code once, do it too many times, you'll want to start making separate methods. So, I think it's
that. We have an array of audio sources,
we go and get all of them, we see if the
priority is 1 and if that is, then the innerVoice becomes the AudioSource. Fantastic!
So, when we start the game, when the player
first starts, we want to be saying that
the innerVoice.clip = whatHappened;
And then, we want to do innerVoice.Play ();
as a method. OK, let's go make sure
whatHappened is connected up to the
player. I think it is, but let's see. It doesn't
go in here, it does not go in the clip,
that gets set up, run time. It goes down in What Happened here, so What Happened.
Let's select What Happened in the resulting dialogue, and let's see what happens, at
the very beginning. [Game Character Talks] Ah, what the hell happened! I better call for some help! I've got to
find an area about the size of a tennis court and call a HELO! [Ben Starts Talking] That's cool! Now, if we look at... I don't know whether it's cool,
but it's something. And now, he's found a clear area, and the helicopter comes in.
Fantastic! So, you can see that, that is a
way of having two different AudioSources
on the player and then distinguishing them by their priority.
We do want a higher priority on the innerVoice anyway. So, now we know what we need
to be doing, when the game starts this...[Game Character Talks in Background]
[Ben Start Talking] Now, I'm not finding these tree colliders particularly reliable, but when we get there,
the rescue helicopter gets called. Now, you may want to polish this a bit, you
you may want to give some affordance to the player, say something like, I better hang
around here and deploy a flare, or you might want to have a countdown or even
make them push a button to call the
helicopter. Mine is just calling the
helicopter immediately, when we get to
a clear area, but that's fine. So, that is how you deal with multiple AudioSources, or
one way of doing it, and then, shortley we'll be looking at the question of how
we arranged for the helicopter to
actually land, at the place that we have found.