So. are you ready for a code refactoring party!
In this message. in this video. we're going
to be sending messages up and down the hierarchy.
using Invoke() to delay audio playback. And
you'll be writing RadioSystem.cs for radio
communications. So. let's get this puppy refactored!
I'm just going to go through the scripts.
from left to right. and I'm going to think
about each one and how we might want it now
that we've moved things around and generally
messed things up. And then. let's refactor.
So. the purpose of all of this refactoring.
of course is. this is exactly the sort of
thing you want to be doing regularly is constantly
improving your architecture but now over improving
it. You want to improve it enough to make
your life easy and to make it expandable.
but be aware of your never going to need it
syndrome. which is where you do so much refactoring
and you try and make so much provision for
future functionality that actually. the chances
are you're never going to need it. And also.
the code becomes more complex then. and so
there's a fine balance. Well. it's certainly
worth us doing some refactoring. right now.
So. let's look at clear area. which is the
part of the of the player that looks for a
clear area. It doesn't need a Start method.
so I'm going to get rid of just the stat block
there. just to save some space. What else
is going to be different on here? Well. when
we do find a clear area. yes he wants to send
a message upwards. which will be very useful.
The other thing that we want to do is we want
to send this message up the hierarchy once.
not every single frame. when these conditions
are met. We need one more condition in here.
It's all very well waiting a second since
the last trigger and then. not going off within
the first 10 seconds. but we also once we've
found a clear area we want to never send that
message again. So. let's just say and not
(foundClearArea) Let's make ourselves a private
boolean. just called foundClearArea and start
it as false. and then check for it there.
And then. of course once we've sent the message
let's just say foundClearArea = true; so that
it no longer sends this message. This loop
just won't trigger in the future. So. that
would be very useful. I think that's all you
probably need to do. Actually. one of our
students. I think it was Doug. very helpful
he said. "you know you need to be a bit careful
with this OnTriggerStay. the player itself
can trigger it." So. we could say firstly.
what's the collider? So. (Collider collider)
and then. if (collider.tag doesn't = the "Player")
so we only want to consider collisions. when
the collider's tag is not the player. OK.
so the name collider. What's wrong? I have
spelled collider wrong. OK fantastic! So.
let's go and tag the player. over in Unity
now. as a player very simply. So. we have
the radio system and the player. and then.
we need... We already have a tag called player
actually. it's a default. Fantastic! So. that
one is done. Now. let's move on to the next
script. I'm just going to go to Daycycle and
see what we need to do inside Daycycle. and
I don't think we need to change anything in
Daycycle. In the last video I already took
out the starting angle. because we didn't
need it just moved things from where they
were. OK. so Daycycle needs no refactoring.
Eyes. what are the Eyes all about? So. the
Eyes are the players eyes and the zooming.
Again. I don't think that we need to do anything
to that. it all looks perfectly straightforward
right now. Some people were asking about zooming
in and out smoothly. but you can look that
up in the discussions. Okey Doke. the helicopter.
I'm sure we're going to need to do some work
on the helicopter. because we're going to
be simplifying the helicopter. Let's think
about it. The helicopter just has a wacky
wacky sound on it. for want of a better word.
which is if we look at it just attached to
the AudioSource. The clip is defined from
the beginning. and it plays on awakened loops.
this helicopter sound. So. we don't actually
need to access an AudioSource in script. I'm
just going to make sure this helicopter sound
is aware that it is. because .oggs are causing
people problems on Windows. OK. so back over
in the script. then. We don't need access
to the audio clip anymore. I do want to keep
track of where the helicopter is being called.
but again we don't need access to an audio
source. We do want the Rigidbody and then.
the red will tell us whatever lines to delete.
The audioSource there. and these two lines
about audioSource. Fantastic! We're actually
going to. rather than have a method called call. I'm going to have a... It can just be
protected it doesn't need to have a public
for private. it can just be default. But instead
of Call. I'm going to have this OnDispatchHelicopter
() message. and we won't worry at the helicopter
level about whether it's called or not. we'll
worry about that somewhere else. So. OnDispatchHelicopter
() we are going to log that the helicopter
has been dispatched. set a velocity. and say
that the call is true. That will do! So. it's
very similar. but instead of using a called
method. we're going to use a OnDispatchHelicopter
() message there. OK. and I seem to have an
extra closing bracket. for some reason. Fantastic!
So. yep that's fine. Now. we won't worry about
the fact that the player doesn't work. I'm
just going to step through the scripts. one
at a time. refactoring them as I go. So. let's
go to innerVoice. How is innerVoice gong to
change? We created innerVoice. added it to
that sub-object of the player. but we never
actually wrote any script. So. innerVoice
is just going to have a list of all the things
that the innerVoice may say. One of those
is an audio clip called whatHappened; What
the hell happened type of thing. And we're
going to have another clip explicitly listed
in here called goodLandingArea; So. hey I've
found a great landing area type of thing.
We're going to have a private AudioSource.
which is going to go and find the audioSource;
component. So. let's do that. The audioSource
= GetComponent&lt;AudioSource&gt; (); and we just
have some squiggle's and a semicolon. Fantastic!
What else do we need to do with the Start.
We're at the very beginning. we may as well
set the first audio clip. So. audioSource.clip
= whatHappened; So. the first thing we are
going to say. is "What happened". when we
arrive in the space. and we may as well go
ahead and play it from the beginning. You
could just do this by attaching that clip
in the Inspector and saying Play. at the Start.
this is just an alternative for you. We're
not going to need the update. but the innerVoice
is going to need to know that when we've found
a clear area. So. OnFindClearArea (). I like
to start with On. to be consistent with Unity.
Then. we may as well print out the name of
this GameObject. i.e. innerVoice. this component
this script. innerVoice. and then. the fact
that this message has been received. It's
going to help us in the Console to see exactly
what's going on. So. we'll see that innerVoice
found clear area. and then. we may as well
change the clip across to to goodLandingArea;
So. he's going to go. "Hey. this seems like
a good landing area. I'm going to put out
a flare." And then. we're just going to go
and play that AudioSource there. OK. and then.
we need to wait a little bit. so we're going
to Invoke ("CallHeli" and you're going to
need this type of thing in your challenge.
in a minute. but we'll do this after goodLandingArea.Length
And we could immediately call the heli or
we could do it a second after maybe this broadcast
is finished. So. he's going to say "Hey. I've
found a great landing area. I'm going to put
out a flare and call the helicopter". and
then. it will play that and then it will wait
for the amount of time that. that sample lasts.
plus an extra second before it Invokes a new
method. Now. because of the way Invoke works.
we can only supply a string name. we're having
to create ourselves a simple new method called
CallHeli (). here. And that can do whatever
we need to do. which is going to send the
message updwards. and the message is going
to be ("OnMakeInitialHeliCall"); And that's
going to send the message upwards. from the
innerVoice. through the player. right up to
the radio system for anything that needs to
receive it to receive it. OK. so that's ("OnMakeInitialHeliCall");.
What other scripts have we got in here? The
player. how do we need to change the player?
Well. let's take a look. We're nearly there.
by the way. You are going to be writing the
final script in this series. which is going
to be the radio system itself. So. let's take
a look at the Player. What needs to be on
the Player. what doesn't? The Player no longer
needs a reference to the helicopter. in our
new architecture. It still wants the spawn
points. We don't need to know whatHappened.
The whatHappened AudioClip is going to be
attached to the innerVoice. Remember. it's
an innerVoice thing happening. so it's nice.
it's separated out. What else have we got.
We've got some things to do with re-spawning.
spawn points. etc. Last re-sapawn toggle.
I might rename that LastRespawnToggle. Now.
we're not really using Player spawning. at
the moment. but there's no point in removing
this functionality. And then. the innerVoice
is no longer directly on the Player. so we
remove that reference to innerVoice. which
means that we can remove all this rubbish
here about finding AudioSources and sorting
them by priority. That can all just go. So.
all we do on Start is just find the spawn
points. Then. in Update. we have a bunch of
stuff to do with the re-spawning. which we
may as well leave where it is. including the
re-spawn method. And now. when we find a clear
area. let's just take a completely fresh view
on finding a clear area. What are we going
to do. when we find a clear area? Well. actually.
all we're going to do. as far as the Player's
behavior. is we're just going to drop a flare.
So. the clear area is going to broadcast a
message upwards. and various things are going
to hear it. including the radio system. but
the player himself is just going to drop a
flare. Not immediately! He's going to say
something like. "This sounds like a good area.
I'm going to drop a flare and call a helicopter."
So. he wants to ("DropFlare") which is going
to be a method that we'll create in a moment.
after say 3 seconds. And then. you can have
another message. DropFlare. it's a method.
and that's a very simple thing that is going
to drop a flare. So. for now. just say drop
a flare. It will be a subject of a future
lecture. to create and drop the landing area.
OK. so is that all building. That seems to
be building. Fantastic! Alright. so finally.
it's your job to write the last script. which
ties it all together. which is the RadioSystem.
so I want you to write RadioSystem.cs. I want
you to make a void on make initialHeliCall
method. I want you to play initialHeliCall.
there's an audio clip. immediately. One second
after that finishes. play initialCallReply.
and then. send a message to all the children
called. called "OnDispatchHelicopter". Alright.
good luck with that! And. I'll see you in
a second. Cool welcome back! So. let's just
get the helicopter's RadioSystem working.
So. what are we going to write in the RadioSystem?
Well. let's have a little think about it.
It's going to need a couple of public audio
clips. One of them is going to be called initialHeliCall;
You see it's much nicer. because everything
sits against the object where it naturally
should site. right. All the radio clips are
against the radio. all the thoughts are against
the innerVoice. etc. It's really hard to talk
and type something completely different. at
the same time. I seem to be doing it though.
OK. so the private AudioSource. this gets
boring doesn't it. We have to keep doing that.
We could almost make a keyboard shortcut for
that. So. let's just go find that audioSource
again = GetComponent of type &lt;AudioSource&gt;
() Boosh. boom. bang. wallop! Fantastic! Alright
now. we need this on... I said I want you
to make a void OnMake initial helicall. did
I say? What was the name of the method? void
OnMakeInitialHeliCall. I think. Now. is that
what we used in the other script? Let me just
see what we did. Clear area. send message
on final clear area. that's fine. What other
messages? I'm just looking around to make
sure we get the message names right. OnFindClearArea.
matches OnFindClearArea good. OnFindClearArea.
yeah. OnMakeInitialHeliCall. that's right.
It's a
good idea to cut and paste message names.
because you don't get any auto-complete help
with them. We may as well. just print out
that this component has made an initial heli
call. especially while I've got it in the
paste bugger. just so that the console gives
us some usefulness. OK. so the audioSource.clip
= initialHeliCall; And then. as I did in one
of the other examples. a few minutes ago.
we want an audioSource.Play (); that. with
some brackets. and then. we want to use another
Invoke. which delays the method. There are
other ways of doing this. I just want to show
you this one. I'm going to call it ("InitialReply".
and we're going to do it after the length
of the initialHeliCall Why is initialHeliCall
not auto-completing? Have I done something
silly? No. I'm just going to cut and past
and force it to behave. There you go .length
plus another second. Just space it out a little
bit. Cool! So. he goes something like this.
You know. "Hey I'm a soldier. I'm lost. I'm
calling the helicopter" blah blah blah.
A second later. we want the reply to come
back from the helicopter. so it's going to
be InitialReply () . and that is just going
to set the audioSource.clip to initialCallReply;
and then. we do audioSource.Play (); and then.
we do BroadcastMessage ("OnDispatchHelicopter");
or probably better to be consistent and say.
OnDispatchHelicopter. which is what we said
in helicopter. Good it fits! OK cool! Let's
try it! That's a lot of writing code there.
without testing it. I have rehearsed this.
I just thought I'd get it done quickly. So.
what's happening? Now. I think what we're
going to need to do is make sure that we've
dragged into these scripts. all of the necessary
voice clips here. So. we haven't. None of
these voice clips are dragged in. Now. I'm
going to do that in a separate video. I'm
going to record all of these voice clips.
in one go. I'm going to save them as mp3's
instead of .oggs. because .oggs don't work
in Windows. And then. we'll come and drag
and attach and make all these things work.
so that'll do for this video. well done in
your refactoring. I'm going to quickly flip
through all of these scripts now. so that
you can see them on the screen easily. That
one. the Daycycle. the Eyes. didn't change
those. helicopter. there's your player. There's
your innerVoice. and there's your radio system.
Now. also please remember that you can go
over to GitHub and once you get to GitHub.
even if you don't have an account. you can
go to Complete Unity Developer. So. www.github.com/CompleteUnityDeveloper.
and then from there. you can go into the Zombie
Runner repo. and if you look at the Commits.
you'll find shortly after I submit this video.
ZR23 will be this video. and you can always
download by clicking over here and down there.
the .zip. So. let's go back. You go to the
master branch commits. which are at this URL.
you click this little guy here. Brows the
Repository at that point. and you click Download
.zip. so you can always get my code that way.
as well. Cool! Alright thanks for watching!
And I shall see you soon!