Hey hey! So. let's talk about normalizing
spelled the American way. audiophiles!
We'll be recording a few more dialogue
placeholders. in my case finished assets.
Remember that you may need a mp3 license. We'll be talking about normalizing sound
volume and then attaching and organizing audio. or organizing and attaching audio. So. if we
have a quick look at Wikipedia here.
you'll find that there's a bit of a long
article about whether or not you need a
license for mp3 audio. I think the bottom
line is. you do if you're going to be making
a commercial game. For the sake of sharing in
the course. I wouldn't worry about it. So.
that's the first thing. and the other
thing is. what audio formats does Unity
support? Well. I may have covered
this before. but I'm briefly going to recap that it supports several but the main ones to
consider are mp3 or Ogg. Either of those are very multi-platform and will work fine.
I'm going to use mp3. from now on. So. let's just go ahead and start attaching all of
our sound files and then. testing things.
So. what needs sound? The helicopter!
It's already got a sound. but it's not normalized. so let's show
you what normalization means. I'm going to open the helicopter sound in Audacity. like so.
and then. I'm going to go to Effect and
Normalize. And what that does is it makes
sure that the sound volume fills the
envelope. It's actually set to 1 decibel
away from the top and bottom. If we do
that with all our sound files then. they
all have a standard volume. and we're also going to just export these back as mp3
files. Now. the helicopter ought to go in the Helicopter Folder. that makes sense. So. let's do that now.
Ok. fantastic! And then. let's just go
through and attach that. So. each one I
get to. I'm just going to attach it as I
go. So. we have two helicopters. a quiet
one and a loud one. I'm going to use the loud one. This may mess around with how I have
my 3D sound setup. but I would rather the
sound was normalized. It is better to
have things normalized. So. there it is. That's great! Now. the player. what do we have on the player?
We have an audio source that the First Person Character Controller is
going to be using. so I'll minimize that
down. we don't need it. We have a Clear
Area... Inner Voice! Ok so. we need a What Happened
Sound. Do we have that? Yep. we have a What Happened Sound. but it's in Ogg format. I want to pop it into mp3.
It's also again not normalized. so
normalizing
won't make a lot of difference on this. you can see it's already close to normalized.
Pop it in here as a... you don't Save you Export from Audacity. If you save it. it
saves as a native Audacity File.
Again. you can get Audacity on Mac and PC. What happened? Let's put an mp3 version of
that in. Sorry that it says hell in there. I
hope that doesn't offend anybody. There's
the mp3 version there. Fantastic! So. the
player needs an Inner Voice. with a What
Happened Script. Now. good landing area. We don't have a good landing area recording.
let's make one immediately. It's good to just do things as you get to them. so here's a
new Audacity File. I'm going to record
myself a good landing area file now. [He Records]
This looks like a pretty good landing area!
I'm going to lay down a flare and call for the HELO!
Now. my audio is clipped here. [Plays Audio Clip in Background]  And that's clipped at source. so I need to re-record that.
[He Records] This looks like a pretty good landing area! I'm going to lay down a flare and call for a
HELO! Ok now. there's no clipping there. which is good.
That's the bit I'm going to export. but in the meanwhile I'm just going to
normalize that again. which again makes
sure these picks are about right. Fantastic!
And Export Selection. and this is going to be good area.mp3. Ok so. fairly simple.
What I want you to be doing while you're
watching this is. or I think you're going to get
the idea already. is just go through and
set up all of your clips. as well. That's the
basic idea of this. So. what else needs
some sound? The radio system needs two
clips. It needs the initial helicopter call.
which is Call Sound. I'm actually going to move
the directory of that. That doesn't really make sense to be against the
helicopter. [Plays Audio File in Background] That's Ok. I'm going to leave
that one as it is. but I am going to
normalize it and change it to an mp3
format. And change it's folder at risk of
confusing people. So. I'm going to say initial call reply. I think is
what we were calling it in the code.
Fantastic! Now. I immediately know that I
need another sound. so once I've put
initial call reply in. which is in audio here against
the radio system... you see the sound all kind of goes against the things that
make sense. I need an initial heli call. I
never made an initial heli call. so let's do that now.
I don't know what to call... I've created blank. What am I going to do here? Let's have a think.
Help! Help! I'm... No. that doesn't sound very gruff does it. [Jokes Around &amp; Uses High Pitch Voice] Help! Help! I'm a stranded
soldier. Let's try again. [He Records] Special Forces 07 stuck in some zombie infested hell hole. calling for HELO
extraction. Something like that. who cares. Now. let's normalize. You don't have to select
before you normalize here. by the way. I'm just selecting. so that I'm ready to export
selection into my audio file. and it's
going to be initial heli call.mp3. Better now.
everything's in mp3 format. Now. it's not actually going to work this properly. and you'll
see why in just a second. There is an
almost deliberate error for you. See if
you can just spot what it is. [Character's Voice in Background] So. if I play now. and then. go
somewhere where the initial pull gets
triggered. we can check that by checking the Clear
Area Script. Now. we're over one second and we're over ten seconds since the start and we haven't
heard any of that happen. Now. the reason is that the Clear Area Script. if you look
at it. does a what?  A send message
upwards I believe. Yes. OnFindClearArea.
which is supposed to be received by Inner Voice. Yeah. but Inner Voice isn't up the Hierarchy. so
this is where we slightly overused
messaging. It's ok. but what we're going to need
to do is put Clear Area as a child of
the Inner Voice. Now. that's going to break the
player prefab. which is okay. We can
reapply the player prefab like that. You can
always check your player prefab. make sure it looks right. Ok so. the Clear Area is a
concept. within the Inner Voice. We're stretching the Hierarchy here a little
bit. so I think it's still Ok. I think the
radio system encompasses the player and
helicopter. The inner voice has the
concept of a clear area. but you can see
we're pushing things a little bit too
far. And there are many other ways that we could be
triggering these sounds. much more standard techniques you've used before. but
I want to stick with messaging here. just
for the sake of it really. Let's try and
see how this goes.  [Game Character Talks] I better call for some help. Got to find an area about the size of a tennis court and call a HELO.
This looks like a pretty good landing area! I'm going to lay down a flare and
call for a HELO. Special forces 07 stuck in
some zombie infested hell hole. calling
for HELO extraction! [Game HELO Pilot Replies] ...rescue helicopter 01 inbound. ETA five minutes.
[Ben Starts Talking] And there's the helicopter on its way! Pretty cool! Ok. it
all works the plan came together. and
that is a reasonable communication system for all of that. So. look forward to
seeing you in the next lecture. when we will give the helicopter a landing area to aim
at and deploy a flare!
=======
Kind: captions
Language: en
Hey hey! So, let's talk about normalizing
spelled the American way, audiophiles!
We'll be recording a few more dialogue
placeholders, in my case finished assets.
Remember that you may need a mp3 license. We'll be talking about normalizing sound
volume and then attaching and organizing audio, or organizing and attaching audio. So, if we
have a quick look at Wikipedia here,
you'll find that there's a bit of a long
article about whether or not you need a
license for mp3 audio. I think the bottom
line is, you do if you're going to be making
a commercial game. For the sake of sharing in
the course, I wouldn't worry about it. So,
that's the first thing, and the other
thing is, what audio formats does Unity
support? Well, I may have covered
this before, but I'm briefly going to recap that it supports several but the main ones to
consider are mp3 or Ogg. Either of those are very multi-platform and will work fine.
I'm going to use mp3, from now on. So, let's just go ahead and start attaching all of
our sound files and then, testing things.
So, what needs sound? The helicopter!
It's already got a sound, but it's not normalized, so let's show
you what normalization means. I'm going to open the helicopter sound in Audacity, like so,
and then, I'm going to go to Effect and
Normalize. And what that does is it makes
sure that the sound volume fills the
envelope. It's actually set to 1 decibel
away from the top and bottom. If we do
that with all our sound files then, they
all have a standard volume, and we're also going to just export these back as mp3
files. Now, the helicopter ought to go in the Helicopter Folder, that makes sense. So, let's do that now.
Ok, fantastic! And then, let's just go
through and attach that. So, each one I
get to, I'm just going to attach it as I
go. So, we have two helicopters, a quiet
one and a loud one. I'm going to use the loud one. This may mess around with how I have
my 3D sound setup, but I would rather the
sound was normalized. It is better to
have things normalized. So, there it is. That's great! Now, the player, what do we have on the player?
We have an audio source that the First Person Character Controller is
going to be using, so I'll minimize that
down, we don't need it. We have a Clear
Area... Inner Voice! Ok so, we need a What Happened
Sound. Do we have that? Yep, we have a What Happened Sound, but it's in Ogg format. I want to pop it into mp3.
It's also again not normalized, so
normalizing
won't make a lot of difference on this, you can see it's already close to normalized.
Pop it in here as a... you don't Save you Export from Audacity. If you save it, it
saves as a native Audacity File.
Again, you can get Audacity on Mac and PC. What happened? Let's put an mp3 version of
that in. Sorry that it says hell in there, I
hope that doesn't offend anybody. There's
the mp3 version there. Fantastic! So, the
player needs an Inner Voice, with a What
Happened Script. Now, good landing area. We don't have a good landing area recording,
let's make one immediately. It's good to just do things as you get to them, so here's a
new Audacity File. I'm going to record
myself a good landing area file now. [He Records]
This looks like a pretty good landing area!
I'm going to lay down a flare and call for the HELO!
Now, my audio is clipped here. [Plays Audio Clip in Background]  And that's clipped at source, so I need to re-record that.
[He Records] This looks like a pretty good landing area! I'm going to lay down a flare and call for a
HELO! Ok now, there's no clipping there, which is good.
That's the bit I'm going to export, but in the meanwhile I'm just going to
normalize that again, which again makes
sure these picks are about right. Fantastic!
And Export Selection, and this is going to be good area.mp3. Ok so, fairly simple.
What I want you to be doing while you're
watching this is, or I think you're going to get
the idea already, is just go through and
set up all of your clips, as well. That's the
basic idea of this. So, what else needs
some sound? The radio system needs two
clips. It needs the initial helicopter call,
which is Call Sound. I'm actually going to move
the directory of that. That doesn't really make sense to be against the
helicopter. [Plays Audio File in Background] That's Ok, I'm going to leave
that one as it is, but I am going to
normalize it and change it to an mp3
format. And change it's folder at risk of
confusing people. So, I'm going to say initial call reply, I think is
what we were calling it in the code.
Fantastic! Now, I immediately know that I
need another sound, so once I've put
initial call reply in, which is in audio here against
the radio system... you see the sound all kind of goes against the things that
make sense. I need an initial heli call, I
never made an initial heli call, so let's do that now.
I don't know what to call... I've created blank. What am I going to do here? Let's have a think.
Help! Help! I'm... No, that doesn't sound very gruff does it. [Jokes Around &amp; Uses High Pitch Voice] Help! Help! I'm a stranded
soldier. Let's try again. [He Records] Special Forces 07 stuck in some zombie infested hell hole, calling for HELO
extraction. Something like that, who cares. Now, let's normalize. You don't have to select
before you normalize here, by the way. I'm just selecting, so that I'm ready to export
selection into my audio file, and it's
going to be initial heli call.mp3. Better now,
everything's in mp3 format. Now, it's not actually going to work this properly, and you'll
see why in just a second. There is an
almost deliberate error for you. See if
you can just spot what it is. [Character's Voice in Background] So, if I play now, and then, go
somewhere where the initial pull gets
triggered, we can check that by checking the Clear
Area Script. Now, we're over one second and we're over ten seconds since the start and we haven't
heard any of that happen. Now, the reason is that the Clear Area Script, if you look
at it, does a what?  A send message
upwards I believe. Yes, OnFindClearArea,
which is supposed to be received by Inner Voice. Yeah, but Inner Voice isn't up the Hierarchy, so
this is where we slightly overused
messaging. It's ok, but what we're going to need
to do is put Clear Area as a child of
the Inner Voice. Now, that's going to break the
player prefab, which is okay. We can
reapply the player prefab like that. You can
always check your player prefab, make sure it looks right. Ok so, the Clear Area is a
concept, within the Inner Voice. We're stretching the Hierarchy here a little
bit, so I think it's still Ok. I think the
radio system encompasses the player and
helicopter. The inner voice has the
concept of a clear area, but you can see
we're pushing things a little bit too
far. And there are many other ways that we could be
triggering these sounds, much more standard techniques you've used before, but
I want to stick with messaging here, just
for the sake of it really. Let's try and
see how this goes.  [Game Character Talks] I better call for some help. Got to find an area about the size of a tennis court and call a HELO.
This looks like a pretty good landing area! I'm going to lay down a flare and
call for a HELO. Special forces 07 stuck in
some zombie infested hell hole, calling
for HELO extraction! [Game HELO Pilot Replies] ...rescue helicopter 01 inbound, ETA five minutes.
[Ben Starts Talking] And there's the helicopter on its way! Pretty cool! Ok, it
all works the plan came together, and
that is a reasonable communication system for all of that. So, look forward to
seeing you in the next lecture, when we will give the helicopter a landing area to aim
at and deploy a flare!
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1:Unity/Section9/ZR24 Unity Audio Formats & Licensing.srt