Hey guys. and congratulations on getting to
the end of Zombie Runner! So firstly. you'll
notice that Brice is. this way. is not next
to me. and that's because he's moved on to
another project. He actually only lives down
the road. I see him once every week or two.
but he's moved on from the course. so you
won't be seeing him in any upcoming sections
but that's why Brice isn't next to me. Right.
so we have finished Zombie Runner. Now. it
feels pretty unfinished right. and that's
because I want you to finish it. As we tale
out the last couple of sections of this course.
I really want to get you in the habit of finishing
the games you start. so that's the reason
I've left it like that. Also. if I was to
go and add a UI and enemy spawning and all
these other things. it's very much repeating
things you've already learned. and we don't
want that. So. well done getting this far
in the course. Please do go and make these
suggested customizations on the slide. a couple
of videos ago. things like maybe skinning
the zombie with a free mesh from the Asset
Store. Certainly arrange your enemy spawning.
get the UI on there. and get the game up on
the discussions and share it. maybe pop a
video on YouTube. or if you really want to
push the boat out. it's time that you guys.
who have got this far in the course. start
thinking about actually publishing your courses
to iOS or the Android store and actually getting
those out there in public and showing us that
way. So. a few people have already done that
with some of the games. this would be a great
game to consider doing that with as well.
I hope you've enjoyed the section. and I look
forward to seeing you in our future content.
=======
Kind: captions
Language: en
Hey guys, and congratulations on getting to
the end of Zombie Runner! So firstly, you'll
notice that Brice is, this way, is not next
to me, and that's because he's moved on to
another project. He actually only lives down
the road, I see him once every week or two,
but he's moved on from the course, so you
won't be seeing him in any upcoming sections
but that's why Brice isn't next to me. Right,
so we have finished Zombie Runner. Now, it
feels pretty unfinished right, and that's
because I want you to finish it. As we tale
out the last couple of sections of this course,
I really want to get you in the habit of finishing
the games you start, so that's the reason
I've left it like that. Also, if I was to
go and add a UI and enemy spawning and all
these other things, it's very much repeating
things you've already learned, and we don't
want that. So, well done getting this far
in the course. Please do go and make these
suggested customizations on the slide, a couple
of videos ago, things like maybe skinning
the zombie with a free mesh from the Asset
Store. Certainly arrange your enemy spawning,
get the UI on there, and get the game up on
the discussions and share it, maybe pop a
video on YouTube, or if you really want to
push the boat out, it's time that you guys,
who have got this far in the course, start
thinking about actually publishing your courses
to iOS or the Android store and actually getting
those out there in public and showing us that
way. So, a few people have already done that
with some of the games, this would be a great
game to consider doing that with as well.
I hope you've enjoyed the section, and I look
forward to seeing you in our future content.
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1:Unity/Section9/ZR27 Section Wrap Up.srt