Welcome to setting up Visual Studio or Xcode. In this video we're going to be getting you the
tools you need to start programming and diving into
this course. It's going to visual studio on the PC and Xcode
on the Mac. Now if you're wondering who's talking, it's Sam. You'll see me in a few of these videos
if you are on a PC then just watch through with me
if you are on a Mac then skip just a little bit ahead to where we show you
how to install Xcode instead of visual studio. Okay
So there is a new version of Visual Studio since a lot of the content in this course
has been recorded. It's Visual Studio 2017. So go ahead
and open up your favourite browser of choice and grab Visual Studio
2017. Go search for it, you'll end up on a page that looks
something like this: visualstudio.com. And you can go ahead and
download the Visual Studio Community Edition, is the one
that's for free. So community 2017. Grab that
small download. This is just an installer download so it wont be very big
at all. You can go ahead, open it, give it the keys to the kingdom
and we will get started. So once you've accepted and signed your life away to
Microsoft with the privacy agreement, then it will download what it needs to
give you an option of packages. Now I'm going to show you, it's very simple
they've actually improved the simplicity of the installer in the 2017
edition. So we will show you just how easy it is. But a couple of things
while where at it to show you about the setup that Ben and I have here
to make things really easy. You'll notice that all the icons, everything is very big this is so
it's easy for you guys to see. It's in HiDPI and it's about
720p. And also, another thing you'll notice is that
we have our Windows task bar over at the side here
and that is again to give you more space to see
everything that we are doing and working with. Okay, so we've got the installer
popping up now and you will see that there's a couple of what they call
"workloads". Now "workloads" basically means what kind of
stuff are you going to be doing with Visual Studio. And there's lots of options
here. You may want to check more than one if you know you want something else. But
if you don't know what you need, then just scroll on down to the section entitled
"Mobile and Gaming" and the bottom most option here
is "Game Development with C++". We are using that and
in fact, if you look in the little description, it also tells you that
it's things like Unreal. So that's exactly what we want, so let's check that
off it's automatically set off a few of the
different options and what we will need so once you checked
off "Game Development with C++" go ahead and hit "Install"
and leave that running.
So, if you're on a Mac I want you to make sure that you
have Xcode downloaded and installed. We need to go to the Mac
App Store, which is the Apple sign, and then to the App Store.
Then, do a search for Xcode,
and then, when the result comes up, I want yo to see whether
the Xcode is perhaps not installed, in which case, it will say Get like this,
Installing like mine is, or Already Installed, in which case it
it says Open. Now, if it is installed, I want you to make sure it is up to date by clicking
Updates, and we want both Xcode and Mac OS to be fully up
to date. Otherwise, just leave it installing. Now, how do you
know how it's doing on the install? Here's a tip for you! If you hit
your Launch Pad Button on your keyboard,and you scroll to
the page that the download is on, you'll actually be able to see the progress here: 3 out of 4
Gig, in my case. So, this could take 20 minutes on your
broadband, it could take mnay hours. So, continue watching the course
while that downloads in the background, and I'll tell you when to install it.