...
Welcome to How to Ask Good Questions! Now, in this lecture
it is Sam talking to you not Ben, so you might notice a different
voice. And I am one of the co-instructors on the
course, I help out in the Q & A, and you'll see me in some of the later videos, way down,
in a few [Laughs] sections time, so don't worry if you don't hear my voice for a little
while yet. And what I'm going to be taking you through
is the process of asking good Q & A questions, so that you can
get the results that you want. Here's an example of the question that I'm going to
ask and get answered, during the process of this
video, and it'll help me solve some really basic, initial, beginner
programming questions that I had. So let's dive right in!
So I've really only just started the course and started doing
my first programming exercise, and I'm already having a problem. So
if you're in this situation, you're going to want to go to the Q & A
and start asking basically: Why is this going
wrong? And that's great and we really encourage you
to participate in the Q & A as soon as possible. As soon as you have issues, just
go dive in there, don't be afraid. And even if you haven't watched this lecture,
don't be afraid to dive in! But I want to show you how you can make
our job of answering you really easy and other students too, how
other students will be able to answer you so much easier, if you follow these simple instructions.
So here I have a simple problem. I've done my first console
application, but I'm getting these build errors and I'm not entirely sure
what's going on. So the first step of the process isn't
even to ask the question, no it's to ask the question to a rubber duck
first! This is called Rubber Duck Debugging, it's something real, real
programmers do it they have little ducks they put on their keyboards, and the
idea is that you speaking aloud and talking about your problem helps
to solve it, even before having to ask the question. So explain your problem
out loud and walk through your current understanding, and
inevitably this enigmatic sensei will say nothing
to you but you may will figure it out. It may certainly give you
at least three things to do, to test your understanding and to see whether you
can fix the problem itself. So my first step would be,
OK well maybe I didn't install the right version of VisualStudio,
so I might go and reinstall VisualStudio. Then, I might say,
well maybe I didn't type it right, so I'm going to retype the stuff out but I still
get a problem. Then, I might say, well
maybe there's actually something wrong with my computer and [Laughs] it's
stalled the entire computer or something, or I might,
you know, try and fix a few spelling mistakes and so on. So that gives me at least three things
to try, just by talking through my understanding of the fact that I've written some code and
it needs to be compiled. And is it actually compiling? Maybe I'll test
it by going to Build and test the Build Solution, see whether it works, and say
no there's these errors happening at the bottom. So what is going
on? I'm still not entirely sure! So the next step is to ask the question, and I'd like
to show you what is the question structure, because once we get into more
complicated types of questions, it can sometimes be hard to understand what people are
actually wanting to get out of this. So the first thing you start with is what you want to get
out of it, the expected behavior. So in this case, I expect my
code to run and to have the "Hello world\n" ?printed but
what's not happening. So what do I actually get? Well I get some error
messages, I get these error messages down here. So it would be very useful to include
these error messages and a screenshot of them into my Udemy
questions. So just to show you the Udemy questions, it's always best to do it against the
lecture where you're having the problem, so it's contextual, we know what stage you
are in the course. So I might say, let's start with my observed behavior!
...
Typing...
And here I can take a screenshot, using the SnipIt Tool in Windows
and just search for Snip It Tool.
On Mac there are some keyboard shortcuts. I'm sure you know how to take
screenshots, I'll leave that up to you. But for example, I'll take a
screenshot of the entire area I think might be relevant, hit Save,
save it somewhere perhaps on my Desktop.
And then, I'm going to load
this into Unity...
...
...and let it do its upload process, and then, I have an observed
behavior. At this point, I should also have an expected behavior beforehand, if I'm following the structure.
...
And then, what comes next? So next up, we need to tell
people how you got here in the first place. What were the steps that will now allow
someone else to do the same thing? Well for me, it's simply
every time I open VisualStudio. As I create a new project
in VisualStudio, it's a new C++ VisualStudio project, and then, I type
in my code, I get this error. So let me type that up!
...
So there we go! Now someone else could try and replicate the
same effect as me! What comes next? Well what have I tried
already? Well I can tell them that I've already tired
reinstalling VisualStudio, I've already tried retyping my code,
and I've already tried, let's say, reinstalling even my computer, for example.
...
So now, what comes next? Other useful
information, such as the version of VisualStudio that I used, perhaps my code, as well. So let's add that in!
...
Now I can find my VisualStudio version by going to
Help, About Microsoft Visual Studio,
and there we go, I've got version
14 update 3. So I'll just put that in,
just in case that might be useful to someone. And what I also want to
do is include my code. So the best way to include
code is not to do a screenshot of it, because that doesn't allow people
to search through your code and really check it. So here's the thing, you
want to include screenshots when they're really useful, such as screenshots of some
error messages, the Unreal Editor windows, when they help basically
explain your steps or when they help explain your observed behavior,
but don't do it for code all the time. You could include your code right
in here, inside the question, by using
this little curly braces button at the top
of your question. That allows you to just paste the code right in there
and then format it nicely, or the alternative, which is probably
better, is to use a gist. Now a gist is provided by github,
so it's gist.github.com. And what you can do is, you can take
your code, like so, copy it and take it
on over to the gist and paste it in there. Now, what you can do
is give the name of the file; in my case, the file is called
ConsoleApplication1.cpp.
And then, what I can do is create a public gist,
and this will have done code formatting, code highlighting, for me automatically
and given me a unique link, which I can then use to link to this
'my code'. I'll select 'my code', I'll select the link
icon at the top of the question, insert the link, and then, paste
the URL in there. So now people can go and take a look at the
code, which is needed, basically, to reproduce
my behavior. Now, what you'll notice is I'm being minimal
with this. Don't include extra steps, there's no extra steps that I took,
and this is all very shortly written, because you've got to think that
people have got limited time, they're reading your question, you want it to be
as brief as possible. So just keep it brief and keep it to the
minimum amount.ￂﾠAnd you  want to also keep the test case to the
minimum amount, so don't include extra steps to reproduce, if you can actually
reproduce it with less. Or maybe take out lines of code, if they're
lines of code that don't cause the error, so that it's really obvious where
that error is coming from. So minimum steps to reproduce.
And then, finally, be a Q & A ninja! So the first thing there is
to summarize in your title. You'll notice that I started off by actually writing the body
first, and then, what I'm going to say is
"Error compiling"... Or that's quite vague, I wouldn't go
with such a vague error. I would say: Error compiling my first hello world or something like that. So...
...
But just make sure that it summarizes your title, and then, you can go ahead
and post that question. And once you've posted
your question, it says sometimes it'll complain about external links, you might have to
post it twice. And then, what's going to happen next?
What are you going to do as a Q & A ninja next?! I'd like you to stay
responsive, so as people are replying make sure you are replying, and fundamentally,
when a good reply comes in it says, for example,
...
then what I'm going to do is go and try that out, because I'm very responsive!
I'll try it out, then I'll go and see that it actually does indeed
work. I rebuild and my "Hello world\n" is functional again!
Then, don't forget to come back and mark a top answer, because
this means that it no longer comes up on our dashboard as an unanswered
question, which means that we can concentrate on solving the questions that haven't
been answered yet. So this is very vital, even if
you come back and answer your own question and mark it as top answer, as
I've just done, that's still very helpful to us. So make sure that you
share if you solve it, that will help other students as well as making
sure that the question gets marked as resolved. And then, finally,
once you've got your resolution go and be altruistic, go and find some
other questions that you can try and help to chime in on and make
a next step for that person. In fact, let's
go and do that now! This is going to be your challenge for the lecture, to go and answer. Go
forth and answer! I'd like you to find a question in the previous videos, try to
provide some sort of suggestion, use your rubber ducking technique on their question,
or just use your own experience and try and make a suggestion
for what they should try next. And then, how well do you think the question was answered?
Apply these criteria to try and think about,
is that a good question? Was that hard for me to answer? And that should help
you, in the future, to write better questions. Obviously don't go telling the person you've
asked a rubbish question, just try and provide some value to them. But try and think,
will this be helpful for me in the future? OK so pause the
video... In fact, we're finished, so you can go ahead and do that!