So well done getting yourself setup with Unreal! You're all ready to
go right now. I know it all looks bewildering and a bit crazy but
that's absolutely fine! The point is, the system is installed.
So, what I would like you to do now is get used to using the discussions. Just go to the
discussion agasint this very lecture, and just introduce yourself.
Just say hi! I'm Joe Bloggs! I'm from this part of the world,
here's my experience, and here's what I'd like to achieve in the course.! Just get
the discussion going. And also make the effort to have a look for other people
introducing themselves, and look for a common point of interest.
Maybe you live in the same place? Maybe you've got the same dreams or goals?
Just look for something in common and start conversations with people. You can
make real friends here on the course. If I may make a suggestion?
Start the next section right now! Don't finish a section
and walk away. It may just be my personality type, but I
personally love to leave it hanging, so that I'm really compelled to go
back. So, dive straigt into the next section, get the first couple of videos done,
and then, kind of finish halfway through a video. And then, you'll be compelled
to come back and get it finished. And use that strategy every time! I find it
really useful for making sure I keep momentum, because getting the most out of this
course is all about just showing up. 99% of it is just
turning up and doing the work. So, do it! It's going to be great fun!
I'm really looking forward to working with you. That's it really!
All I'm going to do now is talk to experienced C#
developers, for a second, and just give you a bit of a rundown. So, it that's not you.
If you're not an experienced C# developer, then
carry onto the next section, and I'll see you soon!
If you've got some existing C# knowledge I just want to say firstly,
great news! A lot of what you already know will transfer over to C++.
Some of it's pretty much identical! Things like if statements
and some of the loops. A lot of the syntax is very very similar.
One major change you're going to have to get used to is
.H files, Header Files. When you specify the signature
of your methods, you're going to have to put those over in a
separate file. And it's just a legacy of how
C++ works, but once you're used to it, you'll be doing
it in a hurry but that's different. You can do a lot of cool bit wise
operations. In fact, in the very next section, we're going to almost artificially
start introducing bit wise operations, just in the spirit of C++,
which gives you a lot more low level control, if you need it.
But on that topic, don't worry too much about memory management. I know people think, oh
I've got to worry about memory. Well, if you're thinking about that too much early on
then you're probably doing something wrong, because Unreal is going to help us a lot with that.
What else to say? Oh, and get used to a couple of syntactic
differences. So, where you're used to a dot operator,
you're going to start seeing a dash chevron and a colon colon,
and all of that is summarized in the section notes for you, by the way.
So let's get stuck in!