Hello and welcome to
Managing a Larger Project! So in this video we're going
to learn how to manage a larger project. This is going to be
consisting of multiple objects, that we're all going to bring all
together at the end, so it's useful to know how to do that. So we're going to learn how to
store your files for quick recall and easy to find. And finally,
this is just a suggested workflow, if you do have something that works
for you that's something you've been doing for years and we're just preaching to the
converted, at this point, then carry on with that you don't have to adopt this
new methodology. Or it might be very similar to what you do already.
So let's hop over to the operating system, at this
point, and just manage our project!
Hi guys, and welcome to my operating system! So I'm on a
Mac here and I use Finder. If you're on a Windows system,
you'll be using Windows Explorer to do a very similar job. I would suggest
that you have a structure. I've got two
chess set folders here, one for the videos and lectures that I'm doing for you guys
and one for the actual assets themselves, the pieces, the board,
etc. So I've got my section here and here! Now,
I would suggest that you guys, if you haven't done it already, do create
yourself a project folder, and you don't have to call it Low Poly Chess Set, you
can simply call it Chess Set. Now, this
will help you lots, later on, as the course gets more
and more complex. So it's a great habit, if you've not started already,
to start managing your projects in this manner.
Alright guys, a quick challenge for you! I'd like you to go and create a Chess Set
project folder. So go and make a folder ready to store all of your Chess Set
in, as we go ahead and make it. Pause the video now and go off
and do that,
and I'll see you in a few seconds!
OK guys, welcome back! Thank you for going and creating that Chess Set
project folder! Let's crack on and start making this chess set!