Welcome to Making a
Chess Board! So in this video we're going to start making our chess
board! We're going to take over the cube object, and that will become
clear in a moment, and then finally, use the grid mesh
to create a grid that we can work from. So let's
hop straight on over into Blender!
So here we are over in Blender, and we've got our default
cube in the scene itself. Now, the reason why we're going to
take over this object, rather than just make our grid
mesh straight away, is we cannot be in Edit Mode and easily
see what's going on.
So, if I go to add Mesh, Grid...
You can see that's in there. I'm just going to move the Radius
up. It's quite hard to see where the grid is itself.
If I apply that new object and go into Edit Mode,
we can see our grid absolutely fine.
However, now we can't change the amount of subdivisions, because it's already
set. So how do we go about making sure that
we can control the subdivisions
and then create the mesh?
So what we are going to do is take
over the cube. So I'm just going to get rid of that, I'm going to go
select the cube itself, the cube object, hop into
Edit Mode, and then, Delete it. Now, if
we have a look over in the Outliner, we can see
both objects still exist, the Grid and the Cube. They've got no geometry in this,
but the objects themselves still exist, and I'm going to get
rid of this one here, I'm going to get rid of our Grid
and I'm going to call our Cube Chess
Board. Very inventive! As you can probably tell, I'm quite lean
with what's going on here, and I'm also just Save my file in my project
folder and call it Chesboard. So
I've got my chess board mockup. Now, I'm going to do it properly, so Chess Board.
There we go!, so that's saved in my project folder!
Now, in Edit Mode, if you go and create the
same mesh again, a Mesh object and a Grid, you can
see it straight away. Now, you may be very tempted
to create this 8 by 8 grid that comes naturally.
If we look over in the Operator Panel, you can see that's actually
10 by 10, that's actually 9 by 9. So what happens here is the
Subdivision are usually 1 higher than the actual number of
real divisions you want, because it includes one of the edges. And then finally, we've got
our Radius here. Now, I don't actually want to create our whole
board at once, because I don't really want to go in and color in black,
white, black, white throughout the entire thing. I just want a small section so I
have basically a 2 by 2 grid that we can apply a modifier
to and actually get our whole board.
So I need to lower the Subdivisions, all the way down to
3 and 3. I think that will give us a,
yep, a 2 by 2 grid! Now, we need to get the size right! Now, the Radius,
remember the Radius is from the middle outwards, and so if that's going
to be one of our squares, we can set that to
6 actually, because we're going to go 1 to
1 on that. So that is an accurate representation
of where we're going with our board. So 6
Radius out is a 6 by 6 square, and that's going to be 6 by 6
centimeters and we're going to work through that scale throughout our model.
OK guys, it's challenge time! I'd like you to finish
the board. So first of all, create a white material
and a black material, and apply those materials
to the board.
Then, go ahead to use two array modifiers. You can do them
together or individually, to create the rest
of the board. Now, apply those modifiers as you go or,
indeed, you can apply them all at the end, that's up to you. Finally, don't
worry about the board not being centered, we're going to be dealing with that
in the next lecture. Pause the video now and give that a
go! OK guys, welcome back!
Let's hop over into Blender!
So we have our 2 by 2 grid here! Let's go ahead
and create our two materials, first of all. So I'm going to go over
to this Properties Panel over here and
go to the Material type. So I'm going to
create our first material. In fact, there's already one here, so I'm going to call this
White Square.
Excellent! And just make sure, down
here, it is set to bright white, as white as it can possibly be.
Now, I'm going to go to Face Select Mode and Select these two
other faces here and create another material,
and you've guessed it, we're going to call it Black Square!
Now that we've got those two made...
I've also got to change the... I'm going to Assign the material
and then change the Diffuse color here, I'm going to ramp it
all the way down to complete black.
Excellent! So those are our materials made, and, in fact, that's our object,
so I'm going to hop back into Object Mode, because we're going to apply a modifier.
So we've got our starting grid going, so we're going to have to
create one modifier, first of all, and it's going to be a
repeat four times. So we're going to Create an Array Modifier,
and we can have them next to each other, so a relative offset,
and four. So there we go, 1, 2, 3, 4, that's great! And I'm
going to Copy the modifier, and, of course, it's going to apply
for those as well and we don't what that. In this case, we want
a Relative Offset the other direction, so in Y by 1,
and we can keep it to 4, as well. There we go, that's
our grid up really quickly! Now, the great thing about
using this Array Modifier, and we can see there are two here, Array one
and Array 2, or Array and Array.001. And
because it's an array, when we go back to our
original mesh and change anything, it will propogate across
our entire board, so we wouldn't have to modify all of these squares individually, very
very powerful!
Alright, so the final thing to do here is just apply our
Array Modifier, so I'm going to apply that one and finally
Apply this one! So now, we've changed our mesh
about!
That's great, so we've made
our chess board! How did you guys get on? Please share
in the discussions, and I will see you in the next lecture!