Welcome to Re-centering Your Objects!
In this video we'll show you how to center your model in the view
and learn how to control an object's origin.
Let's hop straight on over into Blender!
So here we are in Blender, and we're going to
deal with two things. Now, first of all, I'll show you the origin, that
origin is the orange circle right in the middle here
and we can move that about to our hearts' content. It's also acts
on several things, later on, in Blender, so it's important to understand
its placement is critical when doing certain things.
So first of all, let's zoom back out and look at our chess board, and
a very good way of doing this is to simply press
Shift and the letter C; that will
center our view around the model that we have selected. So there we
go! Brilliant! Now, let's go about exploring this
origin! Now, on the Tool Shelf, you may have already spotted
Set Origin, if we click on that it gives us a couple of options.
So one is to move the Geometry to that Origin, so
center the geometry, that is our chess board that's square in front of us
or checker board in front of us. It'll move the geometry all the way across and
center the geometry around the origin. The other, the next
one down, is exactly the opposite, so the selection will stay
absolutely fine, the geometry there, and it will move the origin
to the center of our chess board.
Now, Origin to 3D Cursor, we can move the 3D Cursor
around. You've seen that before! And if we move the Origin to
3D Cursor, you can see that the orange blob has moved to the 3D Cursor.
Finally, Origin to Center of Mass!
Now, because this board is equal
all the way around, then Origin to Center of Mass does exactly the
same, in this case, as Origin to Geometry, but for instance, in our
pin in the last exercise, because it was larger on the bottom
that it was on the top it does a calculation. You'll find the the origin will be
slightly lower because it's got more volume, down at the bottom of that
pin than it has bang in the middle. The Origin to Geometry would have put
that smack bang in the middle of the pin, vertically
and horizontally.
So I've got a challenge for you now!
I would like you to move the board's origin
and its placement. So set the board's origin to the center
of the board, and make sure the board is centered in our
scene. Pause the video now and go and give that a
go! OK guys, welcome back!
Let's give that a go!
Alright, so here we are in Blender, and
I've moved the origin or the origin happened to have moved all the way over here,
far from any logical place. So I need to do a couple of
things here! First of all, we can Set our Origin
to the Geometry. So Geometry to Origin, or origin
to geometry. Since that's already flattened on the X, Y plane, we will do that!
So Origin to Geometry, and that's placed it smack bang
in the middle of our board! Secondly, we want this whole board
centered around the worlds where X, Y, and Z equal 0,
so those two are there. So a couple of ways of doing that. Since we can move the
origin to this 3D Cursor, we can also move the
object of the 3D Cursor, but first of all, we need this 3D Cursor
smack bang in the middle. There are a couple of ways of doing that but a very quick one
is the Shift and S, and we can see there's a
Snap. So we can Snap the Selection, that's currently the selected object, Chess Board,
to our grid. We don't want to do that, so Selection to Cursor. That would move
the whole Selection to the Cursor, as it is, so we'll need to do that in a moment but not
now, because the cursor is in the wrong place and that's an
offset to the one above. So finally, Cursor to Selected,
that would move the cursor to the center of the geometry here. Let's bring back
up the menu. Cursor to Center, now that's the one that we want,
that'll snap the cursor right to the center of our world!
So if we click on that, we can see the cursor's moved all the way over there.
So now that we have the 3D Cursor in the right position, the next
thing to do is move this board to there,
as well. So after we've moved the 3D Cursor there, we can simply
go Shift and S again, and we can move this
Selection to the Cursor. So what we have selected is currently the board.
and If we go Selection to Cursor, we'll find the board will
snap across. Brilliant! A couple of other places you can
find that option is
under the Object Menu, under
Snap we've got all of those options there for you.
OK Brilliant! I'm going to center around our model again,
and there we go!
Let's move on to the next lecture!