Hi guys, we're going to finish off our geometry for our pawn,
so I'd like you to create the low poly pawn! So open up
the new low poly base piece, that we've just made.
Make sure you save that as low poly pawn, for instance,
and then, make sure you're working on that new .blend file,
before you start altering any geometry. Finally, be
mindful, when you've done this, to keep the top sphere to 8 segments,
and then,, it will match up easily with the rest of our model.
Pause the video now, and give that a go!
OK guys, welcome back! Let's hop straight on over into Blender!
So back in Blender we've got our base here! The first thing I'm going to do
is File, Save As, and call
this LP Pawn, I think.
I'm happy with that name! So we
can start working to it straight away. So let's nip on the Properties
Panel, make sure that the Background Image is turned on.
We can see that there, brilliant! So we just need to move around into the
Front View. We should still be able to see our
image. We can't see our image! Why not?
So it's
not hidden here, the axis is all views, we've got the
picture there. The Opacity is turned all the way down! So there we go!
Easy to forget that you've turned the Opacity down, certainly easy
for me to forget anyway. So let's grab this
top face here, whilst we're in Edit mode, which we are,
and we can extrude that up. So I'm going to hop straight back around to the
Front View, and let's move this
up to the right level. I'm giong to pop one line there
and then one line at the top there. Brilliant! So we've got
that bit sorted. We just need to grab this edge loop
around here and scale it outward. Oops, not inwards
but outwards. Grabbing this edge loop
underneath it, I'm going to scale that one in.
So that's roughly right! And then finally,
this top edge loop, as well, will be scaled in as well.
So that's fine there, and as we did before,
we need to pick a certain segment size for our sphere. So I'm going
to hop out into Object Mode, so I can create our
sphere as a separate mesh object.
I'm going to go for a UV Sphere. I'm happy with a UV Sphere! I'm going to drag it up.
We can see, straight away, that's too many sections!
If anything, it'd be really nice if it could line up roughly with our
8 here. So let's recreate
a UV Sphere!
So Mesh, UV Sphere. So Segments, well we only want
8, but 8 by 16 is going to look a little silly as we can
see there. Let's just try 8 by 8 and see how that looks!
That looks OK, actually! Can we go any lower with the rings? We don't
need them higher, perhaps 8 and 4. I think we can
get away with that! That's quite a nice low poly scale there, we'll
deal with the size in a moment. So now, we've got the right size here, we can just
pull it up so it's roughly in the middle, not the right size definitely, and then, pull
it in a little, as well. And the geometry itself
should match up relatively well, often quite a good job there of bringing it
together, actually. That was a complete accident, that was not deliberate at all!
But that's close enough!
Well there we go, that's brilliant! I'm really
happy with that, actually! So the final thing, of course, is to merge these into one mesh
object, and we can use Control and J for doing
that, to join those two together, and there we go!
So let's have a quick look around our piece, and let's flip
it around to the Front View, to just see how it appears against that. Well
yes, actually, I agree with the fact that that sphere is probably still
a little big! So I was kind of lucky and kind of not, at the same time.
So I'm going to, fortunately I've got enough undos, we haven't done
much since then, so the two are separate. I'm just going to zoom in, so I'm
on the right... That's a ball park with that, I'm pretty happy we've
set the origin in the middle there. I am going to have to scale that down a little bit further,
probably there. And I don't think I'm going to be that lucky
lining this lot up this time. Although, because we've got the
8 and 8, they actually line up perfectly! So it wasn't me being lucky, it was just
how we've made our model. Brilliant! So there we go, that's much better!
Let's zoom back out, I'm going to flip it into Perspective Mode,
as well, just to check it out in that view, and yeah, I'm happy with the
proportions there. So let's Join it again! Excellent!
I'm really happy with that low poly pawn,
and I'd like you guys to share yours in the
discussions. So take a screenshot and pop that in there, so I can see how you're getting
on. Take care, and I will see you in the next lecture!