Welcome to Managing the Chess Scene Assets!
So in this video we're going to decide how
we can manage our materials! We'll be creating materials
in one .blend file, not multiple but just one file,
and then,  learning that each project will have
a different way of handling materials, depending on the project's
size and scope. So materials in our project! If we
think about it, we've got 32 pieces in total,
black and white 16 of each. We've got a board that
has black and white squares, and finally, a wooden surround, finally.
So we've got five materials in our project. So what
we're going to do is, we're going to assign materials in a
Chess Scene .blend file. We've already assigned a material
to the board, that's absolutely fine, that will be brought into our Chess
Scene anyway, and we can work on it from there.
So it's challenge time, for you guys! I'd like you to create a
chess scene. There's not going to be much in it, but it's just
to get across what we've learned so far. So we're going to create
a new .blend file, we're going to append the
chess board and the pawn into one scene, and this will
give us a great feedback as to how our pawn is now looking,
in the scene itself. Finally, after you've created
this new .blend file, what I'd like you to do is go to your project folder
on your computer and archive the chess board, the original one, and the
pawn .blend files on your computer. Because we've brought it in, we're now going to
be editing it in this file only, so we don't want any confusion
later on. So pause the video now, and give that a go!
OK guys, welcome back! Let's
hop over into Blender!
So let's open up a new .blend file!
So New, Reload Start-Up File. That's absolutely fine!
I'm going to get rid of this cube, straight away!
I'm going to go to File, Append,
find my project folder, and I'm going to bring in
the pawn... Oops, too far! Object,
Chess Piece Base. Ah, I didn't name it, so I can rename
it in a moment, when it enters our scene. That's fine, let's go to the Outliner
now and make sure that's named correctly, from henceforth.
I'm going to call this Primary
White Pawn,
and the reason for that is, there'll be a primary black one, later on,
as well. So that's the pawn into our scene, and we need to Append
the chess board now. So let's go across
into our
assets folder, and there we have Chess Board, Object.
Chess Board is named correctly, which is great! Append From Library,
that's great! So the final thing we'll want to do here is just remove
this grid. We've already got our own stage, which is the chess
board itself, so we don't need this grid, anymore, here.
So I'm going to open up the Properties Pane, and as we scroll down,
there's our Display. Now, on
this Display, if we drop that down a little,
we can... Where is it? ...Grid Floor, here it is! We can turn that
off, and when we do that,
we've got our board without that grid underneath it.
So there we go, we've got our pawn in here, and
if we select our pawn, we can move it on our board and that's great! And
we can see that it is the right size, compared to the rest of the board,
it suits the board quite nicely.
And the final thing, of course, is to name our scene. So
I'm going to go into File, Save As, and I'm just going to
call this Chess Scene. There we go!
Save the Blender file, and we can see at the top, it's saved as it's new name.
So that's all of the stuff done in Blender itself. Finally, we just need to
clear up our project folder that we're working on. So I've got my low
poly chess set here. I'm going to create a new folder and call it
Archive and actually spell it right, for once. And
we've got Low Poly Pawn, that we're working on, and ChessScene. So the
Low Poly Pawn can go into the archive, because we just brought that in, and I'm happy that
that's finalized. Low Poly Chess Piece Base, we're going to
leave that, because we need that for the rest of our pieces. All of the other stuff that we've
been working on, apart from Chess Scene, can be moved out of the way.
Now, don't worry if you see some extra stuff there that you might not have made,
because I do a lot of tinkering. So there we go! So in your
folder, you should have two files left over, Low Poly
Chess Piece Base, which we're going to use for the rest of our models, and our ChessScene
.blend. So that's all of those sorted out!
Brilliant! How did you guys get on? Please share in the discussions,
and I will see you in the next lecture!