Welcome to Selecting Hidden Geometry! So in this
video we're going to learn how to select geometry that isn't visible to us
in our viewport, in front of us. Now, there are two straight forward
ways of doing that. Number one, we can switch the viewport shading
to Wireframe Mode.
Number two, we can toggle Limit Selection to Visible.
Then finally, we'll go on to build the rest of our bishop. Let's
hop over straight into Blender!
So we have our bishop coming along rather nicely here! So the
first thing I'm going to do is rotate it around to the Front
View, so we've got a good representation of our model.
Now, we need the reference material, we need to go get the background
image. And if we scroll down here to the background images, they're still turned
on, and currently it's set to the pawn, we don't want that.
In fact, we don't need or remove this image, we can just overwrite it by opeining up
a new image and navigating to our section
assets and applying the Staunton Bishop.png.
Excellent! So that's in there! Now, it does need to be scaled
up, because we can see here we've aleady made the base of our pawn
or what was the pawn, now the bishop, the right size.
And if we look down at the scale,
the Size down here of our Image, it's set to 3. Now, that's quite
convenient, not planned I assure you; that is convenient, because the
size of this was originally 3. We just need to change that to a 4 and it should
match. Yeah, matches perfectly! Brilliant! So
now, on the Y axis we just need to shift that up. Let's hope that's another
whole number. I'm happy with that! So we can
see here, these parts align almost perfectly, that's great, but
the bits at the top do not. We need to go in
and edit those and move them out. So I'm just going to collapse this back down a bit, so we've got some more
space. Alright, so using Border Select in
Edit Mode, so I'm going to switch over to Edit Mode. Using Boarder Select, I can
select all of that lot there. Now, I'm in Face Select, if I was in Edge I'd
have to go a little lower, and I can pull that up
to the right place. Ah, there's something weird going on here! Let's turn our model
around and have a look! Ah, that's gone all weird!
It's only moved half of our model. Now, it's kind of cool,
it's made it look kind of head shaped, with maybe a cravat or something around it, but that's
not what we want, be want it to be uniform pulled
up. Now, the reason for that is, I only selected what I could see here,
and of course, plus this face that was already selected. So I'm going to undo
that, so it's back to normal. Great!
I'm going to deselect everything, before I start, and then, switch back over into
Front View. Now, in order to make sure that we can select
our entire mesh, including the stuff behind, what we need to
do and two fold, we can either switch to Wireframe so we can see
through our model, then if we do the Border Select again
it selects everything.
The alternative is a little toggle,
so let's just hop back into Solid Mode,
because it disappears when you're in Wireframe Mode, and that's this option
to the right of the Edge, Vertices, and Face Select.
There's this little button here, which is Limit Selection to Visible.
So if you toggle that off, because it's by default
on, you can see that our model appears slightly translucent now,
and if we perform the same action where we select stuff, it selects
all through our model. So there's two options in manipulating our
model. Then, we can pull that up and down to our hearts' content!
So let's switch back over into Front View and see
how we're doing here! I don't really want to pull that other bit up, actually,
so let's push that back down. Let's do the Border Select around here.
Nope, let's do Edges, I like working with edges.
Deselect everything first and try that once more.
There we go! And I'm just going to pull that up, so that this bit here
is roughly where that is. Now, we're going to have to add some extra bits and bobs
here, in a moment. That's absolutely fine!
And I'd probably want to make it indent here
a little, just to keep that form going up. When it was shorter as a pawn, it was fine.
Now, it seems a bit static, I just want to give it a bit more shape
to it and define it! And we do need to manipulate the top of this
pawn, as well. Now, we're going to leave out the notch for now, and we'll go and
do a cool thing, in a bit, to apply the notch! And we
need a little ball on top, as well.
OK guys, it's challenge time!
What I'd like you to do, if you haven't done it already, do import the bishop's
reference image and scale it appropriately and move it about. Then,
model the rest of the bishop. Do leave out the notch. Try
it out using different techniques, so you can put loop cuts in there, you can extrude
things. You may have to delete things as you go, as well, and possibly even
bridging edge loops, that may help you out. Have fun and
do keep the low poly in mind, so don't go adding a ton of geometry!
And use your own artistic license, as to what details you do
include towards the top of the bishop and which ones you don't. So
pause the video now and go off and create the bishop!
OK welcome back! Let's hop back over
into Blender!
OK, so back over in Blender, we've got this bit level here, and I feel
like we could almost move this ball completely out of the way,
if we did some decent selection there. So I'm going to clear everything
and see if we can just lift that up. So Border Select, I'm going to select everything there,
and I suppose the only other thing I need to select here is this vertex in the middle.
Has that worked? Let's shift that up. Yes brilliant,
it has! I'm going to shift that to the top
of our... Ooh, I'm grabbing stuff, I don't want to do that!
Escape out of it!
So I thought I was grabbing that blue arrow and I wasn't. Let's
select that again
and move it down to roughly the right point. So that's the top of
our mesh here, and this is the bottom.
Now, becuse this sphere, on the top, is made
of the same number of segments as our piece down here, we can use Bridges
Loops to get this bit melded onto this bit at the bottom here.
So all I need to do here is delete this vertex at the bottom.
So I'm going to delete that now and make sure it's deleting vertices only. We end up with a
hole in the top of our model there, and making sure we don't have an
inside face, I'm going to select this face here
and make sure I only delete the face and nothing else.
So then, selecting these two edge loops, that one there and this one
here and going to Mesh, Edges, and Bridge
Edge Loops. And there we go... Nope, select these two edge loops...
I didn't hold down Shift, when doing that! I should know better by now.
So Bridge Edge Loops. So there we go! That's the mesh,
now all as one, which is brilliant! So the next thing we need to do
is just hop back into the Front View and have a look at
our model and see how we're getting on. So this bit here is far too high,
so we can start moving some of these edge loops now. So let's grab this one
and move it down to about there. We can grab
this particular one here and scale it out.
I'm quite happy with kind of that shape there, although it would be quite
nice to add maybe another edge loop in. Ooh, not rotating but another edge
loop around there, just to define this
indent we have here. And that's almost the bottom
of the bishop's hat, which makes it much more defined,
by adding that extra edge loop in. So not much detail but just
enough to define that! And then finally, we've got the wrong taper
here, so I think all we need to do here is bring these edge loops
down and perhaps scale that in, ever so slightly,
and then, bring this one down a lot to make it far more pointy. There we
go! So the only thing we're missing now is the little bit
of the... What shall we call it? The little bobble on top of
the hat. It's like a snow hat or something like that. So in this case, we can
just add in a sphere, a UV Sphere,
similar to everything else, but we're going to lower these Segments and Rings
all the way down to nothing. Well not nothing but as low as they go!
And we really want to match the segments to the rest of the
hat here, so let's up that to 8 in total
and just scale it down to see how it looks. It needs to be a lot smaller,
probably about that big. Now finally, we want to
meld this object to the top here. So we need to
turn on Snapping and make sure we've got Vertex
selected, which is brilliant, and then, we can grab this and move it about and
plunk it against the vertex. And now that's pinged straight to the right point, straight
away! It doesn't always do that, you can always lock it into the Z
axis and move it up and down, and then, it often will behave for you
perfectly. So I'm going to attach that there. Brilliant! The next thing
I need to do is hop out of that. I'm going to turn off this
Limit Selection Visibality and just have a
look at that! Now, something tells me that's gone a bit wonky, at the top there!
OK, it has! So what has gone on there, that seems
to get a little closer. Let's pop back into...
Well let's have a look at this. I don't think we placed our
model in the right place.
In this case, I think we can resurrect our
problem, we can create it again, but I can see here over in the Transform, on the
Properties, the X and Y coordinates. I'm happy with the Z, it's spot on,
but the X and Y aren't 0. So I think, it's just a raw guess, at this point,
by moving those exactly there we'll have it perfect,
and that's starting to look much better. So let's zoom out and look at our bishop as a
whole! OK, that's brilliant! That looks really good!
I want you to share your creation
in the discussions, and I will see you in the next lecture!