Welcome to the Boolean Modifier! In this video
we're going to experiment with a Boolean Modifier and understanding how it works!
We're going to understand how to apply it to our model,
learn that it can be used constructively and destructively.
It can and will work in Edit Mode, if you choose,
and also, it's real time and live, which is exciting, not all
modifiers are! So let's hop over, straight into Blender!
So before we start using this boolean modifier,
what we'll need to do is create another object in our scene. So
I'm going to place the 3D Cursor just somewhere random, over in space here,
and go and create us... I am in
Edit Mode, I will need to be in Object Mode, in this case. I know it works in Edit Mode,
but I do want to keep these separate to demonstrate. So
I'm going to hold down Shift and A and add a new Mesh of UV
Sphere. Now, I'm going to set the Segments here down
massively. They don't need to be quite so high, maybe 8 and 4.
That feels about right, 184, 8 and 4.
Ah, I'm going to increase it just a little! There we go! And
here, too! So we're going to move this now, so it's against our
bishop. Now, let's just push it in,
and eventually it will go close and close and close, and I'm just going to grab it and move
it down there. Excellent!
So now that it's in our model, we can decide how we want to work.
Leaving the sphere there, we're going to shift this over a little
and go to our little spanner or Modifier Icon, and we'll
add a modifier. And again, it's in this second column, the Generate column,
and it's Boolean, just there. Once we click that,
we have to select an object to apply it to.
Now, boolean operations can only apply to other mesh objects.
So, in this case, we've got this mesh object here, the LP
Bishop, so we're going to put that in there. OK,
so the first thing that this has done is, we've now removed
anything that's not within our bishop itself.
And we can demonstrate that by applying it and then just moving it back
out. You'll see that we're left with a surface of the
bishop cut away from here, so we've
still got our sphere on this side but not on that side. So let's plunk it back in and
do a couple of steps, so we can work on there. If we shift into Wireframe
Mode, this is quite exciting, we can see it as it passes through. So if we
set the object back to Low Poly Bishop, we can see what
will be left as we're moving through. Quite cool!
And that's with it set to the Operation as Intersect.
What else do we have? We have Difference and
Union! Well Union, as it sounds, combines the two
together, so if we then applied this, that would become
one mesh without... As you can see there's no sphere inside.
Now, the Difference does
the exact opposite! It's going to cut away
the bishop shape from the sphere, and we can
demonstrate that again in Wireframe Mode. We see there's nothing left of our sphere,
and if we Apply that and move the sphere away, we've taken
a chunk out of the sphere but the other way this time.
Well, in this case, if we want to cut a hole in... Let's see how it applies
back on the bishop! So let's set our
sphere back into the bishop itself and this time select
the Bishop first, and then, Add a Modifier of type
Boolean and select the Object as the Sphere.
Ah, so with Intersect, it's cut out of the sphere. So
that's the opposite way, that was the Difference when it was the other way around.
Excellent! And let's try Union!
Well that's hopefully going to look the same as it did before. Yes,
it becomes one, after the operation! And Difference,
well that, after it's applied,
will eat away at our model. That's brilliant! That's exactly what
we want to see! Well it looks kind of like a spaceship or a hole in there. Perhaps,
if you wanted to make a hole in the bottom of a tree to hide in. Who knows!
So that's the boolean operator! I'm not going to
undo those changes, because I don't want to ruin my bishop,
and I'm going to delete
that Sphere. Excellent! Zoom back out. Yep, everything's
intact, I've not modified our bishop at all. So
challenge time!
I would like you to cut a notch in the
bishop! So using a boolean modifier, cut a notch
from the bishop's hat, in the top. If you need to have a look at reference material, to
make sure its placement is good, then go ahead and do that. Pause
the video now and give that a go! OK
guys, welcome back! Let's go cut a notch in the bishop's hat!
Alright, so the first thing I want to do is
just generate something and think about where it's going through.
So I want to make my notch diagonal, and I also want to make it
slightly wedge shaped. So I'm going to create myself
a new Mesh object in Object Mode,
so it's separate. Excellent! I'm going to make it more wedge
shaped, as well. I don't care about the scale, at the moment, I can play about with
that at will. So I'm going to pop into Edit Mode, grab
an edge like this one, and just move it in to make
a wedge. It doesn't need to be quite that
angled. We definitely don't want it that big! Probably more like
that! And the final thing I think I want to do is just
round it off ever so slightly, not much, this is going to
spoil the geometry if I do that, maybe. Let's leave it like that and
see how that works! The next thing I want to do is move it closer
to my bishop itself. So I'm going to hop back over into
Object Mode, and move it about so it's almost in the right
place. I've still got snapping turned on, that could be useful in this case,
but not... Well it's close enough it's brought it to
our model. Let's pop it there and push it in.
We may need to scale this up and down as we go.
OK, that's looking good
there, however I want mine the other way
around. So I can just rotate that on
the Z axis by 180, and then, move it back here
in on the Y axis, back in. And that's
cutting in there and it looks a bit too deep a cut. I don't
really want to go beyond here, so I've got a couple of options there. In
this case, I'm going to scale that only on the X, Y...
Nope, only on the Z axis I think.
So scale on the Z axis, rather than going to Wireframe.
Oh, I might not have left myself enough space, I must remember
that. Excellent! I do need it to come out, so
about there. I'm going to lift that back up and push it back ever so slightly,
and I do need to scale it, probably on the X axis at this point, so let's do that now!
Scale on the X axis just to push it out. I'm going to whiz
around the model, yep, that's all the way through our model! I'm just going to pull it
up, ever so slightly more, because we're still around there. Do
I want to chop off any of this little bobble
on the top? Maybe? And In this case not, so I'm just going to
rotate it away, to play with it a little further, and pull it out. And
I've exhausted my artistic license, at this point! Alright, I now
need to apply this! So I'm going to select the bishop first,
and then, go to Add Modifier and Boolean.
I'm going to select the object that we're going to use, which is the Cube,
which is no longer a cube, and we don't want Intersect, we want Difference,
in this case. I'm going to Apply the Modifier, and
then, I've got two options. In this case I'm just going to hide the Cube, in case
it's not quite right. Oh, I like that lots! In fact,
I'd like it so much, I'm gong to do one final thing before I let that go.
I'm going to undo those changes and I'm
going to just adjust the Cube, ever so slightly. I'm going to rotate it
around the Y axis, so that our slice
comes through at a slight angle, which I think is going to
add a tiny bit of a dynamic to it and make it look that little bit better.
And I'm just going to move that back out so it's not touching. Alright, I'm
happy with that, so I'm going to Add my Modifier again, which is already there. In fact, all I need to
do now is Apply it! Excellent!
I'm going to hide my Cube in the Outliner and just check that out again!
Brilliant! I've got exactly the slant that I wanted in my
bishop's hat! How did you guys get on? Please share in the
discussions, and I will see you in the next lecture!
<<<<<<< HEAD:Blender/Section 4/CS16 Boolean Modifier.srt
=======
>>>>>>> 61fb7349cf669f249b4a9560c07cf0816c59420a:Blender/Section 4/CS16 Boolean Modifier.srt