Welcome to Parent
and Child Objects! In this video we're going to see how parents
can group together objects, essentially they become their children.
We're going to create a hierarchy, which is easy to navigate,
we'll be using this to logically group our pieces together. Now,
when we're doing parents and children, the children can have children,
and those children can have children, as well. So you can have a whole family there, so parent, child,
grandchild, and great grandchild, etc.! So looking at
our hierarchy, now going from left to right, this is roughly how the Outliner
will be looking. Where we have the chess scene itself,
there will be a Light, some Objects in our scene, and a Camera and a couple of other things,
as well. Now, at the moment, we've already got an Empty in
our scene, which is the White Pieces, and under that, we're going to put the
Pawns, the Rooks, the Knights, the Bishops, the King, and Queen, etc. And
looking at the number of other objects we have in our scene,
it might be worthwhile, we'll see in the Outliner, and
looking at the numbers there it worthwhile actually putting the Pawns in their
own little Empty, as well, just so we can have good control
over all of those bits and bumps. But we'll see how that looks in the
Outliner, when we start working with it. So talking about the Outliner, let's pop
over into Blender!
OK, so over in Blender we just
need to, I think well the first thing I'm going to do is just tidy up our view. So I'm just
going to hide the Timeline at the bottom, since we're not using it, I'm going to
hide the Tool Shelf, and hide the Properties Pane on the 3D Editor.
And I'm just going to move this section across, because we're mainly going to be dealing with the
Outliner, in this case. Now, I'm going to leave the 3D View here, because
when we select our individual meshes we can see what's going on.
OK, so the first thing we need to do here is start
grouping these items together. And we can see here we have our scene.
Inside the scene there are a load of options, we've got at least one mesh object and,
as a matter of fact, we've got several mesh objects, which is why we're doing this organization.
We've got the camera, we've got the lamp, as well. These can all be
parented or childed, if you wanted to. So I think with all
of this in the hierarchy already, it might be a good idea to
group even our small pieces together. So the first
thing I'm going to do
is how to assign a parent object
to its children. So we'll start with the bishops here, because we've only got two
of them, so it won't be a repetitive task anyway, but at the moment,
they're just by themselves in our hierarchy.
So I'm going to give them an empty, first of all, so I'm going to go
Add, Empty, and again just Plain
Axes is absolutely fine. I'm going to call this
empty, White Bishops.
So the way that a parent is
done is, you select in the order,
or rather the last thing that you select will become the parent.
After all three items are selected, ending with the thing
we want to be the parent, we can go down to Object
and scroll up to where it says Parent, and just go
to Object, and we can see here, Control and P is the shortcut.
And then, it will say Set Parent To, and we just want
Object here. So now that we've done that, we can see that White Bishops
has two meshes associated, looking at the Outliner,
and when we drop that down, we can see our Bishops beneath. Now, what you will
notice, and was a bit counter intuitive when I started using Blender,
was when you click White Bishops, it only
selects our empty here, it does not select the
meshes beneath. If you want to select everything beneath, depending on what you
want to do, say we wanted to hide both of the White Bishops without selecting
them all, we could Control and click on
our empty and that would select everything. Then, if we click the little eye or
pressed H, we could hide all of those by
clicking Control. You have to have Control down, when you click.
So to select them all, we can select them all in the Outliner by holding down Control.
To hide them all, we'd have to do that same, and that similar operation applies
to everything else. Finally, we can nest
this inside WhitePieces. So we
select our first object, or rather in this well
it is an object, we select our first object, and then, we select our second object
while holding down Shift, so both are selected. And then, go to Object,
Parent, on to Object, and again, Control and P.
So in this window here you could just go Control and P, and Set Parent
To, Object. Now, under WhitePieces we have
White Bishops, and under that, we have Low Poly
Bishop one and two. In fact, I might name them
1 and 2 now, just for neatness.
OK guys, it's challenge time! I'd like you to finish off the organization
of the hierarchy! So assign the pawns a parent
empty, called White Pawns, and then, make the
White Pawns' empty a child of White Pieces.
Pause the video now, and go give that a go!
OK guys, welcome back! Let's hop straight on over into
Blender!
Alright, so we're almost here with these pawns! So the first
thing we need to do is create our empty, that we're going to assign
as the parent to all of these pawns. So Add,
Empty, Plain Axes. I'm going to call
this White Pawns, P a w n s. Excellent!
I'm going to select all of these, holding down Shift
as we go, with the final one being White Pawns,
and I'm going to go over here, the cursor has to be in the 3D window. Go Control and
P, set them to the Object. Excellent! So that's tidied up
our hierarchy now, and then, finally, I'm going to select White Pawns, it's
already selected, and put them under White Pieces. Again, Control and P
and set to the Object. And now,
we've got a much neater hierarchy! As you can see, there are now
WhitePieces and the Chess Board! Excellent! And when we
open up that, we have our White Bishops and White Pawn!
Ooh, it looks like we have a series of objects selected! So I've made a mistake
there, so let's reassign these,
the parent object of White Pawns. I forgot to
deselect before going forward. And that's excellent, that's popped
all of those under there! So WhitePieces, White Bishops, we've got two meshes under there.
White Pawns, we should have eight meshes, which we do, and if you wanted
to, you could go through here and name these appropriately, if you wanted
to. And to keep that naming convention going, without doing too much work, the first
one would just be called 0 to 7. Excellent! How did
you guys get on? See you in the next lecture!
<<<<<<< HEAD:Blender/Section 4/CS18 Parent and Child Objects.srt
=======
>>>>>>> 61fb7349cf669f249b4a9560c07cf0816c59420a:Blender/Section 4/CS18 Parent and Child Objects.srt