Welcome to Zoom to Mouse & Rotate
Around Selection! So in this video these two
are great for working around more complex scenes,
as our chess board is slowly becoming. Now, we are changing
the user preferences with this, so if you wanted this to apply
again and again and again to all of the models you're creating, you will need to
remember to save your user preferences, otherwise they won't update.
And we're going to demonstrate both Zoom to Mouse and Rotate Around
Selection and also some other view options that are available,
because you can get in a bit of a muddle when you're using
these two, or in fact, just in general when you're zooming in and out
of a model. You may come to a point where you can't zoom any further and
that is really irritating, and we'll show you some ways to get around that.
So let's hop straight on over into Blender!
So the first thing that I want to do is just pull the Outliner
back in, slightly, so we can see more of our 3D view. Now,
by default, when you hold down the Middle Mouse Button and rotate around, it usually
rotates around the center of our scene, which is the center of the board, in this case,
where X, Y, and Z all equal 0. And zooming is also
done to that, until you move the viewport and
pan around, and then, we can zoom back in. Now, there are better ways
of doing that.
So go to File
and go into your User Preferences, and under the
Interface, the second column has View Manipulation.
And there are two options, which by default are unticked, which are
Zoom To Mouse Position and Rotate Around Selection.
If we turn both of those on and Save our User Settings,
we can hop back into Blender, and all of a sudden,
you can see zooming, for instance, is dependent on where
our cursor is. So if I put it over one of these other pawn's
heads and zoom in, it will zoom towards there. Now, that is incredibly
powerful, when you're working on other models! Rotation, however,
will be around the selected model, in this case. Now,
you'll want to play with this and see if it suits you or not. If you find it's
not suiting you and you'd rather go back to the other system, then that's fine,
you turn those off. These are all view options, i.e.
they're optional. Occasionally, you can end up with some weird stuff
going on. So I've zoomed into this one here and I'm going to rotate around,
and if I wanted to go to this one on the end, you won't go very far before
your zoom runs out, which is a little bit annoying. There are a couple of
ways around that though, and usually it involves resetting
the viewport itself to another place. And
one of the easiest ways to do that is, select another object, so I've selected
this bishop, over in the corner, going down to View, and
going to View Selected or Numberpad and the full stop on the Numberpad,
if you've got a full size keyboard. And you can see, it puts our bishop,
the selected object, in the center of our viewport,
and then, because we've got Rotate Around the Selected turned on,
we can rotate around there and edit to our hearts content! A
couple of other ways of getting out that and very useful to go through your
scene if necessary is one that's called the Viewport Dolly
and one is Walk or Fly Mode. Very exciting! So what
are they? Well first of all, let's rotate around, let's go to this
bishop... No that's a pawn isn't it? Let's go to the pawn on the end and zoom into it.
We've run out of zoom again, so I'm [Laughs] going to go to View and View Selected. Great!
I'm going to rotate around, slightly, so I'm looking down, and I've got to remember it's perspective,
I'm going to pan across a little. So the Viewport Dolly is
very effective, in the way that it enables us to go down
our scene, by moving the viewport rather
than zooming in and out.  So if we hold down Shift and
Control at the same time or Control and Shift, it doesn't matter which order,
and hold down the Mouse Button and move it in and out, we can go backwards
and forwards down our scene, which is
really really good; if you imagine these were buildings and you're walking down the street or indeed
this mouse eye view of our chess board. If you
hit the Control well, you'll notice is rotates around,
and if you hold down Alt, instead of Control, it rotates and pivots
the other way. So a couple of useful things there! The final one
is what's called Walk or Fly Mode, and
whether it's Walk or Fly is determined in the User Preferences. I'll show you where that
is now! So under File, User Preferences, under
I believe it's Input, and scroll down.
Here we go, View Navigation! We've got Walk and
Fly! OK, so we're set to Walk, at the moment, let's see what that does!
Shift and F will enable that and we can see a crosshair,
and if we use the W, S, A, and D
keys, much like a first person shooter, and the
Q and E goes up and down. We can move through our scene quite easily!
Now, the other option, Fly, is a little harder to control
but is a little more versatile. So I'm going to Escape out
of that and go to File, User Preferences, and
just change that quickly to Fly mode and close that down.
Now, when we go Shift and F to enable Fly Mode,
it's ever so slightly different. So our cursor enables us
to move around, and the further we stray from that center point,
the quicker the view moves. And we can move forward by pressing W,
and then, the Scroll Wheel itself speeds us up
and slows us down, in fact, it pops us in reverse, as well. and
Very quickly, you can start panning around your model with
quite a bit of precision, and this is great, but it can
get a bit... [Laughs] Whoah, there we go! It can get a bit cumbersome,
at times,
but once you get control
over this, it's very very powerful! And you've got two options here,
if I want this to be our current view I can hit Enter. If I hit
Escape, it'll go back to the previous view. So if I hit Escape, it's going
back to where we started. If I just quickly move us around a little
more, it doesn't really matter where, let's come to a stop and look up at
our ever so tall bishop. Ooh, I've gone through the floor! As I said, it can be a little
bit cumbersome. If I hit Enter, that is our new view, and if I
select that, because we've got rotation on, there we go it's back to center.
so, great fun to be had there!
OK, so a quick summary of the View
Options there! So you can use the View, View Selected, in order to
zoom in to the particular object or objects you
have selected. You can control the view in a View Dolly,
by holding down Control and Shift and using the Middle Mouse Button to Dolly
along the view you have, and you can also use Control and Shift
plus the + and - keys to do that. And finally, Walk or Fly Mode,
using Shift and F, adds a whole new dimension to moving
around your object. I particularly like flying through, even though it
is a bit cumbersome.
OK, so a quick challenge for you guys, and that is try out
the View Options! So go through what we've just done, have fun
with the View Options, try a couple of the different options that you have there,
and if I haven't said options enough, stick with what you
like! They are options, OK, you don't have to have them set
exactly the same as me. However, if you see me rotating around an object
and you're wondering, how are you doing that when it's over there, you now know
why it's set like that, so I can quickly zoom in and out
of my scene and rotate around selected objects.
So pause the video now, give that a go, and have some fun!
OK, welcome back! I hope you
had fun playing about with those options! Remember if you have any
questions to ask in the discussions, and I will see you in the next lecture!