Welcome to Lighting in Blender! So in this video we're going to
understand that the lamps themselves mainly apply to Blender
Render, not the Cycles Engine. In fact, light is
handled differently in Cycles, amongst other things.
We're going to be adjusting lamps properties and seeing its
affect. We will switch into rendered mode in the Viewport
Shading Options, to see what is actually happening, as well.
Now before we hop over into Blender, let's look at the different lamp
options. So we've got a nice table here with the type of lamp
on the left, moving across to its description, and a real world example.
So we have a point lamp, which is an Omni-
directional Point light source. So the light comes out of it evenly in
every direction, much like a traditional light bulb you'd
have at home. Now, a Spotlight is a directional
Point light source, so it's very similar to the Point source, only it has direction
to it. So if you imagine, like a Spotlight, or perhaps when you
put a lampshade over the top of a normal bulb, it
makes it into a directional light. Now, an Area
lamp simulates an area that's producing
light, so like an open window or a TV,
laptop screen, something along those lines. Now, Hemi is the odd one out
here, it doesn't produce any shadows, it's a soft and far away light source.
It's much like the sky is on a cloudy day, without any direct sunlight,
you'll notice that shadows are far and few between outside, when that happens.
And finally, the Sun, well no guesses there, it simulates the
Sun, a far away but still direct light.
Example, the Sun!
This, of course, is like a Spotlight
in many ways, because it has a direction to it, so it
casts a shadow, but it will light up the entire scene evenly.
OK, let's hop straight on over into Blender!
Alright,
so we're in Blender here, and let's just work out our workspace!
Now, I've opened up a new Blender file. If you haven't done this yet,
please save the stuff you're working on and open up a new
Blender file. So I'm just going to organize my workspace here and just remove
the bits that I don't need, so I'm going to get rid of the Timeline at the bottom. I'm going to
pull out these two windows here, because we're going to use both
of those, in a moment. I'm just going to make the Outliner a little larger.
OK, so we can see in our scene, and you probably spotted it before, that we have
at least a Camera, a Cube, and a Lamp
in our scene. Now, all of these are objects, and you can literally grab the transform
handles and move them about to your hearts' content or hit G
and more around the lamp, as well. Absolutely fine, you can do that with
any object that's in our 3D View here. So
first of all, let's go and play with the lamps and see what they look like! So in order
to do that, what I'd like you to do is select this cube here and move it
up, just so it's floating above this surface here.
And then, we're going to Add another mesh, which is just a plane
and simply scale that up to act as a floor. It doesn't really
matter how big it is, in some ways the bigger the better, but there we go!
And now, next to where it says Object Mode, in the 3D
Editor, where you can switch it backwards and forwards, we have the
Viewport Shading options, and usually, we've been working with Solid,
right at the very top of that is Rendered. Now, this
is what it will look like if you have Blender Render selected.
If it looks a bit faded out, something like this, you
probably have Cycles Render selected. And we will be working,
for the rest of this certain section, in Blender Render, so
make sure it's selected at Blender Render, along the Info Header there.
Brilliant! So we're in here, how let's play with our
lamp! So we have our Lamp here and
once it's selected in the Properties Window,
we can see along here is the same icon, it's this circle with
four arrows coming out of it, and these are our lamp options,
essentially. And if we scroll down, there's a Preview there that gives you an idea
of what's going on but even better is the Preview we can see right in
front of us here! So I'm going to scroll down so we just see
Lamp. So, at the moment, it's set to a Point lamp, Omnidirectional light
source. So it fills up the scene, but as you can see, it fades away! There's a couple
of ways you control that fade, number one is this starting Energy. And
if you turn up the starting Energy, it obviously makes the light really really bright,
and obviously, if you turn it all the way down, eventually it will just go black.
And beneath that, we have the Falloff, which
tells Blender how to manage the way that it gets
dark, how quickly the light falls off, essentially, and you can change
those about and just see. Constant, Inverse Square is usually
quite good to work with, but you can play to your hearts' content with that!
Alright, so we've got those two options there, and further down,
we can go into Shadow, we can have it cast No Shadow, which is a
bit odd, I do like it casting a shadow because it looks a bit better.
And we have our sampling for our shadow! Now, in general you want
to have that a bit higher than 1, but I don't suggest putting
it too high, otherwise you may slow your computer down to a crawl. If we say it's
100, for instance, you can see how slow that is to get the detail
into our scene... Sorry, I say set to 100,
you can only set it to 64 maximum! When we set it to something like
10, it's relatively quick to finish off the rendering of that scene.
Now, the Soft Size, if we increase that
you probably gathered it makes the shadow, since we're under Shadow, a bit softer,
and eventually, we end up with something that looks a bit better than that harsh
square that we had before. So let's have a look at the
other Lamp types that we've got! So Sun will also cast a shadow,
but as you can see, the rest of the scene is unformly lit,
apart from... Whoah, if we move around you can see that some
sides of the cube are darker than others, and in fact,
some of them are black. So this is something that you have to get used to with Blender
Render, is that if a surface is not being hit by any light
at all, it just turns black, there's no detial in there whatsoever.
OK, let's zoom out and move around and turn on the
Spotlight! So here we have our Spotlight, not highlighting
our cube very well at all. And if you were setting up a scene like this,
you could hop back into Solid Mode here and actually see the cone
itself. We can see here that our spotlight
is basically not highlighting our cube, at the moment, and if I do
that, the good chance is that it's now doing that. Popping back into
Rendered Mode and there we go, our cube is now being hit with that Spotlight, and
you can see very quickly the rest of the scene that isn't in our Spotlight
goes black. And you can control that, as you scroll down you can
actually change the Spot Shape, so that's underneath the Shadow Options
we were playing with a moment ago. The Spot Shape, you can increase the
degrees that that light is or even narrow it down, if you want
to. Now, we've got the Blend, which detects
how smooth the blend between light and dark is. You can have a
square Spotlight, if you like, and this one, I really love this,
the Halo, it produces that wonderful thing there. Intensity 1
is too much, but if we turn that down a little, a little
more, probably even 0.178, that's brilliant! So that's almost like a window
opening or something like that. I do like that effect that it does there! Now,
this beam here can end up being quite short, and that's all to do with this
Distance here, under Falloff. So if we turn
that down, you can see that you can end up with it looking a bit like that, at times, which
just looks a bit odd. If that does happen, you just turn up the Distance to a certain
amount, and there we go, the cone is
all the way to this surface that it's hitting. Now, Hemi, as I said, that's one of
these odd ones. I'm just going to turn the Energy down just a little.
In fact, I'm just going to type in 1 and set it back to default. Now, here we go,
we can see all around our object. This is one of the ones that
doesn't cast a shadow but also means that the sides that are not
being affected by the light, because Hemi is still directional,
and if we pop into Object Mode we can see that it has a line
coming from it. In fact, the Sun also has a line coming
from it, and you can see the icon changes slightly, as well, depending on
what we're doing. So it still has a direction to it but it does not cast a shadow, but it
illuminates our scene quite evenly. So you can use a mixture of Lamps
in your scene, to emulate the real world.
And finally, we have Area, so let's hop back
into Rendered Mode, on the Viewport Shading, and
that's really bright so, in this case, let's play with some of the options. Let's play with
Distance, that looks a bit better! That looks much better! And eventually, you'll
find a level that works for you. Now, the
shadow here, it looks a bit horrible, actually, to be quite
honest, and that's because we've got Samples in the X direction at
10 and the Y at 1, I'm guessing. So if we put that at 10 and 10 that's
a much smoother shadow. So Area, so
as the light's coming out, it's not coming from a point anymore, it's emulating a
size, and we can scroll down and you can see the Area Shape. So this is where
you would tweak, and depending on the size of the window in the room, or something
along those lines, you could have a really really wide
window in the room, 10 by 10. I presume that's Blender units there!
And obviously the shadow ends up being almost nothing, but if you had a
tiny window in a room, perhaps 1 by 1, that would be more
like a Point light source, because it would be much much smaller.
So feel free to play with these options here, as much as you
like. It's great fun playing with lights in our scene,
and you can see there effect, in real time, on the window
here. Now, perhaps you want to work with the model and
the lamp, so you can move them around independently. Sure grab yourself another
window, so you've got a rendering window. I'm just going to move this one in, because I'm working in
quite a low resolution, and I'm going to get rid of my Tool Shelves. So here we
have our rendering, and it's just two 3D Windows, and we have our rendering on the
left and our 3D View on the right here. And the great thing
about this is, we can move this to our hears' content, and then, on the left-hand
side or wherever you've put it see the differences. So I can change that to Spot
and then move it, and we can see straight away the real
time changes that are being made. Brilliant! So I think
there's a challenge for you guys, coming up!
Setup some lights! So go
ahead and in our chess scene
place some lamps to light our scene. Now, it's your choice of how you
want to light it. Play about and experiment! I'll give you a
few hints here that I'm probably going to use a Sun Lamp and a
Hemi Lamp, in order to generate a uniform light
for our scene. But if you want it to be more dramatic, perhaps play with a couple of Spotlights
and cast some long shadows across the board, it's entirely up to you.
This is your artistic choice! Have fun,
pause the video now, and give that a go!
OK guys, welcome back!
Now, let's see how I would light the scene, it may be different to how you've done it,
but let's have fun and see how we get on!
Alright, so let's open up our chess scene!
So Open, low-poly-chess-set, ChessScene. So
there we go! So this is how it's looking at the moment, which is brilliant! We've got
our hierarchy all setup here. Excellent! So
we've got one lamp in the scene and it's pretty low down. First of all,
I'm just going to see how it looks. So let's hop straight down into
Rendered Mode! Ooh, actually, that's kind of dramatic!
I kind of like that! But I do want to light up all my pieces, I kind of want to
show them off, in this case! And remember, you can always alter
your lamps at any point. you're not stuck. In fact, you could
create lots of lamps in your scene and move them about, as if there was an array
of lights above you. The choice is yours! So in
this case, however, I will want to have a Sun
Lamp that does the entire scene, absolutely fine.
But what it does do, unfortunately, is create these nasty shadows,
so I'm going to simply select the Lamp in the Outliner,
pop over to the 3D Window and duplicate it. Not
Linked Duplicate, that's good if you've got multiple lights and you want to control them all at
once, however, if I just do a simple duplicate, we've
now got two suns. But what I can do here
in... Oops, I'm moving that Lamp, I don't want to do that! We just can't see I'm doing
that because I'm in the Rendered Mode. This Lamp here, so we're going to call this one Sun,
and I'm going to call this one Ambient.
Excellent! So
we've got Sun and an Ambient. Oh, I've named them both
the same! That's really cleaver of me there! And I'm going to group
these together into our lighting, so I'm going to create... You
don't have to do this yourself, I'm just doing it for my hierarchy.
I'm going to create an Empty, it doesn't matter what it is. I'm going
to make it a Sphere,
I'm going to call this Lighting, and that just helps group
my lighting all together, as well. So there we go, all in
there at the parent object, and I'm going to correct the spelling
mistake there. There we go! So Lighting and we've got Ambient and Sun, and both of them are Sun at the
moment and we can see that we've got these dark areas. However, on
the Ambient one, when it's selected, I'm going to go to Hemi.
Now, it looks like that and we've still got some shadows, but I think the Hemi's a bit, actually,
making the board very very bright, in this case. So I'm going to turn
down the energy that the Hemi has, perhaps even
to let's try 0.3 or there abouts.
Yeah, I like that, that's good! Let's go to the
Sun itself and I'm going to split this
window, so I can see what's going on. Now, the Sun
is here in our scene. I don't want it there. If
I put it here and just hit rotate, rotate it around,
lift it up a little more because it is a sun, after all,
and rotate that down, so you can have lots of fun with this. It's now shining on our
board. Let's rotate around the rendering.
Let's go to View and just
View Selected. There we go, we're zoomed in there!
Yeah, that looks good! I like that lots!
Nothing's blown out, we've still got detail over the place. I like
that lots! How did you guys get on? Please share your
lighting attempt in the discussions! I'd love to see what lighting
schemes you came up with yourself! Perhaps some groovy spotlights there
or a deep dark thing. Remember we do want to show off our pieces
and our board, at the moment, so don't make it too noir on us, too
dark and contrasty, because we won't be able to see all the effort you guys are putting in.
OK, as I said, put those in the discussions and I will see you
in the next lecture!