Welcome to Hiding Un-Needed Objects!
In this video, we're going to discover it's useful when
working on larger and more complex assemblies or scenes.
So, at the moment, we're only dealing with a chess set, but it's good to grasp
this notion before you start dealing with something even more complex,
where perhaps parts are hidden behind one another. And we're going to control
whether you're hiding groups of objects, as well as individuals
themselves. So let's go play with this over in Blender!
Alright, so here we are in Blender! The first thing I'm going to
do is just free up a bit of space. Oh, that didn't work terribly
well! Let's hide that and hide that. There we go!
And switch over to Solid, no particular reason other than I can see
what's selected and what isn't. So, as you can tell here, as you're
selecting things, you get the orange marker around them. And to hide something, well it's an
object operation. So we go to Object on the 3D Editor
Header, and I'm going to have to scroll up with the low resolution I'm running.
And here we have Show and Hide, and we can see there are three options,
when it comes to hiding. So there's Show Hidden and that will show everything that you've hidden so
far, bringing everything back into view. With hide Selected, so if you've
selected an object or multiple objects, you can hide them all at
once. And then, finally Hide Unselected, so that's like a
inverse hidden. So if I only wanted this pawn here,
I could select the pawn like it is already, go object,
Show and Hide, and Hide_Unselected.
And there we go, we just have the pawn
visible. Now, of course, we can bring everything back with Alt and H,
and then, we can select a couple of pawns here, let's say, and press H
to hide them away, so it's very powerful! Now, there's another option for
doing this, over in the Outliner. So if we bring everything
back into view, with Alt and H or do the menu option,
there if you want to. OK, so we have our white
pieces all grouped together and there's a little eye next to them. So you can
go to... I'm expanding the hierarchy here. You can go to where it says White Bishops
and click the little eye, and it will start turning things off.
But why hasn't it turned the bishops off? Well underneath
that you have the bishops themselves. So that's grouped,
it has an empty called White Bishops, but it's not going to hid everything underneath.
Similar to what we explored before, you're going to have to hold down Control,
as you click the eye to hide everything underneath that
hierarchy. So if we have the WhitePieces and hold down Control,
as we're clicking the eye, we can hide all of the White
Pieces, if you've got that hierarchy. If you've not, you can
go down and, for instance, go down and hide all the White Pawns or hide all the White Bishops,
whilst holding down Control itself. Otherwise, you'd
have to go in and click them individually like that. So if you've got a
good naming structure, but it's quite difficult to select items, you can
just hide them through this Outliner Menu or hierarchy itself.
OK guys, it's challenge time!
Now, there are going to be several ways that you could accomplish this, I don't
mind how you do it, but I'd like you to hide everything but the
board. So hide all the chess pieces, in our scene,
leaving just the checkered squares, so far, and we're going to build out the rest of
the board in a bit. So pause the video now and give that a go!
OK guys, welcome back! let's hop straight
back over into Blender!
OK, so there are a couple
of options! As you've probably seen already, you could just control
click the WhitePieces over here,
and when we've Control clicked them, they all disappear leaving
just the board itself. Alternatively, you could select the board
and do Shift and H, and hide everything but the board.
Remember there's still the lamps in our scene, as well
as the Camera, and, at the moment, it gives us a nice clean workspace, if
we hide absolutely everything but the board itself. Brilliant!
So now, you've done that, please share in the discussions, and
I will see you in the next lecture!
<<<<<<< HEAD:Blender/Section 4/CS21 Hiding Un-Needed Objects.srt
=======
>>>>>>> 61fb7349cf669f249b4a9560c07cf0816c59420a:Blender/Section 4/CS21 Hiding Un-Needed Objects.srt