Welcome to Control Interfaces!
In this video we're going to talk about keyboards, mice, and the general
interface that Blender has, as well. So first of all keyboards! Well
if you have a Mac then the F keys on your
Mac, at the top, F1, F2, F3, etc., you're going to have to hold
down the Function button, wherever it be. On a laptop it's usually on the
lower-left of your keyboard. If you've got a full
size keyboard, it's above the cursor keys in the middle. So that's something
to remember. And also, it's not only Macs that suffer from this, some
laptops also require the Function (Fn) key now to control those
F numbers at the top. And those are used throughout Blender, if you decide
to use the keyboard shortcuts. Now on Linux,
the Alt key is used as a system key.
So whenever you see me holding down Alt and you
need to use that, you're probably going to have to hold down the Windows key at the
same time, in order for it to work as expected within Blender.
What happens if you've got no number pad? Well in a
moment we'll go over into Blender and enable Number Pad Emulation,
and I will show you what impact that has, because obviously you're going to lose
some other functionality the moment we do this. You will also find
on Macs and Linux, system keys sometimes override
Blender shortcut keys, and Blender is really shortcut heavy.
So don't be surprised that if you use a shortcut key, that I show you, if you're on a
Mac or Linux and it does something unexpected, not only to Blender but
perhaps the entire computer. So just bear that in mind, if you're using
those platforms. Let's talk about mice quickly! So
I would strongly recommend a 3 button mouse.
We'll be going through how to use Blender without a 3 button mouse, so the
examples there would be if you're on a laptop. So you're going to be using a trackpad
a padldle maybe, even a stylus as well, so there's lots of options there for
us. I still highly recommend a 3 button mouse and a full size
keyboard, wherever possible. Later on you may,
if you've not got one already, you may consider a stylus if you're
really into Blender and you want to start doing more artwork. All of these
things are just different tools for us to do our work with, and a stylus is
really good for drawing and sketching and things like that. And a mouse is a bit
crude when it comes to that, but for everything else we do in Blender, a normal 3 button
mouse will be absolutely fine. Blender's visuals!
Well we're going to go through Blender and see that you can change the appearance of
Blender, which is very powerful. You can personalize the interface, and
make it easier for you to see. Not everybody's got 20/20 vision and
Blender gives us, because of its unique interface, it gives us
a unique opportunity to just completely change how it looks.
So now we've gone over that! Let's go explore these things and hop on over
into Blender!
OK, so we're over in the Default layout, which
is generally the first thing that you're going to see, when you first start up Blender. It may look slightly
different, depending on the screen size that you're using. So first of all, we'll
deal with the keyboard itself. If you're using a laptop or even a smaller
keyboard, you're going to be missing the number pad on the side.
Now the number keys across the top of your keyboard, the 1,
2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 0 those actually control
the layout options in Blender. Now,
what we're going to be doing is sacrificing that ability for the
ability of moving around our model, which is in my
opinion more powerful especially early on. So the numbers
across the top of the keyboard change layer, and we can see
on the Header Bar, down here for the 3D View, these...
I don't know how many there are. There are 20 boxes or so of the
layers that you can work on. So you can work on multiple layers and keep things separate
from one another and turn them on and off, it's very very powerful. And since
the option is down there,
it won't disrupt you too much
if you lose the ability to hit the numbers across the top of the
screen. Often it's better to check down here anyway and see which layer you
want to work on, and we'll go through layers much later on in the course.
So the number pad itself enables us to move around our model,
by pressing on the number pad, the various numbers, we can see
the various numbers. We can see it's moving
around our model in various ways and changing the view,
which is very powerful. And of course, if you've not got a
number pad, it'd be best if we setup the numbers at the top. And the way that we do this
is, go to the File menu on the Info Header and scroll
down to where you see User Preferences. Now this area, I will
warn you, you can edit pretty much eveything to do with Blender,
so make sure if you do make a change, it is a change
you want to make. So let's go in and open it up!
So we've got the Blender User Preferences in front of us, and we want to go to
Input. And on the left-hand side we can see
that we have Emulate Numberpad about halfway
down, and if we click on that, it simply changes the numbers along the
top of your keyboard, so that they work as the number pad, which is very very
powerful.
And you can also use this feature, the plus and minus will help you zoom
in and out, if you don't have a 3 button mouse,
which we'll move on now as
we're in the preferences.
So I'm going to turn it off, because I have a number pattern,
I'm used to using that. So I'm going to turn on now Emulate
3 Button Mouse and we'll explore how that works. And I'm
going to make sure I Save the User Settings. That is important.,
if we don't save the user settings, it won't remember what you've done. I'm going to
close down the Blender Interface there. So now that I've done that, I'm going to
move over. I have got a 3 button mouse, but it's attached to my MacBook so I can
now use the Trackpad, in order to control things. Now, it will
vary from computer to computer as to what you can do by standard.
So on a Mac, for instance, the trackpad is rather good, so that
does enable you to use two fingers and
rotate around your model. Now, your Windows or Linux
machine may also do the same. It also allows this pinch to zoom operation,
so I'm just moving my fingers in and out and that
zooms in and out. Now if I want to pan to the left and right, I can
hold down Shift, whilst using two fingers, and we can see that pans
left and right. And using all of those together, we actually get
a reasonable result and quite a quick and easy method of use.
However, if your trackpad only supports
clicking, and it's not got all these multi-touch things, you can still
use the actual system, it's absolutely fine. You simply hold,
once that emulate is turned on and you've saved your settings, you can hold down Alt.
And this is the screencast key for Alt there. And when you
left click, that enables you to orbit around your
model. Great! How do we pan?
Well, we continue holding down Alt and we hold down Shift and then we can click
and pan left and right. So that is really really
powerful! Now let's have a look at what would happen
if you wanted to change the interface, how it actually looks. And some
people will want to do this, so it's higher contrast, so it's easier to see, easier to
work on. And once again, you can go to File, User Preferences,
and this time we're going to go to the Themes.
And this gives us a load of Presets and we can change the colors everywhere.
So if we go to this Presets section, we can see there are loads of different
options, and Flatty Light is one that I
quite enjoy. It really does boost the contrast and make the screen easy
to read. Now, I'm not going to use a special theme, because I want to make sure it
is as similar to the default state as possible, as we're going
through. But one of the other things you may want to do is, change the size of
the font, independently of the rest of the interface, and you can do that
over on the System Tab. Now we have this option here
that says DPI, and that allows us to scale the interface so you can make
the text smaller or you can make the text larger, and that's
completely independent of the window size itself. I'm going to set
that back to 72, and that's really powerful! If your eye sight's not that good,
you can enlarge the DPI of the application itself,
and that's also great because it doesn't effect the rest of your computer either. I mean, one
of the options would be to change the resolution of your screen but that's not ideal. This allows you to
actually scale the text up, so you can read it really easily. Obviously that's
too extreme for me, and I'm going to set that back to 72, which is the default.
So that gives us a great overview of what you can do to Blender's
interface, how you can customize it. And remember, it is your system, make
it your own. Make it as easy for you to use as possible.
Finally, any settings that you have changed, remember to Save your
User Settings, otherwise it won't come back next time. Now,
if you accidentally make a change that you don't [laughs] want to keep,
you may want to revert back to Blender's default state,
which you can do, it's in the File menu itself. If we scroll
down here, let's see, Load Factory Settings. Now the
danger of loading factory settings is, it wipes all of the settings
you have setup, so you know, use this with caution.
And if you've spent a couple of years, let's say, using Blender and then you go
and use this, you're going to have a lot of setup time again. But if you're playing
about with Blender initially, trying to get a style you like, and you overwrite
the default startup file, which we can do here as well Save Startup File.
Then, at any point, you can just click Load Factory Settings,
Load Factory Settings, and we're back to there. And I've got this graphical glitch
again, so I'll just sort that out. There we go, we're back
to the Default layout! So that's very powerful that we can reset everything and
start again and play with it and enjoy it.
So make the alterations that you need to make Blender comfortable for you
to work with, and I will see you guys in the next lecture!