OK, so let's go through what's coming up, so you get an idea
of the course itself! So the course structure, what are we going to do? Well the
first section is going to be designed for complete beginners. So
if you already have experience, you may want to skip ahead
but I generally don't recommend it. You might still find the beginning of this content
useful. I've asked some experienced people, ones who have been perhaps playing with
Blender on and off for a couple of years, and the feedback in general has been, oh
even though I've used Blender for a while, I didn't know that thing existed. So it's
wortwhile just watching, but bear with it, if you are experienced it may seem
a little basic at first. And it is basic because it's just code
with, is to help people cope with Blender, when they first approach it
afresh. Remember you can speed up and slow down
videos. There's a little toggle where you can make it go up to 2 times quicker,
so you can very quickly scrub through these early videos, if you need to.
So the learning journey itself! We're really focused on making sure
you guys have a very progressive learning journey. So we aim
to give you a breadth of knowledge across Blender. Every
lesson will focus on one key area of Blender, or
sometimes not Blender; sometimes it's just how to design, how to organize
but we tend to focus just on one thing at a time, so you guys can
stay focused essentially. Lessons will build on one another,
so often later, especially later on in the course, you'll find that you'll be using
a lot of your prior knowledge, and that tends to not be
retaught over and over again. It does in the early sections but later on,
we'll just use those skills that we've learned. Because of
this, because of the progressive nature, I would not recommend skipping lectures,
because it's very easy to miss something and then
go, oh well how do I do this? So do go through each one individually, and if you
get it then, of course, move on! So one of the big things
that we get, early on in the course, is there are lots of different ways of
doing things in Blender, it's a very versatile package. So there's
always multiple paths to the same outcome, and it's important
to realize that there isn't a right way. As long as you get
to the destination point and you've completed, let's say, a challenge
I give you guys, then that's it! You've completed it, that's brilliant!
My way is not always necessarily the quickest or the way that you're
going to choose. So don't see my way as the all seeing all knowing
way, there are always multiple ways of doing it. And often, I'll be using
the skills we've just learned in that lecture, even if there's another skill
I could use in order to complete the challenge as well.
If you have another route, share with everybody your experience. So
there are multiple ways of doing things, and learning about all the different ones
is valuable for absolutely everyone, so please share when you
do that. Now, you'll see these green slides throughout the course. These are
challenge slides. Now, most lectures will have these challenge
slides in them, and these challenges are important, they really hone your knowledge, they make
sure that what you've just been taught you can actually apply.
And often it's worthwhile going through and trying out
some more things, using the skills you've just learned.
Challenges will focus on specifically what has been learned in that
lecture, and it will incorporate earlier
knowledge too, more so as we progress through the course.
Now, please please share your work! Be proud of it! When you first
start something afresh, it's very intimidating when you're surrounded with
people that are better than you at something. Now don't worry
about that, we all start from somewhere, and we all start from 0, if we've
not used Blender or anything else in our lives. So just remember to
be proud of it! I love seeing you guys develop and I want to see you
start building things out of cubes and cylinders and putting it together,
And then, in a few weeks time, you're building wonderful models! And that will happen,
just stay with it, be proud of your work, and remember to share it!
And do make the challenge your own! So I might ask you to make...
And I will do in a few lectures time, a simple block-work
plane. And I know some people have taken this challenge on their own, and instead of
making a very simple plane, they've taken the knowledge they've learned so far and they've
made some wonderful examples of aviation models. So
it's absolutely wonderful seeing what you guy are doing! Go above and beyond the challenge
whenever you can. Push yourself and you will be surprised
you will be surprised with what you'll be able to do!
So let's move on now to the next lecture!