So, Hi and welcome to
Number Wizard UI! So, in this game, we're going to take what
we did last time, which is the Number Wizard game, a number guessing game,
and turn it into UI. Get it to be visual, get it to be
interesting for the player. And it's the first time you're going to be meeting
the Unity Editor. So far, we've only stayed in the Console,
but now, we're going to dig into the actual visual
editor, create scenes, and create menus for your game,
which is going to be quite fun! And for the first time, you're going to see all those other
bits of Unity: The Scene Tab, the Game Tab, the Hierarchy,
the Assets Tab, the Inspector.
So, we've hidden that before. We literally put
MonoDevelop over the top of it, so we didn't scare you off. Now,
we're going to start making use of that stuff! You're going to build your first UI
or User Interface. You're going to have menu buttons, etc. We're going to run
all those forward, through the future sections, so we're going to start to build a reusable
Menu System now, which we're going to want to use for every game. By the way,
we want you to... Pretty much the first thing you do when you
make a game is, let's get you making the menu system,
and make the navigation around the game from the Start Screen
to a place holder game screen, to a Lose or a Win
Screen. Let's get that in place first, because that's a thing, at the
end of the project... It's such a common excuse,
for not shipping right. Yeah, you'll really want to get that
working straight away, so that you can't have an excuse of oh
I could finish this game, if only I had a menu. Well, add the menu
at the beginning, that way when you get to that point you've got a finished game, which is really
very important actually. Absolutely, and it gives you a really nice kind of context
and structure. It makes you think about the flow of your game,
from the beginning. So, it's like doing a jigsaw, by doing all the pieces around the outside
first, which makes sense. So, let's get the Menu Systems in place, start getting
confident with that, and it's going to get great! It's going to be a great section!
By the way, the learning curve in this course,
it starts off very very shallow, so you might find it really easy in the beginning.
If you do, just watch out because it's going to get steeper
and steeper, as we introduce more and more concepts, so stay with it.
If it's a little bit slow for you, just go through it fast. If it's too hard, go back
a little bit or just take it slow, but you're going to be fine. It's going to be
a good section and we'll see you soon. Good luck and have fun doing this section!
See you soon!