Hey, welcome to Object Orientation
Basics! So, what is an object? What is a
class? What is an instance? Well, let's use Lego
through this series, as an example. This Lego here
is an object or it's an instance, and
the mold that made it back in the Lego factory is a
class, a template that says how to make these things.
And each instance has a couple of things about it. Firstly, it has
properties, like this guy is blue, and it has eight
studs on it, and it also has methods right, Brice,
which are functions. Yeah, so for example, this particular Lego block
would have a click method, when you click it with something else. So,
in your Unity, you use methods and functions already
and you could simply say click with this
block, and the function would be ClickWith and then, you would pass it
another block. That would be an example of a method on that
particular object. And these are very simple
objects, these blocks, but Lego goes all the way up to Mind
Storms, and here I have a Mind Storms motor. So, if this
was a class, it would have a lot more going for it.
You can literally see here that the
object has more places where you can plug stuff in,
it has more method, it has more functions on the object itself.
This block has only eight on the
front and eight at the back, but this has significantly more,
as well as a bunch of moving parts, for example.
Yeah, and there's a lot you could do with this. So, one of it's methods would be
RotateClockwise(deg) by two degrees, it would also do that! It also
has return values. One of it's methods would be
what angle am I at, compared to where I started, to when I was born, when I
was instantiated? What angle is that? So, it would then
return a value in degrees. So, that is a much more complicated
template, and these guys are
really simple object templates. So, the three key
takeaways are, classes are templates
that create instances of the instances, and
instances are what we call objects. A particular Lego block
is an instance of a class, and if you
think of classes, what you write in your editor, as this is the
template for the things that are going to be created in my game,
you won't go as far wrong. Absolutely, so your class
here could be six blocks, for instance. This is
duplo, so it could just be called six block, and then, when you actually
instantiate it, you may say SixBlock.Color =
Blue or SixBlock.SetColor. And then, you would give it
blue. As it was, this guy, when he was instantiated, you might
say that that's the same thing as, instead of SixBlock, but it's red, so there's an example
for you. So, that's it! Really, a
class is a set of properties, like number of
studs, color, etc., and methods like
ClickTogether, like Rotate, like ReadRotation
and those sorts of things. Hopefully that analogy makes it a little bit clearer for you.