Hello and welcome back! In this video we're
going to be looking at creating new scenes
and levels in Unity. So, what do I mean by
that? Well, Unity has the concept of scenes
and you'll often hear it used interchangeably
with the word level, so levels and scenes
in Unity essentially mean the same. And we're
going to creating some levels and scenes,
to show you how to structure your game. So,
let me give you a couple examples of how scenes
and level could be used in your game. Let's
say you have a side scroller and you have
the dangerous castle, that could be an independent
level. And then, you could have the dangerous
plains, that would be a different level. Those
are how you would structure your game, you'd
have one scene for each of those levels. And
you might have scenes fort things like the Start Menu or the Splash
Screen or also the Options Menu. So, you can
basically use scenes to structure the game in
that way. So, here's what we're going to do
together. We're first going to create a 2D
project. In fact, you're going to be doing
that right now, so create a new 2D project
in Unity, and you should end up having something
like this, in front of you. So, let's take
a look. Firstly, I want to draw your attention
to the very top of that window, which is the
title bar, so you'll see Untitled - some name,
and that's going to be the name of your project,
or at least the name of the folder, where
you save your project. Then, a dash then PC,
Mac, Linux stand alone or some other build
option. So, let me give you a little bit of
the structure of what you're seeing here.
The first thing, before the first dash, that's
the name of the scene you're currently editing.
Between the two dashes, that's the name of
the project or the folder your project is
saved in, and then, after the last dash, that's
the name of the build setting you have, so
I'm currently setup to build for PC, Mac,
and Linux, as a stand alone build. So, now
we've got this going. How do we create a new
scene? Well, it's quite simple, we go into
Unity, we select File, and we create New Scene,
and that will bring us to a completely new
scene that's untitled and to actually save
that scene as a file we go, File, Save Scene,
and notice that you can also use the shortcuts
that will appear on the right of the menu
items. So, you click on Save Scene and it'll
bring up the Save Scene Menu, where you can
type the name of the scene. We're going to
start with a start scene, quite originally,
and now you can see that the scene has now
appeared in your Assets Pane, at the bottom
of your screen, as a Unity icon in the Assets
Pane. And you'll also notice that the Title
Bar has changed, once you've saved the scene.
The scene name now appears in the Title Bar,
with a little Unity icon as well. So, that's
pretty simple, that's how we create scenes
in Unity, and now it is your turn. We want
you to create three new scenes, in the same
manner, so you're going to pause this video
and you're going to create three new scenes
called Game, Lose, and Win. And we will see
each other once you're done, so see you very soon. So, hi and welcome back! How
did you get on? Did you manage to create your
three new scenes? Let's get going and see
how we do that. I will just go File, New Scene,
and then, I'm going to use my shortcut, which
is Command Save and that would go Game. And
I can create a new scene. I can use Command
N and then Command Save, that's going to be
Lose. Command New and you'll see that the
Title Bar changes, Save and then finally the
Win Scene. And now you'll see you in my Console
in the Assets in my Project Pane, all four
scenes I want to create, and then, finally
I'm going to go File, Save Project, to save
my entire project  to disk. And that's
how you create new scenes and levels in Unity.
I hope it was very clear and you now can create
new scenes for yourselves, and I will see
you very shortly in the next video! Bye for
now!