Hello, and welcome back!
In this video, we're going to be looking at how to
add text to our scene. So, this is something we've seen,
you might have seen before, but in our video we're going to
be looking at how to add the text elements. We're going
to be looking a little bit more in depth as to how we can scale and
position the text and what the tools are to do so. And we're
going to be using the UI mode, the
specific UI mode in Unity, to
postion our elements and to see the diference between a normal
Move Mode and the UI Mode. So, let's get
started. So, right now I've got a bunch of
scenes, in my Unity game. I'm going to start with
the Start Scene, and you're gonig to see as soon as I double click it
the name of my scene appears at the top of my
window, on the Title Bar. So, now I'm in the Start Scene,
I want to add some text. And how do
I add some text? Well, you've probably done it before, in a previous section,
but let's go over it again. You go to Game Object,
UI, and Text, and
that will bring in quite a few things to your game. And you can
see it straight away. In your Hierarchy, you'll see there
is a Canvas, a Text Element that is
inside the Canvas, and an Event System. So, it'll bring you
three things, so there are three different things brought
in for adding some text. So,
now let's go over them, one by one, and take
a look at what they mean. So firstly, we take a look at the Canvas.
I just double click my Canvas, and we can see it appear on
screen and this is my Canvas right here. Now,
you'll notice that there's a quite big difference between the Canvas
and the Main Camera. If I click on the Main Camera and
we look at the Inspector, on the right hand side, we can see it has
a Transform Component, which has a Position, a
Rotation, and a Scale, pretty standard stuff. And then, some camera specific
things. But if I
click on my Canvas, you will see that the Canvas has
some Canvas specific things like the Renderer and the
Scaler, etc., but it also has a different type of
Transform. It has what's called a Rect Transform.
The best part of this UI System is that
the UI System has a different type of Transform,
that allows us much more control over the positioning of our
elements, in a UI System, in a menu,
or in a physical UI in the world space.
So, that's the first thing we need to notice. The second thing we to
notice is that the Canvas has what's called a Render Mode.
Now, the Render Mode is about how
the Canvas is Rendered on the scene.
And right now, we've got it at Screen Space-Overlay, so
if you look at the Inspector, you've got the Canvas component,
it has a Screen Space - Render Mode Property
or attribute, and it will have Screen Space - Overlay,
Screen Space Camera, and World Space. Right now, we're not going to
worry too much about what they mean. We can keep it in Screen Space Overlay,
and that basically, Screen Space Overlay, means the
Canvas will be rendered on top of everything just before the
screen is shown to the user, so when
the engine renders the scene,
it'll start rendering all the objects within the scene, etc., etc.
And then, in the very final step, it'll render the Canvas,
on top of that, as an overlay on the
screen and not on the scene and then that will be shown to the
user. So, we don't worry too much about that for now, but just remember
that's where you find the Render Mode
for a Canvas, it's in the Inspector. And
finally, once we've got the Canvas
you'll have inside of it a Text Element. So, that's
the Text Element, the element that actually
has the text in it. Now, you can move it around
with your mouse, as you would a normal object,
and you see it has the normal handles, with the
two arrows to show its position and some text in there.
Let's zoom in a little bit to show you the text. So, if we zoom
in here, we can see that there's a new text. It's all black, it's quite
small. Now, you'll notice here that the
Rect Transform has now become active, and this is what's quite Important
about UI Elements, is their Rect Transform.
Now, you've got Standard Position, Width, and Height, etc.,
but it also has things like the Anchor and the Pivot,
which are different concepts kept
for UI Elements. And there's quite a few options,
so if you click this little target area here,
of the Rect Transform, you can see quite a few different options
about where it'll be anchored in
the scene. And really, to see what that means
we need to enter UI Mode, and UI Mode
is entered by selecting the 5th button,
on the top left hand corner of the Unity Editor,
or pressing the T Key. So, if I press the
T Key or if I click this button I will now enter a different
mode, that let's me view what my Canvas is doing.
So, now we've got this element, and you'll see that
it's appearance has actually changed, quite a bit, it now
has a full blue
dots on the outside, and a blue dot
in the middle, and you'll see the blue dot in the middle is the Pivot.
That's where you're going to be scaling from.
And then, it has those four blue dots, so you can
change its size and width, etc. You'll also notice
that if you drag it around, it'll snap
to the center line of your containing
Canvas. Alright, so if I move it around, it'll snap to the
center line of the containing Canvas with a blue line,
when it is centered. So, that's the Pivot.
And then, the second thing that you'll see in the middle, when I've got my
element select, is the Anchor. That's how
the element is anchored, and right now, it's anchored to the center
of my screen. Now, what that means is if we re-scale
the Canvas outside, this element will remain
in its position, relative
to the center of the screen. Now, there are other options
for example, I could have it at the bottom, and you could see how that is.
By clicking on the Anchor Preset, I've anchored it to the bottom, so
it'll remain at this distance, from the bottom, or I
could have it to the side but I'm going to keep it in the center.
You also have the option of stretching it,
so by clicking the Stretch Option, on the
Anchor Selection Screen, what this actually means
is if my Canvas stretches out,
in the Horizontal direction, then so
will my text. My text will remain in that proportion, compared
to the Canvas, that it will actually scale with the
Canvas. Whereas, if it's anchored in the middle, without stretching,
it'll remain with the same dimensions, it'll simply
keep it's position relative to the center.
Alright, that's a lot of stuff, and there's also quite a few
other options. You can use Shift to select the Pivot, change the
Pivot as you move it, or to set the position.
So, there's quite a lot of things you can do. You can see that
when I select different keys, the actual appearance
has changed quite a lot, and you can do quite a lot of things.
What I would advise you to do is, spend some time playing
around with this, playing around with all of the pre-sets and all the settings,
to get familiar with what they mean and how they
behave and what happens when you rescale the Canvas, when you change
its appearance, with the different
settings. So cool! Now, we've gone over this! It's time for you
to play around with it a little bit, but first let's
get this new text looking a little bit better.
So right now, I want it to be in the middle. I do
want it to be anchored to the center, and I'm going to
change the text to be a welcome message, so
we're going to call it "Welcome to
Number Wizard". Let's put
some capitals. [Typing Sound]
And I'm going to
call my player, "Puny Human",
because I like that. Cool! So,
"Welcome to Number Wizard, Puny Human!". Now, we can't really see it
here, it's not really big enough. So, what am I going to do? I'm going
to change the Width, the Height, sorry the Font
Size, and I can do that by clicking and dragging and you can see it
going up and down. I'm aslo going to change the color. I think that
color isn't great. I'm just going to pick a white,
so that it's very bold and bright. You can choose whatever color you want.
And I can change the size of my text,
to make it fit on the screen properly. Here we go!
And center it and there
we go. Maybe stretch it a little bit more. There
we go. "Welcome to Number Wizard, Puny Human!"
Note that I can add a new line, if
I want to, in my text,
so... Oops, Control Z. If I
want to add a new line, I can.
So, let's do that now, here we go. "Welcome to
Number Wizard, Puny Human!" That sounds great,
and that will do for my title.
So cool! That is how you add text and how
you scale it and move it around in Unity.
Now, it is your turn! I want
you to, in the same manner as we did just now,
add a subtitle, prompting the user to make a choice
of number, and that's up to
you. So, just pause the video now and add your subtitle.
OK
then! How, did it go? This is what I'm going to do,
the very same thing, and to add my subtitle
I'm going to select the Canvas first, because I want to add it to my
Canvas. I'm going to go Game Object, UI,
Text, and you'll notice that the second Text component
only adds the text, because we already have a Canvas we're adding to,
and an Event System and you'll only need one of each.
We'll go over the Event System in just a little bit, and I'm going to center this text.
Also, make
it, maybe a little orange,
maybe something like that. That looks more like it.
There we go, something like
orange. Maybe not
that much. Here we go and that's great!
So, now I've got some new text. I'm going to increase the font size.
That looks fine.
Stretch it out. That's a bit too big, I don't want it bigger than
my title, so how about
that. That looks fine! And my prompt is
going to be "Choose a number
[Typing Sound]
[Laughs] Not a nummer but a number.
...between
1 and 1,000
if you dare".
Here we go! Now, I'm
going to change that, and notice that if
I want to re-scale here, you'll see that I'm re-scaling
and my Pivot point is moving, because I'm re-scaling
not relative to my Pivot Point, but just re-scaling
relative to the opposite corner. Now, if I press
the Alt Key, I will be re-scaling
relative to my Pivot Point, so that's quite a nice trick.
If I've got my Alt Key
pressed, you'll see that the re-scaling, that will be here is quite different.
So, that looks good.
Let's center the text. Here we
go! And that is how we finish
our introduction to adding text to Unity.
Now, we have a front screen, let's play it and see what it looks like.
Here we go! Pretty much what we
expected. I'm going to change the background color of my Main
Camera. I think I would much prefer to have a black background.
So, let's set it to black.
Play it again,
and we get what we expect. Great!
Now also, what we'll notice... Let's pause the
game again. What we'll notice is the third and final
thing that's been added, when we created our first Text Element, and that's
the Event System. Now, the Event System is compulsary.
You have to have an Event System for
UI events to work, so if your UI isn't working,
double check you've got an Event System in your scene, and make sure
you've not renamed it to something else. So, that's the Event System
and it's useful, because it's basically handling all the events
that will be thrown by the UI and triggering
the right handlers, depending on the
actions that occure. So for example, let's say you're on a tablet,
the Event System will appropriately detect and
pass through multi-touch events
so that you can know what to do in your game.
So, that's why we've got the Event System, and really the complexity of the Event System
is something you don't really have to deal with but
if you want to get a little bit more stuff done with it,
and for example look at Touch
Input or change different types of input, for example
using the controller; that's when you'll start worrying about
the Event System but not for now. For now, we'll just leave it as it is
and know that it's compulsary for events to work
in our game. So, now you'll
notice, in a lot of cercumstances,
if you're looking online for tutorials about UI, you'll
find this on Unity. This Unity
GUI called OnGUI () function, that you have to use,
and that's the old legacy
UI Framework. So, that's the Legacy User Interface Framework,
where you have to define everything we just had to do in the Editor,
but instead of doing it by hand in the Editor,
with all the handles that make it really easy, you have to do
everything in code and you have to draw every
element of your UI
from your code. So, that's the old way of creating
GUIs. And you don't really want to use this way anymore,
so just a heads up, a
word of warning, if you find some tutorials online that
use that kind of OnGUI method or OnGUI
function or the GUI.Button or GUI.Box or rectangle
functions, then you don't want
to use those, you want to use the new UI System.
So, that's pretty much it, for now. We're pretty much
done with our video. I hope it's
been useful and interesting, and I hope you've had a chance to play around
with the different positioning and scaling modes,
for UI Elements. I will see you
very shotly, in the next video! Bye for now!