Hi and welcome to this video!
In this video, we're going to be looking at how to
add a Start Button to our scene and make it respond
to our mouse click. In particular, we want to
have the button change color, when we
hover over it with the mouse, and we want to
have the button change color, whenever it's clicked.
So, we're going to use a Text Element as a button, to do that.
So, let's get started. So, I'll
jump straight into Unity, and here we have our scene.
Right now, it's missing two buttons, a Start and
a Quit button, so that's what we're going to add now. To do that, the first thing
I'm going to do is, I'm going to change the name of these Text Elements. These Text
Elements are not really named very well, so I'm just
going to rename them, to know what they are. I'm going to call this
one Title and the one underneath Subtitle.
Don't forget to
press Return. If you don't press Return, this change won't take effect.
And finally, I'm going to add a new
UI object text, from my Game
Object Menu, and you'll see the text come up.
I'm going to drag it underneath, and I'm going to rename
this one Start Button.
[Typing Sound]
So, I've got this Start Button here, I'm going to change
the text to Start,
as you'd expect. Change the color
to white, by default.
And I'm going to also
make it a little bit bigger and center it. So, centering it
first, and then, make the Font Size a bit bigger.
How's that? That looks good!
It's now positioned and we have
what will become our button. So, right now it's
just text. So, how do I turn it into a button? Well, I can
click Add Component, and if I look at my
Component Hierarcy I can go to UI and then,
there will be a Button component.
So, I can click the Button Component, and here we
have a interactable button attached
to... Oops, that's not attched to the right thing, that's attached to our Canvas.
Look we've got the Canvas selected
and I've added a Button Script to it. [Laughs] Not quite what I
wanted to do! So, let me remove that component and select the right thing, which
is my Start Button, which I've miss-spelled. That's not
Strart, it's just Start Button. [Laughs] I think that's a much better name for it.
So, now I want to add a component to my Start
Button. So, UI Button
to my Start Button, and now everything in there, it'll automatically
find the right target graphic, it'll find the buttons.
And we've got a bunch of stuff, and then, it'll have this box of,
this OnClick () box, which will let it carry
our actions, whenever it's clicked. Now, if I press Play,
if I move my mouse over this button,
absolutely nothing happens. Can you see that? Nothing at
all happens. We want to change that, so what we're going to be doing is we're going
to use the Transition Attribute of our button
script, and we're going to select the color tint. So, now there's
three options or four.  None, which means nothing happens, Color
Tint, which means you change the color overlay slightly,
and then, Sprite Swap, which means you change the actual sprite,
underlying the button, and finally, Animation, which let's you play an
animation, whenever one of those states is triggered. We're going to use
Color Tint, because it's very simple. No more color is going to remain
white. Highlighted color, I'm going to give it a
nice bright green, to make it very clear,
that we've highlighted it, and then, press Color. I'm going to
choose a deep orange. In fact, I'm going to go
more towards the red than usual, because remember
this is a tint, so it's on top of the existing color,
rather than as a replacement.
So, now if I press play, and go into my game,
I hover over it, and it goes green.
I click it and it goes orange, and that's the kind of behavior I
am looking for. Now, it is somewhat buggy
sometimes, depending on which version of Unity you are in, and
sometimes, when you click, you'll see here that the hover color
remains. This is a known bug with Unity.
Don't worry too much, it doesn't effect
too many versions, but that is something to keep in
mind, and there are work-arounds if you need them.
But for now, that's sufficiently good for us. We have a Start Button,
and now it is your turn.
This is what I want you to do now. I want you to add a quick
button. Same as the Start Button, but instead of having a Start
Button called Start Button, I want a Quit Button
called Quit Button, that has the same kind of behavior as my
Start Button. I'll see you very soon, when you've sorted that out.
[Temporary Silence]
So, I'm going to cheat a little bit to add my Quit
Button. I'm going to go back into my Unity,
and instead of actually creating
a Quit Button, I'm going to duplicate my Start Button!
My shortcut for duplicating on a Mac is Command D.
I'm not quite sure what it is on Windows, but you can also
I believe, use the menu and use
Duplicate, when you have it on the right
click, for your menu. Now, I've got two Start Buttons, I don't want
that many. Bring the second one down, let me rename
it to Quit Button.
And I've got a Quit Button now.
Don't forget you need to press
Return, once you have renamed,
renamed your entity. And I'm going to change
change this to Quit. And now,
if I go back to my page, and I play the game
we now have two buttons that respond to mouse hover,
respond to clicks, and
change their
colors. And that is it for this video! We
have now created buttons. We know how to create menu...
at least text buttons, and we'll be looking at other
types of buttons in future videos, but for now, that
is sufficiently good for us to create our
Number Wizard UI game. So, I'll see you in the next video.