Hello, and welcome back!
In this video, we're going to be calling scripts
from buttons. So, we have our buttons in the scene
already, but we need them to act upon our
scene, to cause something, and to do that we'll need
to write some scripts to handle our button
presses. So, we're going to create a bunch of new
scripts, we're going to add a bunch of functions to it to handle
the different cases, and for us it's only going to be
a new level or rather load the game
than quit the game. And we're going to
call those functions from the buttons. And then,
we'll check that everything works out OK, by looking at the
Console. So, let's get started! So, now
we jump back into Unity, and the first thing we'll notice we'll have those two buttons,
the Start Button and the Quite Button, in our
Hierarchy. We can grab the Start Button,
go down to the Button component in the Inspector,
and find the On Click () list, at the bottom. And it says list
is empty. So, by default it doesn't do anything
whenever the button is clicked. We want to change that. So, how do we
change that? Well, what's the logical thing to do? We just click +
and we can see three things come up. We have
the Runtime Only, Editor And Runtime, and Off. That just
means when the button is active, when you can actually use it.
I'm going to keep it at Runtime Only. Then, we have the
None Object, and that's what object the
function is going to be called from or on. And then, we
have the function drop-down itself. Right now, because we have
no object, the function dropped down. You'll notice it... Oops!
You'll notice it has no...
It deactivated, now we want to drop in an
object here, a GameObject, and then, we can call functions on
it. Now, we have no GameObject right now, to
manipulate the scenes and to quit the game. So,
I think it's time we create our new object, so we create
an empty object, by right clicking the Hierarchy, and we
are going to call this new object a Level Manager.
[Typing Sound]
And our Level Manager is going to be
at position 0. I'm resetting the position,
because objects like this that have no
purpose, other than to have scripts attached to them, by
convention we add them at position 0 to make life easier
for ourselves. We don't want them to be all over the place in our
game space. So, we have a Level
Manager, and then, now it's time to add a script to it.
Now, there are many ways you can do that. I'm just going to click the
Add Component and click
on New Script and give it a new name. And the new name
of our script is also going to be Level Manager.
Now, that might be a little bit confusing, but the point
is this Level Manager Script is a component of the Level Manager
Object right. So, here we go.
and it'll make sense when you start calling it
in your code, because it'll be nice and neat to
see the Level Manager start to do something. So, now we have this Level
Manager, and we can see that the script has actually been created in
our Assets as well. If we look at the Project
Folder, the Project Pane, we can see in our Assets we have a Level
Manager C# script. So, that's great! We
can then start to edit the script, to add the
behavior we want. So, if I double click on this Level Manager script,
we can see two functions have been pre-created for us,
the Start and the Update function. We don't want either of
those. We don't really want to use those. What we want to do is load the
new level. Basically, we want this Level Manager to be able to say
load the new level, so that when we click on the Start Button, we can
load the game level. That's the idea right, that's the aim
of the exercise. The aim of what we're doing right now is when we
are in this game, when we click play and press on the Start Buttton
we load the Game Scene. Right now, we're in the Start Scene,
which you can check by looking at the Title Bar, and we want to load
the Game Scene, whenever we press the Start Button.  So,
let's jump back into our code and creat a new function. So, this
function is going to return absolutely nothing, and we're
going to call it Load Level. So, this
LoadLevel function has the job of loading a level. How
does it know which level to load? Well, we're going
to give it a (string name), which is going
to be the name of the level to load. And what do we want to
do with this name? Well, we want to do nothing, right now. We're just going to try
and log it out to the Console, to make
sure that the function has been called properly. That's all we're going
to do, and we're going to write a little message on our Console,
saying something like
("Level load requested
for: " and then,
+ the name. And now,
if we go back into our Unity Editor, we have
the script, we have the script attached to a Level Manager Object,
and now, we can drag this Level Manger Object
into our Start Button. So, we have a Start Button here.
We grab the Level Manager Object, from our Hierarchy
and we drop it
into the slot that says None Object.
And now, you'll see immediately that the function drop-down
has become active. We can now click it
and we can try and find our function, the LoadLevel
in our LevelManager function drop-down. Now, you'll
see a bunch of other things, including the Game Object the Transform, etc.
We don't care about all those functions, those are default functions or
default attributes, that have been created by Unity, for other
reasons but we only care about LoadLevel. So, why
is LoadLevel not coming up in our drop-down. Well, the reason
LoadLevel isn't coming up in our drop-down is, if we jump back
in, it's actually currently not public.
Now, every function need to be
public, if it's going to be accessed outside of the class it's
in. So, if I put public here, as a
key word, before my function definition, that means
that will tell the compiler, I want this function to
be accessible to absolutely anyone that wants to
call it. This is public, everyone who wants to call Load
Level can do so. Now, we can jump back into our
Editor, and then now when we try the drop-down function,
we should see LoadLevel as a string coming
up in our drop-down. And once we've selected this
LoadLevel selected, we now can type
which level we want to load,
in the box that's created. And I've selected
the Game Level, because I want to load the game
from my Start Button. Now, if I press play
and select the Console and I
click on Start, we should see that some debug
code, the debug comes up
in the Console, to show us that the button has
actually been clicked properly.
So, let's pause that, and now it is your turn.
Your turn to do exactly what I did, but instead of doing
it for the Start Button, do it for the Quit
Button. And we're going to be using the same
LevelManager, but instead of calling the LoadLevel function,
the Quit Button should call the quit request
function. So, the idea is that we have a quit request function
that is called, by the quit button, when you
press it. So, good luck and
I will see you when you're done. See you very soon.
[Temporary Silence]
So, how did it go? Let
me take a look at what I would do
to get that working. Firstly,
I want to add the quit request
function into my class, you know I want to be able to
call quit request. I'm making sure I
make it public. I go Quit
Request (), and it takes in
no arguments, because we don't need to say which
level we're quitting to, because quitting implies quitting the game.
So, now we go Debug.Log
and we will...
...leave
a little message, write a little message to
the Console. Ah, let's call it
("I want to quit!");
Here we go. And that will now
tell us that the Quit Button has been properly wired
to the right place. If we jump back into our Editor,
we can then click on our Quit Button
and we can then drag
the new handler to our On Click (), drag our
Level Manager into the open slot,
select the right function, and we want to select
Quit Request, on the Level Manager.
Now, why is Quit Request not here? Did I make a syntax
error in the code? Yes, I did! What did I
forget? I forgot the return type, which is void. I'm
returning nothing from my Quit Request.
So, now I should be able to call it.
And indeed, it does show up
in the drop-down. So, now I've got my Quit Request
sorted. Let's test it and see whether it works.
I'll press Start and we can see a
message come up in the Console. I press Quit and
a message comes up in the Console. And this
concludes our video on how to get
buttons to call functions
in scripts. I hope you learned something.
I hope you found it useful, and I will see you in another video!
Bye for now!