Hello. and welcome
back! In this video. we're going to be looking at how
to load scenes and to quit the game.
We're going to be using some new functions. that we've not met before. that's the Application
.LoadLevel() and Application.Quit()
functions. to load new levels and to quit the game
in our script. So. we've already got a script in the
game. that gets triggered whenever we press a button. and we want to
make that. actually not just log to the Console. but actually
carry out the actions we want. And once we've done that
we'll look a litttle bit more about the limitations of Application
.Quit. because it doesn't quite work in
all contexts. If we use Application.Quit.
say in the web. it's not going to have any effect. and we'll see that
and we'll list all the things that Application.Quit can't do
and where it doesn't quite work the way we expect. So.
let's go straight to the game and
jump in. So. we've got our Unity
Editor right here and we've got our game. and right now
I've got a Start Game. which I'm in right now. and some
empty games elsewhere. And what I want to do is.
for my Start Button. so when I click it
instead of logging something out to the Console. as it does... Now. let's take a look.
I press play. I open my Console.
I press Start. and we should see that
something gets logged out to the Console. and
that's all it does right now. Instead. of doing that. I want my Start Button
to take me to my next scene. And we already
have a LevelManager. that gets called.
whenever we actually
press the button. and the only thing it does right now is to
log something right. And we've got it
loading a request for game. and we set that.
The thing we want to do is to turn the
click that clicks on the Start Button.
instead of going to a logging to actually
do something. Well. how do we do that? Welll. we can just use the
Application.LoadLevel. So. the
Application.LoadLevel. you'll see it being auto completed.
It's actually right here. LoadLevel is a method.
and we can pass in the name of the level.
we want to load. So. by just adding this line.
this Application.LoadLevel new name. and give it
the name. that will then take our
Start Button. whenever we press it. and it will take us to
our Game Scene. So. let's take a look at that in action.
I jump back into Unity. I press Play.
and then. if I click Start
LoadLevel Game -1 could not
be loaded. because it has not been added to the Build Settings.
I don't know whether you can see that through the Play Tint. so let me pause the game.
You can see this big bright red arrow with a
exclamation mark. Something went wrong! So. what went wrong?
Well. what's actually going on is we started to play a game
and we tried to LoadLevel but it wasn't prepared. We
need to tell Unity. these are the levels that you prepare
and these are the levels that you should be ready to jump to. Right click doesn't
know. So. how do we do that? Well. that's in our Build Settings.
So. we can go File. Build Settings. or we can
use the shortcut shown in the menu. So. if we go to the File
Menu and go Build Settings. we'll have this window pop-up and open.
And we can see a bunch of options in the Platform.
you can see all the builds of Unity. everything from Windows
Phone to the web. And really we don't really care about
this right now. we're going to stick with the PC. Mac. and Linux
Standalone Build. which is what we're currently on. but what we can
notice is that the Scenes in Build list
is actually completely empty. So. you can see the scene here.
the scenes in Build. That's empty and that's a problem.
Basically. what we're saying here is. no scenes should be put together
when you build a game. which is not what we mean. So.
how do we add scenes in Build? Well. we go to our projects. we
select the scenes. and I'm going to select all of them at once.
and then. I can drag my scenes into
my scene list. And the order matters
here. because the order is actually relevant. The first
one in the order will be the first one to be run. So.
when we've got an order. right now. we can then select
the Start Scene. for example. Click it.
and then. we can drag it to the top. And I'm just
moving stuff around until the Start Scene is at the top.
Now. in any build I make. the Start Scene will be the
first to be loaded. and then. my Start Scene will continue
as normal. So. now I've got this; I don't need to build. I don't need to
buld and run. I can just close this window. once I've created
my scene list. and then press play again.
And when I click Start. we should see that we now jump to a different
scene. And obviously. this is an empty scene. there's not distinguishing
feature between my Game. Lose. and Win Scene.
Right now. the only scene that has anything in it is the Start Scene.
We can see the Start Button has actually done its job to
jump us to another scene. So.
awesome! It is now your turn!
What I want you to do is... Now. we can jump to the Start Scene.
We are not going to worry about Quit right now. but what I want
you to do is. create a button
to return to the Start Scene. from the Game Scene.
Now. we can jump from the Start Scene. to the Game Scene. I want
us to be able to jump backwards. from the Game to the Start Scene.
and I want you to create a new button. that's going to do that for us.
So. use what you've learned already. use the
code that's already there. You don't need to rewrite the LevelManager.
you don't need to rewrite the LevelManager Object. or the Level
Manager Script. You can just use Control
C or Command C to copy them. and then.
paste them in the new scene. So. you'll need to grab the existing
LevelManager. and copy that across to your
new scene. And then. also create a new button
in your new scene. that takes us back. and that's just going to be a little
little Debug Button. as an exercise for us. so we can jump
back and forth between those two scenes. So. I'll see you very soon.
[Temporary Silence]
So. how did it go? Did you manage to get a button that jumps back from
the Game Scene to the Start scene? Let's see
how we would do that. So. I'm now in my
Unity Editor. and I've got my Start
scene here. What I want to copy is my LevelManager
and my Start Button. So. I will not worry about the Start Button too much for
now. What I'm going to do is I'm just going to grab the LevelManager.
copy it. and then open my Game scene.
and then paste it in. So. I click again on the Hierarchy.
paste it in. and I can see the LevelManager turning up in my
Hierarchy. in the Game scene. as well.
Now. I need a button. I need a button in my scene right now. So. how do
I do that? Well. I can either do a
create a new button. by going Game Object.
UI. and then. create a text. and then to all the
button addition and stuff like that again. or
I can cheat again. I copy my button across. So. I'm going
to save my game. jump back into my Start Scene.
grab my button and my
Event System. because remember. we need an Event System.
and my Canvas. Copy them across
to my Game Scene
and paste them in. Here we go. now
I've got a Canvas and I've got all sorts of stuff in there. The only thing I
actually want is one of the buttons. I'm going to remove everything
else. delete them.
and use my Quit Button. rename it to
Back Button.
And change the text
and then. go
to my handler. and now it's missing. because we've
copied them separately. So. I'm going to grab my LevelManager
and put it
in my Back Button. So. I get my LevelManager. drag it
into my On Click () Handler. for my Back Button. if
it lets me. Here we go! And then. select the
right function. which is LevelManager. LoadLevel.
and this time instead of loading Game. I'm obviously going to
be loading a diferent one. which is Start. So. now if I
press the game. I go back to my Start scene. Don't forget
to save your changes to the Game scene.
I press play. and then I click on Start.
I've got my Game scene right here. and then. I press back and
I'm back on my Start scene. And that's kind of what we were expecting.
how to go back and forth. using buttons and Load
Level. So. that's awesome! What's the next thing to do? Well. the next
thing to do is to get Quit to work and look at
a bit more about how Quit works and what we can do with Quit.
So. it's pretty simple. in terms of the code. Quit
is just another application function. and we can use Application
.Quit
and that will do exactly what we expect it to
generally. So. we've got an Application.Quit();
We can save and then. we can jump back
and try it out in our Editor. and we'll see what the effect
is. So. now you press Quit.
I've got the request coming up. you can see it in the Console.
however my application doesn't pause.
Why is that? Well. we've just hit the first limitation of our
Application.Quit. Application.Quit works
great. if you're making a build. Application
.Quit works great. if you're making a build for the PC
and the consoles.
however it is limited on the Web Build
and the Debug
Build. So. this is the debug build. this is kind of the debug in Editor
Build. and Quit will have no effect. in that case. It will
also have no effect if you're in the web. If you create a web
plugin and
you use the web plugin. then you're web build will have no
Application.Quit. Clicking it will have no effect. It's
also really important to understand that while it will have an effect on
mobile phone platforms. so if you have iOS.
Android. or Windows. most of those platforms.
form the guidelines for app
developers. means that you shouldn't quit your application youself. You should
have the player and the operating system
manage the application state. in which case Application.Quit
is actually a bad pattern to fall into.
It's a bad practice. and if you try and submit an
application to the app store. with a Quit Button. it'll actaully
be rejected. for example. on the iOS app store.
So. those are the little limitations of Application.Quit.
but now. we at least we can try and build a new
build. So. we go into File. Build.
Build Settings. grab the right one. click
Build and Run. I'll just select
a random location. I don't really care where it's loaded. I just want to
show you the example. And I'm
going to choose a random
graphics size. and there we go. we've got our app.
Powered by Unity. etc.. etc.
And we should see our first scene. "Welcome to Number Wizard Puny Human!".
And if I press Quit here. it will actually take
me back to my Desktop. as we expect
it to. which is great! So. that's just to show you the Application.Quit
Button. working as you'd expect it to.
So. what's next? Well.
let's take a review of a little bit of how we load the scene.
how all this is wired together. So. if you remember. we have
two objects. so those are game level objects. Those are
the Start Button and the LevelManager; those are the actual things we're moving
around with. and we can see them in the Editor in
our Start Scene. For example. this is a LevelManager Object
and this is the Start Button Object. right here
in the Hierarchy. Now. if we do
go into those objects. they each have
a component. The Start Button has a Button Componeent and the LevelManager
has a LevelManager Componenet. And we can also see this in our
Editor. if we jump back. We can see that when we have the Level
Manager selected. the components all showed in the
Inspector. So. we've got a Transform Component. which is default for all objects.
and then. we have a LevelManager Script Component and that's the
component we're talking about. Similarly. the Start Button has a
Button Component. and
inside of its Inspector. We can look at the Inspector here. it has
several components. including a Transform. a Canvas
Renderer. a Text. etc.. and a Button Script
Component. So. those are the components.
If we jump back. what the Start Button's
Component also has an On Click () Event Handler.
and that's represented in the Unity Editor.
At the bottom there's...
at the bottom of the Button Component. there's an On Click ()
list. and we can change that and add things to it. So. right now we have
a reference to the LevelManager Object. which is this
guy here. in the Hierarchy. and we
also have a reference to a function
we want to call. So. tha's the next thing we want to think of.
is there is now a function in LevelManager.
And what happens is. the On Click Event Handler has
the reference to that function. and whenever the button is clicked
it actually calls it. So. that's actually what's happening in the
game and how things are wired together. in our scene.
OK awesome! I hope it's been useful.
I hope you can see how to wire things together now. and
how to create buttons that quit and change scenes.
And you also know a little bit more about the limitations
of the quit function. in Appliation.Quit.
Hope you've enjoyed this video. and I will see you in another one!
Bye for now!