Hello. and welcome back!
In this video. we're going to be talking about how to use a Game Design
Document and what a Game Design Document is.
So. let's take a look at what a Game Design Document is.
It's a tool that we use to communicate between members of our team. so it's
a communication aid. It's for example. when you're going to
be talking to a team member. you're going to be pulling out
a napkin and a big felt tip pen and drawing a
diagram on that napkin. to just show him something you're talking about.
Well. that diagram probably ought to go in the Game
Design Document. Anything that's used to illustrate the point to
help your communication. say refer back to that diagram.
it's this element in that diagram. that probably belongs in your
GDD. So. that's every member of your team. right.
So. that could be the artists. that could be the developers. and the designers.
and everybody else who communicates. Let's say your marketing strategies.
etc.. etc. And the idea is. you
are collecting this data. so you can talk about common
reference points. Every game. every major game. every
game that's significantly large.
will have its own glossary. It will have
its own set of words. that have meanings specific to
this project. and that really ought to be in the
GDD. for example. It's also a place to record your decisions
you're going to be making. about what's in and what's out of
your game. And what's out is actually really important. it's really
easy to define what's in and then. have the scope
creep up on you. while you're developing. It's really useful.
at the beginning. when you decide we're not going to be doing this.
to write it down and set it in stone. so that nobody gets tempted afterwards.
to add a feature that doesn't really add value
to your game. or maybe you want to keep something for
another game or for a downloadable content pack. whatever
you want to do. That's why you record your decisions
in the GDD. And that's both before
you actually start development and also during your development.
The GDD is actually a living
document. it's something that's going to be changed and modified
according to what happens. according to the new things you learn. so
let's say you want to create a new diagram
to explain the new system you've built.
of the code so that the designer can use it. Well. that's
halfway through development. and that also goes in your GDD.
And it's not a plan. it's not something you use to plan your work. it's something you use
to communicate and to record your decisions. and it's really useful
even if you're on your own and your not talking to someone else. because
a lot of the time. you're communicating to your future self.
You want to be able to make a decision
or think of a system and say. hey future self. me
in six months time is actually another person. and that's really useful
to have a place to record these kind of things. you're thinking.
final decisions. so that you can use it in the future.
So. how are we going to be using a GDD. in this game?
Well. let's take a look at our GDD
for Number Wizard UI.
So. we've got it kept. it's very simple right. it's a very very
simple GDD. We've got it kept in Google Docs and
that's because we want to be able to share it and
work on it separately. and when we're working remotely
when we're making games for this course. And the idea
is we've got this simple flow diagram. which shows how the scenes
are hanged together and how they communicate and how
the player goes through scenes. as well as some
sample mock-up scenes. which we have underneath.
And those are pretty simple. you can see it's only two pages. there's
three pages rather. but there's very little in there and that's
because Number Wizard UI is a really simple game. so it doesn't need all that
much stuff. We could add a little bit about the rules of Number Wizard.
but really. the rules for Number Wizard are actually encoded already.
in the previous GDD we made for
Number Wizard Console. So. we don't really need to worry too
much about that. because those are pretty well defined. What we do want to
worry about. however. is this scene diagram. So. this
Scene Diagram shows all the four scenes of the game
and they also show how the player moves through them. And that's a
really useful diagram to have. if you have many scenes. so you understand what
kind of transition you should be expecting. And for
example right now. we have a Start Menu to Game transition. when you click
Start. but we also have a game to Start Menu transition.
and we can see. just by looking at this diagram. that we're not going
to need this transition. for very long. We're not going to be...
It's only a temporary transition. to get used to making them.
But really the game ought to exit to a Win Screen
or a lose screen. and then. those ought to go to
Start Menu. start again. So cool! So. what
does that mean for us and our game right now? Well. if we take a look
at our Unity Editor. we can see that we have
four scenes. however. they're not wired together yet. We only have
the Start Scene and the Game Scene. and they're not
even wired correctly. So. what's the purpose of this video? It's to
use the GDD to refer back to the GDD to get
those things wired up. in the way the final game will
eventually be wired up. So that way. when we get to
grab the code from out previous Number Wizard game. we can simply
slot it into our Game Scene. and everything else will already be done.
Without further adieu. let us get started.
The first thing I want to do is look at the Win Scene
and create the Win Scene.
as we would expect it to. So. I'm going to go into my
Start Scene alright. and I'm going to copy everything.
and go into my Win Scene.
delete the camera I already have. and then.
paste all of the things I've already got from
my Start Scene. I'm not going to need all of them. I'm just
going to change the text on a few. I'm only going to need one button.
and I'm going to remove the
Quit Button. change where the
Start Button is going to go to the Start
Scene. change the Text on a few things.
For example. I want to change this guy to
say. start again
or return to Start Menu or
"Return to Start".
And  you'll notice that I'm going to have to change a few things. For example.
here the size of the box isn't
big enough. Note I'm
using Shift and rather Alt to
scale from the center. Here we go! I don't need a
subtitle here. and we are in our Win Scene.
so let me delete this guy. And for my title.
I'm just going to go "Congratulations. you have defeated
me. but I will rise again". So. this is
the Win Scene. so this is the Congratulatory Scene for the player.
[Hums] And I
need to spell this right. Here we go! "Congratulations.
you have defeated me
but I
will rise again".
[Rock Guitar Music Plays]
Alright!
Cool! So. now I've got this
new scene. that goes back to Start. We can
try it out. press play. click.
and it does go back to the Start. And
now. what's going to happen next
is your going to do the rest of the scenes.
You're going to use this GDD to create a
bunch of buttons. on the Lose Screen.
the Game Screen. to create the rest of the game. So
that way I want the transitions to
look like those on this diagram. rather than to be
the ones they have already. So. we've created this arrow.
between the Win Screen and the Start Menu. We've also created
an arrow between the Start Menu and the Game Scene.
It's now up to you to create all the other arrows using
buttons. in your game. So. I'll see you when you're done all
that and we will carry on and see what we
can make. out of this game. See you soon.
OK. have you
got a button. that does everything like that? Have we got all the buttons
sorted? Well. let's take a look at what I would do.
Now. we're back in Unity. we've got this Win
Scene sorted. we save it.
we jump into our Lose Scene.
and we do pretty much the same thing. We
can just create another scene.
This is going to be pretty boring.
[Rock Guitar Music]
Right cool! Now. I've got a scene here!
I kind of like the look of this.
Now. to wire up with the right
direction. to wire it up to the right scene.
Instead of going to Game. I'm going to go back to Start.
[Typing Sound]
[Temporary Silence]
And we can do the same for the Game Scene. So now.
we've got this guy sorted. we've got the Lose
Scene sorted. Let's take a look at the Win. let's change the color of
this guy a little bit.
Looks good. that way we can very
easily distinguish the two scenes. and go
back to our Game Scene. So now. instead of back. I'm going to change that
to Lose and Succeed.
So. I'm going to
create a Lose Button. for now.
And I'm going
to clone this guy. for a Succeed Button.
[Temporary Silence]
Cool! So now. I just need
to wire those guys up. instead of back to the Start Menu. I want them to
go to the Win and Lose.
[Typing Sound]
And now. if I go back to my Start
Scene. saving everything as I go and press
the Play Button. we should see that the game hangs together
as you'd expect.
And that's exactly what we want. That's what we want out of this
video. is to get the flow of the game
going between all
the scenes. And you'll notice. I've really mocked the...
I've created a mock scene. really. it's a fake
scene. I'm not playing a game at all here. I'm just saying I'm losing
and I'm winning. and I'm creating the buttons here as a temporary
thing. to check that we can flow through the
entire Scene Diagram.
And everything is wired up as we'd expect it. So. right now there's no
game. I haven't added the game yet. and we'll do that in another video.
but I know now that I've got all those buttons to take
me from scene to scene. that it's all hanging together.
and that we can create a cohesive game. And then. when we'll add
the game mechanic in another video. And that's pretty much it for this video.
I hope you've enjoyed it. I hope you see the benefits of using a
Game Design Document. and how we can really really use
a Game Design Document. when we're developing. to help us draw
a rough outline of the game like I've just done here.
and to record all the decisions we're making. So cool!
I'll see you in another video! Bye for now!