Hello, and welcome
back! In this video, we're going to be importing our Number Wizard
code and turning our existing Number Wizard frame-
work into an actual Number Wizard game, because right now it has not behavior,
we can just move between scenes, and that's not sufficient to make a
game. So, we're going to add some code from our previous Number Wizard
game, and we're going to add some win and lose conditions. So,
let's get started. So, I'm
here in my Unity Editor, I'm on the Game Scene.
I've got the Game Scene selected. There's currently nothing but the
Lose and Win stuff and the Level Manager in there.
What I want to do is I want to add my code from my previous
game, so how do I do that. Well, let's take a look at
our Finder. We've got the Finder right here, and that's your
file browser, and I'm now browsing here in my
previous Number Wizard game. And you have a scripts directory,
and inside of there, you have a Number Wizard
script, in there. So, what I want to do is, I want to copy
this script across, into my new game, so I'm going to click
and drag it into my new game in
the Project Pane, at the bottom. And you should
see it come up in the Assets, and I've now got a Number Wizards
script, with an S, so I'm going to change that
S. It's annoying me a little bit, so I'm going to just
change it right now, take out the last S, and
now, it's called Number Wizard. Now, I'm going to
need to change the script, because if we take a look at the script right now
it's really the old code, and that's not going to
be good enough for this game, we need to change it to reflect what we have now.
Also, you'll notice that my Number Wizard script file
is NumberWizard and my class is NumberWizards, with an
S, and that cannot be done. You can't have the file
name and the class being different, so I'm going to change the class
to reflect the file name and save straight
away. So cool! So, this is our old code
and fundamentally, what we want to do is change the
keyboard input we have, in the updates right here, so whenever
we press an Up, Down, and Return key, instead of doing
that, we want to change that to button presses, which means we need
to publicly expose some methods, we're
going to be doing that now, to allow buttons
to call the methods, whenever they're clicked. So, that's what we're going
to do, and really the ones we're going to start with, we want
the Up, so guess higher guess lower
are going to be our first two methods and they're going to replace the Up
and Down Arrow Keys. So, let's get started. So firstly,
these methods should be public, because they're going to be
accessed outside of Number Wizard. So,
I'm going to have a public method. It's not going to return any value, so it's going
to be void, and then, it's going to be guess
Higher. So, that means that's the equivalent
of pressing the Up Arrow, so whatever this method is called, I want to
do exactly the same thing I did before, when I was pressing the Up Arrow.
So, I can just copy and paste this code, right
here, so I'm copying this code. I'm putting it and moving it into
my guess higher function.
I really no longer need this GetkeyDown,
I can get rid of that. I'm no longer driving my game
using keys. Now, feel free to keep it, if you want,
but if you're going to keep it, instead of having this
code duplicated in two places, make sure that this
is GuessHigher instead. So, you're going
to do GuessHigher.
[Laughs] I cannot
type today, so it's going to be GuessHigher ();
instead, and you'll notice that, that's actually equivalent code. There's
no difference here, except that we have packaged all
the things we do, whenever we guess higher, into a method that
we're calling. Now, I'm just going to remove it, because I don't need it, but feel free
to keep it in your code for debugging, if you want.
So, I'm going to do the same thing here, I'm going to take this out and move it
into a new function called, Guess
Lower. Whenever we press the Down Arrow, that's kind of what we're talking about
here. So, I'm going to go void, and that's public
void rather, so public void
GuessLower(){}
[Typing Sound]
Cool! So, now I can put the code in, and that will do exactly
the same thing as before, except now, it's packaged in a
tidy function instead. And I can remove that stuff
to. Cool! And finally it comes down
to the case of what do we do when
we win, when the player
successfully
or rather the computer successfully picks
a number. When the player actually looks at the computer,
finds an number that the player guessed,
what happens then? Well, that will
not be handled here. In fact, it will be handled by pressing the
Correct Button, so whenever we say correct, the button will then
then change the scene to the computer winning
and the player losing. So, that's what happens, so we don't need
to handle it in the Number Wizard anymore, because we're going to be handling it
with our scene flow instead, so we can remove
this stuff completely, because it's not going to be handled there
at all. That leaves our update function empty, and I don't
like empty functions, so it's going away. Bye update function!
And finally, we want to remove this
stuff we have, that's in strings. We don't need to print stuff
out to the Console anymore,  because it's all going to be very visual,
so we don't want to do that. So, let's take those things out,
to start with, and that will leave
kind of the outline
the bare bones of our Number Wizard game.
And what we'll need to do now is set
up the win and lose conditions. So, what are the win and lose
conditions and who's winning and who's losing? So, there are two players in this game.
There's the computer and there's the player, the human player,
and so the human player wins, if the computer cannot guess
the number after a certain number of
tries, and the computer player wins if he can guess
the human number, after
in a certain number of tries. So, we need the idea of a certain
number of tries, and I'm going to call this integer
max guesses. So, int
maxGuesses
Allowed, and I'm going to set that to
10 for now. That's
something you can tune, you can fine tune and pick yourself.
I'm just going to say 10 guesses is the maximum the computer is allowed to
do. So, how do we keep track of this? Well, whenever
we create a new guess, the computer
will have to reduce the number of
guesses, so we can do maxGuessesAllowed
is maxGuessesAllowed
-1 right. So, now we're reducing the
guesses allowed every time, and we need to handle whenever they
reach 0. So, we do if (maxGuesses
Alllowed less than or equal to
0, so whenever they reach 0 basically or
get underneath, then we want to do something like,
well we want to jump to the Win or the Lose Screen right.
That would be the Win Screen. The player
has now picked a number, that the computer
has not been able to guess in 10 tries, so that
would be the win screen, and to move between scenes
we can go Application
dot, and that's load level.
Not loadedLevel, be careful because those two functions
can sometimes clash in the AutoComplete;
loadLevel and we want to load the
Win Screen. Alright, that's the player winning
because he's picked a number that the computer could not guess in 10 tries.
And we save that, and that
could be, actually needs to be
a capital letter. That's LoadLevel with a capital L,
at the beginning. Cool! So, now we have a game
that lets us pick numbers, and whenever we
pick a number that the computer cannot guess in 10
tries, the human player wins, which is exactly what we want.
And that's going to be the way we move from the
Game Scene to our Win Screen. The way we move
our Game Scene to our Lose Screen, is going to be whanever we
press correct right. Whenever we say, yes computer, you have found
my number, well done! That's going to be whenever we move
to the Lose Screen, and that's going to be handled by
the button itself, not in the Number Wizard Script. So,
cool! Awesome! We have this Number Wizard Script! That's great,
we have a game! Now, how does it interact with the rest of the world?
Let's jump back into Unity and look at our
world. We have a script right here, but it's not even included in our
scene right now. So, the first thing we're going to do
is we're going to create a new empty object,
and that's just going to be empty object. And we're going to call this guy Number
Wizard. And that's
to keep track, keep hold of our script that's going to be doing the functionality
in there. So, we click the Number Wizard Script
and we're going to add it into our Number Wizard
Object, in the Inspector, by clicking and dragging
the script into the object only Inspector.
Right, so now we have a script and it's attached to an object, so it's actually
going to run, because if it's not attached to an object it'll not run.
How do we get it to interact with the rest of the world? Well, right
now we have nothing on our scene to interact with, so let's
create something that the Number Wizard
Script can actually interact with. So, I'm going to
go into my Canvas, select my Canvas, go Game Object,
UI, and add a text object.
And this text object is going to be my guess, that's the thing that the
Number Wizard UI Script is going
to intereact with. Notice, I've just put it in UI
Mode, I've removed it from Normal Mode
to UI Mode, using the buttons on the top left.
And I'm going to change this text to be 500,
as a placeholder number, that's going to be my initial guess,
but that should be changed by the Number Wizard when we get to it.
And I'm going to change some styles, make it white
to pop out and also increase
the Font Size. Alright, I want a big guess!
Alright, big guess, I think that's about right.
Looks good to me. That will be good
enough. So, that's my guess, and let's make sure that
the name of this object reflects what it is.
We'll call it guess, press return, and now we have
a guess in our scene. So, how do we get the
Number Wizard code to change the guess? Well, we've already
done this. We did this in our very first
text adventure game, the one we
did just before this. So, the very first visual game we ever built, we
got that going, so let's do that again. So, we jump
into our Number Wizard code, we jump at the top,
and we'll create a public variable.
It is the text itself, so
public
Text. And you'll notice it doesn't come up in the Auto-Complete,
if you look down here. If I press
space, it'll automatically complete it to something else. Now,
that's weird! Why is it doing that? Well, that's because there are no
text objects or classes
defined in my code, right now.  Alright, text doesn't
exist, and that's because it doesn't belong to any of those
name spaces. Right now, we're importing two name spaces,
UnityEngine and System.Collections. For Text, we'll
need to import another one. So, we do using
UnityEngine.UI;
and now, our text will turn blue,
when we create it.
So cool! So now, we have a public Text text; and let's remember
what that means. We have a Text variablle
of type Text, so capital T is the type of the
variable and text is the name.
And I'm going to deliberately call it text,
because you need to be able to read this and understand
which bits are which, depending on the context in which they are.
So, I'm going to name these things the same, and in fact, it's
going to be named the same as something else.
So, to get you in the practice of understanding what these things
mean, based on how they're called and how they're invoked.
So right now, let's remember, remind ourselves what we have.
We have a variable of the NumberWizard class,
whose name is text and type is
Text with a capital T. Cool! So, that's the
text we're going to be representing, and whenever we change
the guess, whenever we do guess = (max + min) over
2, we're going to change the text itself.
So, that we can do by selecting our variable, right
here, so that's the variable in the NumberWizard Class, and changing
one of its attributes. Right, the variable has attributes,
and the attributes we're going to be changing is text.
Whoa, that's confusing right, text.text of type text! Ooh!
That's a bit weird, but this will actually take a
string. So basically, this represents the text
itself, that's stored in the object that you
see on the screen, with 500 on it, and that can be changed
by changing the text attribute of that object.
Now, notice I could have called this guy anything. I could have called it
foobar. Alright, if I called it foobar, then in that
case I would have done foobar.text. So,
this, I've got control of what this is called. This I don't,
this is actually the attribute of the Text
type, and you can check what those things are, by jumping to the
documentation in your browser. So, if you
use a shortcut or just do a search in the documentation,
you'll find this page here and you'll have the Text Object.
And if you click here, you'll find
that you'll see where it's coming from. As well, you'll see
the Namespace. The Namespace will actually be highlighted, so it's
showing you text comes from
UnityEngine.UI, so you'll not be abel to use Text
unless you use this Namespace, as well.
And in this description, you'll find it has
a variable called text,
which is the string value this text will display,
so by changing the
text, you can change what's actually showed on screen.
I hope that's not too confusing, it's kind of
deliberate. Try and get your head around it. I'm going to remove foobar
and pull it back to text. It's
so you can understand the different contexts, in which
the variables are used. So, this is the variable that's
referenced within the NumberWizard class. This is an attribute of
that variable, and this is the type of that variable.
Alright, so anyway, more
to the point, we want to change what the text
is playing to be the new guess, and we can do that by picking
the guess and turning it into a string.
And that's a method called on
the guess itself. So, we're going to do guess
.ToString(); that's going to create a string
with a number in it, and then, we're going to set this string to
be the text that we show on the screen. Oh OK!
I think that's pretty much all the most difficult bit of the code so far,
but don't worry too much about it and let's get
to wiring this up, in the scene itself. So now, we have this
public text variable. Let's jump into our scene.
And we should be able to click on our NumberWizard and
see that there is now a slot missing for our Text right
here. So now, if I click on my guess
and drag it into my
Text, now we will...
...now, we will reference the guess itself
and we'll be changing the guess Text. Cool!
So, what's missing now? Well, we're missing two things, well, three
things really. Three buttons, we need three additional buttons for
higher, lower, and correct.
Correct is always going to be going to the Lose Screen, so
I'm going to keep my Lose Button, and simply change
the Text to Correct.
That's going to be my Correct Button. Now, Win Screen
doesn't exist anymore. Let's do it,
change the pivot, the Pivot Point. I don't want
to do that. So, this little round circle,
I don't know whether you can see it, but the circle at
the center of my object. If I
select them in UI
Mode, you can see the circle, you can actually move it around. This is the
Pivot Point; this is where the scaling occurs from,
and I really want this to keep this in the middle. Just a little side note
to show you what I did wrong there. OK. So, back here, we
don't want a Win Button. This is
no longer a success button. I'm going to turn this into my Guess
Higher Button, so I'm going to name it
Guess Higher.
I'm going to say, Higher on the
Text, and instead of calling my LevelManager,
I'm going to change the object, of course,
to be my NumberWizard. So,
drag and drop my NumberWizard, and instead of calling no functions,
I'm going to call my NumberWizard Guess Higher () function,
and that takes no argument. Now, that's pretty simple and
we've got a Higher Button, that calls NumberWizard to guess higher.
We also want to duplicate this guy and create a
Guess Lower Button,
that lowers the guess right. Guess Lower
and this guy is going to have the text.
Lower, it's going to be
below the correct object the correct
element in our UI, and I'm also going to
be calling a different function. I'm going to call
GuessLower (). Not Send
Message (). Let's get this right, Guess
Lower (). Cool! So now, if I press play, what
happens? Let's take a look at what happens. If I press
Higher, I guess higher and higher and higher and higher and higher
and higher and higher and higher and higher
and correct. Awesome!
So now, we have a game! Right, we have a game
that works, and we had to do almost nothing.
So, let's take another look and try it from the beginning. Let's jump
into our start and see whether everything hangs
together. So, let's press play!
To start, now let's say I pick the number
645, so
645, 6
and
here we go, correct! And the computer tells
me I was "no match for his silicon brain!" and
no problem. Now, let's go back and click to try
again, and this time I'm going to change the number of
guesses allowed, to just five.
I'm just going to go back in my code and change that to 5,
and I'm also going to make this guy public, so we can change it from within
the Inspector. We don't want to jump back into the code, every time we want to
change the difficulty of the game. That seems a little bit silly, so
I'm going to make this public, so we can change it in the Inspector. I'm going to put a default of
of 5. I jump back in. In my game
what I'm testing here, I want to know
whether the computer can lose the game, so I'm going to press 1,
2, 3, 4, 5, and the
the computer indeed does lose the game, after a certain number of guesses.
So cool! Awesome!  So, we'll Return to Start,
and now we have a game! So, what's your
task now? Well, let's take a look at our Game Scene.
I think our Game Scene, if we take a look at the Game Preview,
looks pretty dull and horrible, so your task is to
spice it up. So, spice up the Game Scene, and I will see you
in another video, with a spiced up Game Scene, to
finish and polish this Number Wizard game. So, well done for
getting this far, and I'll see you in another video! Bye for now!