Hello. and
welcome back! In this video. we're going to be looking at finishing Number
Wizard. In particular. we're goingt to be using Random.
Range. to make sure that our guests feel a lot
more natural. when we play the game. So. let's get
started. So. I'm here in the game
and we have a game that starts. pretty simply. Let's
play through it to see what it looks like. I press
Start. I pick a number. if it's my number.
etc.. etc. The problem I've got right now. with this
game is that the guesses just don't look
natural. Every time we start a new game.
it's always the same guess. and the first couple
look very artificial. You know you've got to divide by 2.
so the numbers are pretty obvious
before you even start. really. So. you want to change that.
We want to change that. so that the numbers are not so obvious.
when you start the game. So. how are we going to do that? Well. let's take a
look at the Number Wizard code.
to see what we can do about that. So. in
the Number Wizard code. we've got a StartGame ().
and right now. the algorithm for the first guess
is. really take the max and min and
divide by 2. And what we want to do is change
from max + min over 2. to a different
guess. to a random guess within the
range. between max and min. And to do that. we're going to use
the Random.Range function.
And in fact. I'm not going to use the Random.Range function.
you are. You're going to have to go and look at the Random.Range function.
in the Unity API documentation. and I
want you to use it to pick a number
randomly between the minimum and the maximum
of our guess. our possible guesses.
So. pause the video now and give it a shot!
Using the API documentation. for Random
.Range. to see whether you can guess a random number instead of
picking the halfway point. I'll see you soon!
[Temporary Silence]
So. how did it go? Let's
take a look at how we would do that. Here we are in
our next guess function. and we are a
number here. in the halfway point. between
max and min. And I want to stop that happening. I want instead
to take a number. which is Random.
Range. and that's not going to be... It is going to
be Random.Range. and we're going to pick a number between the
minimum. which is going to be min
and the maximum. which is going to be max.
However. Random.Range.
if you look at the documentation carefully. it'll say it picks
between minimum inclusive and maximum exclusive.
when it picks it's first number. Now. we want to pick a
random number. that could include the maximum. so we're going to have to
do max + 1. Just like
we did here. when we were doing the algorithm manually.
but now. we're actually doing it in Random.Range. The
Random.Range needs to have a number
or the maximum to be one more than the one we
potentially want. so we're adding 1 to max.
and we no longer need to do it here. We no longer
need to do it here. So. we've got this going now. and
if we play the game now and jump in let's
get started. let's jump into our game.
press play. and
press Start. And now. it still starts at 500.
Now. the guesses are random. once I do that.
That's a much better guess. but it still starts at 500.
so what I want to do is. start my first guess
as soon as I launch. So. instead of
waiting and having a predefined guess. instead of using
guess = 500. what I want to do is
to go and run my next guess here.
That way. my first guess will be the first
thing I do. I'll guess first. change the number to
a random one. between 1 and a 1.000. and this is going to
be 1.001. because we want the player to be able to pick
1.000 because we already do
the max + 1 here. So. that's going to be between 1 and 1.000
and I run my next guess. So. I'm going to save that.
jump back into my game. and see what it looks like.
So. if I press Play now. press Start you'll
see there's already a number picked. and that's 888.
So. let's say I pick 324. So. I
324. not bad! That was pretty
quick. for the computer. It randomly gets 324 pretty quickly.
So now. we have a game that does not
look artificial anymore. We're not picking 500 every time
or 750. they look like pretty round
artificial numbers. Now. we're picking randomly. it
still works as we would expect it to.
So. that is great! We have now a game that looks
pretty normal. and we've also managed to. in one
shot. not only use Random.Range. but also
change the computer's guess at the start of the game. so that we show
the right value. when we start. So. we've got an
existing guess. So. here we are and that's it for
this lecture. it was pretty short and pretty simple. but now you've got
Random.Range. That's a pretty useful tool. to do lots of things.
including randomly selecting between
items in an array. For example. let's say you want to randomly spawn
an enemy in future games. you can use Random.Range
to pick a random index into that array and spawn that
enemy and lots of other things. So. that
is it. for this lecture. Congratulations on
finishing Number Wizard UI! You now have a Number
Wizard game. that reflects the very first game you created in
the Console. but now is visual and
you can share it with your friend on Game Bucket
or otherwise. So. that's it for now! I'll see you in another
lecture! Bye!