Hello and welcome back! In this video
we're going to look at how to change User Interface text
directly. using a script. So that's you changing the text
on our scene. using a script. And we've got our Number
Wizard game here. and the reason we want to do this
is. so that we can change the guess on our
game page to reflect what Number Wizard is doing. Right now.
we can play it through the Console but we're not seeing it in the scene. so you still need the Console
to play the game. So we're going to change that by getting this number we're
selecting. this number we're guessing. so say 121 to appear
in the scene itself next to the choices
we can make. So how are we going to do this? Well the first thing
we need to do is to get Number Wizard to change the text.
but Number Wizard doesn't know about the text. If we ever look at the script.
the Number Wizard script doesn't have a text element
in it at all. It doesn't talk about text or anything like that. so what we're going to do is
we're going to add one. We're going to add
a public
TEXT...
Not Texture but Text.
A public Text guessText.
So what. what this is saying is.
we have a field in our class that is a
text item. which we're going to call guessText.
And now it's coming up red. and the reason it's coming up red. and you can definitely see it if
you're say trying to build the project. it'll give you an error.
Because text is a new element that is being introduced with Unity
4.6. it's not a Text Mesh as before in 4.5. It's
a new type of object and it's only available
in the UnityEngine.UI
namespace. So how are we going to get that? Well to introduce a
new namespace into our program we go at the top of the program and
go using UnityEngine
.UI.
And you see it'll come up in the autocomplete. to show you that. in fact.
UI is one of the possible options you have. And when you do that and
try and build again or just leave it. you'll see immediately the text becomes
blue again. to show you that the text is now defined within
this code. So now we have this public Text object.
so how are we going to change that Text object? Well
we're going to change it by changing its
Text property. So the Text object has a Text property.
which we can change. So let's go. Where should we change
it? Well we should really change the guess whenever the guess is updated. whenever the
guesses change which is really the next guess method. So in the
next guess method. once we've finished our guess. we go
guessText and it'll give
you the field in the autocomplete. dot. and it'll
let you find text. And then. we can simply set
the text to whatever we want. and right now we'll set it to
the guess. which is a numerical value. dot
ToString() and this will convert the numerical value to a string.
So now we have the guessText. which represents the
User Interface text being set to the current guess we
have in our Number Wizard. Number Wizard also needs
to set the text. when it gets started. So in every new game.
we should definitely start with it setting the text. so let's
do that straight away in the StartGame () function. Let's do
guessText
.text is my guess ToString().
Here we go! So
now. if we pass in a Text object to our Number Wizard.
it'll update the Text object to reflect to the guess
that we're making. at any one time. So how would this
work in the Editor? How do we connect this public Text property
of the NumberWizard object in our Editor? Well let's take a look!
In the Editor. when we inspect the Number Wizard now.
you see that the script has another item in the Inspector.
So if you have a look in the Inspector. the Number Wizard script or the Number Wizard object
now has a new item called Guess Text. and it's telling you there is
no current item selected but it's of type (Text). So we simply need to
drag and drop a Text object into that
box. So we can grab our guess and drag
it into our box. and now you see. there's a (Text)
object in our box. it's Guess. It's called Guess.
it is a (Text) type. And now. if we play the game.
click play. the guess now appears!
And it should be reflected that whenever we change higher or lower. Let's
pick 725. Higher. Lower.
Higher. Higher. and it indeed does reflect the
current guess. and when you
press Equal it restarts. Now. the behavior when you
press Equal is not the current behavior we want. we want to change that. When you press Equal. you should be
moved to the next scene. to the winning scene the Win Screen.
but that's the topic of another video. Right now. you've managed.
so far. to get a Text object updated dynamically
via script in your scene. So well done. and I'll see
you in the next video!
=======
Hello and welcome back! In this video
we're going to look at how to change User Interface text
directly, using a script. So that's you changing the text
on our scene, using a script. And we've got our Number
Wizard game here, and the reason we want to do this
is, so that we can change the guess on our
game page to reflect what Number Wizard is doing. Right now,
we can play it through the Console but we're not seeing it in the scene, so you still need the Console
to play the game. So we're going to change that by getting this number we're
selecting, this number we're guessing, so say 121 to appear
in the scene itself next to the choices
we can make. So how are we going to do this? Well the first thing
we need to do is to get Number Wizard to change the text,
but Number Wizard doesn't know about the text. If we ever look at the script,
the Number Wizard script doesn't have a text element
in it at all. It doesn't talk about text or anything like that, so what we're going to do is
we're going to add one. We're going to add
a public
TEXT...
Not Texture but Text.
A public Text guessText.
So what, what this is saying is,
we have a field in our class that is a
text item, which we're going to call guessText.
And now it's coming up red, and the reason it's coming up red, and you can definitely see it if
you're say trying to build the project, it'll give you an error.
Because text is a new element that is being introduced with Unity
4.6, it's not a Text Mesh as before in 4.5. It's
a new type of object and it's only available
in the UnityEngine.UI
namespace. So how are we going to get that? Well to introduce a
new namespace into our program we go at the top of the program and
go using UnityEngine
.UI.
And you see it'll come up in the autocomplete, to show you that, in fact,
UI is one of the possible options you have. And when you do that and
try and build again or just leave it, you'll see immediately the text becomes
blue again, to show you that the text is now defined within
this code. So now we have this public Text object,
so how are we going to change that Text object? Well
we're going to change it by changing its
Text property. So the Text object has a Text property,
which we can change. So let's go. Where should we change
it? Well we should really change the guess whenever the guess is updated, whenever the
guesses change which is really the next guess method. So in the
next guess method, once we've finished our guess, we go
guessText and it'll give
you the field in the autocomplete, dot, and it'll
let you find text. And then, we can simply set
the text to whatever we want, and right now we'll set it to
the guess, which is a numerical value, dot
ToString() and this will convert the numerical value to a string.
So now we have the guessText, which represents the
User Interface text being set to the current guess we
have in our Number Wizard. Number Wizard also needs
to set the text, when it gets started. So in every new game,
we should definitely start with it setting the text, so let's
do that straight away in the StartGame () function. Let's do
guessText
.text is my guess ToString().
Here we go! So
now, if we pass in a Text object to our Number Wizard,
it'll update the Text object to reflect to the guess
that we're making, at any one time. So how would this
work in the Editor? How do we connect this public Text property
of the NumberWizard object in our Editor? Well let's take a look!
In the Editor, when we inspect the Number Wizard now,
you see that the script has another item in the Inspector.
So if you have a look in the Inspector, the Number Wizard script or the Number Wizard object
now has a new item called Guess Text, and it's telling you there is
no current item selected but it's of type (Text). So we simply need to
drag and drop a Text object into that
box. So we can grab our guess and drag
it into our box, and now you see, there's a (Text)
object in our box, it's Guess. It's called Guess,
it is a (Text) type. And now, if we play the game,
click play, the guess now appears!
And it should be reflected that whenever we change higher or lower. Let's
pick 725. Higher, Lower,
Higher, Higher, and it indeed does reflect the
current guess, and when you
press Equal it restarts. Now, the behavior when you
press Equal is not the current behavior we want, we want to change that. When you press Equal, you should be
moved to the next scene, to the winning scene the Win Screen,
but that's the topic of another video. Right now, you've managed,
so far, to get a Text object updated dynamically
via script in your scene. So well done, and I'll see
you in the next video!
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1:Unity/Section4/C10 - Changing Text Via Scripts.srt