Welcome I'm Sam! You may not have heard my voice before.
but I'm going to be in this lecture. showing you how to upgrade
the Number Wizard project to Unity 5. And we're going
to exploit this. to enable us to upload that as a Web GL
game. which means that you don't need to install plugins when
uploading it to Game Bucket. That means your family can try it without installing plugins! How great is that?!
So. let's see how we do that by jumping right in!
So. you'll notice that I have
these two versions of Unity again. Unity 4.7.1
and Unity 5.3.2. You can do this on
a PC or a Mac. just by renaming the folders before installing a new version of Unity.
that will ensure that you keep the old version rather than updating it in place.
So. we're going to open up Unity 5. and
use that to import our Number Wizard UI project.
So. I already have a bunch of projects open here. but I'm going to open a new
one. and I'm going to select the folder and hit Open.
Now. you'll notice that it pops up with this dialog box.
asking whether we want to upgrade with Unity's cleaver upgrading tool.
So. we're going to say yes to the Upgrade.
and let it go through its quick upgrade process.
It does some cleaver things. reaches into scripts and even changes the API's there.
in order to make your game fully compatible.
So. let's check that this works! We'll go into our Game scene
and then go and hit the play button.
OK. this does indeed seem to be working. Let me just increase
the size here. In fact. I'm just going to maximize this tab.
And here we go. we have
our UI and our buttons.
and as you can see. we can indeed
play the game as expected.
Now. I just want to show you one more thing. which is new in
Unity 5. and that's being able to export this to a Web
GL build. So. we're going to do a Build & Run.
and then. we're going to select. as
our platform. the WebGL platform.
And let's just hit Build.
and we're going to create a build directory here. So. I'm going to create a new
folder. Build like so.
And I'm going to call this Number
WizardUI. like so.
Hit save and then just let it run
through its build process. which will take about up to 5 minutes. depending
on how fast your machine is. but what this is doing is it's taking all of
the C#. turning it into an intermediate language.
In fact. the intermediate language is C++. and then. it's turning that intermediate
C++ into JavaScript. which is the language that can be run
in your web browser. And it uses all sorts of cool new
HTML 5 API's in your web browser. to allow you
to do 3D graphics without the need for any plugins.
So. you can run this in any browser that supports WebGL. Most modern browsers
do. unfortunately not on mobile. but a lot of modern
browsers on the desktop will. And it allows you to run these games
just by going to a webpage. without having to install the Unity Player plugin.
which can be a barrier for a lot of people who might want to try out your game.
So. this will allow you to share the game with your friends and family.
very very easily. just by uploading it to Game
Bucket and sharing on social media. and they won't have to install any plugins
in order to play your game. And you'll be able to show them
all the cool work you've been doing in this course!
As you can see. we're currently at the compiling
native code to JS. that means JavaScript.
and this is the last stage of the process. After
this is finished. you'll end up with a folder that we can zip and
upload to Game Bucket. So. once again it's
challenge time! We have a
challenge here to share your Web GL build with your
friends. So to do this. you're going to have to first check your game very
thoroughly. to make sure that the Number Wizard is working in exactly the same way you
want it to. Then. I'd like you to make a Web GL
build. just as I've showed you in this video with these instructions. And
finally. share this on Game Bucket and social
media. and I'm going to show you this after the break OK. So pause the video and have
a go!
OK. welcome back! Let's dive right back in and show you
how to share this on Game Bucket. if you have forgotten. a quick revision.
So. before the break I had left the build running. and now you can see that
this folder has popped up. my build folder containing my build.
So. all you have to do to upload this to Game Bucket is simply right-
click on this and compress it. On Windows it's a slightly different proceturre. but
what you want to do is create a .zip of this folder. And then.
we simply go over into our favorite web browser
and get our gamebucket.io opened.
and then. we simply want to upload. We can see
these are the simple instructions. We can upload. And we
will find the code that we're looking for.
[Sings] Da da da. da da da da da! That's my finding the code music!
And we select the .zip and hit open. It couldn't be
any more simple than that. We wait for that to upload and do the various
processing that needs to happen. and boom. you get a URL and a
page that looks exactly like this. and it will load.
if maybe a little bit slowly at first. It'll load into your game.
which you should be able to play in a web browser. There we go!
We have Number Wizard. and we can click Start. we can do Higher or Lower. etc.
And it all works as it does in your editor. but the difference
is this is happening without a plugin. You can tell because I'm in Chrome and Chrome doesn't have a
Unity Player plugin. Perfect! We'll see you
in the next video!