So hi! Welcome to the
end of Number Wizard UI and congratulations for getting here! Well.
well done on completing the Number Wizard. and
let's recap on what you've learned this section alright.
because you've learned quite a bit. So to start off with. you've created your
first menus. your first scenes. You've actually learned
about how to load scenes via your scripts.
You've also started learning about the User Interface.
creating your own buttons. creating your own text. You've dug into
understanding the principles behind the User Interface. how
the Canvas and the Event System and the actual items relate
to each other. so lots and lots of learning. And you've
actually really built a really valuable asset. You're Menu System now is
actually something we're going to take on and develop of the course of the.
of the course. And in the next video.
we'll be reusing it and expanding it to do something
else. So. well done for getting this far. and
hope you've enjoyed it. Yeah. and also. you've done a load of dragging objects
into the Inspector. so you've been publicly exposing
things and then dragging into the Inspector. That's one
of two ways that you can find one GameObject from
another. The other is to do it directly within code. We've chosen
here to do it through the Inspector. Sometimes it make sense to do it there. sometimes
it makes sense to do it in code. Now. remember the challenge structure here.
Remember that if you thought that you could do this on your own.
I hope you finished it and that you've just used this video.
at the end. to check that it's done and that you've complied with the Game Design Document.
Remember that you need to be doing the mini challenges! That's super
important. that's really where you're going to learn! And there's lots of
things actually you can do now. with this. Well. you have a Menu System.
let's take it further. do something else with it. You've got a really
simple game. so make a more complex game. Make a logic game.
make a logic puzzle. for example. or a series
about a game that asks Sphinx
riddles. asks riddles and asks for an answer to a given riddle.
You could build that. and you could also extend your Menu System
to make it more exciting. make it more colorful.
Add images. trying that as a mini challenge. add images to your
menu. a background image or something like that.
Absolutely cool! What else? Game Design Document!
For the first time. the Game Design Document hopefully was useful here.
We started to get just complicated enough that. when I was coding
it. I felt I needed to draw a little picture. So. that's the idea with the
Game Design Document. I want you to start thinking away from it
being something we give that you follow and more towards the
idea that it's something you create for yourself. while you're making
the game. Starting with just an outline and some sketches.
as to what the idea is. And then. as you go. when you get to a
bit you think. well this is a bit complex how am I going to do it? That's
when you draw yourself a sketch in the Game Design Document.
That's the purpose of that. It's a support. it's a live document
to support you and help you. as a game developer. to build the product you
really want. so yeah. Absolutely! And that's it really.
Again. if you have any technical issues ask against the actual lecture.
on Udemy in the discussions. and we'll be sure to answer.
Or you'll find that one of your fellow students may have answered before
we do. And please. you are a fellow student. so if you
see somebody asking a question you know the answer to. just dive
in and help them. It really helps us and it really helps you create
a sense of community and support. So. well done
and I'll see you in the next section! See you soon!