Welcome! In this video
we are going to be creating a rough plan for this game, coming up, this
game that we're going to call Go Home, and we'll going to dig into the details of
obviously, later on in this lecture. So, we'll
start off by defining the user's problem. The reason for this is, we really want to get in
the user's head when we're designing a game. We want to know what makes them tick? Why are we creating this
game? What problem are we solving for them? Then, we go
on to brain storm the core of the Game Design Document, the concept, rules, and
requirements. We'll get into details of what each of these is in a little
bit. And then, we're going to document possible future ideas, because we
don't want to have the scope creep too far on us, we want to know what
things we're going to do in the future, but not now, so it's a no list.
So, let's start off with the problem.
A user might be bored. So, this is a very common
problem that games solve, they solve boredom, or they
I might want to challenge myself. You want to get better, you want
to constantly improve and see how
far you can get in a game. Or you might want to beat your friends, you might
want to play against your friends and see who can get the best score. So, that's the reason that we have
scores in games, is we want to beat our friends.
How about the concept? So, this game is called Go Home,
and basically, you are lost and trying to find your way home.
All you know is your distance from home, so your completely
blind in a world presumably completely mired by fog, but somehow,
you've got a beacon that is telling you, you are so many meters away from home
and you've got to find your way back to home, using this
beacon device. Now, how does that work?
What are the rules? Well you can move up, down, left, and right, those
are your interactions with the game. And your movement is a,
by a fixed distance, so you can hop say 1 meter up or
1 meter down or 1 meter left or 1 meter right. And then, after
each turn your distance from home is displayed. We're going to be using something called a console
but you'll see that in a minute. And when you win,
you win when you get home, obvious, the name of the game!
And the score is how many turns it took you to get
home. So, that's the competitive element, that's the bit that allows you to compete with your friends. You can
say, look I'm able to do it in so many fewer turns than you!
I'm much better! ect. And so, it's fulfilled somebodies need for
competition! Now, this is a
challenge slide. This you can see from the pause button and the
green. Basically it means that I want you to soon pause the video and
have a go at something yourself. So, I want you to have a
go at writing the requirements. Now, let me give you an inkling of what this actually
means. What kind of assets will we need? And so we're talking about
requirements. When we build this game, what are we going to need to have that we can't
produce ourselves. So for example, do we need any 3D assets, 2D assets,
anything like that? Do we need any sound effects? Will our
game require some sound effects? Do we need some artwork to make
the game look pretty, perhaps some level load screens, things like that?
And what featurs will you be leaving out? What will you
need for a future version of the game or just include them at all, as your no
list. So I konw you have never done this before and it might be a bit new
and novel but it doesn't matter. You don't have to worry about getting it wrong, there is no
right answer. I'd just like you to brainstorm your requirements and
brainstorm your no list, and then, share those
requirements in the discussions. So do that, pause the video, and share in the
discussions before coming back and continuing with the video.
OK welcome back! I hope you've all paused and had
a go! It's really important to have a go, even if you're not completely sure it will
really help, when you do go and look through at the solution to actually
have understood it. You know, I've tried it and yes that makes sense, it really helps
your learning a lot more. So what requirements
have I come up with? I'm keeping the scope very minimal and it's just going to be a
text based game, so the requirements for me are going to be an introduction
and story text. That is pretty much most of it. We
might need some ASCII artwork to make our
story look a little bit more pretty and less
left brained, and then, we might want some sounds.
Well, but in this case, I think we'll leave them out seeing it's a text based game,
so we'll say no sound effects for this game.
How about the future ideas, things that we won't implement right now? I'm not
going to be implementing a graphical interface, we'll leave that for future sections and we'll do things like
that then. And again, no sound effects. So that
is everything for this lecture. In the next lecture, we are going
to be getting started and having a go at
programming our first program.