...
Welcome! In this
lecture we are going to be covering. Well what is this
Unity interface all about? We're going to be looking at something called the Console,
what a scene is, which is this file here, and we're going to be creating our
first script in a language called C#. So let's dive right
in, but before I do that I just want to say, if you're an advanced programmer, you might find this section
a little bit slow. So if you do already know how to program,
skip on to the next section. You may want to even take that one at double speed, because that's bringing
us up to speed on Unity, and if you know some Unity, that might be a bit of repitition
for you, but revision's always good. So here we are doing some
beginner introductions to programming. Let's jump right in!
...
OK, so the first thing I want to do is go ahead and fire
up Unity. So I've got a shortcut here on the Desktop. You obviously
know where you have installed it, so I'll leave that up to you. And the first
thing you'll notice is that I'm using Unity 5.3. Make sure you're using
5.3. I don't care what comes after the dot, that shouldn't really matter.
Now the first thing we're going to have to do is, there's a bunch of projects here, but they're not
ones we're going to be working on. We are going to be working on a new project, so we hit the New button,
funnily enough. Now you may be asked to log into Unity.
You may need to create an account in order to do that, so do just
go ahead and do that. Now, first thing's first, I'm going to select a new location
for this to be saved. So I'm going to go to Documents...
No I'm not, I'm going to go to Documents up here,
and then, I'm going to go into Courses, VR Course,
and obviously you stick it wherever you want to,
because I'm not going to force you to do anything. And then,
here I'm going to give the project a name. In this case, I'm going to call it 02, which is the
number of the section GoHome, because that is the name of the section, funnily enough.
OK, and I'm going to make this a 3D
asset and Create the Project. So
you've got options of 3D and 2D in Unity, but for this
whole course we are going to be sticking with 3D,
so just go ahead and do that. And bam, we have here the
Unity interface, and I want to take you on a quick whistle stop
tour through everything that is in here. So what does this
all mean? So the first thing, if you don't see something that looks like this, the first thing
we might want to do is do a quick reset of the layout. Because the
layout is completely customizable, what you can do is you can grab tabs, pull them out
so they float, or you can like drop them into other places. You
can split tabs and you can really generally make a whole mess, so I really
advise you to give this a go. Have a go at messing around and you can even
add more tabs from this Window menu. But once you've done that
messing around you want to know how to get back to normal, so the way we do that is, we click on this Layout menu
at the top-right and then select the Default. And bang
we have our Default layout! So now everyone should be on the Default layout, no
matter what your previous state of having messed around with Unity has been.
So let me show you what there is in this Default layout, all the main
tabs and window areas. So let me draw your attention first off to
this top bar. This is quite useful, because it's obviously got the play button, which
now enables us to preview our game. There's not very much going on with our game,
at the moment, so that's a bit boring. We've also got some tools here, which we'll see
how they manipulate the Scene View a little bit later in our 3D sections, but
the Scene View is the principle of it, right here in the middle, which is our
3D scene, and you can move around it by right-clicking
or middle-clicking to pan around. But we won't be doing anything with
this in this section, because it's quite advanced to manipulate 3D objects. We are going to
be sticking with the Console. Now the Console is this little tab down here, and
it basically prints out text messages for us, so that's the
Console down here. And we will be doing a little game in
text down here, to start off with, and get us introduced and comfortable with programming,
before we move on, in the next section, to use actual 3D objects
in the scene. Now, another important element of the Unity
Editor is the Hierarchy, that's this lovely thing over
here on the left, and the Hierarchy lists all the
objects in the scene and currently there aren't very many. There's a Directional Light and a Main
Camera, and we are going to be adding one, later on, in order to do
some of our game logic but we don't need that just yet.
So this is the Hierarchy, and you notice when I select things, things change
over here in the Inspector, and the Inspector gives us the various properties
of these objects. And obviously, when we're selecting things, you can obviously see where
they are in the scene. OK, so we have covered the scene, the
Console, the Hierarchy, the Inspector, and this top bar over
here. Now one last thing is the Project View! What is this Project View? Well
it shows us all the files that our project consists of.
So there currently aren't any files this project consists of, and that's because we haven't
saved this scene. A scene is basically the building block of a Unity project,
essentially you would use them to do different levels, but basically, they capture
the state of this Hierarchy, the collection of objects in your
scene. So let's go ahead and create our first scene! The way we can do
this is by right-clicking in the project, going to Create,
and then, just heading on down to Scene
right here. Now I'll give our scene a name, I'm going to call it Main, and then,
let's make sure we have this scene open, because currently we have a scene named Untitled
opened and we can see that in the Title Bar. So double-click on Main,
and there you go, this is the Main scene! And it looks exactly the same, because the
Default scene in Unity always looks the same, it has a Main Camera and it has a Directional Light.
OK, so the subject of this lecture was not about
scenes, well not exclusively anyway. So what we're going to do, in this lecture is,
talk a little bit about scripts. What are scripts? Well scripts are very much like
scripts for an actor, ?in that they give you stage directions
or ways to manipulate the object in the scene
or just generally tell the computer steps to
do. So these steps could be like walk into the bathroom, turn on the
shower, stand under the shower, and take the soap. Now you have to
imagine though that this computer or this actor is very very dumb,
because it will follow these instructions to the letter. And what I mean
is, it will literally not even take off the clothes if it has to stand
under the shower, it has no conception of steps that you haven't
told it about, and even if there's like a punctuation error it will go completely
wrong and say I don't understand this, so it's very very pedantic
and we have to be very very careful about that. OK, so I've got
a little bit of a challenge for you, I'd like you to create a script
file. Now, you might be going, oh no I don't know how to
do that! Well let me tell you, it's very very simple. Use the Project pane, very
much like we created a scene, I'd like you to create a C#
script. What is C#? Well it's just one of the many languages the computer understands,
but you have to be consistent with which language you are choosing and C# is one of those
languages. And, in this case, it's a language which is built into
the Unity Game Engine. And I'd like you
to give it a sensible name, such as well... What are we going to be doing with
the script? We're going to be using it to print stuff to the Console, so give it a
name based on that! OK, so pause the video and have a go
at this little challenge!
OK welcome back! Here we are, I'm going to go and
create this script. So we can right-click, go to Create,
and I'm going to get this C# Script! Now I can rename this
script and I'm going to call it
ConsolePrinter.
It is a script responsible for printing to the Console.
Now what happens when we double-click this script, it's going to open in a program
called VisualStudio. So what is a script file, actually? Well a
script file really is just a text file, it just gives you
basically this text in here. And
this is the language that's understood by the computer and interpreted
to basically give the computer or, in this case, Unity some
instructions. So this VisualStudio, what is that?
Well basically, you could write just into text files, but VisualStudio
understands the language of it better and gives you hints and tips that just make you more productive,
and we'll see how that works in the next video. So congratulations
on creating your first script. In the next video, we are going to make it do
something! Let's see you there!