Welcome! In this lecture we are going to be looking at what
is going on in this Unity Editor, it would seem quite confusing
to somebody just looking at it for the first time. And we're also going to be using
this thing called the Console and being able to print
these messages using code, so we're going to actually start programming in
this lecture.
So the first thing we need to do is create a new
Unity project, so I'm going to fire up the Unity Editor.
And we want to create a New
Project, call it GoHome,
and you can put this in any location that makes sense for
you, and it doesn't matter whether it's 3D or 2D at this stage but we'll
keep it on 3D which is the default. So let's create that project
and see what Unity creates for us. It will
do a little bit of generating and different things, and when it's finished with that it
will pop up and look something like this. So
you can resize these different panes, as you can see I'm doing
here, just to give a different amount of space. And
very roughly what we have here is the 3D Viewport
in the middle, a Hierarchy to the left, which tells us what
objects are in this 3D view. We have an Inspector to
the right, we won't worry about what that is, and we have a couple of tabs down
here. We have a Project pane and a Console pane.
Now the one we're interested in is the Console, so let's click on the Console tab
and have a look at what we've got here. OK, so there's some
buttons here for clearing and doing other things with this Console,
but until there's some text on the Console, it's not very obvious what
this is actually for. So I'm going to leave that
for now, and we're going to have a look in the Hierarchy and in
our Project pane. So our Project pane is where all the files are stored,
and we need to start off by creating what Unity calls a scene. A
scene is a collection of these objects at the top here, and it
basically describes something like a level in our game, and in our case
we only have one level. So I'm going to right click in the Project pane,
in the Assets folder, so you can see here I've got the
Assets folder selected on the left and that's why I'm right clicking in the
right. Then, I go to Create and then I select Scene
down here. So I create a scene, and this scene is going to be
called Main. So you can see, I can create the scene and rename it instantly.
Now, if I double-click that, I can see,
up in the top window here, that I've created a scene called
Main.unity. That's what I'm editing at the moment. So the Unity Editor
only edits one scene at a time, and that is important to remember.
Now, in the Hierarchy we have a list of objects. We have a Camera and a
Directional Light, but none of this is actually what we want, so I'm just going to right click
both of these and just delete them. And we're going to want to introduce a
new object. So to do that, you've got two objects, you can right click the...
You can click on the Game Object menu at the top of the page, or you can right click
in the Hierarchy, go down to Create Empty. We want to
start with an empty object. And I'm just going to call this game
object, if you go over to the right there is the Inspector,
and at the top of the Inspector is the name, so you can just change its name. I'm
going to call it GoHomeGame, and
then just hit Enter to apply that rename. Now,
the reason we have to create a new object in our Hierarchy is that Unity can't
run scripts unless they're attached to a game, and we want
to create a script, we want to start programming. So how do we
create that first script of ours? Well again, in the Assets folder,
you can right click, and we're going to create a new Asset, which this time is going to
be a C# script. So let's right click, Create,
C# Script, that's the one I have selected here.
And I'm going to also call this one GoHomeGame.
Now, as I said, we need to attach
a script to a game object. How do we do that? Very simply,
we select the script in the Assets folder and we drag it
onto the game object in the Hierarchy, like so.
Now I can check that that's worked by selecting the game object in the Hierarchy
and then having a look in the Inspector. The Inspector tells us various properties about the
game object. We don't need to worry about Transform, but the important one is
below Transform, where it says Go Home (Script), Go Home Game
(Script). That tells us that the script has been attached to the game object and it
will be run, when we run our game. OK, so there's a
script here, but what does it contain? If we double click it,
on Windows this will open up in VisualStudio, on Mac it will open up
in MonoDevelop. And it's pretty much the same,
there will be some differences between the UI, but
you should be able to follow along in both cases.
OK, so this is VisualStudio and it's basically just for
editing our code. And what is our code? Well it is
things like this. We don't have to worry about what all of this
means right now, we are just going to be adding some code
into this bit underneath Start (), between these two brackets here.
You see these curly braces? We're going to be adding code only between these two
braces, for now. Now the code I want to add
is the following. I'll hit Tab,
so that makes this indented like so, and
I'm going to write code print, brackets,
and then, I'm going to print a message ("Hello world"),
because I'm traditional and that's what we always like to print in our first programs.
Now you can see there's a little red squiggly line, and if I hover
over it, it says that it expects a semicolon. OK,
so I will write that and then, I'll just save my file command
or Control S, depending which platform you're on. So there's no
red squiggly line, so there's nothing misspelled nothing wrong in terms of
the code here. Now what was it that we have just written here? It's a
bit interesting, we have written what is called a print statement
or a call to a print function. It's
very much like a function you'd have in math, like sign or co-sign,
but this function has the effect of writing stuff to the Console.
So that is the name of the function
print, and then, in brackets is what
we'd call the argument to our function, so it is the
thing that we want to print. And because it's text, we have to put
quotes around it, so the program can tell the difference between text and just
other parts of the program, the other names in the program like print,
for example. And then, in C# everything,
every line, has to end with a semicolon, which is why it was complaining earlier.
So that's what we have here. Now if we go back over
to Unity and if we hit our Play Button...
And we need to make sure it's not maximizing on
play, so I'm going to stop it again by hitting the Play Button again.
Now, if we hit play, it shouldn't maximize. That's
correct, it says the "Scene is missing a fullscreen camera". That is fine because we're only interested in the
output in the Console, so if we click on the Console there we go,
we have our message that we printed from our script!
So it's time for a quick challenge! I'd like you to write your own print
statement. I'd like you to introduce the user to the game, some text
basically saying, hello welcome to our game!
And then, I would like you to try something a little bit more difficult, which is how do you write
multiple lines into the Console? See if you can figure that out from what I've
told you, so far, and then, share a screenshot in the discussions,
that tells you basically, shows everyone
what you've been able to do, what you've been able to print out. Don't worry about sharing
something or a question, that's fine, that's what the discussions are there for.
So pause the video, go have a go at this!
OK
welcome back! I hope you've all managed to have a go! It doesn't matter if you've got it right,
we will be going through the solution right now.
So the first part of the challenge was to print a
welcome message. So I'm going to say
("Welcome,
something like that!
("Welcome to Go Home!"). And then, we want to print a second line, so
what we're going to do is copy this entire line and
add a new line, using the Return key, and printing
adding a second print, inside Start (). So print
and then, I'll put some different text on this line,
saying something along the lines of...
[Typing Sounds]
("A game
where you need to find your way home."). That sounds about right, I'm going to delete this
extra line, just for prettiness. And you'll notice it's
very similar, we've got two prints, and hopefully, that will
create two lines for us. So we have to pause the game, stop the game, in
fact,using,  by hitting the Play Button, and then, hit the play again
to start the game again. And as you can see, now we've have two lines. We've got "Welcome to
Go Home" and "A game where you need to find your way home".
Perfect, challenge completed! I look forward to seeing you in the next lecture!