...
Welcome to using variables! In this
lecture, we are going to be creating a location as a starting point.
We're also going to be using pseudocode, a method of basically
outlining our program, so that we can plan what we're going to do in this section and
figure out what we need to know in order to get there. And the first thing we're going to
need to know is variables, and that's what this lecture is all about! So let's dive right in!
...
So here we are again in front of our project and our
ConsolePrinter. So we know now how to print things to the Console but
that's hardly a game, it's hardly interactive. So let's take a step
back and have a little think about how we're going to make our game
do what we want it do do. So what I'm introducing you
to is the concept of pseudo code. So this is not code, because we don't
yet know how to write these things in code, but it is an outline of what we want
to do. It's an outline of that script that we're going to tell an actor to
perform. So what do we want to do as the first step?
Well we're basically going off the basis of the rules of our game
that we want to have a distance and that we move and then we get an updated distance,
and so on. So, for a start, we're going to set a starting
location. So this is where we begin and that
is going to be something that can change, so that not each game
is going to be the same. Then, we're going to calculate that
distance, that location from home, and print that
distance out to the Console, so that the player can
decide which direction they are going to move in.
Then, we're going to have to read the player's move. So the player is going to have to
have some way of telling the Unity interface or
our game, essentially, how they want to move. And then,
we update the location from home and repeat, so
once we've updated the location it will go back through, calculate the distance from home, and print the distance,
and then, the player repeats again until we win. And we'll talk about
the until we win later on. So what I
want to look at now is these first two bits. So far,
we've been able to print things to the console which are fixed. You know, we've
said, in our program, that we're going to print the welcome
to Go Home, but what we want to do
is create a possibility for us to
input things that are variable, such as the location and the distance.
So for that, we're going to introduce, funnily enough, a concept called
variables. Now what is a variable? It's very simple, a variable is very
much just like a box, in which you can put certain values.
So this box, for example, has the value 2
in it, and it also has a label, some number,
so that is the label of the box. So a quick
recap! We've got a box with a label, and inside it there is a
value. So that is what a variable is! The box with the label is the variable
and the value is a value. Now,
these boxes have different shapes, also known as types,
so these boxes will store different types of values.
You can't put a square peg in a round hole, so this value in here, this
one anInteger, this variable can only store things like
this number 2. aString can only store well
text items and you can see it's a different shape, and aFloat can only store
point numbers, so 2 point 0, for example.
So this is because the computer has to store all these things
in memory, and it needs to know what shape these values are
in order to allocate the right amount of space in memory.
So here's a little table to summarize these three
different types, that we will see. You've got integers, which
are used only for whole numbers, not fractional or
you know irrational numbers and they can be both positive and negative, and here
are some example values that you could put inside an integer box or an integer
variable. You have the value 0,  you have
-1, you have 143, so basically any
whole number. Then we have float numbers,
which are basically real numbers. If you don't know what the term real number
means, it basically means anything with a decimal point in it
and that can include rational and irrational numbers. Don't worry if you don't understand
these mathematical terms, basically anything with a decimal point.
And you can see that, in the value syntax there is a special little
f at the end, as well, to denote that it's a floating point, but otherwise, it's just
a number with a decimal point and again it can have a negative sign
in front of it. Then, finally we have the string, which I told you about
in the last lecture. A string is just a fancy name for text, so that
is what we can store in it, and we've seen how to make text values
in the previous lecture, with these double quotes around the text that
we want to store. So how does all of this translate into code?
Well I'm going to show you! Let's go to our ConsolePrinter
and try and print out a value from
a variable. So here it's telling me that I have inconsistent
line endings. You may well get this kind of error
and if you do, you simply need to select what kind of Line Ending you want.
If you're on Mac, you'd select Macintosh, if you're on Window, you'd select Windows, and
you hit Yes. Basically, this is about invisible characters that are
being used to show you line endings in your file but don't worry too much about that.
So how do we go about creating
a variable? Well, first off, like I said, variables require space
in memory, so we have to declare that we're going to use a variable for the
computer to set aside that amount of space. So the declaration of a variable,
we have to tell it the type, the shape of the box, and the name
of that box. So we start off with the type.
Integer is abbreviated to int, so I'm going to start off with the simplest type,
the whole numbers, and we will start with some
Number. And you can put a semicolon
at the end, to say we've finished declaring this variable.
Then, you can go on to assign to the
variable. Assign, what do I mean by that? Well I mean put a number in the box. So
someNumber = 1, for example.
And then, you can go on and print this just like you would
print a string with that print function, and
the brackets around the thing that you're going to print
and then the (someNumber) and remember your semicolon at the end.
Now because this is a variable directly,
you don't need to put quotes around it, because the quotes are simply used
when you're trying to create a string value. Here what it's saying is, get the value
out of the (someNumber) variable and print it. So
we can save that, head over into Unity, and
hit play, and go over to our Console and you'll see that it has indeed
printed out the number 1. Now if I changed some number
to a different value like 134
and go back and replay it,
you'll notice that that is what gets changed in the text, as well.
Now we could obviously do this with different types, too.
So now it's time for your challenge. I'd like you to declare and assign
variables. Declare a new variable of each type, that's int,
float, and string. Assign an initial value
and print the values out, and just
do a little experiment. I'd like to see, can you assign any value
of one type into a variable of another? And if not, what goes wrong?
And if so, which ones? Are there any specific combinations? So pause the video
and give this challenge a go!
OK welcome back! I wonder how you got on with that challenge, particularly the last
bit. A little bit tricky, a little bit challenging. So let's declare
some things. So I'm going to have, first off, my int
called, I'm going to rename it to anInteger.
Then, I'm going to create a float as well, which is just with the keyword
float for the type and then aFloat, like so.
And then, finally a string with aString.
So all these are declared! I'm going to set
an integer, I'm going to
set aFloat
to 0 this time, and
I'm going to set aString
to, well let's just go with "Hello".
Remember I'm always adding semicolons on
the end of any instructions, because our actor is done and doesn't know when the
instruction has finished, otherwise. Now we can go on and print these
all out. So I will print, first, the
anInteger. You see that VisualStudio's automatically giving me
suggestions, based on what I type. If I hit Enter, then it will automatically fill that out.
The same goes for print, it's always
suggesting, very very helpful of it. And
I'm going to also print (aString).
OK, let's go back into Unity and hit play!
And there we go, we've got the float printed
out and the "Hello"! You'll notice that, when it prints out the float, it doesn't bother with the decimal points,
because it doesn't think it needs to, but if  put something in these decimal
points and then play,
you notice it will bother with the decimal points and it will print everything.
OK, so that is with the correct
values aside. But what if I try and swap a few around? So, first off, let
me try and put a string into the floats and the
integers.
Just some random strings, it doesn't really matter what the contents
of the string is. And if we go and play, it'll say
oops, there's an error! Now, you may see these errors, when you mistype things,
it simply means, go back into VisualStudio and check out what you're done wrong. Now you
notice those squiggly lines under here, and if you hover over it, it gives you
the error: "Cannot implicitly convert type 'string' to float. So
that's very easy! Basically it's saying, you've given me a string value and this is aFloat
box and I can't fit a square peg in a round hole.
OK, so that makes more or less, you know, sense. What about integers, if I try
and put integer in all of these boxes?
OK, so the
only one it's complaining about is the string. It's saying that I can't convert an
int into a string. That's fair enough but funnily enough, it's not
complaining with the Float. Now the reason for that is because it can
fit aFloat in here. It's kind of like fitting a circle in a square
box, because it kind of does fit in, and you'll notice that
also if I do... But if I do it the other way around, so if I put a float in the
int, it's saying no I can't do that, because the
floats don't include... Sorry the other way around, the floats
include the integers, but the integers don't include the floats, so that's why we can
convert in this particular direction. Now, let's just set things back to how they should be,
and let's
make this a float value.
There we go, the first few digits of pie. And ah, you see I've
got a syntax error and if I look at it carefully, this error's actually
giving me a bit of a red herring to follow. But this first error says
"Newline in constant" and that's because I haven't got
this end of my string, so it's kind of including the
whole end of the line, include at the new line, so that's what was going wrong there.
So let's hit play and we will notice
that everything works just fine, and actually, if we hit
play, then we will notice that, indeed, it works find. So well
done! Congratulations, you have just been introduced to variables! And just to
summarize why we were doing all of that, it's in order
to be able to do locations and calculating distance from home. So now we can
actually go ahead and make this a location. We
can say, let's make it a float, because we could be like
half a meter away from home. So let's say float
location
and then set that location to
5.0
and let's add what is known as a comment here,
which just doesn't mean anything to the computer but it means something to us.
And we always add these to make a note to ourselves,
so "// Distance in meters".
Basically anything that comes after these
double slashes will be highlighted in green
by VisualStudio and is actually a comment, so it won't be picked up by
Unity at all. So I'm going to remove these print statements, which it's
complaining about, because those variables no longer exist, and
there we go, print out the location. And let's print
out some string before that saying, we're about to print the location.
...
And go back into Unity!
OK, so now it says
"Location", "5". So that makes sense, we have
done our first step of this pseudocode. We're going to have to figure out how to
calculate and print. Well we've done some printing as well, so we're going to have
to figure out how to calculate in the next lecture. See you there!