In this lecture, we are going to be looking at how you can respond to
key presses. Here I'm pressing down arrow keys and getting different log messages
coming up. We're also going to be looking at what on Earth this
Update () thing was about anyway, and we're going to be learning about
searching for the documentation, so that you can help yourselves.
Let's get stuck right in!
So this game is a little bit dull because the user really doesn't have
any way to interact with it. So what we want to be able to achieve
is that when we hold down an Arrow key, it essentially
moves our player around this invisible world.
So how do we do that? How do we get hold of user input in
Unity? Well I'm going to teach you to teach yourselves. I think we need
to go about Googling this, so let's do "get
keyboard input unity".
A search like that should start to bring up
the right sort of results, that's the kind of thing that we want. And if you look
here, you can read around a little bit, but I'm going to
jump straight to it. The one we want is Input.GetKeyDown, this thing here.
So I'm just going to open that up, and
the place to look is in the examples. OK, so
you can see that they have some code very similar to ours, and there's
even an Update (). We have an Update (), if you've seen here,
we've got an Update (), too. So, and in their Update (), what they're
doing is the following. OK, so
this gives us a baseline. This is another one in fact and,
in fact, I like this one more and I'll explain later why later on,
but for now, let's just go with this. Let's take this example,
I'm going to copy it, and I'm going to paste it,
just like they have, in the Update () method. Now
I've just called this an Update () method, I've not called it that before. So these
two things are called methods and they are,
they got names and they have curly braces, and the things inside them are what run
when the method is called. That's what we're seeing in this
bit here, it says "// Update is called once per frame".
And what it means by called is, that this code
runs once per frame, whereas here, this is used for initialization.
This is the Start () method, it's only run once at the beginning.
That's why we're only seeing these messages come out once.
But we want to check whether the key is down every frame,
so that's why it has to go in the Update () method, otherwise we'd only check
the first time, and we'd only print anything if the Spacebar
was down at the very start of the game but never after that,
so that's why we want to do it like this.
Now we don't want to do it on Space, we want to do an Arrow key, so we
want to do the Down Arrow. And you can see it's completing for me.
I want DownArrow, that's that one there, with capitals letters like
so. So if I save that and go
ahead and hit play again,
and have a look in the Console,
we'll see that there is nothing played. But I hit the DownArrow
...
...and we see that the "space key was pressed". OK,
so the message is wrong but the behavior is correct. When I hit
the Arrow key we get a new message, which is exactly what we're looking for.
So one more point to note, now I don't particularly
like how they have done this in their example. It's a little bit naughty, we'll explain
why later, but what you want to do is put braces around,
like you see here. So I've got if brace print
closed brace like this, and they're the curly sort, the ones
that you'll see above the square brackets,
just underneath the plus and minus signs on a standard keyboard,
a US or English keyboard, you'll find it there. So that's
what we want to end up with. And you can just take this as
wrote for now that, that is what we want, and
we can do that same thing for other keys, too. So I'm going to say
"down arrow was pressed"
like so, and we can do other keys, as I say.
Let me undo that, I did that wrong. So I'm just going to select these lines,
copy, and create a new line and paste it on
there. And so we can do an UpArrow as well.
Just to Up and UpArrow here,
too. Now, let's see whether Unity can tell the difference.
We're going to hit play!
"up arrow was pressed", "down arrow was pressed". Up arrow, down arrow,
and you can't see my keyboard but this is corresponding to exactly what I'm
pressing. And you can try it for yourself to see and make sure that I'm not lying.
So I have a challenge for you! I would like you to handle
the other keys, that means the Left and Right keys.
Use the code that you have already written, that's the hint you know. You've already
seen some pattern of how this works, and I'd like you to use that
pattern and try and adapt it to handle Left and Right Arrow keys.
Add new cases for the Left and Right Arrows. So that's what
I mean by handling the other keys. OK, so pause the video and have a go
at that now. OK welcome back!
I hope you have managed to have a go! I'm going to dive right in and show you how it works!
So this one is fairly easy if you have managed to spot the
pattern. All we have to do is copy this bit of code
and do it again. And we're going to do it twice, because we're going
to have two different keys. We're going to have the Left Arrow Key, so I'm going to replace Left Up Arrow
with LeftArrow, and I'm going to replace this UpArrow
with RightArrow. And then, I am
going to change it in the text too, left and right
like so. OK,
now if we go and play, we should be able to see
it all working accordingly and printing back the keys that we've pressed.
Left arrow, right arrow, up arrow, down arrow, etc.
And you can see, that is working exactly as I am pressing the keys,
and you'll have to try it yourself to check that I'm not lying. OK, so in the
next video, we are going to be getting a little bit more advanced with these things, the
if statements. So I look forward to seeing you there!