Welcome to another lecture! in this lecture we are going to be
talking about the structure of this if statement, and we
are going to be talking about how we can prevent a
double key pressing issue, by introducing a new statement, the else
if statement here. And we're going to be talking a little bit about
variables and how their scope works.
So far we've glossed over the syntax of the if statments,
and I want to go, in this lecture, into a little bit more detail about that
and what it's all about. So
let's break it down! The first thing is if, that is the keyword
that we are using, an if statement, and
then, we have this bracketed, what's called an expression,
because it returns a thing, it turns into a
value. So this returns a true or false value
for the if statement. So basically,
this is asking the question, if (Input
.GetKeyDown. So if the KeyDown is DownArrow,
and you can see here there's more brackets, that's just like print,
but we're passing in an argument and the argument is which key. So
which key is down? The DownArrow, and if it is down
then we execute the
thing in these parenthesis here. So the way
this execution flow works is, that the Update () is called
once per frame. Then, it says, is the DownArrow Key pressed?
If so, then print. And then, it asks
if up arrow pressed then print, etc. And
you'll notice we're using indentation to make this easier for the eye to
follow, so we know that this print statement belongs to
this if statement, because of these four spaces. Now
you don't have to use four spaces, in fact, it's best that you don't. If I
use four spaces, it would look the same, but I recommend you use a
Tab. It's much easier to use in VisualStudio, if you just
hit a Tab across like that. OK,
so we keep things indented to the levels,
so if I were to add another print statement here, it would be indented like so, and
the ID makes it really easy for us to do this. So VisualStudio or Xcode will make this
very easy for you.
So, but we don't want that line!
There is something I want to draw your attention to, that you may not have noticed
or you may have. So if I hit different arrows, I get different
logs that's all fine, but if I hit multiple arrows at
once, I get all those arrows at once. Now that's not the behavior
we want in our game, so if I hit
four arrows or some combination of them, they all come out.
So I'm getting the Left and the Right Arrow coming out at the same time. You can try that out
for yourself, to see what that feels like. Now the reason for this is because we're going
if this print that, if this then print that, which means that if I have the Up
Arrow and Down Arrow down at the same time, it's going to print both
messages. Now fortunately with if, there is a companion
to the if statement, called the else if statement,
and it basically works like this. You start off with an if and then
you say else if, if I can spell correctly; else
space if. You must have the space there, then this
condition, and we can do this all the way down, else if
else if. But remember, else must always follow
an if. And in fact, it can stand on it's own as well, but
we won't, we won't deal with that just now. So what this is saying is, if this,
arrow is down then print this, but don't then check anything else.
But if that isn't down, then go on to check the next line and
so on and so on. So let's see whether that has fixed our double-
pressing issue. If I hit play,
you'll notice that sometimes
it happens and sometimes it doesn't anymore, because
it's very hard to get things down on exactly the same frame, but if you do
then it will no longer be duplicated. So that's generally
what we do when we're talking about exclusive conditions,
that we don't want to all be true at the same time, so that is
why we're doing it like so.
So for ths lecture's challenge, I would like you to print the progress
message. Now, what do I mean by that? By the progress message I mean this,
print("After  "  steps, you are " so many " meters
away from home." That's what we're going to want to keep repeating to the user,
when they've made a move, so they know how many steps they've taken and how
far away from home they are. OK, so how are you going
to do this? Well, when a key is pressed, print the message. So we've
got some if statements already, use those, use those
as a basis to start from. Then, I'd like you to cut and paste,
from the Start() method, that progress message we already have. See
not really using more code or creating anything new, I just want you to
be reorganizing what we already have. Then, you need
to paste that code, possibly multiple times, into
the Update() method. And I'd like you to make sure you also
copy the variable declaration, that's quite important, or the code will
fail. You can try and do it without and then see how it fails and then put the
variable declarations in. That's a good way of checking yourself and making sure
that you know what's going on. Then, you will need
those at the top of the Update() method, so by that, I mean underneath the line
where it says Update squiggly bracket. Just under that is
where those variable declarations will need to go. OK, so pause the video
and have a go at doing this yourself!
OK welcome back! Now, it is my turn!
I hope you've all had a go, before watching my solution, because that's really
how you learn. OK, so this
is the code, as I said. I'm going to copy it and I am just going
to be pasting it into each of these different ifs. I'm just double
clicking to get the whole line selected, in fact, triple clicking
and then just pasting. OK,
now we can instantly... I'm just going to delete this original line.
You can instantly see an indication that something might be wrong, with these squiggly red lines.
If we mouse over them it says, "The name 'numberOfSteps' does not
exist in the current context". OK, so what we've got
going on here is that there are two contexts, one in the Update()
and one in Start(). In fact, it's a bit more defined than that
but we'll see. There's even, this if is a separate context, but it's a
context within this context. So if we put something in this context, it's
also in this context, and that's what we call a scope.
So in order for these to be in scope,
we can't have them here, we need to have them in here. So I am going to cut
them and just paste them in above, like I said,
just at the top of the Update() method. Now you can see
the squiggles have gone away, so I'm going to go back into Unity
and hit the play button, and hopefully we'll now be getting
a progress message, instead of key up and down.
There we go! Each time, these are all the different keys I'm hitting, but
I'm still getting the same progress message! Perfect! So
that's a challenge complete, and we are ready to move on to the next lecture!
See you there!