...
Welcome! In this lecture we are digging into a little bit of math, but
don't worry, it's not scary when you are doing it with the purpose of a game. The main
reason people are scared of math is because when they were taught it, they never really had an application,
so we're going to be revisiting it and giving you new confidence. Now, how are we going
to be doing this? Well we're going to be calculating the distance from home, so very simple. We're going to be doing
addition and subtraction. We're doing it with variables, so that's cool! The computer's doing it
for us, as basically a calculator, and furthermore, we're going to learn how
we can do addition with strings, which is a very interesting
thing which will allow us to put this distance on the same line, rather than
on two separate lines in the Unity Console. So without further ado, let's dive right in!
...
So far, we have a location and we're able to
print out that location to the Console. And not only
is that location a variable but well we can change
it whenever we like, and we know about the types of the variables. So how
are we doing on our pseudocode plan. So here's the
pseudocode plan! So far we have set a start location
and we can print that location,
but we're not actually printing the distance from home. In fact, we don't have a location
for home at all, so and then we're going to need to
calculate that distance from home. So let's first start off by creating a
float for a home. Now, one way I could do
this is saying float home
Location = let's say 2.1f,
just for a bit of fun. Now, notice that I've done
this all on one line, rather than splitting it across two
lines like here. Now that's perfectly valid and, in fact, generally I
would recommend doing this, because it's fewer lines of code and
it avoids some repetition, which just means that there's going to be fewer
typos and it's going to be easier for you to read when you come back to it. But I wanted to show you
that, actually, the declaration and the assignment are
two separate lines, really. They're two separate things that are happening in this one line, but
this is just an abbreviation for that and that's what you're going to see most often.
In fact, very rarely do you ever want to declare something without giving it a value,
because then, what value does it have and you don't know! So best practice,
always declare and assign on the same line, but just so you
know, they are two separate things going on there. So one is saying
save space for this shape of object, and the other is saying, put
this value in that object. But as you know, we often want to do the two
together, so we never have an empty box. So, now we
have a location and a home location. We need to calculate
a distance, so well, I guess a distance is going to be another
float, but what is it going to be? What are we going
to set it to? How do we do these kind of
calculations? We really want to find out what the difference between these two is.
So let's find out! So these are our
types again, and we can perform operations on these types. So
we could do a addition of two variables, anInteger and
anotherInteger, where they have values 2 and 3. And
you would get another value come out, a value of 5.
So you can do that! You can also do this between different types,
so you could have anInteger and then add it to aFloat. And
what would you get out? Well you'd get a float out! Now that makes sense because, as we know,
integers can be converted to floats, but floats can't be converted to integers
implicitly or easily, basically. So
how would be go about calculating this distance and printing
it out? Well that is a challenge that is up to you. I'd like you to calculate the distance
home. You need to calculate the distance and store it in another variable,
which we have already handily created here, called distance. And what
values can you mix in addition? So have a little think
about that. What are the other types of values we've seen? We can mix
integers and floats. Is there anything else that we can mix? And
can this make printing easier? That's a bit of a hint! So give this a go!
Pause the video and give it a stab!
OK welcome back! So here we are, we have
our distance, and we know that
we can do addition. What does that look like? Well it's as simple as...
I kind of left you to try and guess the syntax here, rather than show you,
because I wanted to show you how simple it is. This is the addition
Location plus homeLocation, and we could
actually print out the distance here, rather than Location. Call it Distance.
Let's go over to Unity and hit
play! I've got 7.1, but
obviously that's not correct! I've done an addition here, rather than a
subtraction, which is what I actually wanted to do. So what I want to do is say this is
our homeLocation, this is location. So we need to say,
what's our distance home? Well it is going to be, actually, the location
- the homeLocation. So that's another operation
that's supported. You can have +, you can have -. Funnily enough, you
can also have division, well not so funnily really, as
represented with a slash like this, and you can have multiplication. But we'll look into
those in more detail in further sections, we don't really need that
for the Go Home section; addition is enough and subtraction is enough. So we can
see the distance from home is 2.9 meters. Now,
strictly speaking, it's -2.9 meters, because
if my location had been
-1, then
I would need to go in the forward direction to go home, and if it was
as it was something higher than 2.1 then
I need to go in the negative direction. So how do I sort that out? Well I need to
flip this order. That's just a quick math reminder for you guys,
the order of subtraction does matter, in this case.
And we want to do it
this way around. And you'll see that Unity does get it right,
it's a very good calculator, and it realizes that, indeed, we need to go
backwards 0.9 meters. And you
notice it adds a few decimal places in here, that's just because of slight
inaccuracies when we have to calculate floating
point numbers on a computer. OK, so that's,
as I've said, we can do floats minus
floats, floats plus floats, and as I've mentioned in the lectures,
we can also do floats and integers. That's fairly straight forward, I can just
show you this, that I could say (distance + 1).
So notice I don't have to save this into a variable, I can do it right
here, where I would use the value I can do that calculation. That's
called an expression, and we'll be using that word a bit more in
other lectures, too. There you go, you see that's done a +1, indeed!
So that works
just fine! So what other things can we do that addition with?
Well, funnily enough, we can do it with floats and strings, so I can say ("Distance: "
+ distance). So I've got the
distance string plus the distance float. I can remove this line now.
And if we hit play,
sure enough we get our "Distance" on the same line,
and basically, what this has done is it's turned into a string. How can I work that out?
Well if I take this and try and save it into
a variable,
I'll call this distanceString,
then this works! We can tell it's not a float, because if we
try to change the type to float it would complain and say,
well this I can't convert. It doesn't fit into the box because this expression,
i.e. this string
value plus a distance value, a float
value, this makes up an expression and creates itself
another value, is a string.
So it needs to be stored in a string box,
like so, but it's
enough for us to do that straight into the print statement, like so.
And it also
neatens up things, quite nicely, here in the interface. So
have we done everything that was challenged? Yes, we have made the print
better, and we have been able to mix different values, the string
namely. So congratulations on getting through that challenge!
I will see you in the next video!