Hey guys, congratulations on completing your first quiz!
Now, these first few concepts of programming are pretty hard to grasp, so don't worry,
but it is important that we get a good foundation.
And so if you've struggled with anything and anything's been tricky in the quiz, do go back and review the
videos linked from the quiz, they'll really help you get a good foundation to
move forward. So what have we covered? So far, we have done the Game Design Document,
so we know what game we're building. We have also designed using
pseudocode, to help us and give us an idea of what code we need to write,
even though we don't know quite how to write it yet. We've also seen how to use a
computer as a calculator, how to get it to print things, and we know that, really, it's just a dumb actor,
so we give it very very basic instructions. So if, at any point, you
are struggling with the instructions you're giving and it's just not obeying and you're not sure why,
then do use the lecture resources, because there we've got a link to Git
Hub, which shows you all the code that we have written. And you can
compare it side by side and see whether there's any mistakes in how you have written it, and that's
quite common, at this point. So, with that said, let's dive right in to the next
videos!