Welcome! In this lecture we're finally going to be making our game more
fun to play. We're going to be doing this by actually updating
those variables, so that, as we go along, the number of steps
changes, and also the number of meters away from home changes,
depending in which direction we press, so that we can actually get
home and finally have a game. So let's
get stuck right in!
It is all very well that we can input stuff into our program,
but it's still not very interesting if all the program does is repeat the same
message back to us, so it's really time for us to start
changing these on different key presses.
Now the problem is, if we were to update this variable, then
the next time we come around the update, you see it's going to set it back
to being the number of steps being 10. It won't remember
this variable between calls to the
Update () method, so that is where things like
context or, what we're going to now call it is, scope variables becomes
very important. We want the scope of this variable to last
between calls of Update (). Now
fortunately, as I mentioned before, we can nest
these variable scopes, or you can have them one
inside the other, that's basically what I mean. So this
here. these brackets, are a scope as well, but
you can see that it has access to all the variables inside the
brackets outside, so that we say
that these brackets from here to here are
the parent scope of these brackets and these brackets
and these brackets. Now, you'll notice that there is somewhere else
brackets that actually enclose all of this too, and that
is here. Here are some more brackets around the whole
thing, all the way out to here, and what that means is that
this is the parent scope for both Start ()
and Update (), which means that any variables we declare
in here we'll be able to access
in both of these, and also between calls to the Update ().
So let me show you what I mean. I'm going to start off by
taking numberOfSteps, cutting it,
if I can like so, and
then, I am going to paste it here in the top of this.
As you can see, the indentation is now one level less than
we have inside these methods and two levels less than in the if statement, and that's because
it is in a parent scope to these methods. And that means we can
access this, still access it in here,
but also between calls. So if I were to do something like
number
OfSteps = numberOf
Steps... Let me write that properly.
numberOfSteps + 1;
So what we're doing here is we're assigning
the current value of nuumberOfSteps + 1 to numberOfSteps
again. So we're basically incrementing the value
held in numberOfSteps. So I'm going to save that, let's go over to Unity, and
see what that does. OK,
so I'm going to hit the Down Arrow, and that doesn't do...
OK, you can see that incremented! If I hit Left and Right, it's not incrementing.
I hit Up, it's not incremting either. If I hit Down,
the number of steps keeps going up, which means it's variable
has persisted between different calls to the Update () method. We know it
must have done, because we keep repeatedly
changing that Update () method. So that is what we have managed to
achieve, by using a nested scope, a parent scope of
these methods.
OK, so it is time for a little challenge! I'd like you to update your distance from
home, using that same kind of technique again, which we have seen.
So select a starting distance form home. You'll need to choose
whether you're 5 meters away, 10 meters away, that's up to you It's going to be
the same whatever you do. At least the code will be the same,
the output will be different. So then I'd like you to set that
in the Start () method, or even as you've seen before.
You've seen me do it, you can do it here too. It doesn't have to be in the Start () method,
it can be set at the top of this scope here.
Then, I'd like you to
make it so that moving left subtracts from the distance,
and moving right adds to the distance. And each time we keep
printing the new distance to home. Moving up and down
should do nothing, at least for now. We'll sort that out in later lectures.
OK, so pause the video, and have a go at this yourself!
OK welcome back! We are going to dive straight
in and have a go at doing this! So I'm going to take
this distance, as I said, cut it and I'm going to paste it right under the number of
steps, as we have been doing. These two seem to move together quite a lot! As I
said, I want to select a distance to start off with, so
let's say we are 5 meters away from home to begin with.
OK, and then I said that going left
should detriment the distance, so we'll be going towards
home. So the distance is = to distance
- 1.; OK,
there is actually a way of doing this a little bit quicker and
with fewer lines. Because this is such a common thing to
do, this can be abbreviated all the way down to being
-= 1, like so,
which basically says exactly the same thing as what we had just written.
So because even this is very very common, we can abbreviate
it even more to just --, like this. So
distance--; and the Right Arrow we said we wanted
to increment by 1. Well it just so happens that there is a distance ++
and it works exactly the same way. Or we could do += 1
or we could do al the way to distance + 1. But
we'll stick with that distance,
if I can spell correctly, distance++;
OK. So that should do what we want! And one more
thing! Let's just increment the number of steps everywhere! So I'll do
++, and then, I'm just going to copy this down to whatever key.
You see this is now consistent, because
every time we make a move we have taken a
step, essentially, but only in two directions are we actually moving towards
or away from the distance... Away from home rather, not from the distance,
that doesn't make any sense. OK, let's hit play
and hit play again! OK, now if
I hit Up and Down you see I'm taking steps, but I'm not
moving to or from home. But
if I start hitting Left, I do indeed
move towards home, and if I start hitting Right,
I move away from home again.
So we can just see the effect of that,
like so.
Now you see there's a little bit of an odd behavior in that!
When I change direction, it goes up first.
Now the reason for that, if we go and look in the code, is
the order. Now order is very important, because this is the order in which all these
operations or statements are run. Now, what we
really want to be doing is incrementing before we print, because
that is essentially what we're saying. You know, we've moved that distance, now let's
let's show that updated distance.
That's what we really want, so it's very important to get the order right.
So let's try that again!
So I'm going towards!
Now I'm getting away! And you can see I instantly get the feedback about
this current step. One more thing to polish it off is, to go
and change this start number of steps to being
1, so that the first time we
have it printed it, it'll say after 1 " steps you are "...
Now we could do something about the s, but we won't worry too much about pluralization
in this instance. OK, so we have finished that
challenge, and our game is actually starting to be an interesting game that you can play!
In the next lecture we're going to be looking at how we can make this code a
little bit nicer and less repetitive! See you there!