...
Welcome to Booleans and
If Statements! In this lecture we are going to be learning, well reviewing,
the types of variables, as well as reviewing some of the terms that we've  been
using. And there's a lot of terms when it comes to programming, so I know it's hard to keep
them all in your head, so I've made a good list for you, a little glossary. And
how to use booleans and their operators. So booleans are a new type
we're going to learn about, and we're going to learn about operators and boolean expressions and
how to do conditional execution with if statements, because the main point of this
is to react to different conditions, such as a different input from the user. We want to
our script to behave differently, otherwise, it's kind of useless if it's just
doing static calculations. So let's dive right in!
So what is the next step for our Go Home game? Let's have
a look at our pseudocode and find out! So, so far we have
done these first three steps, the calculation
and the printing and the setting the start location.
Now, next up would be to read the player's move, but there's no point reading the player's
move, unless we know how to update the location from home. So let's take a look
at this one next, and it will give us some helpful building blocks
for reading the player's move, which we'll do in the following lecture.
So let's revise the types that we have seen,
so far! So far, we have seen the floats,
integers, and strings, and here are the different types that we actually use when writing
it in C#. Now, what we want to
do is have some way of conditionally doing things. So to
update the location, we want to say, basically,
if home is ahead, we need to go back, and if home is
forward, we need to go forward. So we need to be able to read in a player's move
if it says forward or back and update the location appropriately.
So we need to do different operations, depending on
what the player's move is. So to do this, we need a new type, it's
a type that's known as a boolean. A boolean, basically,
allows us to have true/false questions. As you can see here, we've
got the abbreviation bool but, most importantly, it's for true/false
answers, and the two values it can have are only true and false.
So let's have a look at this! How does this variable actually look?
So I'm going to open up our VisualStudio
with our ConsolePrinter script.
And what we want to do is create a new bool variable
and print it out and just see, see what happens.
OK, so here we have all our variables so far,
and let's create a new bool
for is
TwoGreaterThanOne
Notice how I'm writing these variable names. Obviously, there are no spaces allowed
in variable names, you've probably gathered that, by now, but in order to make it more
readable, I start with a lower case letter and then I do what's called camel case,
which is that every new word starts with an upper case. So this just allows me
to visually, very easily, see what the words are
in these multi-word variable names. Now it's just a typical convention
and in C# that's the one we're going to be using throughout this course. Obviously, there are
different conventions such as, you might say, is_two
greater_than_one. That's also
quite a common one, but we're going to stick with this, isTwoGreater
ThanOne. So let's just say,
so for the sake of argument, isTwoGreaterThanOne? Yes, we know that's true, so I'm
going to type in true. Remember our semicolon. And I
can print this out, so print
("Is two... In fact, I'll put numbers
here. ...2 greater than 1"),
and then, we can just do a +, like we
have already seen with distance, the same thing goes for bools.
So, let's say OK and hit play
and go into our Console and see that
"Is 2 greater than 1:" is indeed "True". Notice that I added a space
after my semicolon, and that allowed me to have this space in the logs,
as well. So let's do that for distance, too, it'll just make things a little bit more
readable. Let's hit play, and there you go,
now we've got a space in front of distance, too! OK, so that's fair
enough but we could actually get the computer to calculate this
for us by saying, well 2 greater than 1. So
this is a boolean expression, that is a
user then operator, and it returns a boolean. Let's just have a quick
revision of those terms that I've been using, because I know they can get slightly
confusing at times. Here is our glossary so far, the terms that we have
talked about. We have the Value, which is things like numbers
and text, and we've seen them use a lot of values, such as these string
values, these floating point values, and these integer values. We also have the
Type, which is the shape of the value, such as the int, float, and
string or now we've even seen boolean types.
Then we have the Variable, which is the box with the correct shape for
values. So we've got things like anInteger, which has the shape of int or the
type of int and the string and so on. We've also seen statements.
These are they things that end in semicolons, they are the commands to the
dumb computer, the dumb actor, and they tell it what to do, basically, step by
step, that's a statement. And finally, as I just said, we've got
Expressions, and Expressions are basically any command to the computer that evaluates
to a value. So, for example, we have a home location minus the
location. We've seen that one before, and we know that this gives us a value,
because it's what allows us to put it into that distance box,
is returning a value. And again, this string, plus the "Distance",
is obviously returning a string value, because it allows us to then
print that string value. So those are Expressions, and as we
can see here, this is a boolean expression because it returns a boolean. It
takes in two integers, and then, we use an operator, which
is the greater than operator, and it returns a boolean. So that is how we
can use booleans to calculate things for
us, do some interesting math for us. OK,
so that's all well and good but, like I said in the beginning, if we go
way back to update the location, what I want to say is, if the player
says one thing do one thing, and if the player says another thing, do a different thing.
So how do we do different things, based on these booleans?
Well there is such a thing as an if statement, as the name of the lecture
suggests, that is what we're going to be using these booleans for. So what I might
say is if and then, in brackets,
(isTwoGreaterThanOne). And
then, I use these curly braces to say that, within the body
of these curly braces I will only execute these
commands if this boolean is true, otherwise I won't execute them at all. So
I can put in, I can remove this print statement here and simply
print("2 is greater
than 1"), simple as that.
And then, what we can say is, go ahead and check that
out. I'm going to stop playing and play
again. So "2 is greater than 1", it gets printed out! But what if I set this variable
to false? Let's try that, too!
Let's hit play! Now you notice, this time, nothing
gets printed, because 2 is not greater than 1, so it's not going to tell us
that 2 is greater than 1. OK, so if statements go hand in hand
with booleans, they are why booleans are useful in the same way as strings go hand
in hand with being printed, because that's why strings are useful. So
we now know why we are going to use booleans, we use them in
something called an if statement. An if statement in here takes a boolean
expression here. I've given it a variable but I could have just as easily said 2
is greater than 1, and that is just as valid
and will also print out, because we know that 2 is greater than 1 and that is true! So
you see, I've just said it, and I've proved it by making the
computer run and do it. So time for you to write your
own boolean expression! I'd like you to evaluate whether the location
is greater than the homeLocation, because, in this case, what we need to
give, as a direction, is that they need to go
backwards, basically, in order to get home. However, if the opposite is
true, then I would like you to print the correct
instructions, as well. So pause the video and have a go at applying your
knowledge of booleans and if statements to this problem.
OK welcome back! Now
remember, if you ever have syntax errors that you can't quite work out,
you can always go into the lecture resources and
find the exact end state of this video, so that you can compare
your syntax to the syntax that I have written in these
lectures. Because sometimes it's very small things that you
don't miss, as a beginner programmer, you won't quite see
that perhaps you have just mistaken the order of something. Obviously, these squiggly
lines, the red squiggly lines, the green ones are kind of OK, but the red ones
will give you an indication of where to look and do use that, because
those are some of the most simple and easy problems to fix. If
you are new to programming, you may not have your eye quite tuned to these
things, just yet, but remember that the compiler is
very very finickity. So basically Unity is very finickity and will
pick you up on any small error, so you need to be
absolutely perfect in times of typing these things out. But don't
worry, it also helps you out by giving you those red squigglies. So
here we have our if statement I want to do. Let's just check on the challenge. All that
talking and I've forgotten what the challenge is. We want location greater than homeLocation.
Well that's fairly simple, we can actually just type that right into the if statement. No need for a variable, I'm
going to remove that variable. That was just to show you there was a type going on
behind this, but often, we can just do this with boolean expressions. So
we've got "location greater than homeLocation).
Simple. Now what can I say? Well what is the instruction if
the location is greater than the home location, it's going to be ("Go back
to get home!"). Now let's
test that out! Yes,
"Go back to get home!", that's because the location is greater. But what if,
what if my location was less?
Hmm, then nothing is
printed, I have no instruction! That's a bit useless, so
what should I do? Well, I'm going to say, if
(Location less than homeLocation) see?
This is a different operator, the less than operator.
Well then, we print
("Go forward to get home!").
Remembering my semicolon, because VisualStudio was
reminding me with that helpful little squiggle. So let's try that out!
Let's play
and then we get "Go forward to get home!". So no matter what our
location is, we are now getting the correct instruction. Well is
that quite true? Let's just try that out! If we got 2.1...
Oops! So
we are at home, what's going to happen then?
Let's play! Hmm, no instruction, because neither of these
two statements is true, because it's not greater than it's not less than, the only
thing that leaves is that it is equal. Now, how do we do
equality? You could try (location =
homeLocation), but what you'll find is a big squiggly here,
saying "Cannot implicitly convert 'float' to 'bool'. So what on
Earth is going on here? Well basically what it's done is, it's taken this
equals sign to mean an assignment to the variable location.
And so, how do we make it a boolean equality?
Well let's have a look at the Boolean Operators we've seen so far! We've got the Greater Than,
we've got the Less Than, and this is the operator we need for Equals,
2 equal signs. A bit weird, I know, but the important thing
is it distinguishes it from the assignment operator we've been using before. So this
is the assignment operator, equality, equals like that. Whereas the
equality operator, the one for booleans, is a double equals sign, like so ==.
And so, here we can say print
("I am at home!").
Let's go back in, and there
we go, we have sussed out the equality sign. And just
one more boolean operator. There is also a not equal sign, where you put
this little exclamation mark. The exclamation mark means not, and so we
can do not equality in just this way. OK, so now
we know all about booleans! Congratulations, that is a big
step in being able to make much more complicated programs! So I will see you
in the next lecture, where we will be taking input and acting on
those inputs instead. So let's see you there!