Welcome! In this video we are going to be learning how to
not repeat ourselves, understanding the DRY principle.
We're going to write our own methods and functions, in order to achieve
this. We'll be calling out to methods and learning
what that means and how to do that. And we'll be introduced to
refactoring. Refactoring is the process of iteratively
making our code better and easier to understand and read,
making it just work more correctly. OK, so let's dive right in!
So I'd like to introduce you to the DRY
principle of programming. So the DRY principle basically states
that you do not repeat yourself. It's very simple and
it's basically saying that we don't want to be writing the same code over and over
again, if we're doing that then we're doing something wrong. We need to be abtracting
away that thing that we keep writing again and again. So is our
code following this DRY principle? Well I'll
let you figure it out, but I would say, given the number of these lines
[Laughs] that look exactly the same, we are not following the DRY principle.
And also, it's not great because it makes it hard to read, because when
we go down this code, looking through, we
kind of don't understand what actually it's trying to
do. What is happening after each of these steps? We have to read very painstakingly
to try and work out and go, oh yeah, the program is saying when I hit
the Down Arrow, then I print out this message that
tells...updates the user. Basically, we
update the user's number of steps, and print out the message
So it's not at the right sort of level of abstraction, when
I'm reading this. And similarly, you know,  I'm in the Start () method, and what is this
text? Well it's a welcome message, but nothing here says that it's a welcome message,
so that's not particularly obvious. So the solution to both of the
DRY problem and the lack of abstraction is one thing, it's a function or
a method, as we've called them previously. This is a method but we can
also define our own methods and that's what we're going to do now. So take this example,
where it's not entirely obvious that what this does,
so we can write code that documents itself, by creating a method.
Let me just explain by doing. So I create a new method
very much the same as Start (), except I replace the word Start with my
method name. So I can have a void Print
WelcomeMessage ()
and then my squiggly brackets. And now what I can do is, I can
cut and paste this welcome message code and put it
in my welcome message function, my welcome message
method. OK, so now I've got it in here,
but how does start know that it needs to run this
method? Well that's what's calling a method is
all about. So you have to type out
the name of the method, followed by some brackets, and as I said, every
line has to end with a semicolon, when we want it to actually execute something.
So that's what's going on here, it's saying execute or call
the method named PrintWelcomeMessage(). Now where's that welcome
message defined? Here in this method! And that's
the code that gets run when this gets called. It's quite
simple. OK, so I would like
you to make your code DRY. I would like you to create a new
method for that duplicated code. You see what I mean, all this code
here? Then, I would like you to give it a
descriptive name. So what name really describes what
this code is doing? Then, replace the duplcate
code with calls in.. to the function.
OK, so I will leave that with you.
Pause the video and have a go!
OK welcome back! I hope you've had a go. The naming bit
might have been particularly tricky, and we're going to struggle through that together with you.
OK, so we're creating a new method.
So I can create it either above here or
below here. The important thing is it's outside of the brackets for this
method, because that is...we can't create a method
within a method. So I'm going to just create it
below the Update(), and I'm going to call
it void. Let's see, what's
the right thing? I think it's PrintUpdateAndContinue().
Generally we don't like writing methods that
do two things, and so we don't like methods that have an And in them.
But in this case, we'll make the exception because
it is kind of doing two things and we don't want to repeat this code. So I'm
going to just cut this code and put it in the method body,
like so, and then, that means I can replace here
just a PrintUpdateAndContinue(), like so.
And I can now replace all
those bits of code that were exactly the same, just like this.
OK, now let's go into Unity
and see whether that's still working, as we wanted it to before!
Now I need to make sure it's not maximizing. It's going back to
doing that for me. And then, we
go into our Console and just check out
what is going on here.
OK, we aren't getting any output!
So let's head back to our code
and just have a think about what this could be doing.
Let's talk through, as we go.
So the first stage is we have the Start() method,
and that is what gets called first and that calls the PrintWelcomeMessage()
and that calls through to here. OK, well that all seems
to be in order. And perhaps
what's going on, if I look up here, it says "Unity Personal" "Untitled",
so that is the problem! What we need to do is open our Main scene
here. So once we've opened the Main scene, it says Main.unity,
and if we hit play
and go into the Console... OK, it
still hasn't! So for some reason it has deleted my game object! Well that's
a good instance to revise! We can create our
GoHomeGame again.
This is probably because I didn't save it properly last time.
We can delete these two because we don't need them, and we just
drop our script onto there again. You may not have to do this, because
you may have saved correctly. OK, we can't do that while we're playing!
It loses it, so I'm just going to do it one more time. Create Empty,
GoHomeGame,
and drag the script back on.
And now make sure we save! You'll have to save the scene, otherwise
things in the Hierarchy won't be saved. So
that is an important lesson to learn and you've learned it by me making the mistake.
Let's go into Console and there we go! We've got our welcome messages printed
out as before, and if I click in the game,
my arrows are behaving exactly the same way as
before. Congratulations, that is a challenge successfully completed, and I'm looking forward to
seeing you in the next lecture!