Welcome! So in this video I'm very excited, because we're about to
use vectors in code for the first time, so it's actually going to be doing something
useful for us! All this math that we learned in high school and thought would never be relevant,
finally, it's going to be put to work for us in making games!
So in this video we're going to be meeting types, classes, and structures
and things like that, and all those kinds of beasts. We're also going to be
learning how to use the Vector2 type, and we're going
to be implementing distance, using this new
vector knowledge that we have.
But before we dive into our code we need to answer this question,
what is a type? So a type is, very simply,
a way to put abstract things into
our variables. So by things I mean, well it could be anything couldn't it? It could
be a vector, it could be a house, it could be a dog, but the idea is it's an abstract
thing, an abstract object, that we want to put into our
variables, and types allow us to do that by giving these
things some sort of behaviors and
properties. So for example,
they're also known... So this is very important, you also need to know that
people will call them Classes and they will call the Structs, and it's very
common to hear the word Class referring to a user defined type.
Just so you know, all of these things are roughly equivalent, like classes and structs
are two different kinds of a type, essentially.
Then, we can instantiate these
types to make a new thing. So that is exactly what we're doing here,
when we say new Vector2 with 2 and 3. That's saying
that we create a new 2 dimensional vector, with the coordinates
2 and 3. So 2 in the X dimension
and 3 in the Y dimension. They also
have properties or fields like vector.x
and vector.y. These basically say, in
this case, 2 and 3 for this particular thing, for this particular
object or instance, all these terms are equivalent.
So we've got X is 2, Y is
3, for this particular new Vector2.
And then, they also support operations, so I could take two vectors a and
b, and I could do a plus operation and the computer would work out the new vector,
that it is equated to.
OK, so what does this all look like in our code?!
So we might want to start off by
considering a vector that is home.
Now I'm going to remove distance, because we're going to be calculating this now,
and we want to create a new vector for home. So
the type of that vector is now Vector2. As you can see,
it's slightly different to those primitive types that we were using before, like
int and float. It's now a more abstract concept, it's a vector
rather than just an int or a float. And we'll call this home
Location. So it's a nice descriptive name
for the thing that we're going to be storing in it, the thing, so the object
and the object we need to instantiate. So how did we do
that? Let's just go to the slide and check! We had new Vector2
and then in brackets, (2, 3)
close bracket. So these are giving multiple arguments to Vector2,
new Vector2() and then
we can do (2, 3). So that's the location of home, and
just let's go back and have a look at that again. There was a completion there, when I started typing
(2). You see it's saying that it wants something of type float
and something of type float. So I can give those like that or I can
give them like this as well,
and then, semicolon to end the line as always. OK,
so that is how we create a
new variable, holding a vector
thing of type vector.
Now, we want to create one more, we want to create one for the
player location. So we do the same procedure, the type is Vector2.
We do a playerLocation =
new Vector2(), and this time we can
put in a different set of numbers. So (5.0f,
and I'm going to put 1.0f), so there's
the floating point numbers. And
we can save that! Now, what did I
say earlier about fields? Let's see, what do these fields look like?
So for example, in
the home, in this welcome message, let's put a
print statement, which prints out
the ("homeLocation
.x". Then, we can do + home
Location.x) like so. And we can see what
that actually returns. If we go into Unity and hit play...
OK we have some errors, let's just go over it. It says
" 'distance' does not exist in the current context" and that is obviously correct. So
we'll just remove these distances for now, now that we've broken, at
the moment. I'm just going to remove it there as well, remove the plus
so that is all compiling. And
let's hit play and see whether this works now. OK
so we've got homeLocation, I forgot to add a space, is 2.
Let's just check in the code! Yes, 2 is exactly what we set
in it! Perfect! So we can see that when we
created this vector, it created some properties or some fields
here, and that is what we're
seeing here, x and y. And the other thing I said is
that we can support
operations, like so.
If I want to calculate a distance,
I can create a new variable to hold the distance,
like so, and I can calculate the distance.
As we said in previous slides and previous lectures, we
said that the distance from home is going to be
homeLocation - the player
location. If I can spell correctly, Location.
If I can type correctly, it's player
Location; like so.
OK it's not complaining. And now, if
I print that distance, what do you think it will print?
Well let's pause execution and
start the preview again. Now if I hit the
arrow, you see
it's giving us this vector notation for it, and
if we have a look at it, it does make sense, because we're saying that we have
to go 3 down
from the player's location to home, that's what it's saying here.
And it's saying we need to go 2 up, from the player's location, to get to
home. So that all makes sense! This vector makes sense,
as being the distance between the two.
Ooh, I feel a challenge coming on! It's time for you
to have a go at updating the player's position! So in the same way as
we we're updating the distance previously, now we actually want to update the position,
because the distance is calculated from that. So
I'd like you to consider each of the if statements, the up, down, the left, and
the right, and I'd like you to... You'll need to make some modifications in
each of those. I'd like you to use assignment,
as you did previously, to modify the player's position.
And here's some hints for you! I'd like you
to... You'll need to build, use the built in vectors, I'm sorry... You'll
need to use the built in vectors, Vector2.up and Vector2
.left. These are exactly what they sound like, they are a vector that points
1 unit up and a vector that points 1 unit left. And there are obviously
the ones for down and right as well, but I'm sure you can guess how to write
those. And here's another hint for you! You will only need to use addition,
in order to do this, no subtraction is necessary. OK, so pause the video
and have a go at modifying this code yourself!
OK welcome back! It was a bit of a
tough challenge, so don't worry if you got a little bit stuck, but the important thing is that you
had a go. And let me known in the discussions, if you got stuck and
how, and I can try and make the challenge a little bit better with better
hints and so on. OK, so here is
our code and here are all our different if statements, and for each one, we want to consider
doing something different. Now remember, we updated our distance
before the PrintUpdateAndContinue(). And that's what we want to do when we're updating
our player position, too. So we've got playerLocation
is equal to, and now what we want to do is, we want to
increase the playerLocation 1 unit in the
down direction. So we want to do playerLocation is equal
to playerLocation + Vector2
.down; Do you see what I'm doing here? I'm adding
1 unit down on top of this playerLocation, which effectively
moves our player 1 unit down. OK so it
shouldn't be too hard to see how we can go from here to all the rest of them.
We just need to do an up, and here we need to do
a left
and here we need to do
a right. I'll save that! We'll go ahead
and play our game and see whether we are actually updating
our distance from home. So
as I go along left that distance decreases.
If I go right it gets more, if I go up
I get to go home, and if I go down I get farther away from home.
Perfect! And now our arrow keys are actually moving us around the world,
thanks to the beautiful maths of vectors! OK, so
that's enough of the maths, let's move on to the next lectures!