Hey guys, congratulations on completing yet another
quiz! And how many more concepts have we learned in these last few
videos? It's incredible, we've learned about objects, methods, everything, you know!
Basically, you have most of the basics of programming now, so make sure
you understand them very well. So again, the same advice as I gave you in the last quiz,
just make sure that, if anything is unclear, you go back
and review it, because it's really important to get the basics right, and there's always
just using the forums and the Q & A to make sure you
really check your understanding. So we've got a working game, how great! Now, we're going to go
in and consolidate all that knowledge in the next few videos and really
understand how this all fits together and how to make our
code, that little bit better, that little bit more maintainable and readable. So
let's dive right in!