...
Welcome to How to
Speak Like  A Programmer! In this lecture we are going
to be doing a recap of all this new terminology and all this new knowledge,
that we have seen this section, because I really want it to sink in for you,
so you can go away with a strong base for the next few sections.
So the key things are going to be understanding the structure of programs that you are
writing, learning the programming jargon, which we've been covering in
our glossary so far, and the statements vs. Expressions question.
What exactly is the difference, as well as methods, and Execution Flow? What
these things mean, well what is execution flow, in the first place, and the components of a
class? So let's dive right in and start to answer some of these
questions! What is a program? So
as we said, it's just basically a script that is given to an actor, so it's
just a series of steps for the computer to execute, and these
steps change data, the data that is stored in variables.
So you've got steps that are going along, changing the data in some sort of
way. And the order of these steps is
Execution Flow. So basically, which step happens after which
other step? And it might seem obvious but once you start to add in
methods it becomes a little bit less obvious and we'll see that in just a second, but
first off, I want to have a look at Statements and Expressions and what the difference
is between the two. So we've seen these lines of code, the print
("Welcome to Go Home!") and ("A game where you need to find your way back.").
So both of these here are Statements, they execute an instruction,
and, in this case, the instruction is to print something to the screen.
How about this thing here? Well quite clearly
it has an Expression in it, which evaluates to a value, that location
+ movementVector creates another vector, a new vector,
which is the sum of those two. But the whole thing
is a Statement, because it has an Expression that is being assigned
to a location, therefore it's this action that's being executed
to assign to the location variable, and so we are changing the
data in that location variable. Now there's
something called a compound statement and we've seen these before in if statements.
So basically, a compound statement sounds like a fancy word but, very
simply put, it has some Expressions in it, such as
we've seen here as well, we've had an Expression inside a statement. So you've got an
Expression there, which is the boolean Expression which tells us whether to execute this
block of code or not, and then, inside this block
we have lots of statements, not just one. Each of these
lines, in fact, is a statement. As we saw, this is a statement, obviously this is updating
the pathToHome, we're printing something as well, and then, we've got another if statement even
or another compound statement inside. So as a whole, this whole
block is a Compound Statement, because it consists of multiple sub-statements.
So just some interesting terminology, in the way that
statements go within statements and expressions go within expressions, t's not
completely trivial. We've also got Methods
and Execution Flow! So what is this? Well firstly, these things here are
Methods. As we quite clearly know, they both have a void return
type, they take some arguments, or no arguments. Then, they've got their body
block of code that they execute. Now, how does
it start? So if we start executing Start(), how does the Execution Flow look?
Let's have a look! Well at first we would do the prints, we'd print and then
print, and then we'd reach the Average() method,
and we would call that method. That means that the Execution Flow
jumps over to the Average() method and starts
executing through that. So we work out our Average,
we print the Average. Then, what happens when we get to the end? Well Execution
Flow returns back to where we left it, so we left
it at 2 and we come back to it at 4, and that means that in at
5 we can move on to the next line in that function
and then it jumps back into Average again. You can see how this is helping
with avoiding repetition, because now we run through this code a second
time with number 7 and then jump back. So
instead of having to write those statements out twice, we just simply
executed them twice. And you can see how Execution Flow really does just
follow along. You can read it from top to bottom and just jump to the
functions and remember where you have to jump back to. Obviously, the more
functions you get, the more jumping around you do, it starts to get hard to remember
where you jump back to, but the computer is very good at remembering this for you.
So Classes, Types, and Variables. Here
we have, obviously, some Variables that we have defined our location
and homeLocation. As we know, these Variables have to have
a Type at the beginning, and sometimes these types are actually Classes, they're user
defined and complex. As opposed to being things like ints and floats and strings,
which are just simple types, you can have Class based Types, often
they have a capital letter at the front, and they have
often much more in them, such as the Vector2 has 2 vectors and
you can do all sorts of operations on those vectors. So
this whole thing, in comprising the Variables and the Methods,
is a Class, and we know that the Class name is given here,
after that little bit of class keyword
that indicates this. ConsolePrinter is the name of the Class.
So time for a challenge for you! I would like you to
annotate your program. So your program may look slightly different to mine,
it might not. You may have chosen slightly different variable names or you may not have.
But I'd like you to take a screenshot of the entire program and put
some annotations on it. So find the simple and compound
statements, for example. Label all your functions or as I call them methods,
they're also called functions. Use an arrow to
show the execution flow through your program. Don't worry about getting the whole
Execution Flow, that might be too much, but just give it a go for some
shallow level. And then, what data does our
class contain? Because we know that the data is what fundamentally gets
changed, as we run through our statements.
And what are the functions? We've
kind of already covered that. And share this on
the forum. Basically, go to your discussions link
in the lecture resources and that will take you straight to the discussions for this
lecture, and just post on the bottom of one of those threads there, where people
are already sharing their annotated programs. OK, so Pause the video and have a go at
creating your own annotation!
OK welcome back! I look forward to seeing your annotations in the thread! There's
loads of people who've done loads of great work there, already! Now I just
want to quickly do a little review. We've seen quite a few glossaries. If you've followed the lecture
resource link here, to these lecture slides, you'll also be able
to take a look at this glossary and revise these terms, if ever you get
confused about something I say, in any of the lectures coming up or that have
been. So we've seen Values, Types, Variables,
Statements, and Expressions. I don't think I need to cover that in too much detail anymore.
We have Methods that take Arguments and they Return Values,
and Methods are essentially Operations. We've
seen the difference between an Object and a Class and how an Object is an
Instantiated version of that blueprint, the Class, and that an
Object is sometimes also called an Instance. And just
in this lecture, we have seen how Compound Statements are, themselves, made out of
sub-statements, the example being the if Statement. We've got
Execution Flow, which is the order in which Statements are executed,
and we have the DRY Principle, which stands for Don't Repeat Yourself
and it is basically the principle of avoiding repetition.
So for example, we, in the last lecture, factored out some
Methods to avoid repeating code, and we've just seen how the
Execution Flow works, when you do that. And Refactoring, as we know, is the
process of doing both that, trying to conform to the DRY Principle
by moving and renaming code for better maintainability just in general.
So an example of that, that we haven't already covered, would be renaming
Variables or Methods and Classes, and we will be doing a bit of that. In fact, let's do that right now!
So here is the code, as we left it!
The thing I'm really looking out for is whether these names are appropriate,
if we read through and check it out. So is it a
ConsolePrinter still? Is this Class a ConsolePrinter? No, not really, it's a Go
Home game, so we want to rename this. So I'm going to change
this to being called a GoHomeGame,
and
obviously, I need to rename the file as well. So I'll go over to the Project
and rename it to
GoHomeGame, because that has to match.
I'll just Reload! It's obviously disappeared, because the file name's
no longer the same. We can't change the name of Start().
Average() here isn't actually doing anything. We don't want that code,
it was just there to show us that we can
factor out methods like that. How about location and
homeLocation? Well location's a bit ambiguous, just by itself, so I'll teach
you a little trick. If we right-click on this, we can go to Rename,
in VisualStudio, and call this the playerLocation
like so. And if I hit Apply, you'll notice that further down
the location has been replaced with playerLocation. So that
is all great! How about CheckForMovement?
Does that seem about right? Well
it does, however, some of it is not actually
checking for movement. So what we have in here, we've got pathTo
Home, and it is printing out the "Distance to
home: " and it's printing out that message. That's not really checking for movement, and this bit is
updating movement, so maybe we call this UpdateMovement.
So I can, again, right-click, Rename,
and call this UpdateMovement.
Apply, and that's starting to get more legible already.
Now, one other trick that you want to do,
when trying to keep things at a steady level of
abstraction. You have this UpdateMovement() Method,
which is doing one thing and it's updating movement here, but then, it's also doing
all this other stuff to try and calculate the "Distance to home: ", which is really happening
at a different level. Really, what this whole block is doing is
update user distance or update display
user, something like that. So what we can do is, we can take this out
into a Method, and it doesn't actually take any arguments or return anything or...
Well it does but it's just the playerLocation,
which is already available to the class. So what we can do is, in
VisualStudio it's very easy. If we right-click, we can do Quick Actions and Refactoring,
and we want to, indeed, Extract a Method. So
we click on that
and we want to rename it
to something meaningful. So what shall we
call it? Basically, it is PrintDistance
ToHome(),
and we'll apply that and suddenly the UpdateMovement becomes very obvious.
We're checking if the key is down, we're updating the location, then we're printing the distance to home,
and that's very clear, and then, if you go into print("Distance to home: ", it's clear
why it's doing all these calculations. So this has
simply made our code that much easier to read, simply by
extracting methods out of our existing code, and
you've also seen how easy it is to extract methods in that way. You'll
notice that this has private in front of it, this is very similar to these methods
here, these Variables which have public. By default, Variables are private
and Methods are public, which is why we need to make this one
private, because basically we don't want other people printing this. And we can do that same
thing with UpdateMovement. We don't want other classes
to be able to Update our Movement, we just want to be able to do that ourselves.
So I will save that and we'll just go, and
it's always a good idea to check that your game is still working, after doing a bit of refactoring,
because it's very easy to break things. So I can
still move. And can I win the game?
Let's get home. Yes, I'm home! So I have been able to
win the game, and I've improved the state of my code slightly, so that
is fantastic! That is refactoring in action, moving, renaming
code for better readability. There you have it! So I will see
you in the next lecture, where we'll be learning to debug our code!