So. as usual. before we dive and start playing with Unreal. we need to have some
concept of what we're going to be doing. So. this again is our Game Design Document
and our friendly starting point for all game development projects. By the way.
on these slides at the bottom right. I'm going to be annotating with the version of Unreal
that the tutorial was recorded in. So. you're seeing it's in v.4.10.2.
That'll just help you be orientated if watching this. once a later
version is out. It always gives you the option to go back.  Anyway. this is about game design.
so let's just take a look firstly at the concept. What are we building here?
The core concept is really simple: escape the room!
You awaken in a locked room. unable to escape; use environmental
clues. such as light and sound. to determine what to do next. So. we're going to design
some nice simple ways of trying to guide the player. as to what they
may need to be doing next. It's going to be a very small scope game. because there's a
lot of new stuff. when we get into Unreal. We're going to do things like
trigger pressure plates and solve at least the bull cow puzzle. to progress towards
the exit. So that's the idea! Rules. well there's no lose
condition. apart from the feeling that you're going to die in this room if you don't get out eventually.
Anything that you can do you're allowed to do. so there's no
kind of restrictions on what you're allowed to do. if you can do it. do it.
and you win by finally exiting the room!
Requirements! So. what does this thing need to make it happen? Well. we're going to use
Unreal's provided Starter Content pack. That's got plenty of wall
sections and a table and a chair and some lights and doors and
door frames. all the stuff we really need. If you've got assets that you've either
bought or made and you want to bring those in. absolutely do that. but I'm just going to start with the
Starter Content. so we're all on the same page. We're going to need to write some C++
code and some Blueprint to encode the behavior. We're going to use C++ where it
makes the most sense and Blueprint where that makes the most sense. We're going to
use various sound effects to enhance the atmosphere. If we can't find stuff in the Start
Content pack. then I will provide you with sounds from a sound
library that's been kindly donated to us. which we'll hear about later on.
And you're going to need some sketches for the layout
of your room or rooms. It's up to you. really. whether you build one room or multiple
rooms. I would either build one big one or lots of little ones interconnected.
I also encourage you go build a different layout to what I do in this section.
And you're going to need sketches or at least one sketch.
for how one puzzle works. Maybe don't sketch them all out yet. because
you'd be better off doing one. encoding one. making it work. and then
design the rest. maybe after that. when you've got a little bit more experience about what would
be involved. before you go and get super excited and start trying to recreate the next
version of The Witness or Myst or whatever else you love. There's a lot of programming
involved in those things and we're not quite ready for that yet. So that's it!
That's the concept rules and requirements. and we'll see how it pans out. What I want
you to do now is sketch your room or rooms. Sketch out one large room
or a few smaller ones. Annotate where the puzzles will be or at least your
first guess. You can change any of this later. you can change your mind later.
Create a more detailed sketch of one of the puzzles. just one.
As I said. we want to make sure that we
understand what's involved in actually implementing these things. before we get carried away with some massive
design that we may not be ready as a team  for. whether that's a team of 1. 2. 3. or
300! We want to make sure we're capable of delivering what we're
dreaming about. so let's deliver things as we think about them. This is very lean to just
make one puzzle. get it completely finished. and then start thinking about the
rest. We're kind of prototyping and testing all in one. And I want you to
just share your sketches in the discussions. with the other students.
By the way. Evernote can be a great tool for storying these things. Once you've
taken your sketches. then certainly on iOS and
Android. you can take a photo of your sketches. using Evernote on the smartphone.
and then. you can store it in Evernote and actually get a link
to the hosted version of the Evernote. That's one way of storing these things.
The good thing about Evernote is. it will recognize your handwriting if it's reasonably neat
and really help you find things later. So. just a thought. you could use Evernote or you could use
anything else. So. that's it really! I want you to pause the video. In fact. stop the video.
go ahead and do your design now. and I'm going to pull out my sketches and
designed. as we go through the section as needed. so it will be a surprise for you!
And in the next video. we'll start setting up our project and looking at Unreal's files
and the file structure and version control and lots of fun stuff like that! I will see you soon!
Vroom! Video end!