Hi. so
let's have an overview of Source Control. I'm going to explain the
what and the way of Version Control Systems. We're going to be
choosing a Version Control System. VCS from now on.
We'll talk a little bit about what files to include
or exclude from your version control. You'll see.
over the coming lectures. how committing is saving a local snapshot of your work.
at this point in time and how resetting is rolling back to a previous
state. that you had before. basically getting you out of trouble.
And we'll leave things like branching and pushing and large file support and other technical terms
of Source Control. till much later in the course. if at all. if needed.
So firstly. what are Version Control Systems? They're
get out of jail cards. if you like! These things are going to allow you to keep very detailed
histories of your work. and make sure that you can go back to your work in
a state that was working and all hanging together properly. at any point in time.
which is going to be extremely useful. It's also useful for when you're working with other people.
There's a load of different systems out there. Git is one of the most popular and becoming
more popular very fast. Mercurial is another. Perforce.
Subversion SVN for short or TortoiseSVN.
or Alienbrain. This is great for art. and it's
very good for things like seeing the difference between two different images files. etc.. but it's of
the order of $10.000. It's out of most people's budget. but it is worth
considering. if you're primarily wanting to control the versions of your
art files. Have a look on Wikipedia there. for
a complete comparison of all Version Control software that... Well.
at least all of it's on Wikipedia. So. we're going to use something called
SourceTree. So. SourceTree is free software by a company called Atlassian.
Why do they give it away for free? Probably because it's very easy to use with their Bit
Bucket service. which does have a paid tier which is the online portion.
We're just focusing on local source control. for now; just on keeping your computer
local versions of your files. Of course. you need to be backing
up your whole computer and your files anyway. and whatever strategy you're using for backup. whether it's
Crash Plan or Back Blaze or hard drives or all of the
above. hopefully. if you're belt and braces. Then. you're Source Control
System will be backed up with that. but we're just talking about local source control.
SourceTree is a visual front end for Git or Mercurial.
So. Git and Mercurial are two Version Control Systems. They work slightly differently behind the
scenes. Both are pretty applicable to what we're doing here.
but we're going to be using Git and we're going to be using SourceTree as a front end to Git. It just
makes it a lot easier. when you're learning and when you're using it. to visualize what's going on.
There's Mac and PC versions of SourceTree. but the Mac version is a little ahead.
so the PC version tends to be lacking a few features. Not quite a pretty looking.
etc. And as I said. it's really good when you're learning. It's really
easy to visualize using SourceTree. so that's why we're going to be showing you SourceTree.
So. it's challenge time! I want you to install your Version Control
System. Pick a Version Control System for yourself. If you're already using one.
don't change at this stage just for us. please just carry on. but if you're not.
we'll be using Git with SourceTree as the front-end.
So. Git is the underlying Version Control System. and SourceTree is just a pretty front-end
system we're going to be using. to make it much easier to interact with than having to remember all  the command line commands.
Install and register it. You will need to register it. at least within the first 30 days.
And have a quick play stroke experiment. You really can't do any harm. so  just
make a folder. have a quick play. and as soon as you feel like you're not getting anywhere. then
carry on watching the videos. and I will show you around SourceTree. that I already have
installed on my machine. So go ahead. pause the video. and get yourself
your Version Control System installed now!
Hey welcome back! So. this
is where you go to get Source Tree. If you do a search for Source Tree. I just want to show you
their official page. in case you end up somewhere funny on the web. It's a strange place. the Internet!
www.sourcetreeapp.com There you go! SourceTree. and it'll detect your
operating system and let you download. It's going to look something like this when it's installed. Now. I'm not going to
go through the install and setup. It is just a piece of software.
and the hardest bit. maybe. is you just need to register with them. and you don't even need to do that until 30 days
is in. I don't think. So. once you've installed SourceTree. it'll open up something
like this! So. this is a project I've been working on recently. for the Unreal course.
It's a piece of code from the Bull Cow Game. and this is the
interface. It's prettier on Mac. so if you're taking this course on Mac. you'll be lamenting the
fact that it's prettier. It's also prettier than this on a PC with a higher resolution
screen. I'm running at 720 p hi DPI. so it all looks a bit funny but it's here!
Now. the things that you need to focus on. really. is we're going to have one or more
repositories. Now. what are they? Basically. it's a folder. containing all of your work for
this section. So. in a particular section of the course. all your work is going to go in one folder
and that will map to this repo on the left here. so each section will have one.
And then. all of these things are actually the videos! This is the last section that I produced.
over in the Unreal course. and each of these stages is
exactly what I did in that video. Now. the great thing with code is. you can see
precisely what changed. I can see exactly what I added to this file. in this
particular revision in video 10. If you're using binary assets. Blender
files. image files. etc. You're not going to be able to see the details using SourceTree.
of what's changed. but it's still going to keep a perfect history for
you. of exactly how things were at particular stages in time. So. I'm not
going to tell you how to use this now. that's going to be in the upcoming videos. I just want you to quickly get your eye
in. What it's going to be doing for you. once you've set it up. is this big panel
here is going to show you what's changed since the last time. You'll be able to see
things called un-staged files. and you'll get to choose to stage these files
and then to commit them. which committing is a bit like
bundling them up into a .zip file and sticking them off to one side. saying yeah. I've got to that
stage. it's done. I want to record that as a stand point in history!
So. that's what a commit is! And then. you're also going to be able to see later how you
can actually go back to a previous point in time. a couple of different ways.
and we'll be showing you Checkout and reset and the difference between those! But for now.
all you need to know is. this is a way of storing a very powerful history. with a detail of at least what files
have changed. and if you've got text in your files. then you're going to be able to even
see precisely what's changed. And this means. that if you always commit
or save your work. in a working state. if everything goes wrong and suddenly
your whole project doesn't hang together properly. you can go back to a previous point in time
and you are back out of trouble and able to carry on working!
So. that's an overview of source control! Over the coming videos. you're going to see exactly how we
use it. and it's going to be a whole new way of thinking for you. You'll hate it at first. if
you need to. and then you'll love it soon after! See you soon!