Welcome to your
first .gitignore file for Unreal! It's more fun than it sounds. So, in this
video, we'll understand that Unreal creates Visual Studio even
projects for us. We'll learn how to re-generate Visual Studio project files,
we'll be writing our first .tidignore file, and committing our project, for the first time,
so that we have a safe basis to start exploring Unreal and ability
to always dive back and get to a previous state of work. So, see you in there!
So welcome back! I just want to show you something about Visual Studio, as
Visual Studio is what we're most familiar with, at the moment. I want you to understand that Unreal is going to be
responsible for building our Visual Studio solution
files and the other ancillary files that are needed. Let me show you something,
we've stripped out all of the files that I said you can delete. Intermediate,
Build, Binaries, Intermediate, and also the Visual Studio database
file can go. If you've done that, because you've deleted
the Intermediate directory, look what happens when you try and open your Visual Studio solution. You get
a Load Failed! So, if you start ever seeing this happen with your Visual Studio
Solution, then the solution to the solution is to right-
click on here on the actual .uproject file,
BuildingEscape.uproject in this case, and select Generate Visual Studio Project
Files. Now, what that's going to do, if we watch, is it immediately makes this intermediate directory.
Unreal will also make an intermediate directory, when you open the project,
but the files we're interested in are the ones that are going
to allow Visual Studio to load, i.e. these project files here.
OK, so once that's done and all of that is finished running, now we can actually open our
Visual Studio Solution, which consists of two projects. One of these projects is the
UE4 Engine, we don't worry about that, but the other is our Games, and in this case, one game Building
Escape. And then, you can go down and you can look mainly at source,
and of course, there's really not much source in here. There's some general top level
files, which we'll deal with in a little bit. Alright, so that's a useful and important tip.
I'm going to save the Solution as I go out. Now, Visual Studio opens, and of course, we're not open in
Unreal. It will say things are missing, because you deleted a load of caches and you'll
start to notice it building up other things, as I said before. So, that's specificly
if you have Visual Studio program problems, right-click, Generate Visual Studio project files,
and it will add some stuff into Intermediate and make it all work for you. Cool!
So, let's get our repository setup now! Unreal is
loading in the background. That's fine, that doesn't prohibit us from going along into SourceTree.
Here's my previous repository for the previous game. What I want is a new
repository. You can get that from File, and Clone or New. Now, what we are
actually doing is creating a repository of git type, not Mercurial, we're going to use Git,
and then, just select the folder. So, repos and I'm going to
select my top-level folder, not the 03_BuildingEscape subfolder. I'm going to keep everything
tracked, in this Source Control System. You'll understand what all that
means, by the way, in a little bit. That was my Editor popping up! But what I want to do now is just turn
this whole BuildingEscape folder into a database that can track my changes. So, you select the folder,
and it's going to bookmark it on the left as 03_BuildingEscape, so it'll appear on
the left-hand side, like that, and I'm just going to say Create!
And pretty much nothing is going to happen, by the way, but let's go back to the
folder, when it's finished, and take a look and see what's actually changed. Upper level
.git. If you're not showing hidden files, of course you go, View, Hidden
Items. Now, if you're on a Mac, then you just need to do Google for "show hidden files
mac", and the instructions that come up
here about typing or pasting this into Terminal will work, but you've also got to read about
Launch Finder. Alright, so the .git folder is your indication
that the repository is ready to go. That is a folder that has a load of stuff
in it. At the moment it's tiny, but it will grow quite rapidly as we start to track all our changes.
So, this is it! Now, right now that this is saying... By the way,
I've got my settings as a Tree View, you can have a Flat List, it doesn't really matter.
Flat List splits view staging, something like that is going to give you a view
something like this! And this is saying, these are all the files that I can see, i.e. everything has changed
since last commit, because we haven't committed, we haven't saved anything, we haven't got a starting
point. The problem with this right now is, it's including all the Intermediate folders
or Saved folders, and
a load of other stuff that we don't want. Alright, so we need to exclude all that
stuff we talked about excluding, in the previous lecture.
As a recap, these are the folders that we need to exclude. We're not seeing derived data
cache yet but we'll put it in because it will come up eventually.
So, we want to ignore these big folders. How are we going to do it? Well, let me show you an
easy way using SourcTree. Select just one of the folders you want,
like this BuildingEscape/Intermediate. You can go to Actions and Ignore.
This will be available if it's the first time you've done it, and you can say Ignore
Everything Beneath BuildingEscape/Intermediate
OK, and then just click OK. Now, what that'll do is, it'll make this guy here,
called a .gitignore file. Now, you can either continue
to add to that the other files, by clicking into it in say Notepad or Text Edit on a Mac
and then editing it. Look what we want to do is make it, rather than being
specific to Building Escape, why don't we make it like this. Intermediate,
forward-slash Intermediate. That's fine! If we put a
star on, that says ignore all directories called Intermediate, so let's
do that. I'll do that in alphabetical order.
*/Build */
Binaries */Intermediate. Now, if you're not sure,
go back to your slides. */DeriveDataCache I'm doing it
in alphabetical order, just for simplicity.
*/Intermediate and */Saved.
For this purpose of a .gitignore, this is what you need. Once you've saved a file,
back into your source control. When you add this file or stage the file,
like that with a tick, have a look through your list of things, and you'll find that
there's a lot of start content but there's not more Intermediate. In fact, there's none of those things we don't want.
OK, the final thing we want to get rid of is the StarterContent
Pack again. You can use the Ignore, actions ignore if you like.
Ignore Everything Beneath BuildingEscape/Content/
StarterContent, and that'll add that line to the .gitignore. You can see it in
here, back in your Text Edit. Now, I will leave the fully qualified path here, because it's
only for this project, this time, that I want to choose to ignore the starter content, because
it's large. So, whereas we may be tempted to
reuse all this Unreal generated stuff at the top, and by the way, you can just annotate
that as Unreal generated files,
like this. Now, if you think that that's not
clear enough, you can just get some more hashes or something, it's entirely up to you
how you stylize this. You know, something like this.
Alright, # Unreal Generated Files#. Hashes
work as comments in these ignore files, and then, we're going to want one more type of
file, of course, which is if we look in here carefully we'll find that we have this
VC.db file. Now, remember that that VC.db file, which resides
in here, is 58 Megabytes and is reproducible and we don't want it.
OK. So again, you can do this lots of ways. One way is to use the Actions,
Ignore, but make sure though that your .gitignore files is
closed in your Text Editor, because you don't want to start having
two different things editing it. So, what do we want to ignore?
Things with this file extension, OK. So, you do that and then if you
look through, you'll find that that VC.db files is no longer there, and that your
.gitignore contains, if you re-add it, it
contains *.db. So, this is kind of doing things for you. If you want to
annotate this as a Visual Studio database file, you might want to.
In fact, *.db is dangerous, that's saying ignore anything
with a .db on the end. Well, that's too onerous, we specifically want
VC.db. So, I am going to finally go back into here, I'm going to copy
my comment at the top, I'm going to say Visual Studio
Generated Files here. Now, you can always add more things to ignore later,
so we don't
need to go nuts. We can save that file back into the source control,
make sure that any changes to this .gitignore have been noticed
by it, so you may need to un-stage it and re-stage it. There you go!
And now, it will not have, specifically, the VC.db
file, so we're only left with the stuff that we actually
care about and that is it. Finally we stage all
this stuff, which is like saying, I want to put you in a .zip. We're going to call it Initial
Commit and you'd click Commit. Now, in my case I'm not going to do that right now, but that's what I want you to do.
OK, so I want you to make your first commit. Catch up with
what I did in this video. Get your .gitignore file working. Mine is attached
to the first lecture of the section. Add and stage all your files or just
click the little checkbox that stages all your files, and then, celebrate entering this new
world of version control. You're not supposed to fully understand what is going on here, what I'm wanting
is for that to happen in context, so go ahead and do that now and I'll show you what
I do when you come back. So, welcome back! Here we are,
everything's ticked and staged. I'm actually not going to call mine Initial Commit. I'm going to call mine
a slightly more boring name, which is BE05 for Building Escape
video number 5, Your First .gitignore for Unreal.
I'm just naming it sequentially, according to the videos, but you might want to call
yours Initial Commit, or you can start naming yours after the videos like this, it's up to you. Click
Commit. Now, the only difference you're going to see is that you're only going to have one commit. I've
got a few more because I've been doing things. Before this, I've been
keeping track of all the other videos that I've made, so as time goes on,
you'll see things like Initial Committ 1, 2, 3, 4 OK, so these are just snapshots, and you
might want to name them after the videos. So that's it, you've made a
snapshot, and what this means is, you can go back here in future point in
time and recover your work as it was. So, that's it for now!
We have our project setup, we're only storing what we need to store, and you are under version
control, so we can finally open Unreal and start safely doing things, knowing we can get back to
this vanilla starting state!