Welcome to Getting
to Know Unreal Editor! In this video, we're going to look at why changes to the
start scene aren't tracked in our source control, be arranging
a simple set of windows to work with, we'll be moving around in a 3D Viewport,
setting up our start map, and committing our work, so that we feel
comfortable, using simple 3D manipulations and saving our work. So, see you in there!
So now, we've got our first opportunity to actually play around inside the Unreal
Editor. Bear in mind, we're in something called the minimal default level here,
Minimal Default OK. And remember that you can go to Settings and then
Project Settings and Maps & Modes, and it will show you that that minimum default
is in the startup content. Now, remember we ignored starter content, because it's a
large amount of data. So any changes we make in here, for instance I click on the chair
and get the Translate Tool, which you can access with the W key, if it doesn't come up for you
and move it up. If I now Save All,
from File, Save All, and go and have a look at my Source Control, I'll actually see that
nothing has changed. And the reason that nothing has changed is because we're not tracking changes
in this scene. So, the first thing we're going to need to do is make ourselves a new scene or
level. I'm going to use those words interchangeably, I'm afraid, but you'll see them used interchangeably. It says
Level here, but you'll also get the
concept of the word scene. So, ignore any SourceTree updates for me for the moment!
So, let's do that! Let's go ahead and make a new level! There it is!
I'm going to go for default. I want this sky map and that piece of
ground texture. I'm going to not bother saving any changes to the minimum default, and I'm going to be
here. And then, as we've done before, I'm going to save
this, Save As. Now, this is where I get to give it a name, so My Map.
We could call it MyMap, that's fine, or NewMap. NewMap will be fine!
So, NewMap is a reasonable name! That's the name of the level. There
it is, NewMap, when I hover over it! And now that that's been saved,
of course, you need to go to your Project Settings, Maps & Modes, and make
sure that this NewMap is the one that both the game would start with
and the Editor would start with. So, make those changes Project Settings, Maps & Modes,
and then, next time you load this, we'll be back here which is cool! Now, if
I just exit Unreal, to be sure of the changes, and then, look in SourceTree; if I wait a minute, we've got some
Uncommitted Changes. And it's found that
the DefaultEngine.ini file, a couple of changes in it. Look it's detected them for us, it's changed the
Editor and game default map, which is what we did in the interface, but also, we've got this
binary file that we can't see the details of, called NewMap.umap, so
that's what starts to happen when we make changes, which is pretty cool!
So, let's dive back into our project
and just give you a quick tour of the Editor, and then I'm going to leave you to
play around. Now, before I start the tour of the editor, look here inside the
Viewport you've got a little question mark. Click on it, it's going to give you a
crib sheet. So, it'll tell you that the Left Mouse Button plus drag up
and down, It will actually trolly around. It's a bit weird, it's like pushing a supermarket trolly but it'll
tell you that. It'll tell you that you can rotate left and right, like
this with the Left Mouse Button, etc. So, just go through those, try using the
Right Mouse Button, the Left Mouse Button, and various things. OK, the Mouse
Wheel will roll you in and out. Also, you can hold down the Right Mouse Button and use W,
S, A, D, also Q and E first person controls. When you're
holding down the Right Mouse Button, you can change the speed. If I roll my Mouse Wheel down, I'm
doing that now, then I've set the speed to very low, and as I roll the Mouse Wheel up,
the speed increases OK. So, bear in mind what current speed you've got
set, and I want you to get really comfortable with just moving around. And the other
thing is, just pop a prop from the Content Browser.
So, find your Content Browser, go to StarterContent, if you're
right at the beginning of the ContentBrowser, you might need to get a second pane up in
here. Content, StarterContent, Props.
Eventually you'll find the chair, for example. Let's put the chair in the scene, you'll notice it just sticks
to the floor. Let me show you one more movement mode. So, we can yes,
sure we can move around the chair, with all of these controls I've just shown you, at various different speeds, but
this is a Meyer style control. Now, if you click on it, click F
to focus that, and then, if you hold down the Alt Key, the left Alt Key is what I'm
holding down now, as I move the Left Mouse Button look, I'm rotating around this object.
And I can go in and out, either by holding down the Right Mouse Button, that's the smoothest
way, or by using the Mouse Wheel, which can be jerky and also has a kind of minimum distance.
So, Right Mouse Button hold down, forward and back, left Mouse
Button around. Now, all of this time, I'm holding down the Alt Key, that's the key here!
You could do the same on the floor. You could hit the F key, to focus on the floor, after you've selected it,
hold down the Alt Key, holding down Alt now... The Left Mouse Button rotates
around, the Right Mouse Button moves in and out. That's a fantastic way of
focusing on a given object and then rotating around and seeing it from all angles.
OK, so there's your crib sheet again, in the Viewport there. What I want you to do
now is, go and have a good play with the Viewport and get comfortable just
placing a few objects on this single ground tile, and just maybe build up a
really simple little scene here, with a chair and a bench and whatever. And
I'll see you when you come back!
Cool, welcome back! So, to bring things into the scene, just show you a few
more tricks. You could say, drag a rock in here. The blue arrow constrains
in this plane, the green arrow constrains in that plane. One more thing is that you can
constrain in two planes at a time by clicking, it's very tricky, but
right in here, if I click there in the little intersection of the two, then I'm
now moving it in this ground plane, which is handy. There are also some other
things to tell you, which is that, up here, you've got snapping tools. For instance, here this
is the position, even snap value. It's set to
10 at the moment, which is 10 units which in Unreal, by default, is 10
centimeters, so every time I move the chair it snaps to 10 centimeters. If I was to increase that to
100, it would jump up a meter. So, be aware of that snap value
for both the Position, the Rotation, but also the Scale. You can
have a Snap Value for Scale. Now, you can switch between these tools with W, E, and R keys,
so it's worth keeping your left hand in that position. When you're scaling, you can scale on all
axis by dragging the middle cube, and then, you can scale on a
given axis, making a very strange looking chair, by using any of these
boxes there. OK, so it's pretty consistent and
simple to use actually. I quite like it! That's the way that you move things
around in the Editor. You have X, Y, and Z. X and Y are in the
ground planes, Z is up and down. You have a whole bunch of other options you should be
aware that are there. You can click here to see things like the frames per second and various other
things, that little down arrow at the top-left of the Viewport. You can choose Perspective or
Top, Bottom, Left, Right, etc. so you can get these kind of wireframe views.
At the top-right you have something that shows you a four way Viewport, which lets you see
simultaneously four different viewpoints. So, I'm seeing the chair and the rock from above
here, and then, I'm seeing from the left on one side and above in the front.
You see, pretty cool! And this can be really hand, when say, positioning things!
And then, you can get back out by just maximizing any of the viewports, say the 3D
Viewport. So, there's that, your snap options... You've got
here, notice the shortcuts Alt 2, 3, 4, etc. let
you change into like Wireframe and other views, that we'll be using a lot more through the course. Lighting
complexity, pretty cool stuff! You generally want to leave it in Lit, unless we have any particular reason
not to. And then, the Show menu lets you turn off various things, which are all
very complex and it's going to be fantastic fun unveiling how all this works!
But look, that's the essence of creating yourself a new level and putting some
of the basic things in it and moving around in it and focusing on things and moving them.
So, you have the very basics, so congratulations with that! It just remains to close
this, saving the map as we go.
I'm going to go and grab hold of the name of this video.
We'll just make it up as I go, so here we go! Uncommitted
changes, we have the map, it's what we've worked on, and the engine file. I'm going to stage
those like this. It's BE06 is the name of my
video or BuildingEscape_06.
BE06 Getting to
Know Unreal's Editor. OK!
Don't worry about pushing things to the Internet, at the moment, unless you know what you're doing, and just commit that!
Great! So, we've not got a snapshot and if I wanted to,
I could go back to where we were before, but let's not do any of that, for now, because we haven't really
made much progress
Anyway, I'll see you in the next video.