So. welcome to A Pointer's Primer! In this video. you're about to meet
pointers for he first time. in the next video. So. I want to prepare
you for that. because they're a little different and we didn't cover them in the previous section
because we didn't need them. The clue that you're using a
pointer is basically. when you see a star next to a type. Obviously.
not a star as in a multiplication but when it's next to type or a variable.
You'll see an example in a minute. Pointers are simply memory addresses.
your pointer tells the system to go somewhere else to find what it's looking for.
So. you have to follow the pointer to the object in question or the
function in question. in order to actually do anything with it.
So why. why would you even bother using pointers? Well. the benefit is it
saves you from moving things around in memory. Say you've got a huge object. a
building a large part of a piece of terrain. any complex game object.
you don't want to be moving that thing around and copying it from one place
in memory to another. So. it saves you from doing that. you refer to things by reference
rather than by value. There is a disadvantage. it's that you can lose
control of the data. The moment I've issued a pointer to something. how about if there's
another pointer to that same thing somewhere else? Who's in control of that data?
You could lose track of the data. You could lose track of the object.
Maybe both the pointers disappear and now you no longer know how to get to the thing? Maybe
two things try and change it. at the same time? So there are potential disadvantages. but plenty of ways of managing
it. So. let's look at the syntax of these things then!
Here's a piece of code! FActorComponentTickFunction*! So. F is just that
prefix that Unreal likes to use. ActorComponentTickFunction*
ThisTickFunction. What's that all about? Well. here we have a
pointer called ThisTickFunction. and it's a pointer to something of type
FActorComponentTickFunction*. And why
do you need a type with a pointer. if a pointer is just a memory address? It's basically for checking so that the
compiler can make sure that you're being consistent. and that when you get
to that address. it's expecting to find something of the type on the left.
Now. that's equivalent to putting a space before the star. like that. And it's also
equivalent to putting the start tightly up against the actual variable on the right-
hand side there. OK. now we're going to go with the first syntax. because that's Unreal
standard. but you will see all three used. So. you have to get used to ignoring where the white
space is there and understand that when those two things are together. with a star between them.
then the thing on the right is a pointer of type the thing on the
left. So. all three statements are equivalent. we use the first. In all cases.
ThisTickFunction is a pointer. and in all three cases the type of the object pointed to is
the thing on the left. OK. Cool!
So. let's talk about the arrow Accessor Operator!
So. imagine we have something called SomeActor; which is a pointer to an actor.
So. AActor* tells us there's a pointer to an actor. and the thing
is called SomeActor; the pointer is called some actor. So. the AActor*
class has a method called GetName(). So.
that syntax there * SomeActor; when you put the star on the left
of SomeActor; on its own. "de-references" is the pointer. That means it goes
to the memory address pointed to by SomeActor;. And then.
as a whole. * SomeActor; acts as if it was just the actor.
so it "de-references" it. it follows the pointer. So. you could
write (*SomeActor) in brackets just to help the compiler treat that as one.
dot GetName();. And that would be the same as following the pointer
over to the memory address. where some actor lives. and then calling the GetName(); method
on it. But that's some more cumbersome. so there's an operator
called the arrow operator. shown there. which allows you to follow and access it
all in one. So. we can access the method by
saying. SomeActor - right chevron
GetName(). So remember. when you're dealing with pointers. and you'll
be able to see that in Visual Studio by hovering. and the intellisense will pop up and show that the result
of the function is a pointer. We'll see that shortly. If you're using pointers. you use
the arrow operator. If you're using the objects directly. then you use the dot operator.
So. what I want you to do as a challenge. as a result of this video. is just to
simply go and do some more reading about pointers. You don't need to understand them in full
depth right now. We're going to do what I call a spiral syllabus. which means that we're going to
have a quick look. like we just did at them. Then. we're going to go use them a few times. so
you're seeing them in context. and then. we're going to loop back and loop back. as we need to. to build your knowledge
of pointers as necessary. Bear in mind. every time you turn a light switch on. you may not know exactly
how that lighting system works and all the details about how electrons
and photons are produces in the light filament. but you can still use a light!
So. you can still use pointers. without knowing exactly how they work. but as you start to use them in a
more nuanced way and start to do more custom things with them. you're going to need to understand them better
and better. So let yourself not fully understand them this time around.o.k.
Where can you go? Well. here's one good place. www.cplusplus.com/ that lot!
And that will take you to a brief tutorial on pointers. I'd like you to share
your understanding of pointers in the discussions. Now. there's lots of different levels of people on this course.
Some of you are super advanced and you know this inside out. and some of you are just
programming for the first time. so I'd just like you to be brave enough to share what you've understood of pointers and what stil
confuses you. It also helps me. of course. insert content as necessary.
And in the next video. I want you to keep an eye out for
pointer in PositionReport.cpp. It's going to be a file we're going to make.
the class we're going to make in the next video. And you'll find a pointer in there somewhere. Have a little
look. see if you can find where that is. and maybe then come back and say. hey
I found it. it's this thing. and sneaky sneaky little thing in there! OK cool!
So. I'm going to see you in the next video. and I will look forward to
introducing you further to pointers!
=======
So, welcome to A Pointer's Primer! In this video, you're about to meet
pointers for he first time, in the next video. So, I want to prepare
you for that, because they're a little different and we didn't cover them in the previous section
because we didn't need them. The clue that you're using a
pointer is basically, when you see a star next to a type. Obviously,
not a star as in a multiplication but when it's next to type or a variable.
You'll see an example in a minute. Pointers are simply memory addresses,
your pointer tells the system to go somewhere else to find what it's looking for.
So, you have to follow the pointer to the object in question or the
function in question, in order to actually do anything with it.
So why, why would you even bother using pointers? Well, the benefit is it
saves you from moving things around in memory. Say you've got a huge object, a
building a large part of a piece of terrain, any complex game object,
you don't want to be moving that thing around and copying it from one place
in memory to another. So, it saves you from doing that, you refer to things by reference
rather than by value. There is a disadvantage, it's that you can lose
control of the data. The moment I've issued a pointer to something, how about if there's
another pointer to that same thing somewhere else? Who's in control of that data?
You could lose track of the data. You could lose track of the object.
Maybe both the pointers disappear and now you no longer know how to get to the thing? Maybe
two things try and change it, at the same time? So there are potential disadvantages, but plenty of ways of managing
it. So, let's look at the syntax of these things then!
Here's a piece of code! FActorComponentTickFunction*! So, F is just that
prefix that Unreal likes to use. ActorComponentTickFunction*
ThisTickFunction. What's that all about? Well, here we have a
pointer called ThisTickFunction, and it's a pointer to something of type
FActorComponentTickFunction*. And why
do you need a type with a pointer, if a pointer is just a memory address? It's basically for checking so that the
compiler can make sure that you're being consistent, and that when you get
to that address, it's expecting to find something of the type on the left.
Now, that's equivalent to putting a space before the star, like that. And it's also
equivalent to putting the start tightly up against the actual variable on the right-
hand side there. OK, now we're going to go with the first syntax, because that's Unreal
standard, but you will see all three used. So, you have to get used to ignoring where the white
space is there and understand that when those two things are together, with a star between them,
then the thing on the right is a pointer of type the thing on the
left. So, all three statements are equivalent, we use the first. In all cases,
ThisTickFunction is a pointer, and in all three cases the type of the object pointed to is
the thing on the left, OK. Cool!
So, let's talk about the arrow Accessor Operator!
So, imagine we have something called SomeActor; which is a pointer to an actor.
So, AActor* tells us there's a pointer to an actor, and the thing
is called SomeActor; the pointer is called some actor. So, the AActor*
class has a method called GetName(). So,
that syntax there * SomeActor; when you put the star on the left
of SomeActor; on its own, "de-references" is the pointer. That means it goes
to the memory address pointed to by SomeActor;. And then,
as a whole, * SomeActor; acts as if it was just the actor,
so it "de-references" it, it follows the pointer. So, you could
write (*SomeActor) in brackets just to help the compiler treat that as one,
dot GetName();. And that would be the same as following the pointer
over to the memory address, where some actor lives, and then calling the GetName(); method
on it. But that's some more cumbersome, so there's an operator
called the arrow operator, shown there, which allows you to follow and access it
all in one. So, we can access the method by
saying, SomeActor - right chevron
GetName(). So remember, when you're dealing with pointers, and you'll
be able to see that in Visual Studio by hovering, and the intellisense will pop up and show that the result
of the function is a pointer. We'll see that shortly. If you're using pointers, you use
the arrow operator. If you're using the objects directly, then you use the dot operator.
So, what I want you to do as a challenge, as a result of this video, is just to
simply go and do some more reading about pointers. You don't need to understand them in full
depth right now. We're going to do what I call a spiral syllabus, which means that we're going to
have a quick look, like we just did at them. Then, we're going to go use them a few times, so
you're seeing them in context, and then, we're going to loop back and loop back, as we need to, to build your knowledge
of pointers as necessary. Bear in mind, every time you turn a light switch on, you may not know exactly
how that lighting system works and all the details about how electrons
and photons are produces in the light filament, but you can still use a light!
So, you can still use pointers, without knowing exactly how they work, but as you start to use them in a
more nuanced way and start to do more custom things with them, you're going to need to understand them better
and better. So let yourself not fully understand them this time around,o.k.
Where can you go? Well, here's one good place, www.cplusplus.com/ that lot!
And that will take you to a brief tutorial on pointers. I'd like you to share
your understanding of pointers in the discussions. Now, there's lots of different levels of people on this course.
Some of you are super advanced and you know this inside out, and some of you are just
programming for the first time, so I'd just like you to be brave enough to share what you've understood of pointers and what stil
confuses you. It also helps me, of course, insert content as necessary.
And in the next video, I want you to keep an eye out for
pointer in PositionReport.cpp. It's going to be a file we're going to make,
the class we're going to make in the next video. And you'll find a pointer in there somewhere. Have a little
look, see if you can find where that is, and maybe then come back and say, hey
I found it, it's this thing, and sneaky sneaky little thing in there! OK cool!
So, I'm going to see you in the next video, and I will look forward to
introducing you further to pointers!
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1:Unreal/Section3/BE06b A Pointers Primer.srt