So. welcome to Unreals Class System! In this video. we're going to be
introducing the idea of inheritance. as it applies to programming.
Unreal's scarily powerful class system is there to be used.
It's both scary and powerful! It's huge. you can do a massive amount
with it. but you need to understand how to access it and how to navigate around it. So.
we'll be using the Class Viewer to do that. and inheritance
is for "is a" relationships. and
components are for "has a" relationships. So that's what we're going to explore! The star. by the way.
just links you to the Class View. a little bit about it in Unreal's documentation. Remember.
you can click these links in the section notes .pdf. and they should take you straight there.
OK cool. let's dive in!
So. welcome back! It's time to start actually start writing some C++
code and making it interact with things in our Unreal game. already before
we get too excited and comfortable with this pretty editor. Let's start working out how to
broaden our horizon completely. to the full idea that we
can do things in C++ and Blueprint and really take control of this wonderful engine.
Bear in mind that once you started to master C++ and how it relates to
Unreal. then in principle. you could go in and edit the source code of the engine and do pretty much anything.
So. let's start this off by talking about inheritance! Inheritance in programming
works quite like it does in terms of bloodlines in animals and in humans.
So. for example. a character in Unreal is a Pawn
and a pawn is an Actor. Let's compare that to a Dog
is a Mammal and a Mammal is an Animal. So. on the right-hand side. the Actor
and the Animal are the most general things. and you can define general behavior
Actors and Animals over there. In the middle. the Pawn and the
Mammal. they have all the shared properties of Actors and Animals. but then they go ahead and
add some more detail. like Mammals have mile. And in the case of Unreal.
Pawns are possessable and can receive control input.
And then. you go down to a Dog. which is a specialization of a Mammal and a Character. in
Unreal has the benefit of being a movable bump-able
object. like a First Person Character. for example. So. we'll see
more about that later! Unreal makes extensive use of inheritance.
It's a powerful tool if used properly. but it can be really inflexible and hard
to refactor. if you over-use it. So. in this course. we'll be sticking to two
or three levels of inheritance in our code. at the most. and trying to keep
our hierarchies what we call very flat. And then. we can use another tool
to add richer behavior. which is components. Now. components are for
"has a" relationships. For instance. the chair and the rock in my scene.
when we're finished. we will have a position reporter. We're going to add a
component up here. The same component to both of them called Position
Reporter. like that OK. So. I'm going to delete that off there for now. but I want to show you the
example. They will both have something called PositionReporter. and it will give the same behavior to both of these
things. Objects become rich through having many components.
in this model. It can be very flexible if it's used
properly. but we do need to use it properly. and we do need to know when to use inheritance and when to use
components. And the rule of thumb is. inheritance is for "is a". component is for
"has a". OK cool! So. back in Unreal. I want to show you something!
I want to show you how big and impressive Unreal's Class System is!
We go to Window. Developer Tools. and then. you have
Class Viewer. Click on that for me! I've got it Maximized. I'm also going to go to View.
Collapse All. and Filters. I'm going to
uptick Actors Only and even untick... Well. doing that will untick both
actually. So. Collapse All. Filters. not
Actors Only. This is all of the top level
objects we have in Unreal. It's huge. it's bewildering. but if you want to see
this hierarchy I just talked about. an Actor is for anything in the world that is
intractable. even a chest or a door. Coming down from Actor. there's a lot of things that come
straight off Actor. in the family tree. One of those is Pawn here.
which as you hover over it. it says it's "the base class of all actors that can be
possessed by players or AI." "They are the physical representations of players
and creatures in a level". OK. And then. you expand Pawn out and you find Character.
"Characters are Pawns that have mesh. collision. and built-in movement logic." So. you can
explore the inheritance tree here. If you want to keep it simple. you can say Actors Only.
and then that brings it down to just the Actor related things. There's still
plenty of all sorts of stuff. including like LeapMotion. which is that cool hand tracking
thing or it just goes on. and there's so much stuff! Unreal comes with so much
stuff! That's a blessing because it gives us a huge amount of capability. out of the box.
and it's also a curse because we have to understand how it works.
What I'm going to do is click on my chair. You can click on any Static Mesh Component
or any Static Mesh Object. How do I now that this is a Static Mesh Object?
Well. there's a hint here. but another that thing you could do is you could go to World
Outliner. from the Window Menu. and you'll see that all objects in the scene tell you their
type. down here. You have the world itself. some fog. and then. you have the floor.
light sources. player start position here. and then the chair
and the rock. In my case. they're both Static Mesh Actors. that means they're meshes that don't move.
they're not skeletons. and they're actors in that they're somewhat inter-actable.
So. grab a Static Mesh Actor! I'm going to use the chair. Go to Add Component. in the Details Tab
or window. and then. add a new C++ component.
It's going to be an Actor Component. because it's a Component of an Actor. and I'm just going to call it
position reporter.
because that's what it does. The chair has a Position Reporter
or just PositionReport is shorter. OK. so it has
a PositionReport. Now. there is a naming convention for
components but don't include it here. it's actually going to be you in this case. But don't
include it because Unreal will do that for you. Let's create the class!
So. what's happening here is fairly heave weight.
Unreal is doing a lot of work. it's controlling Visual Studio for us or
Xcode on the Mac. and it's creating a load of code and a lot of boiler plate.
And in a moment. we're going to be able to see that! It's going to open up in your IDE like
this. and if we drill down into Games. Buidling
Escape. Source. and then. into BuildingEscape again.
you'll see PostionReport.cpp and .h. It's made the header file for us. which is quite
bewildering. It's also made a .cpp file for us.
And there's a load of stuff in here. and it's all completely new to us. Look how it's
named things. by the way. It's called the class UPositionReport. You see over here
class. and it's kind of hidden in all of this
what we call header tool directives. And also. we've got
macros in here as well. There's a couple of different things to catch you
out. but it's put a U in. UPositionReport. so it's doing the naming for us.
OK. the header file is more scary. it's got a lot of stuff in it. The .cpp file
is quite a lot simpler. I will just tell you now that BeginPlay().
here is where you're going to want to put code that runs once at the start of the
game. and under TickComponent. this is where you're going to want to put code that runs
every frame. So. all I want you to do now. actually. is make sure that you
have created your Position Report Component. and then. what I want you to do is take a look at the
generated code. Take a brief look at the .cpp file. take an even shorter look
at that header file. but share what you recognize in the discussions.
You know. I recognize what? Maybe I recognize inheritance or maybe
you don't because you didn't grasp that. or maybe you recognize some methods or
whatever. What do you recognize and what do you not recognize. in there. that's really
weird? And what we're going to do is we're going to explore the files. in a moment.
in the rest of this video and then a little bit more in the next video as well.
OK welcome back!
So I just want to talk you through very briefly. then in the next video. we're going to dive in and actually start coding.
So. let's start with the header file. as this gets cut and pasted to the top
of the .cpp. as all header files do. So. here it's saying
"// fill out your copyright notice in the Description in the Project Settings." Let me show you were you do that
in Unreal. Settings. Project Settings. and then you've
got. over here. you've got Company Name. I'll put mine in. Embrace IT Ltd.
Company Distinguished Name. now that means it's unique.
Homepage. Support Contact. and then. further down here you can also fill out copyright
information. OK. "Copyright" I'm going to say "Ben
Tristem 2016" or something OK. Now. that won't immediately update
your code. because your code was already generated. but that's the Copyright Notice
filled out. if you want to do yours. #pragma once. it puts it in for us. it does a
couple of big hash includes. This thing here is telling
the Unreal Header Tool how to
work with this class OK. so there's going to be a lot of this stuff in
Unreal C++. We want to just look past it. for now. and try and see the  wood for the trees. Also.
ignore this thing here. But what we've got is a classical position report
that inherits from Actor Component. OK.
GENERATED_BODY(). we need to leave it there again. That tells Unreal's Header Tool to do some
magic. Then. we just have the declaration of the
constructor. a declaration of BeginPlay(). It has this virtual word. which means that
we're not actually saying exactly how it works here. We're going to be responsible for that
somewhere else. but we'll talk about that later. And then. you have the declaration of a Tick Component.
Over in the .cpp. it's less scary somehow
because you just come in here and this is the constructor. It sets it up and says this thing ticks.
Things that tick. by the way. means this bit of code will be run every single frame.
on every item that ticks. So. if you want to sleep components or stop them from
taking up resources. we turn that off. We'll look at that later. This here
is a method called BeginPlay(). which
is a part of the UPositionReport class. and this super
BeginPlay() says. do whatever happens up the stream. up the
inheritance tree. Whatever is supposed to happen in the things that I
inherited from. the Actor Component. do that first. the
default behavior. and then. here on line 24 of my code. this is
where we put our new code. And the same with the TickComponent. it runs the super behavior.
the behavior for the things up the inheritance tree. we leave the engine to do that. Then. we put
our own code in here. So that's it. that is an overview of what
happens! I'm actually going to close everything down right now. and then. I'm going to make my commit.
saving the level. Over into my SourceTree.
make a commit. and then. we'll start coding in the next level. So. once it notices. it
should notice the things that have changed. You know. I'll be able to save those. commit.
and go from there. but I won't do that live with you. because I like to do a couple of things just after
the video. to make sure that everything is in order before I commit and finalize the video.
But OK. I'll leave it with you. you make your commit. and I will see you soon!
Just a quick bonus video. for those of you who are
using a Mac. If you are on Windows. you can skip past
this to the next video. no problem. So. if you
ever see this kind of build error in your build.
in Xcode. then the chances are you have got the wrong
scheme select up here. next to the Play and Stop Button. So. if you
scroll down. you want the BuildingEscape scheme selected and then My Mac
and that is the one you want. So. just select BuildingEscape
and then hit Command B. Command B is Build or
find Build in the menu. I almost never do that. I always build with
Command B. but Product. Build is the other option and that should
work just find. But if you try and build the engine. it won't work in Xcode.
This is also a good time to have a look at our .gitignore file for Xcode.
So. I'm going to open up SourceTree here. and you can see we've got a few more unstaged
files that it's talking about. And if we
had built this Xcode project for ourselves and we wanted to track it. we'd still want to ignore
some of these files. For example. the scuserdata. we don't want that.
That's a setup that's particular to our machines and
we wouldn't want to share it with other developers. for example. So. we can click.
right-click ignore. and go down to custom pattern. And what
I'm going to do is do a **/
xcuserdata. I'll make sure.
I have to spell it correctly. And this basically says. anywhere where you find
a folder called xcuserdata. no matter how many levels deep
in the folder hierarchy. just ignore everything beneath it. So. if we hit
OK. and you can see that those files disappear. And then.
in this case we want to ignore the xc workspace as
well. because we can generate
that automatically from Unreal. So. I'm just going to ignore this exact
file name and hit OK. And we just need to
stage our .gitignore and we can do the appropriate
commit. I'll leave that to you to do.