Hey hey!
So. in this video. we're going to use GetOwner() to find the
component's owner. So. this script that's going to be reporting position.
we're going to use GetOwner() to find out what object that's on. We're going to find
out that *AActor is pointer to an actor. and a pointer is a whole
new concept. which we'll start to get used to and will fully define here.
Use that operator there to access methods through pointers.
that's instead of the dot operator. We will use GetName() to find
the object's actual name. We're going to use %s as a format
operator for strings. which is again a brand new thing. and finally
we're going to see how to use star to dereference pointers. And all of that's going to come
tougher to allow us to. inside Unreal. have the
code report here. the actual object that it's on. So. let's dive in and see
how that's going to work!
So. I don't know about you. but I'm getting a bit bored of starting this scene looking
in the wrong direction. So. what I'm going to do is just go into the 3D Viewport
here and click on the Player Start
Object. which is here. You'll see just a capsule there. And then. I'm going to move
it so that it's facing my objects. and you want to just do the same for yours. so that it's
facing all the objects in your scene. And then. I'm going to hit the
E Key on the keyboard. in order to
rotate that around. in my case 180 degrees.
so that the blue arrow is pointing toward your scene. Just have a look. click
play. there you go! So. we're starting facing our objects now!
OK. that's the simple tweak. Alright. so the challenge we've got here
is that the position reporting component is on
both of these objects. but it's saying the word chair on both. What I want to do is to actually read
the name of the objects. as per the actual
World Outliner. I'm going to actually add the World Outliner from Window. World Outliner.
Pop it over here with the rest of these windows. to save
screen space. and then. you can see that these things are called SM_Chair and SM_Rock. Actually. if you
hover over them. you'll see that they've got another number appended on the end. SM_Chair
_5 and SM_Rock_8. It just depends how many
iterations of these things the engine thinks it's had. so don't worry too much about
those. but it's actual name may just have an extra number on the back.
OK. so let's go ahead and edit this code!
So. click on either of them. You can go to PositionReport.h. right-click. and say Open
PositionReport.h. like that. on my screen. and that's going to be a very easy way
to pop over to Visual Studio. It'll go to the Header File but we want to go to the
Implementation file. and it's here we want to learn how to read the name of the object.
So. a bunch of new juicy C++ concepts in here!
The method that we're going to need is GetOwner(). OK. so you
start typing GetOwner(). you'll get that. Now. when you hover. it says it's a
public : Actor *. Ooh. what's the star?
New component colon colon get owner const. OK. so that's a
little unusual. It's going to return an AActor. i.e. an
Actor. AActor because Actor is derived from Actor. it's part
of the Actor class. So. Unreal's naming convention is that if it's derived from the
Actor class. then it starts with A. so AActor *.
Now. the star means a pointer. so it's actually going to return. This
method. the method is called GetOwner(). but it's fully
qualified here. Oh. I forgot to do that. Hang on. let me just hover over GetOwner() again.
GetOwner(). hover.
OK. so the
method name is GetOwner() but it's fully qualified with the class name there. which is UActorComponent.
but it's going to return a pointer to an Actor. I actually prefer
to pout the star with the Actor. and Unreal's coding convention is that you put the star. the
pointer. with the Actor. What is a pointer? Well. I'm going to go over
pointers several. many many times in this course. So for now. all you really need to know
is that a pointer is a memory address. it's telling the
system where to go to find the actual value. So. there's two types of things really.
There's an actual value stored in memory. where you are right now. and then. there's
a pointer to go somewhere else. And we use a lot of pointers in Unreal.
because if you have very large object. imagine you have a big terrain or also a big
building in your game and you're hurtling down the road. you don't want to be moving these huge
pieces of memory around. you just want to deal with the by reference
or by pointer. Now. there's a difference between a reference and a pointer. but it's subtle and we won't
get into that just now. But what I want you to notice here. it's a constant. it's a
getter. We've seen all that before. the only thing we haven't seen is the star. OK.
because we've got a star. because it's a pointer to a method.
we need to not use dot. Dot will not work to go and get the properties
off that. OK. what we need to do is go minus
dash like that. and this is the equivalent to dot.
but we use the minus dash operator. like that. when we are looking
through a pointer. OK. you're just going to have to get used to that.
It's very good because it helps us know where we are. OK. now I'm going to type
the word name. and that'll help me find GetName(). Now. what does that return? It
returns an FString. not a pointer to an FString but an actual FString.
And then. you've got a class that it comes from. but
the name of the method is GetName() const. so it's another getter. So. I'm going
to click GetName. put the brackets in. and at this
point when I hover. I'm seeing that what I get out of this whole thing is an
FString. Now. we've seen FStrings before. Remember you had FText. which we don't
generally use. when we're presenting things to the user. and FStrings. which are mutable
or changeable objects that we use behind the scenes. So. this is an FString
coming back. How are we going to get this FString out to the screen? Well.
I'm going to define... In fact. I'm going to challenge you to simply define a
variable called ObjectName() of type FString.
and then. finish this line that we're on off. Ohh. we're on
off. [Laughs] So. I want you to create a variable to type FString and finish off this line.
Go ahead. pause the video. and do that now!
OK welcome back! So. no challenge slide there. just
to keep you on your toes. What we're going to do is FString.
ObjectName = that. and then. of course we need our
trusty semicolon. So. with any luck this will be storing the object
name as an FString in this variable. The question comes now. how do we
actually get this into this output. Well. it's a little
subtle. Again. Unreal doesn't make our lives too easy!
We need to use something called a format operator.
Now. you can find the documentation for all of this in the same place that I linked
you to before. If I just go into the slide deck and look back here.
where I gave you in the previous video a link to this
blog about printing messages to yourself. If you look down this. you'll
find an example of using these format operators. I believes in here.
So. this is the pattern we're going to use.
Now. there's a note here that strings are wanted as
T plus Char *. we say. but TChar* by the
log. so use *FString(). Oh. we're just beginning! What's going on here. more complexity?
OK. so we've done something like this! We said GetOwner
GetName. and that gave us an FString. What we need to do is put a star in front. which
what we need to do is put a star in front of this. Now bear in mind
This is not dereferencing. which you'll learn about later. because we're inside a macro
here. this is something called an overloaded operator. That means
C++ has been told to do something different with a * in this instance.
It has an effect that's a bit like de-referencing. in it allows this macro to get
to the characters of the string that we need. So that's enough said for now. there's a
video coming up later about pointers and references. But for now just understand
that if you're trying to use a string you need a star in front of it.
So let's bring all that together and see how that's going to work. So. we have an FString here.
which is a dynamically sizable string. It's a pointer to a place
in memory that contains that. We'll go through pointers in more detail later. Let's
just make it work! ("Position report for. and I'm going to put
%s. which is where I want the chair to go. I'm going to come outside of those brackets.
put a comma. and now I'm going to say
*ObjectName); If I don't say star. I'm going to get a strange error.
You want to see the error? Let's see the error! Let's build it. because it's better you see this
error. so that you recognize in the future. No success! What's
wrong? It's complaining. where's the line? Ah. you see it's pretty
nasty. because the lines of these errors.
none of them are actually about this file here. and that is because
these macros. used in the most general sense are
causing the problems. OK. so you're just going to have to be
careful here. when you do a log. that you give it a dereference pointer
like that. because it's pretty hard to debug. OK. so let's
go ahead and let it run! That's built now! Now. let's go back to Unreal
and play. Ah hah! Position report for SM_Chair_
5. There are those underscores I was talking about and position report for SM_
Rock_8. Success! We've managed to get C++ to tell us what the
name of the objects are. according to their names here in the World
Outliner. with their fully qualified names with the instance number on the end.
Alright. so that is pretty cool! Let's just have a quick recap of the code!
What we did is. we got owner but that is a pointer.
If we look at GetOwner() here. that returns a pointer to an
Actor. AActor *. I like to put the star before the space
but you can do either. it returns a point to an Actor.
Then. we looked through that pointer to go and get to the GetName() method.
which returned a FString.
And then. we put that into something called ObjectName. and then we
specified ObjectName over here with a star and we used
%s which is a format operator. So. a lot of stuff in there! We're going to reuse this
again and again and again. But that is your pattern. it's in the docs.
and good luck enjoy! And I'd like to hear in the discussions whether you're
completely bamboozled. whether that's simple because you're a C++ pro. or
what your reaction to that is! See you soon!