So, welcome back! Let's look at how we're going to do this! We're going to want another
string, so I'm going to make the outline of this code for you, and then, I'm going to ask you
to actually fill it in. So, we're going to have an FString and I'm going to call it
somehting like ObjectPos, and
then, I'm just going to call it "X = something...
...for now. Y = something else,
etc" OK. It doesn't matter, this is going to
be replaced by some code that you're going to write in a little bit. Great!
So, I've made an FString, I have assigned it like that. Now,
I want to show you something else. I'm just going to switch this around a little bit, ("%s")
is going to be the ObjectName, is at ") and then, we're going to have another
format operator %s. And the way this works is, it
then goes and has a look for the second thing that matches the correct type.
Now, of course, this is this dereferenced ObjectPos, just because of the
way that this text macro works. It wants this * TChar
thing, which we have to get to by de-referencing the
string, so we just have to deal with these complexities for now. I think that the details of
exactly what all this means and pointers and references will become clear, in context,
as we go through the course. I don't think I want to give you a massive primer on pointers,
etc. right now, because it's just not necessary in order to use
this stuff and make some progress. So, what I'm doing here is relatively
simple. I've added another line, with exactly the same pattern as the line above, but I put a string literally
in there, and then, I'm just adding a second format operator and a second
thing on the end. Let's just build, make sure this works,
and then, I've got a little challenge of you, of course. So, we run the game
and it says SM_Chair is X something Y something, etc. This is the type of
output I'm going to want you to achieve from the end of the challenge, but, of course, instead of X
something Y something, etc. I'm going to want it to actually point out the position that you
would see, if you were to click on either of your objects, and then, go into
the Details tab and have a look at Transform Location. And
it's all in centimeters, you can see this position of the chair and the
rock vary, in my case. So, I want that coming out on the Console,
OK, and that's going to be the end of the challenge. Let me show you the challenge, specifically!
So, I want  you to explore the API using dot and forward slash.
Just before I carry on, let me explain what I mean by this just for the real beginners. So, what
I'm saying to you is, instead of my string literal, I'll get you started.
I want you to say, GetOwner() dot something or
that something, and I want you to go through, using where appropriate,
this operator when it's a pointer, like Actor*.
And when it isn't a pointer, I want you to just use the dot, and I want you to
go through exploring the API using those two operators. See if you can get the
obect's location X, Y, Z.
Run and see if it prints on the output log.
Now, I've got a hint for you. Three hints actually, so if you don't want the hints then just
pause the video now, otherwise I'm going to give you three hints, especially if you're on Xcode. It's harder if you're on Xcode,
because the completion isn't fuzzy. What that means is, if you type the word transform,
for instance, then it's not going to come up. You're going to have to start
right, and the way to start right is with the word Get, the word Get. These things are
the getters. So, both the transform and the location, when you're looking for the right
method, start with the word Get. And the second hint is, you'll need to use
.ToString(), otherwise what you end up won't be a string at the end.
So, see if you can get all that put together, in the right order, and actually get this location
logging to the Console, and if you manage it, share your victory in the discussions!
Cool welcome back! So, let's take a look at the
logic of this! So, putting myself in your shoes, what are
we looking for? So firstly, we have GetOwner().
Hover over hit, we can see that it's a pointer to an actor, Actor star, therefor we need this operator.
OK cool! Now, let's see if we can find something like
the transform. What have we got? GetTransform, that sounds good!
So, it's a method because it says Get. Hover over it and see what it says!
What does this return? This returns something called an fTransform
OK, but it's not a pointer to an fTransform, so we go dot now to
see what's there. Now, let's go find out, at this stage, what an fTransform is.
Google for "ftransform unreal"!
FTransform there, and it'll tell you what it is, OK.
What is this thing? It looks like it's a
struct that contains three different things here, a rotation, a
translation, and a scale OK. So, it is the translation that
we're going to want to get off this. Let's continue exploring in Visual Studio, so dot.
Now, t r a n s... What have we got? TransformPosition.
That sounds pretty good! If you're not sure what you're looking for, go back to Unreal
and have a look in here! What have we got? Transform location OK! Well, they're
interchangeable using the word location and position, but
that's pretty close to me. I think we want to try that! So, dot...
You could try location... GetLocation GetTransform GetLocation
or do we want to go position? TransformPosition
hmm tricky! Which one are you going to use
and why? Well, let's try GetLocation and see what comes
back. Hover over it, it's a method.
What does it return? An FVector, well that should work!
An FVector, we're going to need to go ToString, because we can't
just put a vector straight into this guy. So, let's
try that! See if GetLocation works! At this point, yes you could go look at the
manual and see for GetLocation(), or if you're not sure of which of these alternatives is going to work,
it will be easy enough in a small project like this to build, test, and see if it
gives you what you want. Let's build, run, cool!
That's looking pretty peachy! The chair, and I want to check the
as well, so I'm going to pause. Look at the chair, I'm just going to stop and look at the chair.
It says that the chair is at -90, -210, 20, very nice!
And it says that the rock was a -230, 270,
40. OK, well it should be right, it's simple code! But this is a breakthrough
because we now have inside the C++ code,
we've mixed these different accessor operators depending on whether we're dealing like the owner
is an Actor star, so we use this operator, but the transform returns an
actual transform value, FTransform, so we use the dot the same as location
FVector. So we use a dot and then ToString() because we need the
result of all of the rest of this to be turned into
a string, so that we can put it into ObjectPos and then
ObjectPos gets looked for here. So, this %s looks for *ObjectName,
this %s looks for *ObjectPos.
Ahh, big deep breath, guys! Good job, we have
really made a good bit of headway into Unreal flavored C++!
We can really start to grab hold of details of the world, using
our code, and now, we'll move on and see some other juicy aspects
of Unreal C++!