Oh. I'm very excited for you. because we're going to be moving objects with C++.
really using Unreal with C++ for the first time. In this video. we'll
talk a little more about the editor and temporary actors. show you how to eject yourself
from the possessed pawn. You'll see what that means. Snapping objects to the floor.
The end key does that. We'll be using FRotator struct
to represent rotation and using SetActorRotation() to rotate
objects. So. over in Unreal. by the end of it. I will have taken my nasty
rock away. put a door and a door frame in. and when you click play you're going to find the door
opens based on the code we've written. which is cool! OK. see you soon!
So welcome back! You might we wondering what this funny blue ball is! It's
actually just the back of that blue vector arrow there. so I thought
I'd let you know that. The other thing to know is that when you go into Play Mode. if you're quick
and you don't click into the actual Viewport here. you can
click Eject. and what that'll do is it'll actually let you move around the scene
independent of your player. You're no longer possessing
the player start here OK. The other thing to note
is that. when you're in Stop Mode. there's only certain objects in the game
in the World Outliner here. When you click play. you see a bunch of temporary actors coming.
You can actually make them visible or not here. with the View Options at the bottom
of World Outliner. and then. hide Temporary Actors but it's worth leaving them
there. So a bunch of stuff comes in when you actually start playing. and you might ask yourself.
we know. what am I in the world? Well. Play. don't click into the
Viewport but just click Eject. come out. click on the thing that you're wondering which is
you. and you can see that you're the DefaultPawn. It's got an iterator 7 on it.
but you're DefaultPawn number 7. So. that's one thing I wanted to tell you. The other thing.
you might see "LIGHTING NEEDS TO BE REBUILT". so you can do that from the Build menu here. with the drop-
down. Build Lighting Only and it'll take a while. Cool! So. what we want to
do now is be able to actually get our code to move something in the world.
We've worked out that we can have the code read the state of things in the world
and report the position of the chair and the rock. If we're going to make this a
Building Escape game. we'd better be able to do something simple like open a door right. So. how do we do that?
Let's delete the rock. I don't need a rock in my room. And what I'm going to do is. I'm going  to
dive into the Starter Pack Content and see what I can find. So.
go to the Content Browser Tab. dive into Starter Content.
have a look there under say Props. There's a few different things you can use.
So props will give you a variety of things. window frames.
door frames. etc. So. we could bring a door frame in. In fact. to be honest.
a door frame is all we need for now. we don't even need a wall
in it. So. drop a door frame in. notice that it ends up on the floor. So. if you want to get it to the
floor. if it's not on the floor. there's a few different ways. One is that you can push
the End Key on your keyboard. The End Key will snap it back to the floor.
And another way is. you can explore through right-clicking on it. scrolling
down. Transform. Snap/Align. and eventually you should get Snap
to Floor. OK. so that's how you get things on the floor. but by default they come in on the floor.
which is pretty cool! So. let's see if we can get a door. What have we got? SM_Door!
That's fine! Now. how do I align that door? Well. you can just move around in 3D. is one
simple way. and actually it's done a very good job of snapping into the frame there. But you
just get yourself a door in a frame. If you need to get it lined up a bit more perfectly.
if you're a bit OCD like me about this gap. then you can try just moving it. And if
the snap distance is too big. then this is your first opportunity to come up
here. hover over until you can see the Position
Grid Snap Value. and try a different value like maybe 5 centimeters.
And then. have a good look nice and close. and the door fits snuggly in
the frame. Perfect! Also notice. if you go into the Rotate Tool. that's with the E
Key. that the door's pivot is at the bottom left. which is pretty handy because
that means it opens and closes. So. what we want to do is do this in code!
How are we going to do that? Well. let's stick to the paradigm of clicking on the actor in question.
Let's go to the World Outliner. There it is. SM_Door. OK! Go
to the Details Tab and let's add ourselves a new component.
and we're going to add a new C++ component. of course!
And it's an Actor Component! That's right because it's
the Component on an Actor. We're going to call it OpenDoor.
because that's what it's going to do. and let's create the class!
And once that's happened and the code has been generated and Visual Studio opened. we're going to get
an opportunity to actually see if we can work out how to move the door. So.
I can't do anything in the Unreal Interface. while this happens. By the way. I hope you were able to
commit in your last couple of videos. So. remember to come in and do that. Mine are slighlty
out of order because I just put an update to a video there. but make sure you're committing at the end of all of your
videos. Here we go. we're in Unreal now and
Visual Studio has just popped up. So. before we do that. what are we even trying to access? Click on the door.
rotate the door. and look and see what changes. You can
see it's here. this thing here under Transform.
Rotation. on the Details Tab. you'll see that the Z rotation of the
door is the thing that changes. See that? So you set it
back to 0 and it's there! You may have your door in a different side of the
level. then you're values will be shifted by some multiple of 90 degrees.
Cool! So there it is. that's what we're trying to do! So. how are we going to do that? Well.
I want you to go into the script and to go ahead and find the
owner of this door in the BeginPlay().
I want you to go ahead and "// Find the owning Actor".
so ultimately we can access the rotation. So. find the
owning object. as we did before. Store it in a variable called Owner.
Get the type right or use auto if you're that sophisticated.
Try and access the Owner's rotation.
and hint. there are at least a couple of ways you can access the Owner's rotation.
You don't need to set it yet. I'll do that with you. Just see if you can get as far as accessing the rotation
If you can set it and make the door open great. but I'm only expecting. at the moment.
just to be able to access the rotation. very similar to the last thing we did
but we're using a set rather than a get here. by the way. so it's going to
Now I should say if you're having any trouble with your door rotation. if your door's
not lined-up exactly like mine is. Don't worry. just let it open strangely
and in a few lectures time we're going to be addressing how to make the rotation independant
of how you've laid out the door in your level. so just carry-on through
if you're having those type of issues.
Welcome back! So. let's remember our
pseudocode programming! We're going to find the owning actor. we're going to create
a rotator. although you wouldn't know at this stage that that's what you're going to
need to do. and we're going to set the door rotation.
That gives me an outline. So. finding the owning actor. Well. I said we should call it
AActor. say owner rather. So. AActor*
Owner. Alright. so we are declaring a
pointer to an Actor called Owner. =
GetOwner(); hover over GetOwner() it shows
you that it returns a AActor*. OK. they put the star
after the space. in this case. or at least Visual Studio does.
OK. so we've got the owner there. Now. how are we going to set the door
rotation? Well. let's explore that first! We're going to do something like
this. Owner. now is it dot or is it
arrow operator? Now. I don't know. at this moment. what we're looking for... So
well. I do but I'm trying to tell you how you'd work it out. Come back to Unreal. look at the Transform.
It's something to do with the Transform and it's something to do with Rotation probably.
So what I would do here is bring up the intelli-sense again
and type the word rotation. What have we got? Get
ActorRotation... Ooh. SetActorRotation! OK. that's
pretty cool! So. why don't we just set the actor rotation directly.
When we do that and we open the braces. look we've got two different
signatures here. It's looking for this thing here. a constant FQuat
which is a Quaternion. Reference to a new rotation. How scary is that?!
Or we could simply use a FRotator and NewRotation.
OK. well that's cool! Why don't we imagine we have a variable called NewRotation
in like that? And then. we need to go and create that rotator.
What is a rotator? Well. it gave us the hint. we need an FRotator.
Now. you can go do a Google search and find out what an FRotator is.
Here it'll tell you something: "Implements a container for rotation information. All rotation values
are stored in degrees." OK. so it's a struct. That's pretty cool!
So. FRotation NewRotation
So. we've declared that variable now. =
now how are we going to create this thing in the first place? Well. we go
FRotator() again. and we call its constructor. Now.
its constructor has seven different signatures. We can give it just a single float.
we can give it no initialization. we can give it Pitch.
Yaw. and Roll. which is probably what we're going to use. You can give it a weird Quaternion references.
Ooh. we don't want to do that today. Nasty nasty scary!
OK. so let's go with this one! We're going to give it Pitch. Yaw. and Roll.
So. I'm going to make a deliberate mistake here. because it's funny and it'll show you the difference
between Pitch. Yaw. and Roll. Imagine you didn't read the Pitch. Yaw. and Roll. for a moment. and that you just
assume that it was X. Y. and Z. So. you can go 0.0f
for float. You need to tell it that it's a float. 0.0f and
then 90.0f. Then. you would think
that maybe this is X. Y. Z. Let's try it. see if everything else works.
See what happens if we'd assume that's X. Y. Z. We come
over and the door will flop on its side. [Laughs] That's a bit funny!
OK. what's happened there? That's because the rotator. the clue. was in
the way that it defined it. It's about Pitch. Yaw. and roll. so for this door
let me show you what they are. These are aircraft terms. so I'm very familiar with them but you may not be.
This here is Yawing. it's in an aircraft when you use the rudder pedals.
and it's Yawing like that. It's basically if you put your hand flat and rotate your wrist
like that. then that is Yawing OK. The next
motion is Rolling. that's more familiar. In an airplane this is called Rolling left
and right like that. And then. Pitching is kind of easy to understand. it's Pitching up
and down. OK. so you just have to understand what Pitch. Yaw. and Roll is. What we've
asked the door to do there. if we hover over it. is we've asked it to roll through
90 degrees. So go back to Unreal. grab this one. roll it till it
says 90. and that's exactly what we've done. So. what do we want to do? Is it
Pitch. Yaw.
or Roll? I won't insult you any further. I think you know that it's
Yaw. And which way do you want the door to open? It's up to you! I'm going to open it 60 degrees
outwards. So. put it back to neutral. to make sure it's our code doing the opening.
hover to see which order. Pitch. Yaw. Roll. So. I'm going to put
60. Now. by the way you don't need the 0's
after these points here. You can say 0 point... You don't need the 0. but
you do need a decimal place. which just forces it to understand
that this is a floating point number. So. that's the minimum that you can comfortably write there.
Let's try running or building!
All done. back to Unreal. hot reload
complete. Play. boom the door has opened! It has opened the wrong way. because
I should have gone -60. and you can verify that.
From here you can just see that it says -60. So. if I
did want it to open the other way. I'd go -60. which I will because I want it to do what
I asked it to do. not leave it to fate. OK. so
that's it! We have now managed to actually control a game
object in C++. So that's it. we're Unreal masters. and we don't need to study anymore!
I wish it was that simple. it's quite a complex piece. but it does mean that we can both
read from game objects in C++ and control their states. So. give
yourself a big pat on the back. and I shall see you soon!