So. welcome to Applying
Materials. In this video. we're going to explain that a material is comprised
of one or more textures and one or more shaders.
Textures are image files. Shaders are GPU code. running on your
graphics processing unit. your graphics card. So. Unreal ships with some impressive
examples of materials. Unreal has powerful material editing
tools in it. which we'll take a look at and play with. and it'll be applying materials to our room
interior. By the end of it. you will have created something like this. a chair
so hideous looking that you will be desperate to escape the room. You'll have
nicely materialed floors and walls. and you'll be able to actually change the
colors of things like the metal and seats on this chair. so see you there!
So guys. it's time to make this thing a lot more pretty. Let's
start with the floor. This checkerboard is all very nice with it's. what are they. 5 centimeter squares
inside? What are they? 5. 6. 7. 8. 9. 10. so
by 50 centimeter squares. but it's kind of boring right? So
why don't we get some materials. Where do we find them? Guess what. in the Starter
Pack! Go to Materials and then here they are! Now.
let's have a look! We can preview them here. if you want more detail you can double-click on them.
And then what are you going to get? You're going to get a face full of this thing.
which is basically a Node Editor. It's very similar to the Blueprint Editor. it's basically
built from the same stuff. and it's a little bit scary. particularly this one.
Materials are complicated. they combine together images which can
and have a lot of different purposes. This guy here is something called a Normal Map.
which gives the illusion of surface detail that's not there. of geometry
that's not there. roughness that's not there. and you've got all sorts of things. You have
masks that can mask out things like part of something that emits light
and part that doesn't. emissive masks. You can have all sorts of different things. complicated
bit of kit. but for now. we're going to focus on just applying them and
tweaking them slightly. So. how do we apply them? Well. let's find something that's going to work.
like a Wood_Floor_Walnut. Just grab it. drag it. drop it on
the floor. Oh look at that! If you get close
to that floor. look how pretty that is. that's just ridiculous!
I mean. bearing in mind this is running at how many frames a second? I don't know.
Click at the top-left of the Perspective Viewport. click Show
FPS. and OK I'm running a GTX 980 here and a 4
Gigahertz processor thingy but it's doing 120 frames per second.
which is plenty even for VR. so very very pretty OK!
It's cool! You can adjust various properties of these
materials. I don't think we need to go into a huge amount of detail about that right now. but I want to show you
where you get to the details of the materials. And where do you think it is? It's under the Details
Tab! So we click on Details. we scroll down. and we can see materials here.
and that tells you what material is assigned. If you have something with a material and you
want to see where that is in your Content Browser. you click the little magnifying glass. so
we're in the Details Tag against Materials. Clicking the magnifying glass takes you back to the material
itself. OK. so that's fine! You
can right-click on the material to see various different things. The main thing you're going to want to do
there is to say Edit or just double-click. You could also go
to Asset Actions and Select Assets Using This Asset. which is kind of a way of going back
the other way. That's selected the floor. We've got the floor selected.
we can go to Details. and we can go back to the material. So. that's how you can kind of get back and forth between
those. The rest of these properties here aren't really too specificly
related to the material. but there is a sneaky thing going on here. If you look at Static
Mesh under the details. you can actually drag that down and
there's other stuff there. and sometimes you'll see other property panels
here that have the ability to drag down or click down and show more
information. So. just watch out for that. when you're exploring to see what's available. Obviously
we will show you things as they're necessary. Rendering here. there's some more information about rendering
and to do with all sorts of stuff that we don't need to get into right now.
OK. because we can't boil the ocean by teaching everything at once.   So.
that's how you apply a material to the floor! How do we apply materials to the wall? Let's go and find a
reasonable wall material. I think we're going to end up with a really boring basic wall
material. One way is to just grab that and drag it and drop it on the wall panel
OK. but they already have that basic wall material on them. So. if we want to make
it a little bit different. we could maybe use a brick. So. one wall panel at a time. we can go
around dragging the material we want onto it. So for instance. this may be a brick
wall down at this end here. and then. we may want to have. I don't know.
concrete grime. That's a bit weird but I suppose. if we're going to be trapped in a room
then that's maybe what we want on these wall panels.
So. I'm just going to apply materials to the rest of the walls here.
fairly painstakingly. When you're doing BSP. there is actually a way of selecting adjacent
walls. but we're not doing BSP editing. So. look how much better that's looking already!
OK. so now what I want to show you. before I briefly leave you to
go and customize your materials. is a little bit of customization. Let's take this chair
and say I don't like that yellow there! That's horrible! I'm just going to show you how.
in the Material Node Editor. we could actually change that yellow. So. go
to the chair. go to the Details Tab.
click to browse over to the actual
material. so not here under Static Mesh but the one below under
Materials. That'll take you to here M_Chair. which doesn't look much
like the chair. Now. you can zoom out with the Mouse Wheel. we can get rid of the
Palette. and there is the general pattern of the chair. Now this thing here. this sphere.
is actually the chair. but it's mapped onto a sphere
right now. so this is probably the baseplate of the chair or the back. You can map it onto
a chair model. but in order to do that. as it says: "You need to select a
mesh-based asset" first. So. let's just not bother right now. it's easy enough to do.
but let's keep things simple. What I want to show you is how you could change
this yellow color. So. it's actually quite well laid out. You've got a Color
Seats parameter here. which leads into some Lerp. which is a Linear Interpolation.
which leads into another one. which multiplies with something to do with
metal coloring. and eventually changes the base coloring of the chair. So.
this is not the time to get into the full details of how material node editing works.
but what I want to show you is the lever you need to pull. And you need to go and find your color
seats. for example. and you can change that to maybe a blue
color. with this picker here. Click OK
so that's then changed. and then we just need to save at the top-left
and then close the whole Node Editor. And look
what's happened to my chair! It's actually quite a disgusting blue. I find now!
Maybe you like it. So. I'm going to go and edit that once again. just to reinforce
it. and then. I want you to go and play but at least change the seat color. You're welcome to
play with other properties of the metal. etc. as well. So. let's take another look at
that M_Chair material. which is in Content.
StarterContent. Props. Materials.
We go into it. we have a look around. you zoom with the Mouse Wheel. you drag with the Right Mouse Button.
This thing here is a complicated
map. which is actually a mask which is telling the system what
is metal and what is reflective and what's not. etc. But we want to look around for
the color of the metal and the color of the seats. Let's just focus on those two.
Customize them to your needs. So. I'm going to go for... I don't know what color seat I want. Bright
red. Ferrari Red seat! OK! Wait. make sure it goes
red! Don't really like that. it's not quite Ferrari red enough for me.
That's a bit better. It's not quite coming out right.
Hmm. anyway it's close enough! And then. the color of the metal.
Well. maybe I'm going to make the metal a little more goldie. That's going to be a bit bling isn't it? So.
then I save the material there. It's now saving the asset.
Close. look at the chair. and now it's got... That's actually worse!
[Laughs] But so what. it's comic! So. what I want you to do now is to go
ahead and customize your materials. Apply materials. as you see fit.
from the Starter Pack. play with their properties to see the effect that is has. and then. share
your creations in the discussions. See how disgusting you can make that chair!
For example. how foul a combination of colors can you create or how cohesive and
exciting a combination of colors you can create. Either way. either astound us with your artistic
abilities or sicken us with your incoherence.
OK guys. welcome back! So there's
not really much for me to do here. I've already created a fairly sickening looking chair.
and I've already applied materials to everything. I'm leaving the roof open just for lighting. at the moment. So.
I would just simply take a screenshot of this. share it in the discussions. I'm going to turn off this
frames per second indicator. because it's kind of irritating me. So. that's at the top-left there.
And I will see you shortly. when we will carry on building this. Building Escape!
With that chair there. you're going to want to escape this building now. so that's the incentive to leave!