Welcome to
Macros Starting with UPROPERTY. By that I'm talking about. we're
introducing you to macros and the first one we're going to introduce you to is a UPROPERTY.
So in this video we're going to explain that a macro is a programmed
cut-and-paste operation that happens before compile time. Ooh. I just did
explain it! [Laughs] This happens before the code is compiled. This can
unlock some pretty powerful functionality. but we don't get code completers
standard. Our IDE will not fill out the macro for us. so we have to be super
careful about what we type. We can also create some really weird build errors. so we need to
watch that. We can't avoid them though. we can't use Unreal C++ without getting into macros heavily.
And at the end we're going to do something called exposing ATriggerVolume* pointer.
to the details window. What does that mean? Well it means that by the end of the video.
I'll have created another door like this. We'll have something called ATriggerVolume in the world
here. and that TriggerVolume will actually be associated to
the OpenDoor component of both of these doors like this. so as a
pressure plate. So what we're working towards is being able to stand on the pressure plate and open both of the
doors. Pretty cool hey?! So I'm going to start by
giving you an example. which is allowing us to specify the open angle of the
door. I'm going to make it private. from the point of the code
privacy. because well firstly it's a property. It's just going to be a float
OpenAngle like that. and we better
default it to something sensible in the code. like 90 degrees. maybe if I can [Laughs] type straight.
OK now. the thing about that is it's private. which means that other methods
can't just set it. which is good because we want to use getters and setters as discussed before. but here's
something cool that we can actually do. Watch this. we can use something called a UPROPERTY.
now this is a macro. and what this means is it's going to do some strange
cut-and-paste on our code before... [Sighs] Ah. I'm talking and typing
at the same time! ...before it actually compiles. and you don't even put a semicolon
on the end. If we say UPROPERTY() like that. then you can read
all about U properties over here. "uproperty unreal".
and then. here you go. the Unreal documentation will tell you all about it in much more
boring detail than I'm going to. But if we make this thing a UPROPERTY
and we say (VisibleAnywhere).
Now bear in mind that these things will not be in autocomplete
for you. because VisualStudio doesn't understand what's going on. If you want to know what's
possible in UPROPERTY then you're going to need to use
a Google search right. And if you find the right one of these. then
you're going to be able to find property specifiers. perhaps. and down here.
VisibleInstanceOnly. VisibleAnywhere. and you can see what that says. OK.
So I'm going to make this thing VisibleAnywhere and see what it does.
and then. we'll see what a UPROPERTY does. (VisibleAnywhere. I'm going to paste that in.
because I want to make sure I've spelled it right. which I probably hadn't. I think I put an A in here?
Now i'm going to build the project. Now I warn you. if you get anything wrong with one of these things.
then you're going to get horrible weird indecipherable build errors. because of when this happens in the
compile time. You need to make sure that the UPROPERTY... Like these! [Laughs] You need to make sure
that the UPROPERTY does not have a space after it. that it's immediately above the
thing you're trying to set as a UPROPERTY. that everything is spelled correctly. So let's
see what the problem is. It's good news if you get problems in the actual file. the
OpenDoor.h in this case. because they're likely to be easy
to understand. And the problem here is that I needed a 90 point.
at least or 90.0 and that's what it was complaining about alright.
So that's an easy one to solve. because it is giving us an error in the
actual syntax of our code. in this file. If we make an error in the spelling of
UPROPERTY or VisibleAnywhere or something we'll get a weird error. and it's very very likely if you've just
added a macro. you haven't added it right. Let's see what it does! It's compiled
and over in Unreal we see that we have a non-editable Open Angle that
just defaulted to 90 degrees. If you want to make this editable for later.
well you'll see how to do that after the coming challenge. So that's pretty cool
right?! We can now see things from our code. in the Inspector. whilst keeping them private.
As far as other classes are concerned. they're now visible in
the Properties Panel and the Details Panel or what I will also call the Inspector.
Cool! So I want you to write your first UPROPERTY now! I want you to
open your OpenDoor.h file. we already have it. I want you to declare this.
ATriggerVolume* pointer PressurePlate. Now that can be private as well.
and this is going to be a pointer called PressurePlate
to ATriggerVolume*. which we've already put in the scene. I want you to use the
UPROPERTY macro. but this time use EditAnywhere parameter.
And the documentation is available there. you can click on that in the section note .pdf's.
So basically. almost exactly what we've just done. I've nearly given it to you on a plate here. but
by doing it yourself. you're going to understand it obviously a lot better.
So it doesn't need to be kind of wired to the PressurePlate. We're not actually linked to
that pressure plate yet. but it's going to give us the facility and I'll show you that in the solution. So pause the
video. go ahead do that now!
Welcome back guys! So what I'm wanting to do then is do something
very similar to this. so I'm actually going to copy it. I'm going to make
this. Instead of VisibleAnywhere. EditAnywhere. I'm
not going to call it OpenAngle. it's going to be ATrigger. Now how do I know
it's ATriggerVolume. by the way? Well over in Unreal. I want to briefly
introduce you to something called ATriggerVolume. We'll look at this more in the next lecture but let's get it in the scene
now. So if you go to your Modes tab and then you look down to the Volumes
sub-tab. you'll see there's a whole lot of Volumes. Volume is in a thing
in 3D space. so not an audio volume that's confusing. but all the
rest of these are talking about a 3D space and one of those is ATriggerVolume.
You can find out more about it by clicking on the question mark. it'll take you to their website and
show you that ATriggerVolume. for example. is an invisible volume in the game world
that can be used to tell code to do something. So in our case we're going to be using
ATriggerVolume as a PressurePlate to tell the door to open. So what we want to do is we want to
add ATriggerVolume into the world. So drag it from the
Modes tab there. into the world. and then. you can just drop it down into the
floor and that's good enough! If we walk over that we're going to catch the top of the ATriggerVolume. Make it
bigger if you like. so we can't jump over it. and I'm just going to leave it low like that. and then. we have
ATriggerVolume in the world! If you go to the Outliner. you can have a look in here.
and under Type you can see a strict type name. TriggerVolume. and that is the actual type
name we're going to need in C++. So the way that you discover that for yourself.
in the future. is that I've got this thing in the scene. it's ATriggerVolume. We found that out maybe
through a Google search or just by browsing. You go back to your code. you come in
here. and you just type trigger. You make sure that this little whirligig at the
bottom of VisualStudio. and there's some similar indicators in Xcode. has finished. because
right now it's still going through and parsing the files. Eventually. it'll come up and
give you some help. ATriggerVolume sounds like the puppy! Star
because it's a pointer! Remember most of the things in Unreal. we don't need copying
around by value. we want to leave it where it is in memory rather. And then. I'm going to
call it PressurePlate. like that. OK
so no other class can set this from the outside. it's private
which is great but it is going to be EditAnywhere. Let's try and see
what that means. What does
being able to edit a PressurePlate mean? What am I talking about here? Well it'll come clear
right now. I'll show you the design we're going for. In Unreal we
now click on the Door. go to the Details tab.
click the OpenDoor component. and look the Pressure Plate
property here is saying. show me ATriggerVolume. and very helpfully it
filters everything in the World Outliner by TriggerVolume
and I can just click it. So I've now associated this door with this TriggerVolume!
That's pretty cool! You see the power of that? From the designer's point of view.
they can come in and there could be another door and we could associate the other door
with the TriggerVolume. In fact. why don't we. just for fun. do that just to
show the generality of what we're doing. I'm going to select the door.
the door frame. I doesn't matter. that'll do for now; If I'm missing something. I'll just duplicate
that across. No I think I've got it all! Oh no. I missed the
frame. so I'm going to grab the frame. hold down Alt. drag a new frame
over. So now we've got another door here. and. actually. it's
already associated with the same TriggerVolume because I duplicated it. So both of these
doors are associated with this TriggerVolume. so this volume will open both doors
at the same time. Cool hey! So I think that's enough for this video.
I just want to recap now what we've done over in here. because there's a lot to think
about. We made a couple of simple private properties. they are pretty
normal to us. We've made them private because. well basically we make all data
like this. all information or member variables private. and we use getters
and setters. so we're certainly not making every other class be able to reach in and change these things.
We want to keep the OpenDoor class responsible for changing these things.
but also. importantly. we have used something called a macro to make this one
Visible and this one Editable in the Inspector
or the Details tab here. When we look at the OpenDoor component. you can
see the difference between an non-editable OpenDoor Angle. which we could easily
make editable and a PressurePlate which is editable. and it let's use choose
the TriggerVolume and both of these doors are now associated to that TriggerVolume.
The only other thing we might want to do is possibly consider
how we organize our hierarchy. but to be honest. right now. the hierarchy is simple enough. We've
got a folder for Walls and the rest of it is still fairly
fairly conceivable. so it's tidy enough. Alright that's great!
Let's commit what we've done in our source control and crack on with the next video. where hopefully we'll be able
to walk onto this PressurePlate and have both doors open!
=======
Welcome to
Macros Starting with UPROPERTY. By that I'm talking about, we're
introducing you to macros and the first one we're going to introduce you to is a UPROPERTY.
So in this video we're going to explain that a macro is a programmed
cut-and-paste operation that happens before compile time. Ooh, I just did
explain it! [Laughs] This happens before the code is compiled. This can
unlock some pretty powerful functionality, but we don't get code completers
standard. Our IDE will not fill out the macro for us, so we have to be super
careful about what we type. We can also create some really weird build errors, so we need to
watch that. We can't avoid them though, we can't use Unreal C++ without getting into macros heavily.
And at the end we're going to do something called exposing ATriggerVolume* pointer,
to the details window. What does that mean? Well it means that by the end of the video,
I'll have created another door like this. We'll have something called ATriggerVolume in the world
here, and that TriggerVolume will actually be associated to
the OpenDoor component of both of these doors like this, so as a
pressure plate. So what we're working towards is being able to stand on the pressure plate and open both of the
doors. Pretty cool hey?! So I'm going to start by
giving you an example, which is allowing us to specify the open angle of the
door. I'm going to make it private, from the point of the code
privacy, because well firstly it's a property. It's just going to be a float
OpenAngle like that, and we better
default it to something sensible in the code, like 90 degrees, maybe if I can [Laughs] type straight.
OK now, the thing about that is it's private, which means that other methods
can't just set it, which is good because we want to use getters and setters as discussed before, but here's
something cool that we can actually do. Watch this, we can use something called a UPROPERTY,
now this is a macro, and what this means is it's going to do some strange
cut-and-paste on our code before... [Sighs] Ah, I'm talking and typing
at the same time! ...before it actually compiles, and you don't even put a semicolon
on the end. If we say UPROPERTY() like that, then you can read
all about U properties over here, "uproperty unreal",
and then, here you go, the Unreal documentation will tell you all about it in much more
boring detail than I'm going to. But if we make this thing a UPROPERTY
and we say (VisibleAnywhere).
Now bear in mind that these things will not be in autocomplete
for you, because VisualStudio doesn't understand what's going on. If you want to know what's
possible in UPROPERTY then you're going to need to use
a Google search right. And if you find the right one of these, then
you're going to be able to find property specifiers, perhaps, and down here,
VisibleInstanceOnly, VisibleAnywhere, and you can see what that says, OK.
So I'm going to make this thing VisibleAnywhere and see what it does,
and then, we'll see what a UPROPERTY does. (VisibleAnywhere, I'm going to paste that in,
because I want to make sure I've spelled it right, which I probably hadn't. I think I put an A in here?
Now i'm going to build the project. Now I warn you, if you get anything wrong with one of these things,
then you're going to get horrible weird indecipherable build errors, because of when this happens in the
compile time. You need to make sure that the UPROPERTY... Like these! [Laughs] You need to make sure
that the UPROPERTY does not have a space after it, that it's immediately above the
thing you're trying to set as a UPROPERTY, that everything is spelled correctly. So let's
see what the problem is. It's good news if you get problems in the actual file, the
OpenDoor.h in this case, because they're likely to be easy
to understand. And the problem here is that I needed a 90 point,
at least or 90.0 and that's what it was complaining about alright.
So that's an easy one to solve, because it is giving us an error in the
actual syntax of our code, in this file. If we make an error in the spelling of
UPROPERTY or VisibleAnywhere or something we'll get a weird error, and it's very very likely if you've just
added a macro, you haven't added it right. Let's see what it does! It's compiled
and over in Unreal we see that we have a non-editable Open Angle that
just defaulted to 90 degrees. If you want to make this editable for later,
well you'll see how to do that after the coming challenge. So that's pretty cool
right?! We can now see things from our code, in the Inspector, whilst keeping them private.
As far as other classes are concerned, they're now visible in
the Properties Panel and the Details Panel or what I will also call the Inspector.
Cool! So I want you to write your first UPROPERTY now! I want you to
open your OpenDoor.h file, we already have it. I want you to declare this,
ATriggerVolume* pointer PressurePlate. Now that can be private as well.
and this is going to be a pointer called PressurePlate
to ATriggerVolume*, which we've already put in the scene. I want you to use the
UPROPERTY macro, but this time use EditAnywhere parameter.
And the documentation is available there, you can click on that in the section note .pdf's.
So basically, almost exactly what we've just done, I've nearly given it to you on a plate here, but
by doing it yourself, you're going to understand it obviously a lot better.
So it doesn't need to be kind of wired to the PressurePlate. We're not actually linked to
that pressure plate yet, but it's going to give us the facility and I'll show you that in the solution. So pause the
video, go ahead do that now!
Welcome back guys! So what I'm wanting to do then is do something
very similar to this, so I'm actually going to copy it. I'm going to make
this. Instead of VisibleAnywhere, EditAnywhere. I'm
not going to call it OpenAngle, it's going to be ATrigger. Now how do I know
it's ATriggerVolume, by the way? Well over in Unreal, I want to briefly
introduce you to something called ATriggerVolume. We'll look at this more in the next lecture but let's get it in the scene
now. So if you go to your Modes tab and then you look down to the Volumes
sub-tab, you'll see there's a whole lot of Volumes. Volume is in a thing
in 3D space, so not an audio volume that's confusing, but all the
rest of these are talking about a 3D space and one of those is ATriggerVolume.
You can find out more about it by clicking on the question mark, it'll take you to their website and
show you that ATriggerVolume, for example, is an invisible volume in the game world
that can be used to tell code to do something. So in our case we're going to be using
ATriggerVolume as a PressurePlate to tell the door to open. So what we want to do is we want to
add ATriggerVolume into the world. So drag it from the
Modes tab there, into the world, and then, you can just drop it down into the
floor and that's good enough! If we walk over that we're going to catch the top of the ATriggerVolume. Make it
bigger if you like, so we can't jump over it, and I'm just going to leave it low like that, and then, we have
ATriggerVolume in the world! If you go to the Outliner, you can have a look in here,
and under Type you can see a strict type name, TriggerVolume, and that is the actual type
name we're going to need in C++. So the way that you discover that for yourself,
in the future, is that I've got this thing in the scene, it's ATriggerVolume. We found that out maybe
through a Google search or just by browsing. You go back to your code, you come in
here, and you just type trigger. You make sure that this little whirligig at the
bottom of VisualStudio, and there's some similar indicators in Xcode, has finished, because
right now it's still going through and parsing the files. Eventually, it'll come up and
give you some help. ATriggerVolume sounds like the puppy! Star
because it's a pointer! Remember most of the things in Unreal, we don't need copying
around by value, we want to leave it where it is in memory rather. And then, I'm going to
call it PressurePlate, like that. OK
so no other class can set this from the outside, it's private
which is great but it is going to be EditAnywhere. Let's try and see
what that means. What does
being able to edit a PressurePlate mean? What am I talking about here? Well it'll come clear
right now, I'll show you the design we're going for. In Unreal we
now click on the Door, go to the Details tab,
click the OpenDoor component, and look the Pressure Plate
property here is saying, show me ATriggerVolume, and very helpfully it
filters everything in the World Outliner by TriggerVolume
and I can just click it. So I've now associated this door with this TriggerVolume!
That's pretty cool! You see the power of that? From the designer's point of view,
they can come in and there could be another door and we could associate the other door
with the TriggerVolume. In fact, why don't we, just for fun, do that just to
show the generality of what we're doing. I'm going to select the door,
the door frame. I doesn't matter, that'll do for now; If I'm missing something, I'll just duplicate
that across. No I think I've got it all! Oh no, I missed the
frame, so I'm going to grab the frame, hold down Alt, drag a new frame
over. So now we've got another door here, and, actually, it's
already associated with the same TriggerVolume because I duplicated it. So both of these
doors are associated with this TriggerVolume, so this volume will open both doors
at the same time. Cool hey! So I think that's enough for this video,
I just want to recap now what we've done over in here, because there's a lot to think
about. We made a couple of simple private properties, they are pretty
normal to us. We've made them private because, well basically we make all data
like this, all information or member variables private, and we use getters
and setters, so we're certainly not making every other class be able to reach in and change these things.
We want to keep the OpenDoor class responsible for changing these things,
but also, importantly, we have used something called a macro to make this one
Visible and this one Editable in the Inspector
or the Details tab here. When we look at the OpenDoor component, you can
see the difference between an non-editable OpenDoor Angle, which we could easily
make editable and a PressurePlate which is editable, and it let's use choose
the TriggerVolume and both of these doors are now associated to that TriggerVolume.
The only other thing we might want to do is possibly consider
how we organize our hierarchy, but to be honest, right now, the hierarchy is simple enough. We've
got a folder for Walls and the rest of it is still fairly
fairly conceivable, so it's tidy enough. Alright that's great!
Let's commit what we've done in our source control and crack on with the next video, where hopefully we'll be able
to walk onto this PressurePlate and have both doors open!
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1:Unreal/Section3/BE14 Macros Starting with UPROPERTY.srt