So, it's time to
start talking about Unreels Player Controller! In this video, we'll talk
about the fact that we've used... Well, I'm talking about it now! [Laughs] ... the fact that we've used GetOwner() to
search bottom-up. Basically, we've gone from a component to the door.
For example, the open door has gone up and look above it and said, well I'm part of a door.
Now, let's use GetWorld() to search top-down. Let's start at the game world and go
down to what we need. We're going to see that it's Game Mode
specifics the Default Pawn Class. Why does this thing called Default Pawn even appear,
when we start? That's specified in the Game Mode. We're not going to play with that particularly.
But you do need to know that the Default Pawn is your body, basically. We're using a Default Pawn as the body,
and it's transient, the body might disappear while the game is playing. But does a Player
Controller, when you start playing the game another one of these temporary actors.... And that's your mind
and that will persist even if your body disappears. This all sounds very metaphysical
right now. And the Player Controller class has a method called Get Pawn, so the
way that we're going to get to the pawn we're looking for is, we're going to GetWorld(), we're going to find the Player Controller,
then, we're going to GetPawn() on that. By the end of it, you'll be able to just walk over that pressure pad and open
the doors, without having to Stop and Eject yourself and all that rubbish that we did, in order to
see the nuts and bolts. So, I'll see you in there! OK, so how are we
going to make this happen? We've got our pressure plate area here, and the challenge we have, of
course, is that the player, well the Default Pawn here,
is only instantiated when we start playing the game. If we Eject, then we're kind of taking
the mind out of the body, if you like. The Pawn here is the body, and now our mind is
drifting around, observing ourselves from the outside, which is kind of fun!
The challenge is, of course, we need the code to be able to find this thing in the scene. How do we do
that? So, let's break it down! The first thing is, if you go to Settings
and Project Settings, you'll find under Maps & Modes that
we have something here called the Default Game Mode. It's set itself to BuildingEscapeGame,
just game mode, because that's what we called our project Building Escape.
And it's got things here, Default Pawn class, etc. They're not directly editable.
We won't worry about editing them right now, but the reason that the thing
that instantiates, when we play the game, is called Default Pawn, the body that appears for us
is because that's what we've got set as the Pawn Class. So, we play, the game
goes OK let's make ourselves a Default Pawn! There's also a Default
Player Controller going on in here. Now, it's not listed
as a... Well it is actually! Here it is, PlayerController3!
Alright, so the PlayerController is the mind and the
Pawn is the body, but it's the body that we want to interact with this
volume, so we need to go find the body. How do we do that? How do we find the Pawn at runtime?
Alirght, so up to now we have been finding things by
going upwards, by bottom-up search. By that I mean, if we click on the
door and then we look at the component that we put on the OpenDoor component. We have been
searching upwards saying what's my owner, what's the door by saying Get
Owner(). Well, now we're going to search down. From the world as a whole, we're going to find
from the world the Player Controller, which only comes into
action, once the game is playing. We have the PlayerController, and from the Player
Controller we can say, what is the pawn that I am
controlling? Remember that as we Eject, think of the pawn as the body
and the PlayerController as the mind. So let's go look at how we do that
over in the codes. I'm going to open up our code here.
And it's a relatively simple job we've got here. The difficulty is knowing
what you would type. How would you know what to do? So, let's recap what OpenDoor()
is doing. At the moment, we are in BeginPlay() not doing
anything anymore, and we have exposed, of course, the Actor that
opens as an editable property over in the blueprints. Well, I'm actually going to take off
the UPROPERTY now, so that it is no longer in the Inspector. I'm not going to compile
but if I had compiled, this Actor that opens would disappear. We're taking that
functionality away, for the moment. We can always add it back if we want
to later. Just so that we're very clear on how ActorThatOpens
is getting set. Go to the C++ file. What we need to do in
BeginPlay()... So play has actually begun, so the PlayerController exists. Is we need to
start finding the PlayerController, this is how we do it. We go GetWorld(),
it's a method, and we need the arrow operator. You'll see why in a second.
So, let's just let the Visual Studio catch up with itself here.
If we go GetWorld() and if we hover over
GetWorld(), of course, what does it return us? Well, it's going to turn us a pointer to a world.
Because it's a pointer, World * there. In the pop-up, we know that we need an arrow
operator. What do you get from there? Well, you could start
looking for pawn or you could start looking for getpawn, for example.
You won't find it. OK, you're going to get the number of Pawns and some
Pawn iterator, but what you can get directly from the world, is you can
get the PlayerController, specifically the first PlayerController.
Look what it returns, it returns a PlayerController or pointer to one. It returns
the first PlayerController or null if there isn't one. Well, there will be a PlayerController, that automatically
comes into your game. The PlayerController is the link between the
Pawn and the intentions of the person, of the gamer, using the machine if you like.
So we are going to get the first PlayerController that
exists, in this case the only PlayerController, and from there, we can directly get the...
Oops... We can directly get the Pawn in question.
Now, what does that return? It returns a pointer to a Pawn. Is that
OK? Is it OK to try to install a pointer to a Pawn, in
ActorThatOpens, which is
a pointer to an AActor*? Well it is because Pawn inherits
from Actor. A Pawn is a. Remember we talked about "is a" and "has a"
relationships? A Pawn "is a" Actor. We go over to Unreal,
we have a look at Window, Developer Tools, Class
Viewer, and we remind ourselves that we go from Actor down into
Pawn. So, a Pawn "is a" Actor! Because a Pawn is
a Actor, it's perfectly valid here to send a Pawn, which is the result
of this long statement here, into an Actor. OK,
so that should find the ActorThatOpens first. Let's try it! Let's
build the game and see how we do. What do we do while it compiles?
[Sings] We go skippity beepy dee, skippity beepy do, or something. What I
tend to do is look down on the bottom-right here and just see how the output is going and just kind of cross my fingers, that nothing is going to fail.
So, just before you hit play, I want to make you aware of something. If you've, at some
point, selected that Simulated Button you can see there. You see to the right of Play there's a little
drop-down arrow, and then you've got a few different modes of play. We want to be in
Selected Viewport Mode, not in Simulate Mode. If you're in
Simulate Mode, you won't actually possess the Default Pawn and therefore
what we're about to do won't work properly. So, just be aware of which Play Mode you're in. If you've got
a cog behind your Play Button, you need to just click the arrow to the right of it, and then,
select there what I've got in yellow, Selected Viewport.
OK, so here we go! Let' play! Now, before I even test it, I'm going to Eject immediately, take the
mind out of the body. Let's have a look at the Pawn, it's called DefaultPawn5.
Now, I'm going to look over at a door, I'm going to look at the OpenDoor,
and of course, I can no longer inspect it because I made the thing
not visible. So, let's just test and then I might actually put a read
only inspectability back. Oh, it's opened that door! That's cool, so it is working!
So, I don't even need to actually make it a read only property, that Pawn, because we
know that it's worked. We can see that it's worked there, but the other door doesn't work
and that's simply because it's not moveable. If I make the door moveable, it will
work. Cool, so that's pretty good stuff
right! So, what I want you to do now is to finish your pressure plates. You've got a whole process of
pressure plates now. When you do adjust the size and position of your trigger volumes, link to
the appropriate doors, ensure all doors are moveable, and
briefly test the gameplay. So go ahead, pause the video, and make use of this ability to use
pressure plates, right now.
Welcome back! So thinking about the gameplay of my little bit of game here, I'm
just going to let this evolve organically as we go. And I think I'm going to stick with
what I've got here actually, which is that I go over this pressure plate, the doors open, but when I try and
get to them, they need to close. So, one thing we're going to need to
have is a delay. OK, so it's all very well that they open. Escaping the room
is rather too easy right now. So, I think what we're going to deal with next is the ability to delay
the closure of those doors and expose that delay to a designer,
so that the designer can say, you stand on the pressure plate, the doors open, but
how quickly do they close. So we can end up with a really frustrating situation where they open, we think
we're home free, but they close in our face. That can lead
to various other things like, maybe later we move the chair over the pressure plate or something.
OK, so lots to be done, which is pretty cool. Let's just quickly
recap how we've done this. We've said that in order to find the
Default Pawn we've gone to the world, we've gone top-down. We've looked for the PlayerController
that we know is there, every time you play the game, and then, we've gone and got the Pawn
from the first PlayerController that we find. Why would we ever have more than one? Well, it could be a multi-
player game. You may have a multi-player game, basically.
So that's all pretty cool! I'm just going to go over to my Source Control now and make a commit
and maybe talk to you, very briefly, about an extra Source Control thing that we may not have covered.
So, I'm going to close both Unreal itself and
Visual Studio, making sure I save everything as I go.
Look at my untitled changes. Now look, this .suo file is still here,
and it's kind of getting in the way and annoying me. Why is it here, when I
have already ignored it? You see it's in my ignore.suo. The reason
is, once something is being tracked by Source Control it will not go unless you
move it. OK, so we need to stop tracking that. Very easy to do here
in Source Tree, right-click and Stop Tracking will do the job. There is a way
in the Terminal for those Terminal people as well. You could get rm
*.suo which is saying, remove anything
with the extension .suo. It'll go through, find the .suo, but tell me I need
to use a force, so I could go Up Arrow to get that command back and go
-f. And after all that, if we come back here and let it update, this
.suo is now being removed from Source Control as part of this commit, and these
other files are being modified. So red means removed, this one, yellow,
means modified, and then, the green would mean a new file. So, we haven't actually added anything.
What we have done is make a couple of adjustments to the map, that is probably where we made those doors moveable,
and then, we've added just the line that we talked about. And
we've removed the ability to edit this thing in the
Details panel, because we don't want to be confusing about who's in
control of what Actor can open the door. So that's it! Congratulations getting this far, we'll see you soon!