Welcome to
Using GetTImeSeconds()! It's a lot more fun than it sounds. In this video.
we're going to be using GetWorld() and then ->GetTimeSeconds(0. We'll be making our
game highly play tunable. be refactoring our code
for simplicity. We'll be using a spotlight to provide some
affordance to guide the player as to what they need to be doing. and we'll be play-testing
to ensure the game is annoying. annoying enough to really give them the motivation to want to escape!
By the end of it. we will have a situation something like this. We will be able
to find a spotlight. stand on it. see some doors open. and have them close in
our face. as we run towards them so that we can't get out! So.
let's see how that's done!
OK guys. let's do this thing! I'm really excited. because I know how frustrating this game is going to
be at the end of this relatively short video. Actually. it might end up being quite a long video.
Anyway let's do it! So. what we want is to have this
TriggerVolume... I'm actually going to move it around and do a couple of things first. I'm going to move it in
the ground plane. Notice I'm dragging it in a very specific place on that
right angle there. We're going to move it in the ground plane. to say the corder of the room for fun.
lift it up. scale it up with the R Key...
R Key. there we go! Might as well have it go all the way up there.
And then. what I'm going to do is I'm going to do is I'm going to come and put a light in to give some affordance.
i.e. some indication to the player as to what on earth they need to be
doing. So if I come into the quad view. get overhead this
squarey thing. Trigger Volume. I'm going to go to the Modes Panel
and Lights and Spot Light. and I'm going to drop it
in the scene. is probably easiest. something like that. And then. using all these other views. I'm
going to just move it around until... It doesn't
really matter. The idea is it's going to make a big messy
mark on the floor. Let's just move this
here. down in there. And what I'm trying to do
is just get the Spot Light over the center. or
roughly the center of the pressure pad. which is
like that.
Confusing things in here. so the pressure pad is the green. the trigger
volume... There we go. finally there! Now. what you need to do.
once your light is where you want it. is to go into the details of the light and
mess around with things like the intensity. By the way. you can click on the number 5.000 and
then just drag until it has the desired effect. OK. you can change the
cone angles here. so I'd prefer my cone is somewhat
constrained to the TriggerVolume. The Inner and Outer Cone Angle. you can make it quite...
Let's go back into the 3D. You can make it quite focused if you like. like
this. It's kind of saying this is the area that this thing is going to work in. We could make it a little more
subtle. This is a bit screaming at you. like go stand over here. but if we made it a bit
more subtle and perhaps say the color of... I mean later on thinking
that maybe the chair is the thing that triggers this. so we could use the Color Picker
from the chair. although it's not doing a great job. so I'm just going to
pick a yellow that looks a bit like it. somewhere around there.
Yeah. so the light has some sort of indication of the chair. which might indicate
that they might want to drag the chair over there later. Let's have a look! The point is
it's kind of subtle but there's a visual cue that you may want to stand here and that. that opens
the doors. Cool! Let's deal with the delays guys. without further delay!
Click on the door. let's go into the OpenDoor code...
...and let's start thinking about how we're going to do this. So. in order to
put a delay in. what we're going to need to do is have some concept of time.
So. what have we got in terms of the time component?
Well. if we get the world. once we've got the world and start looking for
methods that contain time. then let's see what we have.
While we wait for Visual Studio to finish loading and working out how it's autocomplete
works. let's just go to Google. get time Unreal's
c++ would be an example of a Google search you could do here. and
"Get current system time and date". That type of answer might lead you to it!
I've got something from Visual Studio stuck on my screen. Let's just see if I can...
That's popping over the... There you go! Hmm?
It's not leading to a lot of good results. Let me just tell you the answer. We want "gettime
seconds". OK.
Unreal. UWorld::GetTimeSeconds. And the thing about this is. it "Returns
the time in seconds since the world is brought up for play" and it "IS stopped when game
pauses" or if we change the time scale. if the game slows
down or speeds up. like it was slow motion or something. So. that's what we want. GetTimeSeconds
and it's from the world. so let's go in and take a look. I seem to have
two editors open. This can happen. so if it does happen what you need to do is
make sure you close the one where you didn't make your changes. There you go!
So. GetTimeSeconds()
and there it is! So. that is how we return the seconds! So. what are we
going to need? Well. what I'm going to do is make myself something. a couple of
different variable here. One is going to be editable anywhere. and it's going to
be something that says. to the designer. what is
the DoorCloseDelay as a float.
floating point number? OK. and let's give it a sensible value
to start with. 1 second perhaps. DoorCloseDelay.
We're also going to need a few other privates here. for this guy
to work. So. we're going to need to know float. Why float? Why is it a floating point
number? Because you can't count it on your fingers. it has a decimal point in it.
LastDoorOpenTime;
that would make sense. and I think that's probably
all we need for now. We may also need a level low time
or something. but let's just see how we go with this. So. we've got a couple of things
to store time in now. Now. what we need to do is write some code that's actually
going to check when the door last opened. So. the
first thing we're going to need to do here is. once the door is opened. we're going to say Door
LastOpenTime = this
guy here. Yeah.
that's fine! So. you open the door and you store when you open the door.
Now. what we're going to need to do is regularly check to see if it's time to
close the door. just underneath here. So. "// Check
if it's time to close the door".
And if we do. we're going to call a closed door method. Now. I'm going to leave you to write
"// Check if it's time to close the door". But I'm just going to refactor. do some refactor. I'm going to Open
Door() with you. so that we can make the ClosedDoor() method really simple. So. let's go look at
OpenDoor() and let's copy it.
make a new method called ClosedDoor() because it's so similar.
and let's take a look at it! So. it's big right? It's a bit too much!
It's not so easy looking at OpenDoor() and ClosedDoor() to see exactly what they do. So.
AActor* Owner. they both need Owner. so why don't we have a private
variable here called AActor* Owner;
and this is "// The owning door". OK.
and then. we can go and set the Owner on Begin
Play(). So. on BeginPlay() we find
the Owner and the Actor that opens. so therefore we don't need this
AActor* Owner = GetOwner(); to happen in the OpenDoor() or the ClosedDoor().
And somewhat I did that. I just pulled it out!
I took it out and said OK. this guy has a private property that
is found on Start(). and therefore we don't need to use it both open and close. We've made it a more
global variable. Cool! Now. ClosedDoor(). did we ever make Closed
Door() a method here? We didn't! We need to say void ClosedDoor() in the header file. because
that's C++ making our life a little bit harder. but
makes also things very clear. Good! So we now have ClosedDoor(). so this will
stop complaining eventually. I also think that we don't need this complexity of creating the rotator
and then calling it. I think that we can take this f rotator and stick it
straight in here. So that gets rid of all that code. remember less code is better. And also.
this angle is hard coded. whereas we've actually already made ourselves
an OpenAngle thing. It should be -90 degrees.
as a default. and then. here we can just say OpenAngle.
Does that make sense? So we've really simplified OpenDoor()
and we don't even need the comment. because it's obvious it sets the rotation. OpenDoor() just sets the
rotation to the open angle. Simple. what does ClosedDoor() do? Well.
it's just going to set the door's rotation and your roll pitch to 0.
OK. so again. we don't need any of this stuff.
How simple is that now? That's what you want! OpenDoor(). ClosedDoor() just reads
English simple. It's worth it! Make the effort. refactor. refactor. refactor! OK
guys. you've got a ClosedDoor() method to call now. I want you to write the code that goes in
here. that is continuously checked to see if it's time to close the door.
Implement close door delay. Write some simple timing code. get the doors closing after a specified
delay. play-test to ensure you can't escape.
OK welcome back. let's get this done! So. it's relatively a simple thing to do! We
just need to say. if and then this thing here. Now. you might argue. you
might want to store the time in seconds in a variable but that's fine. If
the current time - the LastDoorOpenTime is greater than
the... What do we call it? DoorCloseDelay.
then...
CloseDoor(). I know it almost seems too simple when you
get all the naming right. when everything lines up. it is almost too simple.
and that's what you want. And it's almost too simple. because we've made the effort.
Go over to Unreal. I'm just going to make sure by compiling here. because
what I see in Visual Studio is that this compiled a bit too quick for my liking.
So. to make sure it's compiled. I'm compiling over in Visual Studio. Now. let's play and see what
happens! Go into the light. they open. move out... Do they close?
They do! Perfect! Can I escape? Ah yes! So. how do
I play-tune it? Now. this is the beauty of the way we've set this up! Have a little look!
How do we play-tune it? Well. you click on the door. you go to the OpenDoor. look what I've got! Ooh.
my Open Angle is not controllable. so let me just quickly fix
that in here. The reason it's not editable is because we've changed it to (VisibleAnywhere).
whereas it could be (EditAnywhere). OK. so that is
easy! Save back in Unreal. We can quickly compile.
As soon as that compile finishes. this Open Angle should become editable.
So this door is going to open 90 degrees.
when something intercepts the Trigger
Volume and we have
a DoorCloseDelay of 1 second. Let's try half a second!
OK. let's try that door then. So. we come over here. boom. and it closes
in our face! Great! Now. let's take the other door. What time
does that need to be? -90. I'm actually going to have it open less. -60 just for fun.
And the Close Delay. you can click on here and drag and I'm going to try 0.7-ish.
So. can I get out of this door? Not quite! How annoying!
So. the game is finally really annoying! Look I'm stuck! [Grumbles]
[Grumbles] I can't get out! OK. so now I'm really annoyed! I'm this drone or something
flying around in this room. I can't get out of the sealing! I can see freedom. I can taste it. I can
smell it. but I can't get out. and I can't get out of these doors either!
So not a problem. we will have a solution. which I think in my game
is going to be moving that chair over the pressure plate and dealing with how that's going to work. We have
affordance. The color of this light is the color of the chair. It's subtle visual
hints. and that's what we'll deal with next!
=======
Welcome to
Using GetTImeSeconds()! It's a lot more fun than it sounds. In this video,
we're going to be using GetWorld() and then ->GetTimeSeconds(0. We'll be making our
game highly play tunable, be refactoring our code
for simplicity. We'll be using a spotlight to provide some
affordance to guide the player as to what they need to be doing, and we'll be play-testing
to ensure the game is annoying, annoying enough to really give them the motivation to want to escape!
By the end of it, we will have a situation something like this. We will be able
to find a spotlight, stand on it, see some doors open, and have them close in
our face, as we run towards them so that we can't get out! So,
let's see how that's done!
OK guys, let's do this thing! I'm really excited, because I know how frustrating this game is going to
be at the end of this relatively short video. Actually, it might end up being quite a long video.
Anyway let's do it! So, what we want is to have this
TriggerVolume... I'm actually going to move it around and do a couple of things first. I'm going to move it in
the ground plane. Notice I'm dragging it in a very specific place on that
right angle there. We're going to move it in the ground plane, to say the corder of the room for fun,
lift it up, scale it up with the R Key...
R Key, there we go! Might as well have it go all the way up there.
And then, what I'm going to do is I'm going to do is I'm going to come and put a light in to give some affordance,
i.e. some indication to the player as to what on earth they need to be
doing. So if I come into the quad view, get overhead this
squarey thing, Trigger Volume. I'm going to go to the Modes Panel
and Lights and Spot Light, and I'm going to drop it
in the scene, is probably easiest, something like that. And then, using all these other views, I'm
going to just move it around until... It doesn't
really matter. The idea is it's going to make a big messy
mark on the floor. Let's just move this
here, down in there. And what I'm trying to do
is just get the Spot Light over the center, or
roughly the center of the pressure pad, which is
like that.
Confusing things in here, so the pressure pad is the green, the trigger
volume... There we go, finally there! Now, what you need to do,
once your light is where you want it, is to go into the details of the light and
mess around with things like the intensity. By the way, you can click on the number 5,000 and
then just drag until it has the desired effect. OK, you can change the
cone angles here, so I'd prefer my cone is somewhat
constrained to the TriggerVolume. The Inner and Outer Cone Angle, you can make it quite...
Let's go back into the 3D. You can make it quite focused if you like, like
this. It's kind of saying this is the area that this thing is going to work in. We could make it a little more
subtle. This is a bit screaming at you, like go stand over here, but if we made it a bit
more subtle and perhaps say the color of... I mean later on thinking
that maybe the chair is the thing that triggers this, so we could use the Color Picker
from the chair, although it's not doing a great job, so I'm just going to
pick a yellow that looks a bit like it, somewhere around there.
Yeah, so the light has some sort of indication of the chair, which might indicate
that they might want to drag the chair over there later. Let's have a look! The point is
it's kind of subtle but there's a visual cue that you may want to stand here and that, that opens
the doors. Cool! Let's deal with the delays guys, without further delay!
Click on the door, let's go into the OpenDoor code...
...and let's start thinking about how we're going to do this. So, in order to
put a delay in, what we're going to need to do is have some concept of time.
So, what have we got in terms of the time component?
Well, if we get the world, once we've got the world and start looking for
methods that contain time, then let's see what we have.
While we wait for Visual Studio to finish loading and working out how it's autocomplete
works, let's just go to Google, get time Unreal's
c++ would be an example of a Google search you could do here, and
"Get current system time and date". That type of answer might lead you to it!
I've got something from Visual Studio stuck on my screen. Let's just see if I can...
That's popping over the... There you go! Hmm?
It's not leading to a lot of good results. Let me just tell you the answer. We want "gettime
seconds". OK,
Unreal, UWorld::GetTimeSeconds. And the thing about this is, it "Returns
the time in seconds since the world is brought up for play" and it "IS stopped when game
pauses" or if we change the time scale, if the game slows
down or speeds up, like it was slow motion or something. So, that's what we want, GetTimeSeconds
and it's from the world, so let's go in and take a look. I seem to have
two editors open. This can happen, so if it does happen what you need to do is
make sure you close the one where you didn't make your changes. There you go!
So, GetTimeSeconds()
and there it is! So, that is how we return the seconds! So, what are we
going to need? Well, what I'm going to do is make myself something, a couple of
different variable here. One is going to be editable anywhere, and it's going to
be something that says, to the designer, what is
the DoorCloseDelay as a float,
floating point number? OK, and let's give it a sensible value
to start with, 1 second perhaps. DoorCloseDelay.
We're also going to need a few other privates here, for this guy
to work. So, we're going to need to know float. Why float? Why is it a floating point
number? Because you can't count it on your fingers, it has a decimal point in it.
LastDoorOpenTime;
that would make sense, and I think that's probably
all we need for now. We may also need a level low time
or something, but let's just see how we go with this. So, we've got a couple of things
to store time in now. Now, what we need to do is write some code that's actually
going to check when the door last opened. So, the
first thing we're going to need to do here is, once the door is opened, we're going to say Door
LastOpenTime = this
guy here. Yeah,
that's fine! So, you open the door and you store when you open the door.
Now, what we're going to need to do is regularly check to see if it's time to
close the door, just underneath here. So, "// Check
if it's time to close the door".
And if we do, we're going to call a closed door method. Now, I'm going to leave you to write
"// Check if it's time to close the door". But I'm just going to refactor, do some refactor. I'm going to Open
Door() with you, so that we can make the ClosedDoor() method really simple. So, let's go look at
OpenDoor() and let's copy it,
make a new method called ClosedDoor() because it's so similar,
and let's take a look at it! So, it's big right? It's a bit too much!
It's not so easy looking at OpenDoor() and ClosedDoor() to see exactly what they do. So,
AActor* Owner, they both need Owner, so why don't we have a private
variable here called AActor* Owner;
and this is "// The owning door". OK,
and then, we can go and set the Owner on Begin
Play(). So, on BeginPlay() we find
the Owner and the Actor that opens, so therefore we don't need this
AActor* Owner = GetOwner(); to happen in the OpenDoor() or the ClosedDoor().
And somewhat I did that. I just pulled it out!
I took it out and said OK, this guy has a private property that
is found on Start(), and therefore we don't need to use it both open and close. We've made it a more
global variable. Cool! Now, ClosedDoor(), did we ever make Closed
Door() a method here? We didn't! We need to say void ClosedDoor() in the header file, because
that's C++ making our life a little bit harder, but
makes also things very clear. Good! So we now have ClosedDoor(), so this will
stop complaining eventually. I also think that we don't need this complexity of creating the rotator
and then calling it. I think that we can take this f rotator and stick it
straight in here. So that gets rid of all that code, remember less code is better. And also,
this angle is hard coded, whereas we've actually already made ourselves
an OpenAngle thing. It should be -90 degrees,
as a default, and then, here we can just say OpenAngle.
Does that make sense? So we've really simplified OpenDoor()
and we don't even need the comment, because it's obvious it sets the rotation. OpenDoor() just sets the
rotation to the open angle. Simple, what does ClosedDoor() do? Well,
it's just going to set the door's rotation and your roll pitch to 0.
OK, so again, we don't need any of this stuff.
How simple is that now? That's what you want! OpenDoor(), ClosedDoor() just reads
English simple. It's worth it! Make the effort, refactor, refactor, refactor! OK
guys, you've got a ClosedDoor() method to call now. I want you to write the code that goes in
here, that is continuously checked to see if it's time to close the door.
Implement close door delay. Write some simple timing code, get the doors closing after a specified
delay, play-test to ensure you can't escape.
OK welcome back, let's get this done! So, it's relatively a simple thing to do! We
just need to say, if and then this thing here. Now, you might argue, you
might want to store the time in seconds in a variable but that's fine. If
the current time - the LastDoorOpenTime is greater than
the... What do we call it? DoorCloseDelay,
then...
CloseDoor(). I know it almost seems too simple when you
get all the naming right, when everything lines up, it is almost too simple,
and that's what you want. And it's almost too simple, because we've made the effort.
Go over to Unreal. I'm just going to make sure by compiling here, because
what I see in Visual Studio is that this compiled a bit too quick for my liking.
So, to make sure it's compiled, I'm compiling over in Visual Studio. Now, let's play and see what
happens! Go into the light, they open, move out... Do they close?
They do! Perfect! Can I escape? Ah yes! So, how do
I play-tune it? Now, this is the beauty of the way we've set this up! Have a little look!
How do we play-tune it? Well, you click on the door, you go to the OpenDoor, look what I've got! Ooh,
my Open Angle is not controllable, so let me just quickly fix
that in here. The reason it's not editable is because we've changed it to (VisibleAnywhere),
whereas it could be (EditAnywhere). OK, so that is
easy! Save back in Unreal. We can quickly compile.
As soon as that compile finishes, this Open Angle should become editable.
So this door is going to open 90 degrees,
when something intercepts the Trigger
Volume and we have
a DoorCloseDelay of 1 second. Let's try half a second!
OK, let's try that door then. So, we come over here, boom, and it closes
in our face! Great! Now, let's take the other door. What time
does that need to be? -90, I'm actually going to have it open less, -60 just for fun.
And the Close Delay, you can click on here and drag and I'm going to try 0.7-ish.
So, can I get out of this door? Not quite! How annoying!
So, the game is finally really annoying! Look I'm stuck! [Grumbles]
[Grumbles] I can't get out! OK, so now I'm really annoyed! I'm this drone or something
flying around in this room, I can't get out of the sealing! I can see freedom, I can taste it, I can
smell it, but I can't get out, and I can't get out of these doors either!
So not a problem, we will have a solution, which I think in my game
is going to be moving that chair over the pressure plate and dealing with how that's going to work. We have
affordance. The color of this light is the color of the chair. It's subtle visual
hints, and that's what we'll deal with next!
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1:Unreal/Section3/BE18 Using GetTimeSeconds().srt