Welcome to Grabbing System Overviews!
So. in this video we're going to do a quick look at the end result of the
next few videos. because it's going to be a mini series about how to create a
grabbing system. so we can actually pick up the chair and put it on a pressure plate. A very useful
general tool. right. in a a game. to be able to pick something up and move it.
So. you can try and think about how it may be done. as a part of this video.
and I'll be outlining how we'll be doing it. So. you can think about it. work out what
you're questions and concerns are. and then. I will show you my solution and
outline the end result. So. we won't actually be doing any changing or any coding. we'll just be
getting a mental model of how it all fits together. So. let's dive in and do
that and just watch this video. Nothing to actually do in Unreal. until the next video.
So. let's take a look at roughly how this may end up! We're going to play the game!
The idea is that. as we move around we're constantly sending
out a beam that decides what we're going to collide with. When we get close enough to the chair. we suddenly grab
hold of it and that means that we can then move and manipulate it around the scene.
OK. so how may this work? Well.
the first thing I want you to do is. just write down your ideas. using your knowledge to date. as to how
it might work. Use the knowledge you have already. Would you use a
component to do this. or would you use inheritance?
Hint: either could work. I just want to hear you reasoning to yourself at this
stage. so do it in the discussions with the other students.
How might you know what to grab? How
might you ask the game what to grab? You see. you don't know the answers to these questions. but what I
want to know is what your questions are. It would be interesting to see what you're thinking
at this stage and what open questions you have and what ideas you have. And what game
object would you be working with? So. we want to know. you know. what game object are we going
to be working with? Are we going to make a specialization of it? Is it. is a
or is it a has a? Do we put a component on? And then. perhaps maybe how it's going to
work. So. I just want you to get in the habit of thinking about a chunk of work like this. like a grabbing
system. That's going to take several lectures worth of teaching to get it out.
And think about what the issues could be and be brave enough just to share them. You
don't have to have all the answers. Some of you will have great answers. some of you will just be full of questions.
but that's part of the process. so have a go!
Welcome back! So. let's take an overview of how I
plan to do the grabbing system. We want to be able to life the chair next. as I said. So.
we'll add a Grabber.cpp component to the player. Now. remember that the
player. in this case. is a default pawn. and it's a Default Pawn that we don't
have access to until the game runs. which will introduce some interesting
challenges. So. the player is a temporary actor and
it appears on play. The player is a Default Pawn. a pawn is an actor.
so the player. the temporary actor. the Default Pawn. they're all the same thing. and they
don't appear until the game starts playing. It's the Game Mode. which sets
which Default Pawn to use. so
we need to be making a modification to the Game Mode. So. we're going to create a Default
Pawn and a Game Mode Blueprint. We're going to do both of those in Blueprint. because it's just
easier. and you'll see why later on. It avoids something called hard coding of
assets. What that means is. we don't end up typing the exact name of
our modified Default Pawn into code. because
if we do that and we change the name in the editor. then it won't be tracked.
So. we'll see why Blueprint is very useful for binding assets to our code.
And once we have changed the Game Mode
and made ourselves a new Default Pawn. we will specify
our modified Default Pawn to the Game Mode. So. all sounds a bit
confusing doesn't it? Let's work from the top and just think about it once more. Let me show you
it in action. Bear in mind. your project won't look like this right now. because I have it setup.
This is the end result of the next few lectures. alright. So. what I'm saying is that under
Project Settings and Maps and Mode. what
we're going to end up with is a different Game Mode. We're going to make a Blueprinted version of our Game Mode.
Previously we had this set. and that doesn't let you choose the Default Pawn
class here. in the Editor. You could do it in code. but we want to be able to do it in the editor. So. we
change to a Blueprint version. after having made it. We will then make a
new Default Pawn Blueprint. I'll show you that in a minute and specify it here.
The Default Mode Pawn Blueprint thingy will be here.
and it will be something that we could create in the world. like this. if I've modified the shape into a
rugby ball. to prove that it's a different version. And that thing there can be
edited. We can change the Default Pawn and we can change its
size and it's shape. and crucially we can change the fact that it has a grabber on it!
So. we'll make this different. slightly odd shaped Default Pawn. We'll probably
put the shape back afterwards. just to prove that we're making changes
and that the Grabber component will be added. So. once we've done that and we've
made this Default Pawn thing. that's based on Pawn. we will then be able to pass that
back to the Game Mode and say. here Game Mode. this is the thing that you need to be
instantiating when the game starts. This new Default Pawn. I'll
just call BP for Blueprint. Alright. so that's an overview of how we're going to
do all this. What remains next to just get on and make that happen!
But before we do. I just want to tell you a tiny bit about Game Mode. so that you can go off and read about
it. So. Unreal describes the Game Mode as "Anything from what inventory
items a player starts with or how many lives are available to time limits
and the score needed to end the game belongs to GameMode."
So the parameters. the rules of the game in general. You can go ahead
and click that link there. from the digital version of the slides. or just Google
for it and read a little bit more about Unreal's GameMode now. And I'll see you in the next video.
and we'll start putting it all together!
=======
Welcome to Grabbing System Overviews!
So, in this video we're going to do a quick look at the end result of the
next few videos, because it's going to be a mini series about how to create a
grabbing system, so we can actually pick up the chair and put it on a pressure plate. A very useful
general tool, right, in a a game, to be able to pick something up and move it.
So, you can try and think about how it may be done, as a part of this video,
and I'll be outlining how we'll be doing it, So, you can think about it, work out what
you're questions and concerns are, and then, I will show you my solution and
outline the end result. So, we won't actually be doing any changing or any coding, we'll just be
getting a mental model of how it all fits together. So, let's dive in and do
that and just watch this video. Nothing to actually do in Unreal, until the next video.
So, let's take a look at roughly how this may end up! We're going to play the game!
The idea is that, as we move around we're constantly sending
out a beam that decides what we're going to collide with. When we get close enough to the chair, we suddenly grab
hold of it and that means that we can then move and manipulate it around the scene.
OK, so how may this work? Well,
the first thing I want you to do is, just write down your ideas, using your knowledge to date, as to how
it might work. Use the knowledge you have already. Would you use a
component to do this, or would you use inheritance?
Hint: either could work. I just want to hear you reasoning to yourself at this
stage, so do it in the discussions with the other students.
How might you know what to grab? How
might you ask the game what to grab? You see, you don't know the answers to these questions, but what I
want to know is what your questions are. It would be interesting to see what you're thinking
at this stage and what open questions you have and what ideas you have. And what game
object would you be working with? So, we want to know, you know, what game object are we going
to be working with? Are we going to make a specialization of it? Is it, is a
or is it a has a? Do we put a component on? And then, perhaps maybe how it's going to
work. So, I just want you to get in the habit of thinking about a chunk of work like this, like a grabbing
system. That's going to take several lectures worth of teaching to get it out.
And think about what the issues could be and be brave enough just to share them. You
don't have to have all the answers. Some of you will have great answers, some of you will just be full of questions,
but that's part of the process, so have a go!
Welcome back! So, let's take an overview of how I
plan to do the grabbing system. We want to be able to life the chair next, as I said. So,
we'll add a Grabber.cpp component to the player. Now, remember that the
player, in this case, is a default pawn, and it's a Default Pawn that we don't
have access to until the game runs, which will introduce some interesting
challenges. So, the player is a temporary actor and
it appears on play. The player is a Default Pawn, a pawn is an actor,
so the player, the temporary actor, the Default Pawn, they're all the same thing, and they
don't appear until the game starts playing. It's the Game Mode, which sets
which Default Pawn to use, so
we need to be making a modification to the Game Mode. So, we're going to create a Default
Pawn and a Game Mode Blueprint. We're going to do both of those in Blueprint, because it's just
easier, and you'll see why later on. It avoids something called hard coding of
assets. What that means is, we don't end up typing the exact name of
our modified Default Pawn into code, because
if we do that and we change the name in the editor, then it won't be tracked.
So, we'll see why Blueprint is very useful for binding assets to our code.
And once we have changed the Game Mode
and made ourselves a new Default Pawn, we will specify
our modified Default Pawn to the Game Mode. So, all sounds a bit
confusing doesn't it? Let's work from the top and just think about it once more. Let me show you
it in action. Bear in mind, your project won't look like this right now, because I have it setup.
This is the end result of the next few lectures, alright. So, what I'm saying is that under
Project Settings and Maps and Mode, what
we're going to end up with is a different Game Mode. We're going to make a Blueprinted version of our Game Mode.
Previously we had this set, and that doesn't let you choose the Default Pawn
class here, in the Editor. You could do it in code, but we want to be able to do it in the editor. So, we
change to a Blueprint version, after having made it. We will then make a
new Default Pawn Blueprint. I'll show you that in a minute and specify it here.
The Default Mode Pawn Blueprint thingy will be here,
and it will be something that we could create in the world, like this, if I've modified the shape into a
rugby ball, to prove that it's a different version. And that thing there can be
edited. We can change the Default Pawn and we can change its
size and it's shape, and crucially we can change the fact that it has a grabber on it!
So, we'll make this different, slightly odd shaped Default Pawn. We'll probably
put the shape back afterwards, just to prove that we're making changes
and that the Grabber component will be added. So, once we've done that and we've
made this Default Pawn thing, that's based on Pawn, we will then be able to pass that
back to the Game Mode and say, here Game Mode, this is the thing that you need to be
instantiating when the game starts. This new Default Pawn, I'll
just call BP for Blueprint. Alright, so that's an overview of how we're going to
do all this. What remains next to just get on and make that happen!
But before we do, I just want to tell you a tiny bit about Game Mode, so that you can go off and read about
it. So, Unreal describes the Game Mode as "Anything from what inventory
items a player starts with or how many lives are available to time limits
and the score needed to end the game belongs to GameMode."
So the parameters, the rules of the game in general. You can go ahead
and click that link there, from the digital version of the slides, or just Google
for it and read a little bit more about Unreal's GameMode now. And I'll see you in the next video,
and we'll start putting it all together!
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1:Unreal/Section3/BE19 Grabbing System Overview.srt