Hey. so welcome to
Modifying the Default Pawn Actor! In this video. we'll talk about why Blueprint
is helpful. I'll tell you right now. Blueprint is helpful when you are making
templates of assets. because
it's very visual. it's very clear in the Editor what you're changing. and you're preventing yourself from
hard coding changes and assets into actual C++ code. which means that
if you want to change the name of an asset. for example. then the editor will track those changes.
I'll show you how to make a Blueprint from the Default Pawn.
Note this Blueprint class inherits from the Default
Pawn. So. Blueprint class is based on the C++ class. it is a
relationship. Blueprint is like a
template. As I said before. it's like it sounds. it's a plan for building something.
And you can make an instance in the scene of a given Blueprint template.
we'll be doing that. and we will explore instantiating from Blueprint.
which is exactly what I just said. It's creating an instance. it's instantiating
and then modifying the thing that's in the scene and seeing that. that doesn't change the Blueprint.
So. the blueprint is a template. basically. So. let's dive in and see all of this happen!
So. let's see how we're going to get a handle on this Default Pawn. Remember.
that when we start the game and we eject ourselves. the Player Controller.
from the Pawn Body there. there it is. that this pawn that's being
spawned into the world. which is available in the World Outliner here as Default Pawn 1.
is being specified by the GameMode under Project Settings.
Maps & Modes. and then. if you go into the detail of the GameMode.
it's here. It's grayed out because this is a
C++ GameMode and you'd have to specify this in code. We're going to make a
Blueprint version. so that we can specify it here in the Editor later. but
for now. what we want to do is better see how we can modify the pawn. So. how do we do that?
Well. so with the game running. click on your Default Pawn that has spawned.
Go to the Blueprints Menu and say.
Convert Selected Actor to Blueprint Class.
OK. you'll get a name. I'm going to call it DefaultPawn
_BP. for our blueprint
Default Pawn. There you go. that is done! OK. let's just close
the Blueprint Editor. for the moment. and stop to see what we've done. So.
with the game stopped and under Content your new DefaultPawn blueprint
available. note that you can drag it into the world. and it's just a copy. just
the blueprint of the very pawn that was being spawned.
because we based it on the existing Default Pawn. So. if we double-
click it. look up here at the top-right. Parent class Default
Pawn. OK. So. this is no different to the
other Default Pawn. but the crucial thing is we can change this now. We can actually make changes
to the Default Pawn. so double-click. If you get this screen. which is only showing
the Class Defaults Tab. you can click Open Full Blueprint
Editor. and that will then open this. which has the default tabs on the right but
we have various other things. Now. we don't need to worry ourselves about Event Graph or
Construction Script windows yet. but. in the Viewport. you'll see the Default
Pawn and you'll see that you can manipulate it. You could rescale it. for example. using the
R Key. and that's exactly what I want you to do now. I want
you to try making a Rugby Ball Pawn! Modify the Default Pawn somehow.
i.e. as in not that it's a mystery how. I've just shown you how. but
change it somehow. For example. scaling on one axis. Create an instance.
once you've done that. by dragging it into the world. So. close the Blueprint Editor and then
drake your Default Pawn Blueprint. like I did a moment ago.
from your Content Browser and drop it into the world. and see how
modifying the instance... So. go into your world. modify
the thing. the instance of this Default Pawn you've created. and note that it
doesn't change the blueprint. OK. And then. when you finish. just
revert whatever change you made to the Default Pawn. So. I know the instructions are
not absolutely step by step and that's on purpose. because how are you going to get any good
at manipulating the Unreal Engine. if you don't work things out for yourself. So. go ahead. pause
the video. and see if you can make sense of that now!
OK. welcome back! So. let's just take a look! Here he is! I'm going to scale
the pawn there. Now. the bit you may have noticed
is. you need to click Compile. If you just click Save or you just exit let's try it. let's see what
happens. There it is! There's the Default Pawn! Let's drag it in. you see
the new version that I just dragged in has not taken on those changes.
I'm going to delete with the delete key. Let's go back to here and see what the minimum we can do
How about saving the blueprint. does that work? Drag it in. Yes. saving the
blueprint does! OK. the reason the blueprint doesn't need to compile
is because there's nothing compile worthy going on. it's just a scale.
But in general terms. what you're going to want to do. when you edit a blueprint. is just
click Compile. which will also save it and leave. So. I didn't tell you that.
hopefully you discovered it for yourself. There you go! So dragging from Default Pawn. in the
Content Browser into the world. makes an instance of that Default Pawn. There's
two of them. Now. imagine that I scale one of these guys or rotate
it. like this. Now. we have two instances. right. One is just a
rugby ball. one's a rugby ball on its side. but if you look at the Default Pawn
itself. in the Viewport. of course it hasn't changed. it hasn't rotated.
The changes do not get written back. There is a way of writing them back from the world. but. for now. let's
keep things simple. I just want you to understand that you change the Default Pawn here. You can
add components to it. which is what we're going to do now. and that's going to be super handy.
and you can also make various other changes. So. first thing I'm going to do is scale back. OK. so
here is my Default Pawn. I scaled it on the Z axis.
and I'm just going to put it back to where it was. like that. OK. Compile
and close and just check by dragging one in. that it looks normal again. It does!
Cool! Going to get rid of all of these weird Default Pawns in the scene.
And now. we're going to talk about adding a component! So. create yourself a
new C++ class. called Grabber. but it's an Actor
Component. because it's going to go on the pawn and the pawn is an Actor. OK. it's a reusable
component! Just call it Grabber.
There it is! So. another one of these nice reusable components. like our Position
Reporter and various other things that we have in the Door Open script.
And let's just let that compile.
because until it's compiled. we won't be able to actually add it to anything.
Well. we may be able to. but let's just let it finish compelling. It doesn't take too long on my machine.
So. there you go! Let's open up an empty
component here. with all the boiler plate code that we've seen before. OK. so back
in Unreal. we now have a Grabber code here you see. Grabber (C++ Class) under
your Content Browser. C++ Classes. and then the name of the game.
Crucially. what we can do now is we can go back to Content and our Default Pawn.
We can add a Component to it. scroll down to Custom components.
and add the Grabber. Compile
and then just exit. Now. when we drop the Default Pawn in the scene. there it is! It looks very similar
but when you inspect it. it actually will have a Grabber on it. Pretty cool hey!
So. this is the reusable object that we are now going to use as a
template. to replace the one that the GameMode inserts when we play.
Remember. when we play. currently if we were to play and then eject immediately.
the one that it creates here does not have
the Grabber on it. and the one that we put in does have a Grabber Component. So what we need
to do next is. look at changing the blueprint for the Game
Mode. because it is the GameMode that determines what the Default Pawn is.
So. there you go. I hope that made sense. and I'll see you soon!