So, welcome
to Inherit Game Mode Blueprint! In this video, we're going to inherit a Game
Mode Blueprint, from a Game Mode. So, I'm going to
explain, right now, that hard coding means assets are actually written into
the code. It would mean that we refer to something by its name and file path, in the
code, and the problem with that is that it's pretty hard to
track changes, so the DefaultPawn_BP is an asset. We want to be able to rename that if
necessary, without worrying about updating all our code, as I've said there.
So, it's convenient to use Blueprint for this purpose, and what we're going to be doing
is extending the C++ Game Mode that our project
came with. By the way, why did it come with C++ Game Mode? Because, when we set
the game up, we chose C++ game in the very beginning right,, and that gives us
C++ Game Mode, which we always want, because you can always just extend nothing with Blueprint,
at least you've got the C++ there if you want it. Once you've started with Blueprint, you can't
quite as easily add C++ before it, you have to inherit
from C++ to Blueprint, and we will then ultimately be
selecting on your DefaultPawn. So, by the end of it, what'll happen if we play if I
play and... Oops, here we go! If I play and then
eject myself and then look at the pawn, a couple of things about it. Firstly, on
details, we have a Grabber component there coming by default, which is cool. And also,
we're proving that our code is getting called, because we have "Grabber reporting for duty!" So, let's see how all that works!
So, welcome back! The first thing I'm going to do is tidy up this pawn that I instantiated,
that's sitting here. It doesn't need to be sitting on my floor, so I'm going to delete that and just check
where we are. We're in a situation where the DefaultPawn is still
spawning, but at least, in our Content Browser, we have access to a Blueprint
default pawn and what we need to be able to do is actually set it under Maps & Modes.
And I'm repeating myself here, but this is important stuff! So,
first thing we're going to need is a blueprinted Building Escape Game Mode. So, our Building Escape
Game Mode, at the moment, is a C++ class right, it's here! And yes,
we can add behavior to that, and if it's going to be more natural to add it in code, we'll do that,
but what we want to do is inherit a blueprint from there.
So, it's going to be a blueprint, based on the BuildingEscapeGame
.cpp, GameMode.cpp. Alright, in
very much the same way, that if we go into our content we look at our DefaultPawn,
if you see me hover over that you see how it says Parent
Class Default Pawn. So, it's actually got a parent class already,
it's just that it's not inside our code. It's actually in...
Well, let's go into Visual Studio and see where it's getting that from. It's not solution
files that we have written. It is going to be right inside the
engine, OK, and you're going to have to dig right in to see where
"defaultpawn" is. Let's do a little search in
here. DefaultPawn
.cpp, there's an example of it. So, it's in the engine files, we don't want to mess with
those, right. So, that's why we're inheriting from the DefaultPawn
as a blueprint. We could also inherit from the DefaultPawn
as a C++ file and extend its behavior, but we're using Blueprint. So, we're going to do
exactly the same thing for the Game Mode, so I want
you to do that. Actually, I think you can work it out with what we've learned so far! So, make a Game Mode Blueprint,
find the C++ Game Mode in the Content Browser, create a Blueprint class
derived, inheriting from it. Set this as the Default GameMode in
Settings, Project Settings, Maps & Modes, and make sure
the game still runs the same what it did before. So, go ahead, pause the video,
and see if you can make the game run off your Game Mode Blueprint now!
OK, welcome back! So, this is how
I think we do it. We go find our C++ Game Mode, which is here, right-click.
Create Blueprint class based on BuildingEscapeGameMode. Cool!
Now, what are we going to call it? Well, I'm going to give you a convention, which we used before,
which is just a suffix with BP not cp, to say it's
a blueprint. Create Blueprint Class! Wicked! There it is, there's the Blueprint Inspector
and one of the cool things in here, and you can do it right away actually, is we can
set... Now, the Default Pawn Class, search for p a w n, to the
Blueprinted one that we made. Cool hey, Compile!
Remember, I said when you change a blueprint you click compile?
Nearly there, Settings, Project Settings,
Maps & Modes, Default GameMode,
pick our blueprint, close. See what happens when we play!
Now, how do we know if that's worked? Well,
we can play and eject ourselves and have a look at the blueprint.
Is this the one we're looking for? Click on it, look at Details.
Grabber, it's got a Grabber on it! Woo hoo! So,
we have changed the Game Mode to our own one. We have changed the Default Pawn
and now we've got a Grabber. Why don't we go ahead and just make that Grabber like
report for duty right. So, we Play, we Eject, we take a look at our own
body, we find the Grabber, we Open Grabber.h.
And then, I'm going to go and
find an existing UE log entry, because I don't want to have to worry about remembering
the syntax, although occasionally I'll challenge myself to remember the syntax but there it is!
OK, going to go to Grabber.h! Go find Grabber.cpp
actually, because I need the implementation. And what I'm going
to do in here is, just on BeginPlay(), I'm going to do this, I'm going to say
without any of these funny format parameters, I'm simply going to say
("Grabber reporting for
duty!"); OK, and then
match the brackets. Let's immediately build this because I get quite nervous about macros,
because if we do get them wrong then it's nearly impossible to fix.
Because the error message that you get from macros
stink or they're inadequate
to easily fix the problem. So, here we go, it's built,
which is fantastic! If we now go over, play the game again,
and look, we can see down, oops, here in
Output Log: "Grabber reporting for duty!". I think we've achieved what we want to in this
video, we have made a Grabber actually appear and report.
So, what we can do, moving forward now, is to start to actually write the functionality
into this Grabber file. We'll have a Grabber.h, which I'm going to
arrange on the left-hand side, which basically is just
boiler plate code, at the moment. We have a constructor,
it has prefixed it with U because that's Unreal's coding convention. We have a Begin
Play() and a TickComponent, and then, in Grabber.cpp it's
saying yes that it's ticking here. And, by the way, as a simple
tip, if you ever have any components that don't need to tick, i.e. that don't need to do everything every
tick, then we would disable that for performance, but we're going to let this guy tick,
which means that this TickComponent() method will be called by the engine every single frame.
OK, we've logged out that we're beginning play, and what we're going to do down here
is to start thinking about the very structure of how our grabber is going to work. So, in the
next video, we'll pseudocode that up and then start
actually making it happen! So, see you there!