So. welcome to Using
DrawDebugLine. a very handy tool! In this video. we're going to show you
how to add vectors. we'll be calculating our line trace end point.
then end of our laser vision. We'll be using debug functions
for visualization in Unreal. that's the whole point here. and we'll use Draw
DebugLine() to visualize the vectors that we're playing with.
The purpose of this. by the end of it. you will have a situation where if we come out of the player's body
for a moment. you can see that there is a red line that points wherever the player is looking.
If I repossess the player and look down and maybe move near the chair.
like something like that. and then come back out of the body you'll see that we can visualize
where the reach of our grabber is and it's really handy for working out what's going on.
So. in order to draw our line trace in the world
we're going to need to know the start point and the end of it. So to do that. we're
going to need to know a little something about vectors. so here's a quick primer on adding
vectors. So. if we have some vector A. like that. just represented
as an arrow like our player viewpoint location.
and then. we add to it some vector B like our laser beam coming out of our
eyes. Then. a + b is that vector there. You simply
add the tail of one to the head of the other. and the resulting vector is just the sum of
the two journeys. A took us to the point at the top there. B took us to the right.
so a + b. the result of those two journeys. is that overall green line.
the bottom line. OK. so how does this apply to our player
viewpoints and things? Well. we are wanting to calculate
LineTraceEnd. so we know where the system needs to draw the end of our tractor beam.
So. what have we got? We've got PlayerViewPointLocation. That's just three numbers
that tell you where the player is. relative to the origin which is at 000.
So we're already dealing with and logging out Player
ViewPointLocation and that's pretty simple. There it is. it's represented by that yellow arrow.
Another thing we've already got hold of is the
PlayerViewPointRotation. but that is stored as a rotator.
In order to use it like a vector we have to convert it to a vector. So.
PlayerViewPointRotation.Vector there just converts our
FRotator into an FVector. and we could store that in something like LineTrace
Direction. that tells us the direction in which we are going to trace our
line or the direction in which we are looking. They are the same thing.
OK. the only thing with that LineTraceDirection we've got there
is that it is something called a unit vector. When we've asked for the PlayerViewPoint
Location and gone .Vector. we've just got a vector of length
1. which is fine for telling us the direction. but what we need to do is multiply
that by the reach. How far out are we going to be able to reach? Is it 1 meter.
half a meter? It depends on how long our arms are right. So. LineTraceDirection
times reach is the resulting vector from our eye
viewpoint at the top there. out to the end of our hands.
So the question is. what is LineTraceEnd? Well. by
referring to the previous slide. that should be pretty simple to work out. But before we go
ahead and do it. let me set you up with something very useful that we can use to test
whether you've got this right. before I put you into the challenge. So here we are. what we want to be able
to do is visual in the world. at least when we eject. we want to be able to see something
sticking out the front of the player. a bit like that vector. Look imagine the
origin in the world is down here on the left for a minute. there was that vector player viewpoint location.
and then. we want to look down here. So. we want to be able to actually visualize this. How are we going to do that?
Well. let's go over to the code. there's something very useful. I'm going to put another line in
here. Yes. we're logging out to test and that's fine. We can continue doing that or
we can just comment all of this. Now. one way in Visual Studio is to hold down
Control and push K. and while still holding Control. look at the bottom left.
you can push Control C. So. you hold down Control and then push K
then C and that will comment that entire block out. So. I'm no
longer logging for the moment. but what we can do is "// Draw
a red trace in the world to visualize.
O.K. I'm going to temporarily put in the end points.
so let me make a temporary variable for the end point here. I'm going to call it FVector
and then you can finalize it in your challenge. FVector
LineTraceEnd = and let's just
make it. for the moment. the PlayerViewPoint
Location + I'm going to make a new FVector here.
and then. I'm going to make it (0.f.
0.f. and then say 20 centimeters
in the Z. So. it should draw a line going straight up. based on what we've talked about before.
The end of the line trace is our viewpoint. plus 20 centimeters up.
So. the method you want to use to draw a DebugLine just in the editor is this.
Draw. it's pretty cryptic. DebugLine() pretty cool!
Let's open the brackets. give ourselves some space. because there's lots of parameters. What does it want from
us? It wants a UWorld. it wants a pointer to a UWorld. Look UWorld *.
So. would you get that? Well. just GetWorld() and that's just going to return
the world. You see it returns a pointer to a UWorld! Wicked! Next perameter.
the line start! Well. let's draw the start of our DebugLine. for now.
from the PlayerViewPointLocation. It's a
effector right. we're all happy! We're all friends here. that's cool! Alright. what's
going to be the ending point? Well. I'm going to define here an
ending point temporarily for you. as LineTraceEnd
is PlayerViewPointLocation + a new vector.
which is (0.f. 0.f. 20.f); So. the end point is going to be 20 centimeters
above the player's head; because of the vector addition
we talked about a moment ago. it's the viewpoint + 20 centimeters up.
OK. so we're going to trace to LineTraceEnd. Just so we've got this working.
the idea is I want you to have the line tracing working. before I put
you into the challenge to actually get the reach working properly. and then you can tell it's working.
OK. now it wants a constant FColor &Color. What's that?
Constant FColor &Color. Lots of weird things going on there. we're seeing an ampersand. We've seen those
a couple of places. That's something called a reference. which we'll go into in a little more detail
shortly. but basically. you can treat things that are a reference very much like the original
object. So. don't be too off-put by that. but what we need is an FColor
so we could construct one. FColor with the American spelling. no U's here.
And you just open the braces and it's going to want something like
RGB. Now. you can click through the different signatures. and one of them here
will just simply be RGB. Here's a contructor
that just takes RGB. In fact. that's the one we want. constructor number
3 here in my Visual Studio. So. I'm going to go 255.
for the red. I'm going to go 0 for the green. and I'm going to go 0 for the blue. so that's going to give us
a pure red line OK. I'm not going to comment
that. because it's going to go out of date the moment I change those numbers. but that's the color.
What's the next parameter that it wants? Well. we're going to need to wait for the
autocomplete to catch up. Here we go! Do the lines persist? So. we're going to draw a line
in the world to see which direction we're looking. but we don't want them to persist in this case.
that is from one frame to another. They're just going to disappear immediately and be redrawn every
frame. so we're going to say false. What's the lifetime it's asking
next? Well. I don't care. so I'm going to say 0 because it's not persisting. LifeTime
is not relevant. and the Depth Priority has to do with the priority
with which this is drawn in terms of depth filtering. Does it draw in front of
or behind other things? We don't care for now. 0 is fine as well OK.
Cool. little semicolon on the end of that! And that is just
giving it all the parameters it wants. Let's try building. see what happens
What I'm hoping is we're going to get a red line. Oh. I've missed one parameter haven't I?
I didn't give it a thickness! You see it was asking for thickness! It's
happy without one. but I'm going to make the thickness say 10 centimeters
OK and just rebuild. By the way. with building. you see this file isn't
saved here in the IDE. If you go over to Unreal. even without the file saved. and click Compile.
go back to your IDE. you see it has actually saved the file for you
and it's compiling. but of course. we have a compile fail so let's see what the
problem is. Literal suffix F operator on line 59
and you can get your errors from Unreal too! Let's go see what's wrong with that.
and it's because if you're going to have a float you've got to put a decimal in it. Again. I could go back
to Unreal and compile from there. This time. we should get more joy! That's
it! Now we play! Now. I can eject either by hitting the Eject button or
you can see the short key there. it's F8. If I zoom out. then
do we have a debug trace?Either inside. Yeah we do. but it's inside our body.
and that means that 20 centimeters is simply not enough. So. let's do the
hot reload! I'm still playing here. you see! Now. I'm going to pop back to the IDE.
I'm going to make the length of this vector
here. above your head. more like 50 centimeters. I'm going to go
back to Unreal. without even saving. and just click compile while we're running!
It's going to do what we call a hot reload! Ah here we go! Now. because we're quite
big. 50 centimeters just sticks out the top but it is sticking out. Cool. so
now we have a vector from the center of the sphere sticking out the top. You're now
ready for your challenge. here's your challenge! So. calculate LineTraceEnd! I want
you to create a private variable. float reach = 100.f; 100 centimeters to start with.
I've kind of done that for you. just put it in the right place in the right file. Calculate Line
TraceEnd through the simple vector addition. I've set you up for it. you may need to recap the
last couple of slides or earlier in the video. Test the debug trace. eject
to visualize. like I just did. to make sure it's working right. and then. share in the discussions
why. from your point of view when you're inside the player. it looks like a square.
From the outside it'll look good. but why from the inside does it just look like a square?
Share that in the discussions and I'll see you in a moment!
OK welcome back! So the LineTraceEnd that we actually want
is the PlayerViewPointLocation. per the slide. plus the
PlayerViewPointRotation oops
.Vector()
times Reach; OK.
now I need to make something called Reach. So. we're going to go to the header file.
which is one way to get to it is to go drill in here to Source. BuildingEscape.
Grabber.h. Down in the private section. I'm going to make a comment
first. so that it's self documenting. "// How
far... Hmm. what do we say?
So. "// How far ahead of the player can
we reach in cm" (centimeters)? And then. I'm going to go... I don't need to say private. I just need to say float. private. I just need to say float.
Woops. this is an edit after the fact! It looks like I failed my own challenge here! Of
course. I do need the word private. so please go ahead and put private colon above.
I'll add that in. in a few lectures time. because to do it now would mess up my
code history. so well spotted if you saw that!
Reach. which I've kept copied. = 100f to give it an initialization.
Now. back in the actual implementation file.
Reach should work absolutely fine. and this is basically ready to go. All I've done
is taken the PlayerViewPointRotation times the Reach and added it on there. You can
put all this in brackets if you want. If you're in insert mode. you can put it in brackets.
but because of body math. you may have heard of the presence of arithmetical
operators. The star here will bind. the multiplication will
bing more strongly than the plus. so it's going to do it this way anyways. So. strictly speaking
you just don't need the brackets. but if in doubt stick them in.
OK. let's build! It's running the
header tool. Skippity beepy dee... OK. so we've got a
problem on Grabber.h 25. and I've done the same
thing that I did before. You need the decimal before your f. OK. rookie
error. Let's go back into Unreal and compile from there! It doesn't really matter whether you build from
Visual Studio or compile from Unreal. it's the same job. Unreal is reaching into Visual
Studio and doing that compilation for you. So.
I've actually already ejected and it's running. and look it's straight out in front. Now. if I repossess
and look around. it's just a square. You're going to explain in the discussion why that's
the case. and that's because we're looking straight down that vector. If I F8 to
un-possess and come out. it's because our camera is right in the center of this
looking straight down that debug trace. and that's why. from that point of view.
it just looks like a square! OK. congratulations.
that's massive progress. and I will see you soon!