So welcome to
LineTraceSingleByObjectType()! In this video, we're going to meet references
for the first time, that's when you see an ampersand. We'll be using, well
we won't be using LineTraceSingle, because it might be deprecated. So, we're going to use
LineTraceSingleByObjectType(). We will build our parameters,
including something called an FcollisionQueryParams object, and there's a couple
of places you can go looking for documentation. One is there and the other
is there. Sorry, that's a little hard to read at the bottom, but I think you can see it clearly enough.
So, without further ado, let's dive in! By the end of the video
what we'll be doing is, as we walk up to objects like the table and the chair, if you look in the
output log there you can see that it's recognizing that we're hitting those
and logging it out, but it's not recognizing walls and doors. So, let's do it!
So, here we are ready to do our ray-cast, or in other
words a line-trace. I'll put ray-cast in brackets,
in case you ever want to search for that. Remember your future self and what you might want to search
for. OK, so what's the method and how do we find it? Well,
the method actually applies to the world. We're going to be line-tracing
in the world, so firstly we get world, and then, we
see what we've got. So I'm just going to do a search for trace and see what we have, all sorts of
stuff. Here you go, these are the ones we want! We have LineTraceMultis
and LineTraceSingle. Now, a LineTraceMulti will pass through multiple objects and
report multiple answers, so if you look at the signature for this one
you can see here we have an array coming out. OK, so we
want LineTraceSingleByObject
Type(). Remember we were going to be sorting for the object type,
which is the physics body over here. You see on the table.
And then just to recap what we talked about before, Collision and then
Collision Presets, Object Type of the table is a Physics
Body. OK, so that's what we want to filter for. So,
we're going to look for the method that is LineTrace
SingleByObjectType(). Now be careful,
if you use LineTraceSingleByChannel, for example, it will appear to work,
but it will ignore your filter and it'll return all objects.
So, just a word of caution there, use the right method. There are
actually a couple of methods which have
different names but behave almost exactly the same. Alright, so what do we
do? How do we do this? So, let's open up the brackets just to get our exploration
going, give ourselves some space. The first thing is, we need an out
parameter called an FHitResult, so let's go create one.
Here we go! FHitResult
LineTraceHit.
Something like that! Alright, well you could just call it Hit.
That's what you're hitting, so we could just call it Hit, nice and concisely.
FHitResult Hit; So, that's our first parameter, but it's an
OUT parameter, so I'm going to mark it as an OUT parameter. OUT Hit.
OK, now once Visual Studio catches up, what do we have next? The start, so this
start is the PlayerViewPointLocation. What's the end?
Well, we've already made the end, it's the LineTraceEnd.
Cool! Then what? Now it wants an FColliision
ObjectQueryParameters, and there's an ampersand in here, like you may have seen an ampersand
in a couple of other places, ObjectQueryParams.
OK, so let me explain what this ampersand is firstly. This ampersand
is a reference. So, introducing references!
References are special pointer denoted by an ampersand. They can't
be null pointer or any other null value. You'll discover with pointers later that we can point
at nothing, not the case with a reference. They can only be assigned,
they cannot be reassigned, so once you've assigned a reference to a particular object that's it,
you're stuck with it. And think of them just like an alias, you basically
use them just like the object they reference, so they're not too scary. They behave very
much like an alias to the object they're referencing. OK, so back over here,
the next type of parameter that is says we want is an
FCollisionObjectQueryParams. What is that?
Well, let's go take a look at it! Now, we can do this right in line here, so let's go FCollision
ObjectQueryParams. What is this? "It's a
structure that contains a list of object types, the query is
interested in". OK, so let's just write that type, and then open
the braces to get the constructors. What have we got? We've got one here.
InObjectTypesToQuery is an int32.
That looks horrible because int32 does not look like a good
way to encode an object type, this one takes no parameters.
Don't worry about that signature type for now or that one.
Ah, but this one here will construct a set of query parameters, based
on a collision channel. That is the one we want alright! So again, just look at this
signature and go, well how on earth would I make any progress here? Well, just try typing
)ECollisionChannel). What is that?
It's an enum, so colon colon to access it's members,
and then, if you start typing phy for physics, we have ECC
i.e. E Collision Channel PhysicsBody. That's how we
tell it we only want to look at physics bodies. Finally,
it wants an FCollisionQueryParameters input as well, not
FCollisionObjectQueryParameters but FCollisionQueryParameters. Now, I'm just going to
show you how this works, because it's the first time you've seen this. It's no good me challenging
you to do this. I will challenge you to do the last bit of this. So, let's
do a couple of things. Let's firstly make
"// Setup query parameters".
Now, by the way, with these comments if you use double forward slash
like I have been, we create a small problem. Look at this, let me zoom up to here.
You see these two lines, "// Get player view point this tick" and then
FVector immediately below. Look what happens if I hover over PlayerViewPointLocation here.
It says "Get player view point this tick" because the comment that I've highlighted is binding
to the declaration below. So for comments that
apply to a whole block of code, you can use triple forward slash to stop that from happening. I'm going
to get rid of my log there, and I'm going to put some triple forward slashes
in here and here
and here and here. OK, and that's just
going to stop Hit from getting the comment and the documentation of what's
above. Alright, we'll talk more about comments and self documenting stuff later
on. Alright, so we have this f result here, and it's an OUT parameter
yada yada. So what we need next, as we say, just to recap is
something of type FCollisionQueryParams. So, let's explore this
FCollisionQueryParams thing.
What constructors do we have? Open the braces.
So, this one here is asking for binTraceComplex = false.
What does that talk about? Well, let's talk about that parameter briefly. What this is about
is, if you do a complextrace then the ray is going to go
out and find out whether it intersects with this stuff, this detail of the chair like
the arms. Whereas if you put false for that, so you do a simple trace, then it's just going to look
like this collider. We're going to do simple. So, when you see that parameter
we're going to false, but we're not going to use this constructor, because we want more control.
I'm going to use this one. It's got the TraceTag, which we're not using. Don't confuse that with any
of the other trace. Forget what TraceTag is for the moment. I'm actually just going to provide that
as nothing, so I'm going to say FName open braces (Text) open
braces, then just nothing OK.
And then going carefully outside of there, I'm going to go to the next parameter. I'm going to
put false for complex, because we want to do a simple trace into
these colliders, these simple colliders.
OK, and then the final parameter is it wants an Actor to ignore.
Well, let's just GetOwner(), we're just going to ignore ourselves
right. So, this is tricky
to use but once you've done it once, that's a template for getting started with a
simple trace. If you do want to be able to intersect with say the arms of the chair, per the Visibility
Collision, then you would change this false to true. We won't worry about the
tag for now, and obviously you ignore yourself, because if you look when the game
runs and we Eject we have a finite volume, not that you can see us in this view.
We have a finite volume and the trace starts right from right in the center of this sphere,
and if we don't ignore ourselves, the first hit will be ourselves.
So, we setup the parameters, now we can pass those in. Of course, we haven't given them
a name yet, so FCollisionQueryParams give them a name
TraceParameters
like that. OK, and then TraceParameters
and a semicolon on the end, keeping track of all
our white space. And hopefully we then have something
that's going to compile. Let me go to Unreal and compile it, and then, I'm going to give you a quick challenge to
do. And it will be a relatively quick and simple challenge, it's a
logging challenge. I want you to log out what the Actor is. But let's just check that our code compiles
to this point.
It's taking a little longer than usual. There it goes! Let's just run!
And it works but we're not getting anything on the console, because we haven't got a log statement. So, I want you to log
the Actor here. Get the Actor* pointer from the Hit. The Hit that
comes back is quite a nice complex object, it's got a lot of information in it. See if you can get the Actor*
pointer from that. Perform a ->GetName() on this Actor* and then log the
name to the Console, making sure it works, so when you walk up to the table or the
chair or any of your other Physics Body objects it should log to the Console that you're hitting them,
once you're within a meter, and any other object like the floor and ceiling shouldn't.
So, let's explore this Hit thing here. What is it?
It's an f Hit result, it's not a pointer, so we can use dot. What
can we get from it? We can get the Actor. Fantastic! What does GetActor
return? A pointer to an Actor. So, let's do that! Let's
say Actor AActor* pointer to
an Actor. ActorHit = Hit.Get
Actor(); OK, if I could spell right
then we'd be there. Now, a useful protection mechanism,
you don't have to do this, is to say if (ActorHit). It reads nicely and it makes sure
that, that pointer isn't associated with nothing, so that if there wasn't an ActorHit we skip this
code. So, we're going to do a UE_LOG() again here. Open the
brace. Good old Visual Studio is completing the closing brace for us. We're going to make
it (LogTemp as usual Warning,) verbosity. Keep it in yello
format, so it needs TEXT() remember? Then, what do we put
in here? Well, I'm going to say something like (Line trace hit: ")
and then put a string in with a format operator %s.
After those braces I'm going to do what? Well, I need
to get the Actor name, so we have ActorHit,
and then, it's a pointer so it's an arrow operator. GetName()
which is a method. Now, we're nearly there but I'm going to put Actor
Hit ->GetName() in some brackets, then point out that ActorHit
->GetName() is going to return an f string and that the UE_LOG wants us to dereference
those f strings with a star, as we've seen before. So that line there, carefully
written, should give us the result we want. Let's go have a go in Unreal and see!
I'm being lazy, I'm not even saving the file in Visual Studio,
and something has gone wrong! Let's take a look! Line 73
"unexpected end of file and macro expansion". So, let's see what we're doing wrong there.
I'm missing a closing brace, I didn't match my braces.
Let's try again!
And that make sense right, the error was unexpected end of file. That's because it
was missing a brace. OK, let's look around! Look at the floor, look at the wall, hit the
doors! None of it's logging anything, but the chair
and the table are logging! Awesome, we now are line tracing out
and working out what we're intercepting. It's nothing to do with that red line you
see, that's just a debug line we could turn that off, but it's absolutely working
and that's great news!