So. welcome to References & Pointers! The purpose
of this video is to make this difficult topic a little more clear. One of the hardest things about C++
is that fact that we get bogged down in these details of references and pointers. We
have to because a lot of the Unreal API's make us think about these things.
but let's get it out of the way and let's understand it better than we have before!
So. let's start by comparing pointers to references. Firstly. what is stored in
both a pointer and a reference? Well. it's a memory address in both cases.
but can it be reassigned? Well. a pointer can be reassigned. If you're
pointing to something. you're at liberty to change that pointer to point to something else.
however. the reference. once it has been assigned to something. it cannot be
changed. Can it be null? Well. a pointer
can. A pointer can actually point to nothing. In fact. you're going to see shortly that we're
going to initialize our pointers with null pointer. and
later. go and find something to make them point at. So yes.
pointers can be null but no references can't be null. and that ties into the
previous point. is that they cannot be reassigned and they must be initialized.
They've got to be given a value at creation. So. how do
you access the contents that these things point to? So. they point to a memory location. both of them.
and they're both a memory address. In the case of a pointer. you need to say star.
A way of saying star. by the way is. contents
at. so contents at ActorPtr. Go get me the
contents. at the memory location. which actor pointer points to.
but with a reference. you just treat it like an object itself. you just say ActorRef.
How do you access the address? Well.
with a pointer. the pointer is the address. If you just print out a pointer. you're
going to get a number and that number is going to be. if you're in a 32 bit system. a 32 bit number telling
you the memory address. But in the case of a reference. if you want the address.
you have to use the ampersand operator. or you can call
ampersand address of. We'll see that shortly. So. star
is contents at. ampersand is address of.
How do you assign a value? Well.
if you've got an actor and you want to assign.
make ActorPtr point to the same thing. basically. So. on the right you've got
an actor. and on the left you want the ActorPtr to point to that actor. You need
to find the address of first. so you use &Actor to get the
address of the actor and you just set the pointer to that address.
Now. ActorPtr will go to the same place that that actor does.
How do you do it with a reference on the right hand
side like that ? Well. you just use a simple assignment. It's another fact that you just
treat references like aliases. to the object that they underline
or that they represent. So.
I would suggest. even if that previous slide
was like an eyeful. then what I suggest if you move on. There's two more slides coming.
that I'm going to build up and that you watch this whole thing again. once you've seen it from beginning to end. That's
going to be better than trying to fully understand this page. right now. if you didn't get it the first time.
So. let's look at another thing that's intrinsic to understanding pointers and references
and that's the ampersand sign and the star symbol. What
do those two things do? Well. does it depends entirely on the context. If they're a prefix.
if they go ahead of the thing. they mean one and. and if they're a postfix.
they mean something else. So. let's look at those combinations! Those four combinations of prefix and postfix
for star and ampersand but let's do it by example.
So. star actor pointer. this first column
here. What does that mean? Well. that's saying
go and find the contents at. whatever *ActorPtr points to.
So. *ActorPtr is a memory address. Go get me the contents at that memory address. that's what this
is saying. The next one. now note you can do it on an
object. like an actor itself or on an actor reference. it doesn't matter.
You can use the address of operator. so you can say
what is the address of this actor? We've got an actor here. where is it stored? Or
if you've got an actor reference. you can do exactly the same thing. If you've got an actor reference.
what is the memory address? You don't do it very often. but you might want to assign it to a pointer.
for example. So. how about if it's a postfix?
Well. they do completely different things in the case of a postfix. they actually change the
type here. So. UActor alone is a UActor type. UActor* start
is a pointer to a UActor. It's a different type. UActor
could be a big value object. it might take megabytes of storage. A UActor*
is only going to take 32 bits or 64 bits. depending on your system.
and you have to follow that to go and find the actual actor.
What is UActor&? Well. that is a UActor reference.
so it's similar to a UActor pointer. with the constraints we talked about in the previous
slide. So. what's the meaning of
these things? Well. we've been saying this. *ActorPtr is the contents
at ActorPtr. The ampersand in front is the
address of the actor or the actor reference.
Whereas Actor* is pointed to Actor and Actor& is reference to
Actor. OK. and this is a class.
Notice that's why it's UActor. it make it very clear it's a class. Unreal's naming conventions are
useful in this respect. One little health warning is. that to add insult
to injury. any of these symbols. i.e. ampersand and star can have a different meaning in other contexts.
For example. ampersand can mean bitwise AND. but I think you know the
context we're talking about. We're talking about. typically. where we have a type on the left and then
maybe a symbol and then like a variable on the right. OK. so just
be slightly aware of that. they don't always mean this. Of course. star means something else. as well. doesn't it? It means multiply.
So hopefully. between these two slides. that's given you a better idea of how pointers
and references work. So. in the upcoming videos. we'll be making use of all this knowledge
and really putting it into practice. so that you can cement it and get an even
deeper understanding. So. I'll see you soon!