So. welcome to FindComponent
ByClass(). In this video. we will find out what FindComponentBy
Class() actually does. We will find out how to use it to find an
attached component. We'll be introducing angle brackets for generics. for the
first time. You'll use nullptr go initialize your pointers.
and we'll log a useful error if a particular component
isn't attached. in this case the physics handle. So. because
we're going to be using a physics handle. in a couple of videos time. let's use this as the
example as to what we add as a component. So. I want you to open your Default
Pawn blueprint. Now. if you don't see this view. you should have a link across the top
that allows you to get to this full blueprint view. If you're just seeing details and
this link across the top. that you don't see here. you should have it.
Where you want to go to is the Components section. We're going to add a component. Let's have a little look down this time.
rather than just searching. And you've got all sorts of different areas
and one of the things you've got. worth having a look at this by the way. is a Physics
Handle. "Utility object for moving physics objects around." That sounds pretty Ideal
for moving the table or chair of the component. So. let's add a Physics
Handle to the Default Pawn blueprint and then compile OK.
So now. it's got an extra component on the Grabber and a Physics Handle. Cool!
Now. we're going to refer to this in our grabber code. in a minute. and it does
mean that you have to have the Physics Handle for the grabber to work. but that's OK. we can
deal with that in code. So. let's go look at the code!
What I want to do is in the Grabber.h.
in the private section. And naughty me I. a couple of videos ago. asked you to
do a challenge and I said make the reach a private member. and I didn't put it in the
private section. So. there you go. private now exists! I'm now
going to put an uncommented thing here. because it's pretty obvious from reading it what it
is. And if it's completely obvious from reading it. why comment? What we want
is a way of storing this U
handle. And then. how do we know what it is? If I go grab handle...
Do we have a sufficiently fuzzy search? Well. you do
in Visual Studio. You can say Uhandle and you can
see the UPhysicsHandleComponent. so that's handy. There is a way  to install it in Xcode. you can ask
in the discussions or we'll show you later in the course. But what you're looking for is something of
type UPhysicsHandleComponent. We want a pointer to a UPhysics
HandleComponent*. Just going to call it PhysicsHandle
and I'm going to initialize it to nullptr.
which is a properly type checked null value.
It actually points to memory address 0. OK. so we're going to
point it to null pointer right now. because. in very beginning. when we're constructing this
object we don't necessarily know that. that
grabber that's against the PhysicsHandle has spun up.
before Grabber. So. we need to wait till the game starts. at begin
play. to go and find this Grabber. PhysicsHandle. So let me show you this. it'll come clear as we do it.
We have a reference called Physics Handle. I'll copy that. Let's go into
Grabber.cpp. and in BeginPlay() is where we're going to go
looking for it. So. find or "/// Look for attached
Physics Handle".
OK. that's what we're going to do in this section. three forward slashes to prevent
the comment from binding to the line below. So. how are we going to do it? Well.
it's going to be a new method for you! We've got PhysicsHandle. we've already got that local variable. It's a pointer.
right. to a new PhysicsHandle component.
So. how are we going to find it? Well. firstly
what object are we looking for? This PhysicsHandle. Let's go back and take a look!
If you think about it. it's the Default Pawn isn't it?
We're in Grabber right now. so we need to go up to the owner. which is the DefaultPawn.
So. we GetOwner up to here. and then we come back down to find the PhysicsHandle OK.
or sibling. So. we GetOwner().
That returns us a pointer to an AActor.
which we've got now. Because it's a pointer. we use the arrow operator.
OK. so we have that pointer to an Actor. Now. what we need to do is.
we need to FindComponentByClass. This is the method
you're going to need. FindComponentByClass. Now. there's
something a little bit different about this. the first time you've used this in angle. We're going to use some
angle brackets. This is something called a generic
signature. What this is. is this FindComponentByClassMethod will
work for multiple different classes. It's going to go and find us the physics component.
the PhysicsHandle. and it's going to find it by class. so we actually specify the class
in here. <UPhysicsHandle
Component> in square braces like that. And then.
in the brackets. Well you actually don't need anything in this case.
So that's it! So.
that's working because GetOwner() gets the owner. and then.
FindComponentByClass looks down the owner. i.e. it looks down the
Default Pawns components and looks for one that's of type UPhysicsHandleComponent.
this guy here. OK. so out of this whole statement. we get the
PhysicsHandle reference. Great! So. now what we need to do. immediately you've done
something like that. is don't assume it works! So we say if (PhysicsHandle).
So. if we get here then the "// Physics
handle is found" and we don't actually need to do
anything. in this case. else. and this is where your challenge comes in. I want you to log
a useful message that includes the name of the object.
i.e. the parent. the owner. the Default Pawn telling you
that the PhysicsHandle is missing. So. log an at Error verbosity. if no
component is found. It's an error because it's worse than normal.
Write an error. as I said. that helps the reader fix the issues. find and include the name of the object.
the Default Pawn. and temporarily remove the component
from the Default Pawn blueprint. test that it works. and put it back on. OK. so just
test that we can detect if it's not connected.
Awesome. welcome back! So the log. it's going to go something like this. It's going to go
something like UE_LOG(LogTemp. Error in this case a new
verbosity. TEXT(). Remember. we need that macro in their. And then. we're
going to say something like the name of the
object "%s missing physics
handle component") And then. the
string is going to be Get
Owner() which is going to take us up to the Pawn -> GetName()
like that. Now. remember that the GetOwner()->GetName)
this whole lot is going to return an FString and it doesn't want that.
We need to use the star. which is actually a little confusing here. It's
not a standard contents at operator.
It's actually overloaded here. which is pretty horrible. but it has the same type of
effect. It's saying. give me the contents at this FString. That's not going to
have anymore detail on that. you know you need to put a start in front of that. Let's try this!
I haven't yet removed the component. so I'm going to try it working and then I'll remove the component
and add it back. to make sure you know how to do that. So. here we should get no
error log. because the PhysicsHandle is attached. Let's go to the Default
Pawn. remove the PhysicsHandle. recompile it. play the
game. and see what we get in the logs. Ah. here we go. "Default Pawn"
"missing physics handle component". And it's quite handy. Default Pawn
BP C underscore 2. So you can reference that against the world and you'll get
almost exactly the same thing there. OK. so you would know
where does that DefaultPawn come from? You stop the game. it disappears. you think oh. it's an
object that comes on at playtime. so that's probably because
of my Game Mode. So. you'd come in here
and you'd look at Maps & Modes and you'd look at your Game Mode
and you'd realize it's the DefaultPawn blueprint. So. you'd go find your DefaultPawn blueprint
and you might then work out that you need to add a
PhysicsHandle to that. Compiling your blueprint. coming back out.
maybe clearing the log for clarity and playing again. eventually you will
see no errors. which is pretty cool. By the way. we don't need
these logs talking about where the chair is at. So. just before we finish off this video.
I'm going to go clear up the PositionReport.cpp or just remove
it actually. That's probably the best. rather than changing the code. which would break the Position
Report. I'm just going to go to say the chair. and I'm going to look for
PositionReport as a component and just remove it from the chair and the table if necessary
and anything else. like the door. None of these things need
PositionReport. That's cool! So the game plays. it's all working well! We
have a PhysicsHandle attached. you now know how to find components. and in the next
video. we're going to reuse this knowledge about finding components to start dealing with
input and input management. so that we can actually press a key to
enable grabbing mode. So that'll be fun!