Welcome to
Introducing Input Binding! A little note on these slides, I've changed the version
number of Unreal that I'm using, to the top-right of the slides because it was
conflicting with Udemy's new overlay, that they put down at the bottom right. I've also removed
the last digit, because changes in the last digit in 4.10.2
4.10.3 don't really matter. So, you just need to make sure,
if you're watching this well after 4.10 is out,
that you're aware the I'm on 4.10 and that may change things. You can always
install previous versions in the Epic Games Launcher. So, in this video,
we are going to look into Settings > Project Settings > Engine > Input.
We're going to explain that action mappings are used for on / off actions, and that axis
mappings are used for analog values like sticks or
steering wheels or rudder pedals,
that you can give players a way of re-mapping their keys. We're not going to show you how to do that right now,
but I just want you to bear in mind it can be player re-mappable, just like when you reconfigure your controls in a game.
A many keys combined to one action, which is useful, and
how to call a function on a key press or release. So that's it! By the end
of it, we're going to be in a very simple situation, where you can click say the Right
Mouse Button, and you'll see grab pressed like that coming up in the output log. OK, let's dive in!
So, let's take a look at this input component issue then. Firstly,
what is this input component and where is it? Well, firstly I'll ask
the first question first, I think. If we go to the Class Viewer... Sorry to those Mac users who currently can't
get to things that aren't in the Actors class, but if we look for input component, you can see here
that we have ActorComponent. InputComponent
is inherited from ActorComponent. OK, so it's just another Actor
Component. And if we play the game and then inspect the
DefaultPawn that comes up, you'll find that at runtime we have this thing here. Pawn
InputComponent. You can hover over it, in the Details Tab, and you can read all about it. You can also
do Control and Alt and it'll tell you more stuff, so do have a little read of that.
You're welcome to pause the video now and do that, if you like. It may not all make sense
to you, but if we stop it playing and then have a look at the...
Well, you can't stop it playing and look at the DefaultPawn because he's not there, but what you can do is look at
the DefaultPawn blueprint. You'll notice it's actually not here. This
input component comes into play at runtime. OK,
so we need to go find that. It's going to end up
against the pawn, just like the PhysicsHandle or the Grabber. Look let's see again and runtime! We run,
we inspect the DefaultPawn that's instantiated... Whoops, we
don't click on Marketplace! [Laughs}] And then, you go to Details and you can see that you've got
the Grabber and the PhysicsHandle, but you've got this new PawnInputComponent, which is just of type
UInputComponent. So, what I want you to do before we go any further is go
ahead and find that component, just like we did previously with the PhysicsHandle. Find the
input component. Create an appropriate private member. Check for the
component, as we did with the Physics Handle. Log a similarly helpful
error, if it's not attached. By the way, you could be using assert here, rather than errors.
We'll cover assert shortly in the course, probably in the next section just to keep the number of concepts
down, but yes, assert, if you're more advanced, is another way of doing things.
Don't bother trying to remove the test, remove the component
the test this time. It's not easy to stop that input component, coming on the Pawn at
runtime. So, don't bother trying to remove it, but just make sure that you've got all your error code
there. And when it actually does find the
input component, we are going to write code in that top part of the if statement. You know in the PhysicsHandle
we just wrote the comment saying, well, you know, we've got the PhysicsHandle! Yippee, we don't need to do anything right now!
Well, in this case, with the input component just pop me another log entry and perhaps just a
say physics input component found, and then, we'll replace that later on
with the actual input code. So, go ahead, pause the video, at least find the input component for me.
Cool!
Welcome back! So, let's go take a little look at this thing, over in Visual
Studio! We're going to do something almost identical to what we did before with the
PhysicsHandle. We're going to say U because that's the name of classes that are component
types. Then, we're going to start looking for something like input, and we find UInputComponent.
Wicked! It's a pointer again!
InputComponent = null pointer.
OK, so we don't need to comment that,again I don't think, because look it couldn't be...
It's self commenting, self documenting. It's just
don't comment it. [Laughs] So, what next? Now, we're going to go
into the actual implementation file and go ahead, not in the engine,
in the Games, and go ahead and actually do some stuff with it! Find it! We're going to do it
in the Start again, and we're going to have code that is very similar to this. So, I'm actually
going to copy the "// Look for attached PhysicsHandle", and I'm going to say "// Look for attached
Input Component".
"(only appears at run time)". OK, so we're going to
say InputComponent = GetOwner()->FindComponentBy
Class but ();
OK, so if (InputComponent).
That's why this is hopefully a good exercise, because it's just like the last one.
Then, we do something. Well, we're going to log to say that we've got
it. We're going to
get rid of most of this stuff at the end, and just simply say
("input component found") that'll do!
And it's not an error. We can put it as a warning, just so we can see it. We'll, start
using other types of log, at some point, just to make life clearer, but this is working
for now. It's just re-enforcing the way we're using logs, but as soon as it gets boring,
don't worry, I'll change the logs on you and make it different again. So, what are we missing?
We're not missing the PhysicsHandle component, we're missing the Input Component. So,
that's all we need to do, is very very similar to what's above. It's just modified for
the input component. Let's just test this! So, over in Unreal, let's just
compile and run and we should see a yellow log
saying input component found, if all is well. Let's see what happens!
Compiling, compiling, compiling! Taking a little longer than usual, because I've actually,
between videos, done a clear out just because I wanted
to practice something. OK, so let's take a little look! It says
here... I don't know why I'm moving the screen around. It says, "Input component found" there, which is
great news! So, with the Input Component found, it's time to start processing the input.
Let's start by going to Settings and Project Settings and then
Input, under Engine. So, Settings, Project Settings, and then, under the Engine Section
you go to Input. So, new stuff! We have Action Mappings and Axis
Mappings. Actions are binary on or off buttons, mouse clicks, etc. Axis are
analog like sticks or rudders or joysticks or steering wheels or whatever.
We won't bother with the advanced stuff. So, we're going to have a new action. So, you click the
plus and then a dropdown appears, and we're just going to call it grab, because that is
the action. Now, next to grab I'm going to bind two keys. One is going to be,
just to show that we can do more than two, one is going to be say the Left Shift. Now, you might
as well just search for it. Oops, that was very unfortunate!
OK, Left Shift, there we go! And then we will also look for the
mouse button and the Right Mouse Button.
So, either Right Mouse Button or Left Shift will map to an Action
that we're calling Grab, and you need to spell it in the code exactly like this.
So, that's it! And this is the type of stuff that the player can control, if you give them access
to it in a Menu System, for example. By the way, this is where you remap your keys.
So, two mappings to one action. OK, so just come out of there once your binding is setup,
like that, or use whatever keys you want.
So, over in our BeginPlay() we already have the code that goes
and looks for the attached InputComponent. What we want to do next, instead of logging out or
as well as logging out, we can "// Bind
the input axis". Now, what does that mean? Well, let me show you! We go
InputComponent, which is the component we found. Now, what is that? It's a pointer right,
so we use our arrow operator .BindAction.
I'm sorry if I said axis, BindAction. We're going to bind an action to
a method, so let's look at this function. One thing
at a time. Constant FName ActionName. What is that?
Well, it's just ("Grab"). That's what we used, it's got to be spelled
exactly the same as we said up in the InputPanel. OK, what next? Well,
next we need an Input Event. It's an enumerator and we want to be able to
press. It's about pressing the button, you've got IE_
input event Pressed). OK, there's another one for released as well, by the way.
So up next is the object that this is going to operate on. We're going to use this,
which is a reference to the component itself, the Grabber component.
OK, so when we push a key that is mapped to ("grab"), so
when we push highlighting the words as I go, the key that
is mapped to ("Grab") or either of the keys in this case, then
we look for a method on this which is the grabber. And then, finally what's
the method name? Now, the signature of this is horrible. Look at it! It's a horrible
complicated signature, so I'm not going to go into detail about what all these generic
syntax means right now. Well, what you do need here, is you need
to point to a function, which doesn't exist yet. So, the function
is going to be just simply called grab. So, how do we specify it? That's the
question. Well, what I'm going to do is I'm just going to specify it, and then, in the next
lecture, I'm going to talk a little bit about why we specified it
that way and then we'll go on to use it. So, the way that you do it is, you need a reference,
and then, we fully qualify i.e. UGrabber as the
class and then the method name is Grab. And you just leave
it like that, without any brackets around it.
That is just qualifying the method name. So, it's just complaining because &UGrabber::Grab) doesn't exist.
Let's make Grab, and I think for now, it needs to be private.
It can be private, that's fine. It can be void Grab()
and it's a method, so that's all there is. And I will actually comment this one. It's
"// Ray-cast
and grab what's in reach" is what Grab is actually going to do.
So, void Grab(); OK! And then we actually define Grab
over here. so, void UGrabber because that's the class name, just
like any method we've defined here. Grab() OK
and then it's going to do something, and what it's going to do is define
what was commented over here in the header file, "// Ray-cast and grab what's in reach".
So, this method will get called. That's
what we're doing here. We are providing the address of,
which is the address of operator the Grabber OK. So, we're going into that in a little
bit more detail in the next video, to keep this one at a reasonable length, but that's
how you bind the Grab component. OK,
let's just see it in action! Let's do a quick log and
then we'll leave this video and we will challenge you to do the other bit! Let's copy this log
file here, and just say it's a Warning just
so it's yellow. TEXT
("Grab pressed").
OK, so let's see this in action with the final closing
bracket. Let's go to Unreal, check it compiles,
play it! Now, let's click the Right-Hand
Mouse Button, Grab pressed, Grab pressed, or the Left Shift, Grab pressed. OK, so
I'll leave you with this code on the screen. You can hopefully see what's going on there. As I said, there's a little bit more detail
in the next lecture, but we are binding any key that maps to "Grab", when it's
pressed. We look at this, which is the Grabber, and we look for
a method called Grab, and this is an address of operator,
so it effectively jumps to this method, when we push a key.