Welcome to Reducing
Code in "Hot Loops"! A little bit of a long video. this one! You might want to grab a cup of tea and be ready
for the disciplined art of refactoring. So. in this video. we're going to
explain that a "hot loop" is code that gets called often. So TickComponent is a great
example of that. Any code in there gets called every single frame. So. I want you to be
aware of code that you know is going to get called a lot.
and you want to make it very clear what happens every
tick. so when you look at your TickComponent method. it wants to be super
clear what's going on. So. we're going to refactor our code for speed.
but also make it ready for the PhysicsHandle code to be
put in. By the end. the game will be doing exactly what it's doing now but with a much
better foundation. So. no progress on the surface but tons of progress behind the scenes.
So. let's roll up our sleeves and refactor this thing. making way for
inserting the PhysicsHandle. The code just really isn't ready right now. so let's take a
look through it. Firstly. let's zoom right out to the header file. Remember
what I said a little while ago. in the previous section. that the public section of your header file
really should sing what your class does. So. we have a constructor. which is
normal. We have a BeginPlay() and a Tick. which are normal for any engine driven
class because the engine needs to be able to begin play and Tick. The
one thing that we could argue should be in the public would be
Grab() and Release(). Now. for this example. we're going to keep the Grab() and Release() here as
private. and we're going to handle the input as we have been.
inside this grabber class. But it's a little bit mixing concepts.
Really you could consider that we could have an input controller somewhere else.
that this grabber registers with it. and that actually it's the job of the
input controller. for example. or the player controller or something
else to call the grabber and say: Hey. grabber attempt Grab() or hey grabber.
Release(). And then. we wouldn't have any of the input component code inside
here. So. just be aware of that. but we're going to leave it here for now. because it's manageable
and it's simple and it keeps us just inside one class. while
we're trying to take on a lot of different concepts. Alright. so the
API is basically nothing. There's nothing you can do from the outside. which
is fine apart from the caveat about the input I just told you. Fine. everything else looks good!
Now. what we want to do is go over to the .cpp file and start thinking about
well. how can we improve things here? Alright. so let's
start at the top. the Grabber() the Constructor(). Fine. I'm just going to get rid of a couple of empty
comment lines there. The constructor is otherwise very simple. It needs to tick.
i.e. the Tick has to be called. so let's leave it!
OK now. BeginPlay()! We want to run Super::BeginPlay(). We always leave that in place.
It's because the thing up the class hierarchy. i.e. the U
ActorComponent that we inherit from may do some stuff in the engine that we want
to be done. so you generally leave this in place. Grabber reporting for duty! We
can probably lose that. OK. what next? Well. I don't like BeginPlay(). it doesn't
fit on one screen. So. I'm just going to simply factor out the "// Look
for attached Physics Handle" bit. You can just literally cut the code.
We're going to do this manually this time. rather than letting the system do it for us.
We're going to come down below and make a new method. so I'm going to indent it.
and we've got to decide what method we would be calling here in BeginPlay(). What are we
actually doing here? Well. we are FindPhysics
Component(); That's what we're doing. we're finding the Physics
Component! Only finding it and not doing anything else. so let's now void Find
PhysicsComponent() or PhysicsHandleComponent().
Yeah. probably PhysicsHandleComponent. I'll do that in a second!
So. let's just rename this to PhysicsHandleComponent(). See if the refactor
tool will behave.
OK. void
FindPhysicsHandleComponent() and of course. we need to pop this in the headed file.
So. it can just be down here. and
this is "// Find attached
physics handle". OK cool! So. we find
the PhysicsHandleComponent. Better be good and just check that this still runs! There's no
reason it shouldn't. but when you're refactoring you want to be constantly checking
that your code still runs. So. trying to run this.
we get another compilation error. Now. this is not a helpful error. Look here. other compilation
error doesn't tell you which file. and another error here talking about the
make file. Hmm interesting. nothing on the output. so here's a tip. Here's a way
of getting a better error. By the way. if you accidentally detach like this. drag the bar
and drop it in there. Go over to Unreal and do your compilation over there.
The reason is that. the errors you're going to get in the output log are going to be more helpful
in general. So. once it's compiled. let's see what error we get.
see if we can track this down. show the log. OK. so it's saying that in Grabber
.h on line 42 it's not expecting a closed curly
brace. Did I miss a semicolon? Grabber.h line
42. Grabber.h not .cpp interestingly. Ah. yes
I missed a semicolon on the end there. Cool. let's try again. see if it'll build
now. Not in here. back in Unreal! Let's just click Compile.
That will. as I said before. actually save the file in Visual Studio which is pretty
helpful right. So it's compiling away. I think it's going to fail again. because I spotted
another error when we were in there. but I want to kind of run home
how to handle these errors. because you'll create them when you're
refactoring like this. So. let's take another look at the log. Ooh. lots of errors!
The question now comes. where's the first one? OK. so we get to line
42 of Grabber.cpp. That's the earliest line number and it says physics
handle not declared. OK. so let's go to line
42 of the .cpp. What's wrong with Physics
Handle? So. look through the comment and say. if I was a compiler and I'm reading this. why am I not
expecting to read PhysicsHandle. Well look. the problem is that in
C++ you need to put the name of the class in front of
the method name. So boom! One way to prevent that happening. by the way.
is to go to the .h file. in the future. Define your
functions in here. right-click and say Quick Actions. Create Definition.
There you go! So that was the problem there. Let's go
back and run. So. hopefully this is useful stuff about how to track down errors. Start with
the earliest line number. use the Unreal output. Good so that's working! OK. so
let's carry on now. at a little bit higher speed. We find the PhysicsHandleComponent.
Now this next lump of code. what does this do? Well. I'm actually going to write the name of the method
first. and I'm going to do it in the .h file. I think this lot sets up the input
component. so let's make one here. let's make a method. "// Setup
input component". Nice and simple void Setup
InputComponent(). Now. why am I
bothering with a comment there. you might ask?
As it is. it's not worth it. "// Setup attached input
component" or "assumed attached input component'. That's more
useful because it reminds us that it needs to be attached. Now.
if we were a little bit further into the course. I would be getting you to make these
things attached. Well. this does attach itself. the input component. but I would be getting you to make the Physics
HandleComponent attach itself. rather than attaching it to the blueprint but we're going to keep it simple.
OK. setup input component. Let's us the ability to create a definition
over here. Now. you have to wait a little bit and there you go.
you can just to the .cpp. and this time it's actually made us a setup
input component and it's put it immediately below FindPhysicsHandle
Component. in the same order as the header file. I like that! That's nice! Now that all
we need to do is go find the code that I've highlighted up in the BeginPlay().
cut it. and pop it down into SetupInputComponent(). Now. if you're a beginner. you'll wonder
why is all this worth it. what's he doing? Well. bear with me a second.
I'm going to put the comment above. You'll see that this will suddenly read a lot more nicely.
Let's look now at our begin play.
All we have to do in here is make the method call.
SetupInputComponent();
OK. and look how clear it is what happens in
BeginPlay(). You can also. if you put your comments above your methods.
if you need extra commenting here you can collapse down these two methods.
so we don't even need to see the lines with a little minus sign there.
and then. that's all super clear. On one screen. now. we can see
exactly what goes on. without worrying ourselves about the exact details unless we decide to
go in and see what's happening. So I'll just sort out a little bit of indentation in here I've spotted
and we're good to go. Alright. let's continue to move down. What should we
be doing when we grab? Well.
is it actually a Grab or is it an attempted Grab? Let's leave it as Grab for now. keep
life a bit simple. What we are actually going to do is. we're going to "// Try
and reach any actors with physics body
collision channel
set".
We're going to reach out to that distance and try and do that. Then. we're
going to say "// If we hit something
then attach a physics
handle". OK. we're going to do that later. so I'm going to put a
TODO in. "// TODO attach
physics handle". I'm going to put a triple forwardslash
here. because we're probably going to have blocks of code. OK. so that's
the fundamental of what happens on Grab(). Let's move down. What happens on Release()?
Well. you say ("Grab released") and you "// TODO" in a bit
"release physics
handle". We don't know how to do that yet but we'll get there.
OK. now we're into a hot loop here. We're into an important bit which is the TickComponent.
The question is lots of stuff happens in Tick right now. what should happen in
Tick? Well. Tick actually should be really simple. It should say something like
"// if the physics handle is attached"
then we should just "// move
the object that we're holding" each frame.
otherwise we just do nothing. Hmm.
Well. that makes it simpler. so all the stuff below needs to go
somewhere else. So. what does all
this stuff below? We're getting the player view point. we're reaching out to a certain distance. we're
drawing a debug line. which I'm going to get rid of. I'm going to get rid of the debug line. we don't need it.
We're setting up some query parameters. we're doing a line trace. we've seeing
loads of stuff. which we don't need to be doing any of it unless we're actually
holding on to something. because it's when we push the
Grab() that we're going to try and find something and do the line trace. So. try
and reach. let's say "line trace
and see if we reach any actors with physics body".
OK. so you line trace here. I'm going to put it in capitals.
only when you push the Grab Key. only one quick instantaneous
line trace. and we don't need to be doing anything every single tick.
So. what does all of this code below
do? Let's abstract it away into another method and not call it unless we need to.
and then split it up further if we need to. Well. what I think it does is. it gets the
first physics body in reach. so I will put a little comment.
"// Return hit for first
physics body in
reach". And it's going to be something like this. What we're going to have is a method that
is actually constant. It's going to return an
FHitResult and it's going to be called GetFirstPhysics
BodyInReach(). It doesn't
need any parameters. but that does mean we'll need another helper function or two.
OK. and we're sorry we're not actually giving it
any implementation here. So. that is the name of the method. Let's just go ahead
and define it. Give it a second to pop the code in.
There it is! Pop over to Grabber.cpp! So. let's try taking
all of the code from the Tick.
all this stuff apart from our comments about what it's going to do in the future and put it in
this new method. so first physics body in reach. There you go! We are
going to have to return an FHit result. so paste all that in. and then.
I'm going to put this method at the bottom. because it's kind of the latest code we've written.
Just do that now. down at the bottom here below TickComponent.
There you go. so let's go back up to Grab and actually call the Get
FirstPhysicsBodyInReach();
And that's what
we're going to do when we grab. I'm just going to highlight those and go Shift. Tab. and go back.
Later on. this is where we'd do the physics handle. Let's see what happens now. when we
actually try and Grab. Does the GetFirstPshysicsBodyInReach() work properly.
and are we back roughly to where we were. with the code all neatened out apart from the
problems all being kind of shuffled down do that huge GetFirstPhysicsBodyInReach() method.
which we'll refactor in a second.
So. let's play the game! Grab. press. and release. Let's get to the table. Ah hah.
"Line trace hit" "Grab released". That's good. so the line trace is now hitting the things
that we want. so that code is a lot more efficient now.
The Grab is working! We've got some more work to do. TODO attached the physics
handle. and then. there's a lot of stuff in GetFirstPhysicsBodyInReach().
That might get further refactored when we start working with the physics handle. That's pretty
good! Let's just have a look at our Task List. just to attach and release physics handle. All looking
good! So. at the end of this. you have absolutely no progress in one
way but in that your code does the same thing. but you've reduced
a lot of work inside the tick component. which is taking a lot of stuff outside of the hot loop
and you have prepared yourself for where you're going to be inserting
the physics handle code. So congratulations! That's refactoring. it's one of those things
you just have to grit your teeth and do. and I'll see you in the next video.