So. welcome to
Using Physics Handles! In this video. I'm going to explain that Unreal provides a really
handy tool called a Physics Handle. that's ideal for picking things up.
The Physics Handle component documents are very scant. You can look that
word up if you're not English. [Laughs] Find an example of this and
use it in the engine. So. it's a hard thing to use. unless you can see it
being used as an example. I'm going to show you how to find an
example of it in the engine. then we'll get the Physics Handle working. So. there are the docs.
And it's an exciting video because. by the end of it. we will have a situation where we can
actually pick things up and throw them around and drop them. Look at that! How cool!
So. just before we get this working. I want to talk to you about a
mental discipline that I call Red. Green. Refactor. It comes from Test Driven
Development. which is where you write your code to pass certain formal
tests. but in our case it still applies. So. the first stage
is Red. it's not working the test is failing. That's where we are now. the Physics Handle isn't
working. So. our job is to get to green. which is where it's working.
and ugly is OK. And this is the important bit. is to be
clear on whether you're just trying to get something working right now or whether you're trying to refactor.
which is the third step to make things pretty. and of course. they must still work.
So. the beauty is this. we start off with it not working. which is where we are. We
work hard to just get it working. kind of whatever it takes. We then
commit our work to source control and say. OK it works. I can now safely
make it how I really wanted it. make it pretty make it clear.
knowing that I can always go back to the working version that's ugly and try again
if I mess things up. and then. you just keep repeating that sequence. So. I just want
to stress that. before we dive in here. I'm just trying to get the PhysicsHandle
working. We're going to do whatever it takes. if it's copying and pasting code. it doesn't matter
for now. because we want to focus on one thing at a time when things get complex. And now. it's
just let's get it working. OK. so we need the Physics
Handle component. Let me just go back a slide to here. which is
the documentation of the Physics Handle. Let's start there.
this tells you lots of stuff about it. all of the functions that are available on it. These are the ones we're going to use. we're
going to start by grabbing component in that grab method. and we're going to
pass in a UPrimitiveComponent* pointer. which we won't look at in detail but
I'll show you how to get hold of one of those. We're going to pass in a null bone name.
because bones are to do with skeletal animation. where you have a skeleton
of a humanoid of a dog or anything. We don't have
one of those. in this case. The meshes that we are dealing with are all
static meshes. Let's take a look. click on the chair. and you can see in the World Outliner its
Static Mesh Actor. So. we're not dealing with the
bones. so we're going to be passing in a no bone name here.
Then. it's going to say the grab location. that is where are we going to grab this
thing? Well. where are we going to grab it? What part of it
are we going to grab hold of? We're just going to use the base point. You see this
circle here. the white ball which is the origin of the
chair or the table. that's a good enough point to grab. If we're standing here and we grab that.
it'll end up straight in front of us at the end of that reach line. So. we're going to attach the
end of the reach line. Let's just move forward and just visualize this
a little. then eject with F8. zoom out. Remember that reach
line that used to stick out? I've turned the debug trace off. but the idea is that it's going to stick out
and it's going to touch onto this white origin point. so that your
chair will kind of lift up into the air. and then. as we walk around we want to update its position to
stay on the end of the reach line. So. this chair will end up
kind of... Well. we've got Physics on at the moment. so I need to pause. This chair will end up staying
at the end of the reach line. That's difficult for me to simulate.
OK. so that's that bit! Then. once we have grabbed the
component. then every frame we're going to set the target location to the end of the
reach line. and then. the
final thing that we're going to need to be able to do is to actually drop it and somwhere
should be a release component. Where is that?
Am I being blind? I can't see it right now. I'm going to do a search. Ah. here you go!
It's just out of alphabetical order. You have a Release component method there. which releases
the currently held handle. So. you'll notice though that this Unreal documentation
doesn't actually have any full example code. so let me show you a little trick here
for getting hold of example code. in some cases. You can go into your IDE.
you can do a search. If I use Find in Visual Studio here.
and I search the entire solution for the method that we want to use first. which is
"grabcomponent" open bracket. just to make it as specific as possible and I do a Find All.
So. I want you to do this find. Find an example in the engine.
Search the engine for PhysicsHandle. look for examples of it being used. If
that returns too many results. then try GrabComponent(). as I just started.
and see if you can find an example of its usage in the engine.
And remember. there's a link to the documentation. And I just
want you to have an example in front of you. before we go ahead and try and do it for ourselves.
Cool welcome back! So. I'm going to complete this
search now. by going Find All. and I'm looking for somewhere.
where they've already used it. to give us a clue as to how we use it. And one example
here is in this PhysicsManipulationMode.cpp. We have
GrabComponent right here. GrabComponent (ComponentToGrab) some
NAME None. which is the bone name. Where are we going to update? Where are we going to
grab it. i.e. that white handle. as I talked about. the origin of the table or
chair. and then. whether rotation is allowed or not. say true there. So. that's quite handy.
I'm going to copy that code. GrabComponent. So. where do we put it?
Well. in our GrabComponent() method.
Let me just close these other files. Here you go!
Then. we have to attach the Physics Handle. So. we've
got the Physics Handle. alright. We've found the reference in the method above. So. we go PhysicsHandle.
Now. that's a pointer so arrow operator. Now. paste
their code in. GrabComponent. and then let's go through
and see what we've got. We've got a component to grab. which we need to create.
They've got this NAME_None thing. What's that about? It's an enumerator
for the bone. and we don't need anything.
so we're going to use NAME_None. because there is no bone to grab hold of.
Where are we going to grab the thing. the table
or the chair? Well. we're going to grab it at its location. that white
anchor pointer. and we're going to allow rotation. So. I'll just comment to say
allow. So. it means that when we're grabbing it.
it's allowed to spin around. So. what we need to do is get this component to grab now.
So. what do we get out of GetFirstPhysicsBody
InReach()? Well. we get a let's use auto HitResult.
Remember. if we go and look in GetFirstPhysicsBodyInReach() let's go see what it
returns. Ooh. well that's a mistake. It shouldn't return a method like
that. it should be returning hit. Remember that we made this variable. we used it as
an out parameter. and then. we
return what's actually hit. so return Hit. Now. this
code arguably shouldn't be here. but I'm not in refactor mode right now. I am
in just get it working. So. I'm going to resist the urge to refactor anything. We just need
to fix the fact that our GetFirstPhysicsBodyInReach() was not returning
the right thing. it now returns a hit which is better. Now. the hit
ends up in HitResult up here. OK. so that's cool! What do we do with that HitResult?
Well. we need a couple of things. don't we? We need the component to grab.
That means. what part of the chair or the table do we grab? How do we
even know? Well. let's go auto. so it's got a
type that's inferred for us.
Then. we go HitResult dot. Now. you could just type component.
and you'll see that you've got a GetComponent method that returns this UPrimitive
Component pointer. which is the type that we want
for this first parameter. Look if I delete
this first parameter and just open the brackets again.
you see it wants a UPrimitiveComponent pointer. OK. so we're
just matching types here. We're just giving it the type it is
looking for. and we are following the example from Unreal's code. so that
sounds promising. Then. we've got the bone name. which is none. and then.
we've got the grab location which comes next. which is just the
ActorLocation. Then. we want to "// allow rotation"
so that's pretty cool. The other thing we're going to want to do is. it says
we only want to do this if we hit something.
So. auto ActorHit
= HitResult.Get
Actor(); Then. we can say and as a recap for the
beginners I'll explain what this really means. if (ActorHit).
Now. that's the same as saying. if the (ActorHit) is not equal to
null pointer. i.e. if we actually got something out of this HitResult.
there is an Actor attached. then if ActorHit doesn't equal null pointer.
or more succinctly if there is an ActorHit then we go ahead and attach the PhysicsHandle.
Does that make sense. what I'm doing there? I know it's a lot to take on in one go.
Mostly I need some curly braces around this lot. so I'm going to highlight it
and just go Shift and curly brace to do that. that's how
it works in Visual Studio. So. if there is an ActorHit. attach the PhysicsHandle. I don't
need anymore to say TODO. just attached the Physics Handle allowing
rotation. That's pretty cool! Now. we're not going to know if that's worked right now.
because every frame we need to say "// if the physics handle is attached". move
the object that we're holding. So. how do we say "// if the physics handle
is attached"? Well. we can say if
(PhysicsHandle->)
and then. we've got a method called GrabbedComponent there.
Well. it's actually property called GrabbedComponent. which is this primitive component we've grabbed
hold of. So. we're saying. if we have a GrabbedComponent then.
we need to move the object we're holding OK.
So. how are we going to move it? Well. we're going to say.
PhysicsHandle again.
and then. there's a method on there which is the SetTarget
Location. Remember that was the third method I told you about? I know I'm doing a lot for you here. but this
is a very new thing. and it's not very well documented so I thought I'd help you out a
bit. We have SetTargetLocation().
Now. what are we going to set the target location to? As I said earlier. we're going to set it to the
end of the reach line. Now. this is not the nicest way of doing it. but we're not
refactoring now. So. if we want the end of the line trace or the reach line. I'm just going to grab
all this code that we know does it. copy it.
and just paste it up here where we need it. That's horrible and we'll
refactor it in a bit. but at least it gives us access to a LineTraceEnd right
now. OK. and I'm just saying we're still just trying to get this working.
Let's try.
So. we compile the code.
and we're still compiling the code.
and then. we come along and we have a look and if we right-click... Ah. you see
that white point that I talked about. the origins come right in front of our face. Let's try
it with the chair. Right-click or Left Shift. See what's happening?
And the reach handle is working perfect! Let's just make it drop.
And when we've actually finished getting it working. how do we make it drop? Well.
on the Release() method. where we have "// TODO release physics handle" let's just
see what methods we've got. Well. we looked at it. I told you earlier didn't I? It's PhysicsHandle.
it's a pointer.
ReleaseComponent(). it's all you have to do. We've already
bound the inputs. so the release gets called when we let go of the key. Let's see if that
works!
Compile was quicker. because a lot of the work has already been done. We come along. we
grab the table. let go. and it falls. Grab the chair. that feels
great! Look at that. awesome! So look. our work is now done
because it's working. so here's the discipline. Save everything in Unreal.
File. Save As. Save All. close it. I'm going
to save everything in my IDE and close it.
I'm going to go over to my source control. and then. at this point. I'm going to stage
everything and I am then going to Commit these changes.
So. do that before we move on in the next video and refactor and make this
code something that we can build on!
=======
So, welcome to
Using Physics Handles! In this video, I'm going to explain that Unreal provides a really
handy tool called a Physics Handle, that's ideal for picking things up.
The Physics Handle component documents are very scant. You can look that
word up if you're not English. [Laughs] Find an example of this and
use it in the engine. So, it's a hard thing to use, unless you can see it
being used as an example. I'm going to show you how to find an
example of it in the engine, then we'll get the Physics Handle working. So, there are the docs.
And it's an exciting video because, by the end of it, we will have a situation where we can
actually pick things up and throw them around and drop them. Look at that! How cool!
So, just before we get this working, I want to talk to you about a
mental discipline that I call Red, Green, Refactor. It comes from Test Driven
Development, which is where you write your code to pass certain formal
tests, but in our case it still applies. So, the first stage
is Red, it's not working the test is failing. That's where we are now, the Physics Handle isn't
working. So, our job is to get to green, which is where it's working,
and ugly is OK. And this is the important bit, is to be
clear on whether you're just trying to get something working right now or whether you're trying to refactor,
which is the third step to make things pretty, and of course, they must still work.
So, the beauty is this, we start off with it not working, which is where we are. We
work hard to just get it working, kind of whatever it takes. We then
commit our work to source control and say, OK it works, I can now safely
make it how I really wanted it, make it pretty make it clear,
knowing that I can always go back to the working version that's ugly and try again
if I mess things up, and then, you just keep repeating that sequence. So, I just want
to stress that, before we dive in here. I'm just trying to get the PhysicsHandle
working. We're going to do whatever it takes, if it's copying and pasting code, it doesn't matter
for now, because we want to focus on one thing at a time when things get complex. And now, it's
just let's get it working. OK, so we need the Physics
Handle component. Let me just go back a slide to here, which is
the documentation of the Physics Handle. Let's start there,
this tells you lots of stuff about it, all of the functions that are available on it. These are the ones we're going to use, we're
going to start by grabbing component in that grab method, and we're going to
pass in a UPrimitiveComponent* pointer, which we won't look at in detail but
I'll show you how to get hold of one of those. We're going to pass in a null bone name,
because bones are to do with skeletal animation, where you have a skeleton
of a humanoid of a dog or anything. We don't have
one of those, in this case. The meshes that we are dealing with are all
static meshes. Let's take a look, click on the chair, and you can see in the World Outliner its
Static Mesh Actor. So, we're not dealing with the
bones, so we're going to be passing in a no bone name here.
Then, it's going to say the grab location, that is where are we going to grab this
thing? Well, where are we going to grab it? What part of it
are we going to grab hold of? We're just going to use the base point. You see this
circle here, the white ball which is the origin of the
chair or the table, that's a good enough point to grab. If we're standing here and we grab that,
it'll end up straight in front of us at the end of that reach line. So, we're going to attach the
end of the reach line. Let's just move forward and just visualize this
a little, then eject with F8, zoom out. Remember that reach
line that used to stick out? I've turned the debug trace off, but the idea is that it's going to stick out
and it's going to touch onto this white origin point, so that your
chair will kind of lift up into the air, and then, as we walk around we want to update its position to
stay on the end of the reach line. So, this chair will end up
kind of... Well, we've got Physics on at the moment, so I need to pause. This chair will end up staying
at the end of the reach line. That's difficult for me to simulate.
OK, so that's that bit! Then, once we have grabbed the
component, then every frame we're going to set the target location to the end of the
reach line, and then, the
final thing that we're going to need to be able to do is to actually drop it and somwhere
should be a release component. Where is that?
Am I being blind? I can't see it right now. I'm going to do a search. Ah, here you go!
It's just out of alphabetical order. You have a Release component method there, which releases
the currently held handle. So, you'll notice though that this Unreal documentation
doesn't actually have any full example code, so let me show you a little trick here
for getting hold of example code, in some cases. You can go into your IDE,
you can do a search. If I use Find in Visual Studio here,
and I search the entire solution for the method that we want to use first, which is
"grabcomponent" open bracket, just to make it as specific as possible and I do a Find All.
So, I want you to do this find. Find an example in the engine.
Search the engine for PhysicsHandle, look for examples of it being used. If
that returns too many results, then try GrabComponent(), as I just started,
and see if you can find an example of its usage in the engine.
And remember, there's a link to the documentation. And I just
want you to have an example in front of you, before we go ahead and try and do it for ourselves.
Cool welcome back! So, I'm going to complete this
search now, by going Find All, and I'm looking for somewhere,
where they've already used it, to give us a clue as to how we use it. And one example
here is in this PhysicsManipulationMode.cpp. We have
GrabComponent right here. GrabComponent (ComponentToGrab) some
NAME None, which is the bone name. Where are we going to update? Where are we going to
grab it, i.e. that white handle, as I talked about, the origin of the table or
chair, and then, whether rotation is allowed or not, say true there. So, that's quite handy.
I'm going to copy that code, GrabComponent. So, where do we put it?
Well, in our GrabComponent() method.
Let me just close these other files. Here you go!
Then, we have to attach the Physics Handle. So, we've
got the Physics Handle, alright. We've found the reference in the method above. So, we go PhysicsHandle.
Now, that's a pointer so arrow operator. Now, paste
their code in, GrabComponent, and then let's go through
and see what we've got. We've got a component to grab, which we need to create.
They've got this NAME_None thing. What's that about? It's an enumerator
for the bone, and we don't need anything,
so we're going to use NAME_None, because there is no bone to grab hold of.
Where are we going to grab the thing, the table
or the chair? Well, we're going to grab it at its location, that white
anchor pointer, and we're going to allow rotation. So, I'll just comment to say
allow. So, it means that when we're grabbing it,
it's allowed to spin around. So, what we need to do is get this component to grab now.
So, what do we get out of GetFirstPhysicsBody
InReach()? Well, we get a let's use auto HitResult.
Remember, if we go and look in GetFirstPhysicsBodyInReach() let's go see what it
returns. Ooh, well that's a mistake. It shouldn't return a method like
that, it should be returning hit. Remember that we made this variable, we used it as
an out parameter, and then, we
return what's actually hit, so return Hit. Now, this
code arguably shouldn't be here, but I'm not in refactor mode right now, I am
in just get it working. So, I'm going to resist the urge to refactor anything. We just need
to fix the fact that our GetFirstPhysicsBodyInReach() was not returning
the right thing, it now returns a hit which is better. Now, the hit
ends up in HitResult up here. OK, so that's cool! What do we do with that HitResult?
Well, we need a couple of things, don't we? We need the component to grab.
That means, what part of the chair or the table do we grab? How do we
even know? Well, let's go auto, so it's got a
type that's inferred for us.
Then, we go HitResult dot. Now, you could just type component,
and you'll see that you've got a GetComponent method that returns this UPrimitive
Component pointer, which is the type that we want
for this first parameter. Look if I delete
this first parameter and just open the brackets again,
you see it wants a UPrimitiveComponent pointer. OK, so we're
just matching types here. We're just giving it the type it is
looking for, and we are following the example from Unreal's code, so that
sounds promising. Then, we've got the bone name, which is none, and then,
we've got the grab location which comes next, which is just the
ActorLocation. Then, we want to "// allow rotation"
so that's pretty cool. The other thing we're going to want to do is, it says
we only want to do this if we hit something.
So, auto ActorHit
= HitResult.Get
Actor(); Then, we can say and as a recap for the
beginners I'll explain what this really means, if (ActorHit).
Now, that's the same as saying, if the (ActorHit) is not equal to
null pointer. i.e. if we actually got something out of this HitResult,
there is an Actor attached, then if ActorHit doesn't equal null pointer,
or more succinctly if there is an ActorHit then we go ahead and attach the PhysicsHandle.
Does that make sense, what I'm doing there? I know it's a lot to take on in one go.
Mostly I need some curly braces around this lot, so I'm going to highlight it
and just go Shift and curly brace to do that, that's how
it works in Visual Studio. So, if there is an ActorHit, attach the PhysicsHandle. I don't
need anymore to say TODO, just attached the Physics Handle allowing
rotation. That's pretty cool! Now, we're not going to know if that's worked right now,
because every frame we need to say "// if the physics handle is attached", move
the object that we're holding. So, how do we say "// if the physics handle
is attached"? Well, we can say if
(PhysicsHandle->)
and then, we've got a method called GrabbedComponent there.
Well, it's actually property called GrabbedComponent, which is this primitive component we've grabbed
hold of. So, we're saying, if we have a GrabbedComponent then,
we need to move the object we're holding OK.
So, how are we going to move it? Well, we're going to say,
PhysicsHandle again,
and then, there's a method on there which is the SetTarget
Location. Remember that was the third method I told you about? I know I'm doing a lot for you here, but this
is a very new thing, and it's not very well documented so I thought I'd help you out a
bit. We have SetTargetLocation().
Now, what are we going to set the target location to? As I said earlier, we're going to set it to the
end of the reach line. Now, this is not the nicest way of doing it, but we're not
refactoring now. So, if we want the end of the line trace or the reach line, I'm just going to grab
all this code that we know does it, copy it,
and just paste it up here where we need it. That's horrible and we'll
refactor it in a bit, but at least it gives us access to a LineTraceEnd right
now. OK, and I'm just saying we're still just trying to get this working.
Let's try.
So, we compile the code,
and we're still compiling the code,
and then, we come along and we have a look and if we right-click... Ah, you see
that white point that I talked about, the origins come right in front of our face. Let's try
it with the chair. Right-click or Left Shift. See what's happening?
And the reach handle is working perfect! Let's just make it drop.
And when we've actually finished getting it working, how do we make it drop? Well,
on the Release() method, where we have "// TODO release physics handle" let's just
see what methods we've got. Well, we looked at it, I told you earlier didn't I? It's PhysicsHandle,
it's a pointer.
ReleaseComponent(), it's all you have to do. We've already
bound the inputs, so the release gets called when we let go of the key. Let's see if that
works!
Compile was quicker, because a lot of the work has already been done. We come along, we
grab the table, let go, and it falls. Grab the chair, that feels
great! Look at that, awesome! So look, our work is now done
because it's working, so here's the discipline. Save everything in Unreal,
File, Save As, Save All, close it. I'm going
to save everything in my IDE and close it.
I'm going to go over to my source control, and then, at this point, I'm going to stage
everything and I am then going to Commit these changes.
So, do that before we move on in the next video and refactor and make this
code something that we can build on!
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1:Unreal/Section3/BE32 Using Physics Handles.srt