So, welcome to
Refactoring Rules! Now, you can take that to mean the rules of refactoring, or you can take
it to mean that refactoring is pretty cool! Either way, I think both apply!
In this video, firstly, in an instance like
when we want to get the start and the end point of this line trace that we're doing,
you could return a struct with two vectors in it, you
could use out parameters, or you could use multiple
getters to get the two different vector, and we're going to be doing that in this refactor.
So, in general about refactoring rules, less lines of
clear code is better than more. So, we had 143
at the start, in my code, and by the end of this video we'll have 122
lines. So that's about a 15% reduction in the number of
lines of code, and it still works and I think that's a good thing.
I want to reiterate that naming is really important. Take the time to think about the names
of things, it's worth changing them.
Now commenting! It's good to comment why you're doing things. Don't assume it's
obvious why you're doing something, but the watch
should be obvious. If the what's not obvious, then
maybe you want to add some further comments
for clarification. OK, so we want the code as self documenting as possible
but adding further comments for clarification is just fine.
So, let's recap this Red, Green, Refactor! Remember we start off,
when we start a new thing, with something not working, so our physics handle wasn't working.
We then just got it working and we made a commit over
here. It was this one, Using Physics Handles, so that was our green commit,
and now we're going to refactor, so the whole purpose of what we're going to do next is refactor
and make it pretty. So, you can say that, by the way, you can write your commit message. I quite
like to do this before we even start coding,
then that reminds you what your little micro sprint is. What are you doing
in the next section. So,
my video is called Refactoring Rules, but you may want to make a commit
that is something like Refactoring
Physics Handle Code,
and then, that would get committed next. Alright, so that can be a really useful thing to
do, is so that you know... And your message will stay, by the way. If you go back to Commit
it'll stay here. You can always refer to that and say, what am I doing right now? What am I doing?
Well I'm refactoring, I'm in the blue stage OK.
So, this Accessors & Memory Layout, that was getting something working.
This Reducing Code was a refactor commit, and you might want to standardize to the first
word being refactor. And then, this was getting something working and now
this is another refactor. A couple of other things on Source Control, while we're here. I
don't really like this .opendb file being tracked by Source Control.
It's a lock file and it's there whenever Visual Studio is open.
What it kind of forces you to do is close Visual Studio, before you commit. But the
problem with that, if you get in the habit of just closing, if you don't say yes when it
asks you if you want to save everything, you could lose your work. It's better to positively save your work
and not worry about whether this .opendb file is there.
So, I'm going to ignore the .opendb file. I'll go and get it's name
from here, from the file system. There's another file I'm going to
ignore, which is the .solution file, and the reason for that is, if we look back at Using Physics Handle,
the changes in it aren't helpful to us. It's a generated file anyway, so I'm going to get rid
of those two. Just as a recap, you go find the .gitignore,
you add the things you want *.VC.opendb and
*.sln, pop those into the file, save the .gitignore.
Back over in your Source Control, you may need to do a refresh.
It will then notice, in the Uncommitted Changes, that there's a change in the .gitignore.
Well, you just add that, and that's all we need to do for right now! So, we're ready to go! We know
what we're doing, we're going to be refactoring the physics handle code, and we've
ignored what we need to. Let's go get on with the refactor!
Not so easy, of course, I want you to do it.
Refactor your code, yes again. Yes it's soon, but as I've said, clarity is
worth fighting for, we want to get into that discipline. Commit your work once it's done
and it runs well and make sure it's so clear you'll remember it
in a year. So go ahead, pause the video, and have a go at your own refactoring
now, before watching my solution!
So, let's just start at the top of Grabber.cpp, go through make sure it's clear, again! Yes,
we're refactoring again! As I said, that's fine! So, less lines is better. Let's
get rid of spaces we don't need. I want to see what's happening in BeginPlay().
I'm going to change this one around. Rather than if PhysicsHandle,
I'm going to say if (PhysicsHandle == remember null
ptr, i.e. if there's no PhysicsHandle attached
then we're going to log the error. Yes, we could use an assert, but we'll introduce
that later in the course. So that's less lines of code, so that's better!
Remember we started off at 143 lines or something like that.
Let's see what we can get it down to, while still being super clear! I'm going to collapse that down, that doesn't
change the number of lines, but it makes it clearer. Setup the input component. I don't think we need to
say that it's found or that we're binding the axis anymore, cause the code
says that. So, that's fine if InputComponent
exists, otherwise log an error. Good that's clear! Close that
down, drop the gap, "// Called every frame". Now, this bit is horrible
here. This bit here about getting the player view point this tick, that is
a separate method, so let's refactor that out. I'm going to take that out,
I'm going to make a method called GetPlayer...
Or actually, what am I getting here?
Getting reach line end is what
I'm really doing in this method, isn't it? I'm getting the reach line end. So, let's just
make a method, a helper method. So, I'm going to put it at the bottom called GetReachLine
End(), pop all of this in it,
and let's go.
Not void, FVector. It's going to return an FVector, Get
ReachLineEnd(). Now, by the way,
in terms of your refactoring either watch what I'm doing or refactor yourself at the end,
and I'm going to challenge you, at the end, to refactor this, so it's entirely up to you how
you do your refactor. If you're a beginner, you may want to copy me. If you're an expert, you may want to
do things your way. I'm just trying to teach you the thought behind how I'm refactoring.
So GetReachLineEnd and let's pop in some braces.
Now what, of course, we can do at the bottom is, rather than making this intermediate variable, we can just return
that result. Return the PlayerViewPointLocation plus the Rotation.Vector
times the reach and that's it! Do we need to say "/// Get player view point
this tick"? Not really! It's not necessarily this tick anymore anyway, it's when
we call GetReachLineEnd(). OK, so one more thing we need to do,
of course, is put UGrabber. Fully qualify the class name. The
colon colon, remember, because it's known at compile time, and then let's go and
declare this thing, or right-click, Quick Actions, Create Declaration,
and with a little bit of time it will do that.
Let's go check that it's in a sensible place in Grabber.h.
It is, apart from it's bound there, so I'm going to do this
and say "// Returns current end of
reach line". And this, of course, would allow us to have a reach line that changes
during the game play. If we're going to get the end of the reach line, I'll be we're going to be getting
the start of the reach line as well.
OK, and then let's go and define
another method, which is for the GetReachLineStart().
I prefer start to come before end. I'm copying and pasting code because it's so
similar. And what we do here is we allow ourselves
to duplicate this first little bit of code, these lines I've just highlighted,
and then, up to twice I don't mind duplicating
code like that. And then, we just return something a lot simpler, in this case, which is just the Player
ViewPointLocation. So we have GetReachLineStart() and Get
ReachLineEnd(). They are nice and simple. Now, let's go
use those. Let's go use this GetReachLineStart() and GetReachLineEnd().
Where is the first place we need it?
So, we do the super tick in the
tick. We find out if the PhysicsHandle is attached.
Then, we move the object we're holding to what?
To (GetReachLineEnd()). That's a bit clearer isn't it?!
And then, that's called once per frame, once per frame, that we're
holding something. So that's OK! Then, how does the Grab() work? Well,
("Grab pressed"), don't know if we need the log anymore, as it works.
Line trace to see if we are reaching an any
actors. Yeah, that's fine! That comment does clarify things, so that's one of the things you're checking
for. If we hit something, then attach a Physics Handle. That's fine!
I don't think we need to say that we're attaching a Physics Handle here.
Where are we grabbing?
Yeah that's right, we can't use the reach line, but we're grabbing at the location of the Actors,
so that's all fine. "// no bones needed".
This component that
we're grabbing turns out to be the mesh, but I'm not going to
comment that. Let's leave that.
Release(), ("Grab released"). I don't think we need a comment anymore.
GetFirstPhysicsBodyInReach(). Now,
that's got a load of this stuff! You see all that stuff? We've separated it out, haven't we, so that we can
delete all those lines of code. We can bring all our query
parameters together.
And then, where it says, we're ray casting from PlayerView
PointLocation, we're playing from GetReachLineStart()
like so, to GetReachLineEnd(). It
reads a lot more nicely.
There you go nice! See what we hit? We don't need to do that here anymore!
And just return Hit. I don't like Hit I like Hit result,
so let's rename. Control R, Control R, in Visual Studio.
HitResult. Ah,
looking a bit better! GetReachLineEnd(), what's wrong with that? GetReachLineEnd(), let's
check the header file. GetReachLineEnd(). I don't think there's anything wrong
with it. I think it hasn't caught up. I know, I can't spell!
Cool! I think that looks and feels a lot better!
A final thing I like to do is, just have a look through it all and make sure that
we are happy that what's commented needs to be commented, that
comments talk about why, or if they talk about what for the sake
of adding clarification, and that
all of our code will make sense to us in a year. So, here's something to remember. Will
it be clear in a year? So, you come back to this in a whole year, would you still understand
what on earth you are doing?
I'm going to say, what we get here. Component to Grab "// Gets the mesh in
our case". If you log out this component to Grab(), you'll find that, when you get
the HitResult back and you get the component, it's the mesh component that it
happens to be. So, it's the mesh that we are moving down here.
Release() just releases, it couldn't be simpler.
GetFirstPhysicsBodyInReach(). Line trace is after the
distance and returns what it hits, provided that it's a PhysicsBody, which
is why that's in the name. That's good! You could of course make this PhysicsBody a parameter, so
you could get first object channel in reach or something, but this is fine.
Don't make it more general than it needs to be, earlier than you need to make it general.
Anything that's slightly grating is that you've got two bits of code duplicated here, but the only other
option is to either return a struct, which is a bit over the top from here,
or to use out parameters which I'm not a great fan of. So that's it! Of
course, the most important thing now is to check that our refactor works. Now, if you're
less confident in refactoring than that, you need to just do it in smaller lumps. Change
something, compile, check. Change something, compile, check. The important thing is it keeps
working and that you've got this safety net of the Using Physics Handles
commit, which you know will work because you checked it,
before you save it. So, we can pick, we can drop, we can pick,
and we can drop. Wonderful! Look at that! Great!
So, we now have nice looking code that still works. So just finally
commit your work, as a refactor. We already have the commit message remember?
And we are good to go!