So, welcome to
Iterating over TArray with for. In this video, we'll be
using an auto reference as an auto reference type,
automatically iterating over
a TArray, without going through all the elements in it. The pattern we'll use
uses for, const, some auto iterator,
in or over Array, like that, and we'll look at how to find
an Actor's mass. And finally, we'll be tweaking and testing our mass values.
By the end of the video, you'll be in a situation where something like this will be
happening. We will be able to go  across, grab the table, put it down,
and when we're standing on the pressure plate, with the table, the doors will open, and
then, we grab a chair and stick it on top of the table. Look at this! I move
away, the doors are open, and we are free! So, that's cool! See you soon!
Hi, welcome back! So, I left you reading this rather unweildy
piece of documentation here, I hope you haven't spent all night reading it. I just wanted you to skim it as I
I did say, and the idea was to find the bit that talks about
how we can use a for, in order to iterate
automatically over the array. Alright, so this
is an example here. This says for
auto reference. So, don't worry about what the type is, you decide for me, but make an
automatic reference type, called the
iterator, the thing that changes each loop's Str and then,
iterate across StrArr, String Array. So, for auto-reference
String and String Array, basically is how I'd read that. Do some
stuff! And it goes through as many elements as there currently are in String Array
doing things, so it's very neat and tidy and it knows when the end of the array is,
and it's just kind of meaningful and simple. So, let's go ahead and use
a syntax very much like that now, and get our
thing-a-majig working OK. [Laughs] So, we have overlapping
Actors here, and we need to use this range based for loop to go
through them, firstly, printing out their names and then secondly adding up their mass.
But of course, it's not that easy, I want you to do it. So, iterate
over OverlappingActors, using that syntax I showed you in the beginning.
Then, for each Actor found, log their name out to
the Console, and as a bonus, add their masses together and test that this whole method
works. Now, I've got a hint coming up, and if you don't want the hint, and you want the bigger challenge
just pause right now. And then, the hint is coming now, which is if you are
going to go and add those masses, the class you need to find is UPrimitive
Component. That's the thing you're going to need to find on the
Actor, and furthermore, you're going to need to go ahead and find the mass for that. OK,
pause the video and at least log out the names of these guys, if you possibly can,
using that for syntax and the documentation. And I'll see you in a moment!
OK welcome back!
So, let's take a look at this! What we want is for. Then, we want
auto-reference, because we don't want to be typing the type of an iterator,
we don't really care. But it's going to be an Actor and it's in the
overlapping Actors.
OK, so for every
Actor in the overlapping actors, do something. By the way, I'm just going to reinforce
things, pop a const in here. Why? Because I want to just emphasize
that the Actor does not change in this process, we just receive the Actor
and do something with it, we don't change it. OK, so for each Actor what are we going to do? What is this
Actor, firstly? It's a pointer to
an Actor. So, we're going to use the
operator. Then, we're going to FindComponentBy
Class and the class is
How would we know that the class is UPrimitiveComponent? You would have to do a little bit of
Google searching and find an example where somebody is setting mass,
and then, you'd realize that the mass is set on the primitive component.
You may also make some headway, remember, by going to the Developer Tools, the
Class Viewer, and then, turning off Actors Only on a PC, and
looking for "mass" may give you some results. It doesn't tell me anything here.
So, in this case, just search if I wasn't here to help you, but
I am here to help you and I'm telling you that what we want to do is get a primitive component that's a
method. Once we've got the primitive component, we can drill into that and we can
say GetMass(). OK, so that
returns the mass. Pretty cool! In fact, what we're doing is saying Total
Mass +=. So total mass = total mass +
the mass of the Actor we found in this loop. Then, we keep
going around the loop. Cool hey! So, let's do a quick log! Just say that what we've
got UE_LOG(LogTemp,
Warning, TEXT) remember we have to pass it TEXT, and then, we're
going to pass it something like
("%s on pressure plate"))
And what is %s? Well, it's going to be the Actor
->GetName() and
remember that we have to use a star, which means
contents of. OK fantastic! Let's go ahead
and just check a couple of things. The chair mass needs to be sensible. So, what is the chair
mass? 10, that's very light for a chair. My chair is 15, the one I'm sitting on right now, so
let's use 15. I'm sitting on a diffurient world
chair, spelled very strangely. OK, so what's the mass of the table? Let's call it 25! So,
15 and 25 add up to 40! What was our nastily hard
coded boundary threshold?
50, so let's say make it 30!
So, 30 kilos is not enough for either the chair or the
table on their own to trigger. That's good, let's make double sure that
the Default Pawn has enough mass. Remember, that's under the CollisionComponent.
Mass 70, yeah plenty! OK, let's see what happens!
So, back in the game! Let's start by coming over.
Sorry compiling first of course. Coming over
and grabbing the table, and let's see if
that generates the relevant events. There you go, the Default Pawn...
No, that's the Default Pawn, that's me on the pressure plate, but the table isn't generating the event. So,
this is what you need to do to the table. You need to click on the table, and
where it says Collision in the details of the table, of course, we need to generate
at least overlap events with the table. Let's prove that fixes it with the
table, then we can do the same with the chair. Overlap events are the event
where you overlap with a trigger. There you go, the table is now on the pressure plate!
That's cool! Now, I've got a little bit of phantom movement going with my pawn here.
It would be interesting to know, in the discussions, if you get the same thing, a little bit of
drifting, since we made the modifications to it. Just let me know if you get that, and then, we'll solve
the bug if it's common.  Let's fix the chair as well. The chair needs to
have generate overlap events, and then let's make sure of three things. Firstly, I open
the doors, which I do. Secondly that the
oops... There you go! ...that the table alone does not
because it doesn't have enough total mass. Yep, it did while I was standing
on it but not when it's on its own. And then the chair.
Yeah that's good! Now the doors stay open, and let's just try the table
on its own. So, the chair, on its own, should not be heavy enough.
[Laughs] I nearly got the table out the door then
and that doesn't! OK great! So, I just have a little bit of phantom
movement going on with my default character now. Let me know in the discussions if
you have that, and if you do, also see if you can work out what it is and I will see you in the next video!