So. welcome
to Debugging Game Issues! This is a little bit different to debugging
code issues. cause our particular bug we're seeing. with our drifting
Pawn. is not actually caused directly by a code issue. so a slightly different
approach when it's an engine editor side issue. So. in this video
firstly. I want to ask you are you using Source Control yet? Are you using SourceTree.
GitHub. some sort of Source Control? If not. then I would really urge you to start now.
even if you just zip up your project after each
video. The problem with doing that. of course. is you end up with a massive amount of data. because every time
you zip up your project. it's going to get bigger and bigger. You could delete all the
derived files we've talked about. binaries. build. intermediate. saved. etc.
and then. just zip that up if you wanted to. But please
do the difficult thing. and you know. I've heard somebody say that if you do what's easy life will be
hard and if you do what's hard life will be easy. paradoxically. So. consider
getting into Source Control. if you're not already. Sorry to lecture you if you already are. So.
once you're using Source Control you can use binary search. You
can binary search commits pretty fast. So what I mean by that is. even if you've got
1.024 commits. remember that 2 to the power of 10 is 1.024.
So. as I'll show you in a second. even if you had 1.000 commits. you could
chop that search space in half. just 10 times
and get down to the commit where the problem started. if that's what we want to be able to do.
as I've just said. So. think about what's changed and what the
possible side-effects are of what changed and what could be causing the problem.
and remember that you can eject with F8 during gameplay.
So let me just show you this Source Control business. show you about ejecting.
and then. we will challenge you to go and find the solution to this
problem. So. let's recap what the problem is. The problem is that some of the time. when
we say pick up the table and let go. look we're kind of drifting around now.
What's going on with that drift? Now. remember you can hit F8
and F8 will take you out of the body of the
Default Pawn. Now. I'm not going to look back at it. because that will show you the solution which you're going to do in a moment.
But remember you can use F8. which is the same. by the way. as
clicking Eject. But of course. once you've come into the game window and
you've started using your mouse. you can no longer click that Eject Button right. You can't
look up at it. so you have to hit the F8 Key. The other thing I wanted to just
recap was what I was talking about with the Source Controls. So. here I've got 35 commits. Let's call
it 32 for the lectures. Now. 2 to the power of 5 is 32.
which means that even if I didn't know at all. even from the beginning of the
project where this problem started; I could go well. let's do a round 16
about half way through. check out there. see if the problem exists there.
if it does then it happened before that and if it doesn't it happened after that. Let's
imagine it happened after 16. Well then. we go well let's go half way between 16 and 32 about
here somewhere. Is the problem existent there? Say maybe no.
OK. so it happened later. Is it existent there? Yes! OK. so it happened half
way between there and there. and you can see you really quickly can hone in on
the place where the problem started. Then. you can start to think. well what changed between
these two videos or between these two commit stages. in your case.
And you can say. oh well I changed the door asset or I changed the. you know. something.
And you can see that. actually. a few videos ago... I don't know quite where
it was. We change something about the Default Pawn.
I think it may have been pretty recent. I think it was in the last video? Yeah! It's something
changed on the Default Pawn. unfortunately we can't see what. So. your
challenge is to find and eliminate this drifting bug. I'm using the word drifting because the other
word would solve it for you. When did it come in? Well. it looks like in the last video or the last
few. What feature did we recently enable. of the Default Pawn?
Go look at the Default Pawn blueprint. and then. have a
look under the Details Tab at both the Pawn itself. the root object. but also the
collision object. the collision component. How did the Pawn
look when ejected? Look back at it. see what it's doing.
I'm going to give you a couple of hints. One hint is. by the way.
if you don't want the hints pause now and go and solve the problem. If you do want the hints. then hint number 1
is enabling physics caused the issue. That's what caused it.
And if you want more hints... Then go ahead and try and solve it yourself first. before
listening to the second hint. Go and pause! Go do it do it do it!
In case you need more help and you want to solve this challenge. go
to the Collision Component of the default pawn blueprint. and then look at the Constraints section
and under Details and then Physics and that will give you something that you can tick
or three things you can tick. which will stop the problem. So go ahead. see if you can get rid of the drifting
bug. OK
welcome back! How did you get on solving that problem? Well. according to drifting
bug. but as we can see when we eject and look back at the Pawn. F8
it's not really a drifting bug. it's more of a... Hang on. I need to
cause the bug in the first place. So. pick the chair up. do that.
we're drifting. but we're actually rolling.
There you go. you can see it rolling around. It's just a Physics
Engine quirk this. The floor is actually flat but it's just rolling. and
if we look at the Default Pawn blueprint...
Which how can I get to that? I can just edit it here. that's one way!
And then. I go to the Collision Component and then I go down to Physics. You can see
that there's no Angular Damping. there's no drag force against the rolling.
so once it starts rolling it carries on forever. Alright. now you
can't actually edit the Default Pawn while the game is running like this. so I need to stop.
Now. of course. I can't see the Default Pawn so we go find it from our
Content Browser. come down to the Collision Component
because that's the thing that has Physics enabled. and I could put Angular Damping on it.
and it would stop rolling quicker. So if I put say 7 units of Angular
Damping. Play. pick this up.
go drop it down. Eject. and look
back before it stops. you'll see that it is rolling but then it comes to a halt. But this has
still not solved the root cause. has it? It's still weird that it's rolling. By the way. you might wonder
why this is rolling and yet our view
is not tumbling around. That's because even though it's rolling. it's staying upright and
we have. if you look in that blueprint. if I could find it again. we
have the root component of the Default Pawn. we have this Camera Base Eye Height.
So what's happening is. that the camera is effectively sitting
above the Pawn. We'll just minimize that this time. so
Play F8. What's happening is
that the Pawn is staying upright. even when it's rolling. and then the camera is sitting up here somewhere. just above
it. Alright. so that's why we're not tumbling. it's because the Pawn isn't actually...
The Pawn MeshObject is rotating but the
pawn base object. as you can see here. the CollisionComponent
object and it's MeshComponent are rolling. but the base Pawn
is not and the camera is hanging off the base
Default Pawn here. OK. that's why you don't see a view tumbling. Now. the
solution is CollisionComponent. What you do is you come down under Constraints. So. Collision
Component. Details. Physics. Constraints. and you can just lock the rotation in X.
Y. and Z. And it's really handy that. and sometimes you want to log just
in one or two axes. So. if you lock that rotation now and play. then we kind
of go relatively to the root cause of it. We want to keep Physics on.
So. now we can have Physics on and the problem has gone away. So there you go!
Well done to those of you who spotted that. that was really good news! And
that's a general approach to solving those types of problems. Work out
where they started and what the side effects could be. Don't be afraid to use Binary Search.
and please get into your Source Control. So. I'm going to save everything
and lead by example here. go over to Source Control. and then.
I'm just going to commit those changes. Basically. I've only made a change to the Pawn
asset. We can't see that change because it's a binary asset. We can't see the details
in it. but I staged that. of course. as usual. And then. I will Commit using the current lecture
name. So. go ahead. commit your work. and I'll see you in the next video!