So. welcome to Managing
Texture Tiling! In this video. you may want to
resize objects. for example. wall panels. ceiling panels. etc.. and doing
so will stretch the texture and it may look odd. so you may have even avoided
certain textures because of that. Well. we want to fix this issue. You can rescale a texture in
a few ways but one way is in the material blueprint. I think it's the most natural
way. because that's where we adjust the material. And I want to say straight
away that one of the things we're going to be looking at is something called UV Mapping. and you might wonder why
they're the letters U and V. It's basically because we ran out of letters. but I'll explain that
when we're in there. Now. at the end of the video. I will have made a small adjustment to my
world where I have this ceiling. which would have started off looking really strange
and stretched. and I've showed you how to reposition it. resize it. and actually
adjust the texture. So. let's dive in and see how it works!
OK. so let's look at this issue of texturing! I'm going to use my
ceiling or my roof. my glass ceiling. as an example. You guys might want to
use something else. like maybe you've got some walls that you've tried stretching and the textures
have gone a little bit wrong. So. let's take a look! Firstly.
I'm going to get my ceiling the right size before I start. It's good to get the things
the right physical size. before we worry about adjusting the texture to
them. So. where it is! I'm going to use the Scale Tool. which I can get to with the R Key.
and I'm just going to scale down this roof panel and move it so I'm switching
between hitting R and W. until I get it how I want. Now.
remember that you've got a top view. and feel free to go to the top view with
this minimize button and then maximize the top view.
And then. in the top view. I can see both the position of
the roof and of all the walls below it. So then.
when I come to rescale. etc. I can do it much quicker if I'm in
this view. So. here we go. I can pull it down.
and then. remember also your snapping options up here. You can choose to snap at a different
rate if you need to. OK. so that's going to
help you to get the roof exactly the right size. so that it just fits over.
So. this may apply to your walls or whatever. Now. I'm not going to make it absolutely precise.
it's not worth me spending the time. but you get the idea of moving it around
and getting it pretty much right. Now. the question is. I want to change the
texture on it. so how do I do that? With the SM_GlassWindow
selected. you need the Details Panel. which I've closed by mistake.
So. what we have here is a glass window. at the moment. I'm going to stick with a glass window.
in my case. and I'm just going to change the material on it. So. let's go to the
Material Editor there. and I'm going to go to the View Options and make the thumb
nails a lot larger. So. we are. just to
recap. Material is against the Materials section. I've gone to the
drop-down arrow to get this pane up. and I've gone to View Options
to make the thumbnails larger. then. I can see the materials options. Now. one of our students
used. I think. this hex tile or was it the one below?
It was Tile_Pulse I think? Yeah. Tile_Pulse!
There it was! So. I'm using Tile_Pulse in this case. Now. what's wrong with it? Well.
what's wrong with it is the texture is not scaled properly. We look at the object
itself. the roof object. We can see that it has a scale of 10.25.
Let's make that a nice round 10 by 5.
Make that a nice round 5. just recenter.
So. I'm going to make it precisely a scale of
1 in the X. 10. and then 5.
OK. and it won't quite do that and that's because of the way it's
locking the uniformity of the scaling. It's saying that this thing
previously had a none-integer scale. so you can turn off the lock
to make that give you all the flexibility you want alright.
Then remember that you can drag in the X Y plane. by carefully selecting
here. And now. that roof does actually fit quite well. and it's scaled
to actual round numbers. Now. that's going to be important in a minute!
Let's go and look at this texture in the Texture Editor! What I'm going to do
is make the Unreal Editor only half of the screen like that. Then.
I'm going to go to the texture. Now. one way to get to it is to just click on the magnifying
glass. Now. before you edit this texture you've got a choice.
Do you want to use the actual texture and edit that. or do you want to make a copy
of it? Well. I think we're going to make a copy of this. I'm going to Duplicate
it. I'm going to call it My_
Pulse. and I'm going to put that. actually.
straight in Content. not in the Starter Pack alright.
Now. where has it gone? If you lose something
you can search and then you can look and see it's still in Starter Content.
Materials. So. let me try and move it again. My_Pulse.
Move or copy My_Pulse. and then I miss this dialog. Move Here.
So I've just moved it back to Content. and that means that
I can find it easily and it's not confused with any StarterContent.
So the roof. I'm going to change its material instance to My_Pulse.
I can search and therefore I'm not changing
the one that's in the StarterPack. It also means that if you .getignore that your changes will get
saved. OK. so it's My_Pulse that we're going to change! Great! Let's go
into it. into the Material Editor. I'm going to put this on the right-hand side so we can see. on the left
here. the actual roof in question and how it's looking
OK. and then. on the right-hand side we've got the Node Editor for the materials. Now. we briefly
popped in here before. but the bit that we need to worry about is
if the material is setup properly. Then. you would hope that somewhere on the
left-hand side. probably. you'll have a Text Coord node. Texture
Coordinate node. OK. If you click on that. you can see
here we have UTiling. VTiling. Now. what's U and
V about? Well. at some point we've got to map the coordinates. the
X Y coordinates. if you like. or the row column coordinates of the
texture to the actual object. but we're using X. Y. Z in the world
here and we've run out of letters. so we use U and V like X and
Y. Alright. so these are the X and Y coordinates of the texture!
So. just grab your UTiling and then try changing it. Now. you're going to have to
click Apply for it to actually apply back to the world.
And if we say 10 for the UTiling. let's try that!
And this entirely depends on how much density you want. Let's try
10 for the VTiling. Apply.
OK. that kind of looks
OK. I probably want to have the VTiling the other way
a little bit more or less. I think. I think it's more
because what I'm trying to aim to achieve is that. the way this roof is stretched.
I want it to look fairly uniform. It doesn't have to be perfectly square.
So. that was the wrong way. so I go 5. So. sure you can be
more methodical and work out what you should be putting in these places. but obviously a quick
doubling and harving. a binary search again. this can be a good way! Look
that looks pretty even! So. let's go inside the room. back in the game.
In fact. I'm going to give myself a luxury of a full screen view with F11. and
it's much darker in here now. so we'll sort that out with the light in a minute. But I've got a roof that
has a texture on it that isn't tiled too strangely. so that's pretty cool!
Alright. so all I'm going to do now is fill the room in with a little bit of light.
Let's go and have a look! F11 we're going to find some Starter
Content. Let's go find some props
and ceiling lights or wall lights. I think we could probably
just use wall lights here. What else have I got?
Hmm? I could turn the brightness of this
guy up a lot. that should bounce around. Let's do that for a start!
How are we looking? I
actually don't mind it being pretty dark in the corner here. because it kind of gives some affordance.
I think. actually. I've overdone that light. Let's bring it back down. I don't mind it being
dark in this room. You're welcome to add as many lights as you want. but this kind of
indicates where we want to go. it's into this dark corner. So. I'm happy
with that! Alright. so that's it! That's how you adjust your
texture tiling! So. what I want you to do now is to adjust your textures. Experiment with
new textures. So. now you can be bold. You may have avoided textures
earlier in the section. because they didn't tile properly. Adjust the tiling. as I've just showed you.
Share the results in the course. Please take some screenshots. share them around. show off your work.
I've seen some amazing results! Don't be put off by other peoples' work. if it's better than you think
you can achieve. just share what you've got and it's all good just doing and
sharing is all good. So. see you in a moment!
OK. welcome back! I'm only coming back because I normally
come back from challenges. and it may be confusing for you if I don't. So. I'm back but
nothing to do right! I hope you've gone to the discussion and you shared your awesome
graphical results. and yeah. I shall see you in the next video!
=======
So, welcome to Managing
Texture Tiling! In this video, you may want to
resize objects, for example, wall panels, ceiling panels, etc., and doing
so will stretch the texture and it may look odd, so you may have even avoided
certain textures because of that. Well, we want to fix this issue. You can rescale a texture in
a few ways but one way is in the material blueprint. I think it's the most natural
way, because that's where we adjust the material. And I want to say straight
away that one of the things we're going to be looking at is something called UV Mapping, and you might wonder why
they're the letters U and V. It's basically because we ran out of letters, but I'll explain that
when we're in there. Now, at the end of the video, I will have made a small adjustment to my
world where I have this ceiling, which would have started off looking really strange
and stretched, and I've showed you how to reposition it, resize it, and actually
adjust the texture. So, let's dive in and see how it works!
OK, so let's look at this issue of texturing! I'm going to use my
ceiling or my roof, my glass ceiling, as an example. You guys might want to
use something else, like maybe you've got some walls that you've tried stretching and the textures
have gone a little bit wrong. So, let's take a look! Firstly,
I'm going to get my ceiling the right size before I start. It's good to get the things
the right physical size, before we worry about adjusting the texture to
them. So, where it is! I'm going to use the Scale Tool, which I can get to with the R Key,
and I'm just going to scale down this roof panel and move it so I'm switching
between hitting R and W, until I get it how I want. Now,
remember that you've got a top view, and feel free to go to the top view with
this minimize button and then maximize the top view.
And then, in the top view, I can see both the position of
the roof and of all the walls below it. So then,
when I come to rescale, etc. I can do it much quicker if I'm in
this view. So, here we go, I can pull it down,
and then, remember also your snapping options up here. You can choose to snap at a different
rate if you need to. OK, so that's going to
help you to get the roof exactly the right size, so that it just fits over.
So, this may apply to your walls or whatever. Now, I'm not going to make it absolutely precise,
it's not worth me spending the time, but you get the idea of moving it around
and getting it pretty much right. Now, the question is, I want to change the
texture on it, so how do I do that? With the SM_GlassWindow
selected, you need the Details Panel, which I've closed by mistake.
So, what we have here is a glass window, at the moment. I'm going to stick with a glass window,
in my case, and I'm just going to change the material on it. So, let's go to the
Material Editor there, and I'm going to go to the View Options and make the thumb
nails a lot larger. So, we are, just to
recap, Material is against the Materials section. I've gone to the
drop-down arrow to get this pane up, and I've gone to View Options
to make the thumbnails larger, then, I can see the materials options. Now, one of our students
used, I think, this hex tile or was it the one below?
It was Tile_Pulse I think? Yeah, Tile_Pulse!
There it was! So, I'm using Tile_Pulse in this case. Now, what's wrong with it? Well,
what's wrong with it is the texture is not scaled properly. We look at the object
itself, the roof object. We can see that it has a scale of 10.25.
Let's make that a nice round 10 by 5.
Make that a nice round 5, just recenter.
So, I'm going to make it precisely a scale of
1 in the X, 10, and then 5.
OK, and it won't quite do that and that's because of the way it's
locking the uniformity of the scaling. It's saying that this thing
previously had a none-integer scale, so you can turn off the lock
to make that give you all the flexibility you want alright.
Then remember that you can drag in the X Y plane, by carefully selecting
here. And now, that roof does actually fit quite well, and it's scaled
to actual round numbers. Now, that's going to be important in a minute!
Let's go and look at this texture in the Texture Editor! What I'm going to do
is make the Unreal Editor only half of the screen like that. Then,
I'm going to go to the texture. Now, one way to get to it is to just click on the magnifying
glass. Now, before you edit this texture you've got a choice.
Do you want to use the actual texture and edit that, or do you want to make a copy
of it? Well, I think we're going to make a copy of this. I'm going to Duplicate
it, I'm going to call it My_
Pulse, and I'm going to put that, actually,
straight in Content, not in the Starter Pack alright.
Now, where has it gone? If you lose something
you can search and then you can look and see it's still in Starter Content,
Materials. So, let me try and move it again, My_Pulse.
Move or copy My_Pulse, and then I miss this dialog, Move Here.
So I've just moved it back to Content, and that means that
I can find it easily and it's not confused with any StarterContent.
So the roof, I'm going to change its material instance to My_Pulse.
I can search and therefore I'm not changing
the one that's in the StarterPack. It also means that if you .getignore that your changes will get
saved. OK, so it's My_Pulse that we're going to change! Great! Let's go
into it, into the Material Editor. I'm going to put this on the right-hand side so we can see, on the left
here, the actual roof in question and how it's looking
OK, and then, on the right-hand side we've got the Node Editor for the materials. Now, we briefly
popped in here before, but the bit that we need to worry about is
if the material is setup properly. Then, you would hope that somewhere on the
left-hand side, probably, you'll have a Text Coord node, Texture
Coordinate node, OK. If you click on that, you can see
here we have UTiling, VTiling. Now, what's U and
V about? Well, at some point we've got to map the coordinates, the
X Y coordinates, if you like, or the row column coordinates of the
texture to the actual object, but we're using X, Y, Z in the world
here and we've run out of letters, so we use U and V like X and
Y. Alright, so these are the X and Y coordinates of the texture!
So, just grab your UTiling and then try changing it. Now, you're going to have to
click Apply for it to actually apply back to the world.
And if we say 10 for the UTiling, let's try that!
And this entirely depends on how much density you want. Let's try
10 for the VTiling, Apply.
OK, that kind of looks
OK. I probably want to have the VTiling the other way
a little bit more or less, I think. I think it's more
because what I'm trying to aim to achieve is that, the way this roof is stretched,
I want it to look fairly uniform. It doesn't have to be perfectly square.
So, that was the wrong way, so I go 5. So, sure you can be
more methodical and work out what you should be putting in these places, but obviously a quick
doubling and harving, a binary search again, this can be a good way! Look
that looks pretty even! So, let's go inside the room, back in the game.
In fact, I'm going to give myself a luxury of a full screen view with F11, and
it's much darker in here now, so we'll sort that out with the light in a minute. But I've got a roof that
has a texture on it that isn't tiled too strangely, so that's pretty cool!
Alright, so all I'm going to do now is fill the room in with a little bit of light.
Let's go and have a look! F11 we're going to find some Starter
Content. Let's go find some props
and ceiling lights or wall lights. I think we could probably
just use wall lights here. What else have I got?
Hmm? I could turn the brightness of this
guy up a lot, that should bounce around. Let's do that for a start!
How are we looking? I
actually don't mind it being pretty dark in the corner here, because it kind of gives some affordance.
I think, actually, I've overdone that light. Let's bring it back down. I don't mind it being
dark in this room. You're welcome to add as many lights as you want, but this kind of
indicates where we want to go, it's into this dark corner. So, I'm happy
with that! Alright, so that's it! That's how you adjust your
texture tiling! So, what I want you to do now is to adjust your textures. Experiment with
new textures. So, now you can be bold. You may have avoided textures
earlier in the section, because they didn't tile properly. Adjust the tiling, as I've just showed you.
Share the results in the course. Please take some screenshots, share them around, show off your work.
I've seen some amazing results! Don't be put off by other peoples' work, if it's better than you think
you can achieve, just share what you've got and it's all good just doing and
sharing is all good. So, see you in a moment!
OK, welcome back! I'm only coming back because I normally
come back from challenges, and it may be confusing for you if I don't. So, I'm back but
nothing to do right! I hope you've gone to the discussion and you shared your awesome
graphical results, and yeah, I shall see you in the next video!
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1:Unreal/Section3/BE37 Managing Texture Tiling.srt