Hi and welcome
to Pointer Protection Process! So. why are we even
looking at this. at this stage. suddenly? Because in the upcoming videos. we're going to be making
a blueprint of our openable doors. so that we can actually control
their movement with a nice piece of graphical interface. called
Bezier Curves. And when we blueprint the doors. we're going to end up with some horrible
null pointer issues. that are going to make the game crash. unless we get our pointers
protected properly. This is an important habit to get it to. so let's start talking
about it. Basically. horrible crashes will happen when we follow a
null pointer. We must always check pointers before use. When declaring  we want
to always initialize to null pointer. We've done that in some places.
in our header files. where we've made a pointer type. but we haven't always
said equals null pointer in the beginning. So. we'll fix that. by basically looking
for stars in our header files and then helping finding any pointers. We also want to
check before every use of a null pointer and a
pointer for null pointer and handle it appropriately. Sometimes we'll choose not to.
like if it's an owner and we're talking about a component like an OpenDoor. We're going to assume that.
that has an owner. but if you want to you can check that too. So. let's
dive in and take a look! So. let
me show you the problem first. For example. if we take this right-hand door. look at its details.
go to the OpenDoor component. If I was to remove
the pressure plate here. then what would happen over in the code
is that our pressure plate pointer... Do you remember how we did that? Let's take
a look! Grabber. no it's an OpenDoor.h!
In OpenDoor.h. we declare a PressurePlate. we
naughtily don't initialize it. so let me just do this now. Why would we initialize
it to null pointer. if following null pointers is such a problem? Well. following null
pointers is a problem. but one thing that's worse than that is following a pointer to something undefined;
because at least we can check for a null pointer and at least we know that
it's just going to make the program crash horribly. At least it's not going to do something really weird and
unexpected. so it is important whether we have a start to follow it. So by
not assigning this PressurePlate over here. in the Details Tab.
what's going to happen is this PressurePlate pointer is going to take the value of null pointer.
and then. when we try and use it. the first time we try and dereference
it. where does that happen? Well. let's take a look! If we look for
pressure plates in the current document. there when we do this arrow operator.
the thing is going to crash. Let's see it in action! So. are you ready? Let's hit
Play. and we get this type of very unpleasant crash.
It doesn't tell us what's going wrong. and if its
this kind of terminal and suddenly it could be a null pointer
error. OK. so I'm going to re-open Unreal. and we want to make sure systematically
this does not happen in our project. because we lose or work. we don't know what's going wrong.
it's just a horrible horrible type of crash. So. I'm going to go to the Grabber. and I'm going to
make sure things are OK on the Grabber. then you can do the PressurePlate.
So. the first thing to check is that all pointers. which we can find by saying start in the
current document and looking in the margin for the yellow bits here. all pointers.
these to here. have a null pointer initialization. They do! Great!
Now. let's take the PhysicsHandle firstly. and make sure that in Grabber.cpp.
in the implementation. that in all cases we check carefully.
So. here we try and set the PhysicsHandle pointer to this stuff. and
we check if it's null pointer. and if it's not. then we log an
error. So. this is the one place where we log an error. and we should
get a helpful error coming through. which is saying it's missing the PhysicsHandle
or component. Great! But where else do we use PhysicsHandle? We use it here!
And down here we are not checking before we do this
arrow operator. so if we manage to get to the Tick. which is what just
happened. we're going to get a problem. So. here's a general piece of code you can say
if not (!PressurePad)
then just simply. at this stage. a little tiny
block of code in the same line. if you like. . If not...
...pressure Sorry. pressure pad. I'm writing the wrong thing! (!PhysicsHandle).
If not (!PhysicsHandle)  OK.
and then. we continue to look for other instances. Well. if we've returned.
which means leave the TickComponent function. then none of
this will get called. So. that protects that one there and again down here.
just before we try and use it. if not (!PhysicsHandle)
and before the ReleaseComponent(); So. in all cases. we want
to just bail out of the method if the PhysicsHandle pointer
is not set. And in one place. at the top. you want to
log a useful error message like this. that we've already done. to tell the designer or to
tell yourself how to fix the problem. Let's try again! So. let's
go back into the engine. I'm going to go to the DefaultPawn
blueprint. I'm going to remove the PhysicsHandle from it.
Save All first in case it crashes. and then try playing.
And it crashes horribly! So. somewhere in here. we have
not quite caught all of the uses or I didn't compile.
That's the other possibility now! It looks like I've compiled. because in Visual Studio there are no
stars against any of these files. but I want to make sure that. that compilation actually made it
all the way through to Unreal. If it crashes. then those changes
you make. like the DefaultPawn PhysicsHandle. may or may not get saved depending on
when you save. Before I play again and risk another crash.
I'm just going to check for PhysicsHandle.
and I'm going to make sure
that I have return statements above all of the uses in
each method. I seem to have there
and here! Yep. we just log an error! OK. so I believe this will work now!
And it crashes again! This is
why these are so insidious. these problems. and we must from now on
get really tight with how we use pointers. So. let's go find out what's
wrong! It's probably nothing to do with the PhysicsHandle! I've probably left one of these doors unassigned!
If I look at the door. the OpenDoor component. that one's got a Trigger
Volume. but this guy hasn't you see. and the way that it
crashes you just can't tell. Ah. now the doors are OK! We get a log
red error message. and it's very helpful. "DefaltPawn_BP_C_0" the exact
instance "missing physics handle component". and when I try and pick stuff up.
it just doesn't work! So. this is failing graciously. I would say!
We are getting an error that we can now fix!
Well. what do I need to do? It's very obvious right! I go to the DefaultPawn and
I add a PhysicsHandle component
to it. compile it. and run.
and now I can pick up and drop and we're all back to normal. Awesome!
So. your challenge is to protect all of your pointers! I want you to protect the pressure
plate pointer. before use. I want you to log a helpful error if it's null.
test that that works. and then. initialize any other
uninitialized pointers in the whole solution. So. check all your header files for anything with a star in it.
and make sure all pointer usages are properly protect with the
pattern I've just showed you. OK. cool! Pause the video. go ahead
and do that now! And by the way. if you don't remember the pattern. it is in the first instance.
you want to log out saying which item which pointer
is not being properly allocated. and then.
every other use you want to just use a if not pointer then return type pattern.
OK. go ahead do it!
OK. welcome back! So. I'm just now going to go through my solution
and see what needs fixing up! I'm going to go alphabetically. and we're going to
ignore all the things starting BuildingEscape. because we didn't write them. I'm going to start with Grabber.h.
Both of these pointer types are initialized. I'm going to go to Grabber.cpp.
There's a PhysicsHandle. which we've just dealt with.
but there's also an input component. Let's see where that is!
Now. SetupInputComponent! This is already
protected here and that is the only use.
Good! OK. now let's move onto OpenDoor.h! Let's look for stars!
We have another naughty down here! Look Owner should
still be pointed to null pointer. and we may as well put the comment
above it. Great. are there any other stars in this entire header file?
No. so let's take one at a time. PressurePlate. let's go to PressurePlate. find
it! Where's it used? Well. it's used just in this
one place! So. this is probably not the
place to log out. because this happens regularly. and it's quite deep in your code.
So. what I would suggest we do here is. we say if not (!PressurePlate)
then
OK. and then. somewhere further up the code. we're going to log
this useful error. In fact. I'm going to get it from Grabber.cpp. It's going to
be something like this stuff here.
I just want the log message
really. So. in OpenDoor.cpp it's in the BeginPlay()
that I want to make sure that we actually have this PressurePlate
right? So. let's do it there! I'm just
going to simply say. actually. if not
(!PressurePlate) then
log something missing pressure plate.
OK. so now if we were to search for "PressurePlate" we have
at the top of our code. we have a useful error. and then. in all usages
we have a protection line. this. Great! What was the other thing.
in here. that was a pointer. it was an owner? We're going to choose to not worry about
Owner. because this is an component. OpenDoor.h. and it's very
likely to find the Owner. But if you want. you can go and protect Owner in a similar way. I'm not going to bother.
Let's check the PressurePlate now. Compile!
Remember previously when we removed the PressurePlate
from a door. it caused a problem? So. let's
remove the PressurePlate now. from the right-hand door. and once my compilation finishes...
OK. we're getting an error that says. "GetTotalMassOfActorsOnPlate must
return a value". Let's look at that function.
And the problem here is that we're
just returning. when we need to return total mass even though it's 0.
We need to come out of the function. but we need to get something back. because the return type that's expected is
float. OK. let's try now again! So. the
compiler is checking that all code paths are returning something useful. I have. on the door.
removed the right pressure plate. What do we get? Ah. SM_Door2
missing pressure plate. We of course can Eject. without stopping playing.
go to the World Outliner. click on SM_Door2. and then. it's highlighted
in the word so we can see exactly which one is causing the problem.
We can reassign the pressure plate. and the. we're back in business! Awesome!
Let's finish the job off now! PositionReport.h. do we have any
pointers in here? No. we should really actually do a search.
but no. so therefore we don't even need to look in the .cpp. because we're not dealing with any
pointers. OK. wow hard
work! Yes. worth it absolutely! Now. our solution is
much much more robust! I'm going to close it. I'm going to save all over here.
and I'm going to have a nice relieved commit here
that's going to be talking about the fact that we are not protected. So.
I hope you're committing your work. I hope you're using version control. I hope you're having fun.
and in the next video we will start doing even more exciting stuff!
=======
Hi and welcome
to Pointer Protection Process! So, why are we even
looking at this, at this stage, suddenly? Because in the upcoming videos, we're going to be making
a blueprint of our openable doors, so that we can actually control
their movement with a nice piece of graphical interface, called
Bezier Curves. And when we blueprint the doors, we're going to end up with some horrible
null pointer issues, that are going to make the game crash, unless we get our pointers
protected properly. This is an important habit to get it to, so let's start talking
about it. Basically, horrible crashes will happen when we follow a
null pointer. We must always check pointers before use. When declaring  we want
to always initialize to null pointer. We've done that in some places,
in our header files, where we've made a pointer type, but we haven't always
said equals null pointer in the beginning. So, we'll fix that, by basically looking
for stars in our header files and then helping finding any pointers. We also want to
check before every use of a null pointer and a
pointer for null pointer and handle it appropriately. Sometimes we'll choose not to,
like if it's an owner and we're talking about a component like an OpenDoor. We're going to assume that,
that has an owner, but if you want to you can check that too. So, let's
dive in and take a look! So, let
me show you the problem first. For example, if we take this right-hand door, look at its details,
go to the OpenDoor component. If I was to remove
the pressure plate here, then what would happen over in the code
is that our pressure plate pointer... Do you remember how we did that? Let's take
a look! Grabber, no it's an OpenDoor.h!
In OpenDoor.h, we declare a PressurePlate, we
naughtily don't initialize it, so let me just do this now. Why would we initialize
it to null pointer, if following null pointers is such a problem? Well, following null
pointers is a problem, but one thing that's worse than that is following a pointer to something undefined;
because at least we can check for a null pointer and at least we know that
it's just going to make the program crash horribly. At least it's not going to do something really weird and
unexpected, so it is important whether we have a start to follow it. So by
not assigning this PressurePlate over here, in the Details Tab,
what's going to happen is this PressurePlate pointer is going to take the value of null pointer,
and then, when we try and use it, the first time we try and dereference
it, where does that happen? Well, let's take a look! If we look for
pressure plates in the current document, there when we do this arrow operator,
the thing is going to crash. Let's see it in action! So, are you ready? Let's hit
Play, and we get this type of very unpleasant crash.
It doesn't tell us what's going wrong, and if its
this kind of terminal and suddenly it could be a null pointer
error. OK, so I'm going to re-open Unreal, and we want to make sure systematically
this does not happen in our project, because we lose or work, we don't know what's going wrong,
it's just a horrible horrible type of crash. So, I'm going to go to the Grabber, and I'm going to
make sure things are OK on the Grabber, then you can do the PressurePlate.
So, the first thing to check is that all pointers, which we can find by saying start in the
current document and looking in the margin for the yellow bits here, all pointers,
these to here, have a null pointer initialization. They do! Great!
Now, let's take the PhysicsHandle firstly, and make sure that in Grabber.cpp,
in the implementation, that in all cases we check carefully.
So, here we try and set the PhysicsHandle pointer to this stuff, and
we check if it's null pointer, and if it's not, then we log an
error. So, this is the one place where we log an error, and we should
get a helpful error coming through, which is saying it's missing the PhysicsHandle
or component. Great! But where else do we use PhysicsHandle? We use it here!
And down here we are not checking before we do this
arrow operator, so if we manage to get to the Tick, which is what just
happened, we're going to get a problem. So, here's a general piece of code you can say
if not (!PressurePad)
then just simply, at this stage, a little tiny
block of code in the same line, if you like, . If not...
...pressure Sorry, pressure pad, I'm writing the wrong thing! (!PhysicsHandle).
If not (!PhysicsHandle)  OK,
and then, we continue to look for other instances. Well, if we've returned,
which means leave the TickComponent function, then none of
this will get called. So, that protects that one there and again down here,
just before we try and use it, if not (!PhysicsHandle)
and before the ReleaseComponent(); So, in all cases, we want
to just bail out of the method if the PhysicsHandle pointer
is not set. And in one place, at the top, you want to
log a useful error message like this, that we've already done, to tell the designer or to
tell yourself how to fix the problem. Let's try again! So, let's
go back into the engine, I'm going to go to the DefaultPawn
blueprint, I'm going to remove the PhysicsHandle from it,
Save All first in case it crashes, and then try playing.
And it crashes horribly! So, somewhere in here, we have
not quite caught all of the uses or I didn't compile.
That's the other possibility now! It looks like I've compiled, because in Visual Studio there are no
stars against any of these files, but I want to make sure that, that compilation actually made it
all the way through to Unreal. If it crashes, then those changes
you make, like the DefaultPawn PhysicsHandle, may or may not get saved depending on
when you save. Before I play again and risk another crash,
I'm just going to check for PhysicsHandle,
and I'm going to make sure
that I have return statements above all of the uses in
each method. I seem to have there
and here! Yep, we just log an error! OK, so I believe this will work now!
And it crashes again! This is
why these are so insidious, these problems, and we must from now on
get really tight with how we use pointers. So, let's go find out what's
wrong! It's probably nothing to do with the PhysicsHandle! I've probably left one of these doors unassigned!
If I look at the door, the OpenDoor component, that one's got a Trigger
Volume, but this guy hasn't you see, and the way that it
crashes you just can't tell. Ah, now the doors are OK! We get a log
red error message, and it's very helpful. "DefaltPawn_BP_C_0" the exact
instance "missing physics handle component", and when I try and pick stuff up,
it just doesn't work! So, this is failing graciously, I would say!
We are getting an error that we can now fix!
Well, what do I need to do? It's very obvious right! I go to the DefaultPawn and
I add a PhysicsHandle component
to it, compile it, and run,
and now I can pick up and drop and we're all back to normal. Awesome!
So, your challenge is to protect all of your pointers! I want you to protect the pressure
plate pointer, before use. I want you to log a helpful error if it's null,
test that that works, and then, initialize any other
uninitialized pointers in the whole solution. So, check all your header files for anything with a star in it,
and make sure all pointer usages are properly protect with the
pattern I've just showed you. OK, cool! Pause the video, go ahead
and do that now! And by the way, if you don't remember the pattern, it is in the first instance,
you want to log out saying which item which pointer
is not being properly allocated, and then,
every other use you want to just use a if not pointer then return type pattern.
OK, go ahead do it!
OK, welcome back! So, I'm just now going to go through my solution
and see what needs fixing up! I'm going to go alphabetically, and we're going to
ignore all the things starting BuildingEscape, because we didn't write them. I'm going to start with Grabber.h.
Both of these pointer types are initialized. I'm going to go to Grabber.cpp.
There's a PhysicsHandle, which we've just dealt with,
but there's also an input component. Let's see where that is!
Now, SetupInputComponent! This is already
protected here and that is the only use.
Good! OK, now let's move onto OpenDoor.h! Let's look for stars!
We have another naughty down here! Look Owner should
still be pointed to null pointer, and we may as well put the comment
above it. Great, are there any other stars in this entire header file?
No, so let's take one at a time. PressurePlate, let's go to PressurePlate, find
it! Where's it used? Well, it's used just in this
one place! So, this is probably not the
place to log out, because this happens regularly, and it's quite deep in your code.
So, what I would suggest we do here is, we say if not (!PressurePlate)
then
OK, and then, somewhere further up the code, we're going to log
this useful error. In fact, I'm going to get it from Grabber.cpp. It's going to
be something like this stuff here.
I just want the log message
really. So, in OpenDoor.cpp it's in the BeginPlay()
that I want to make sure that we actually have this PressurePlate
right? So, let's do it there! I'm just
going to simply say, actually, if not
(!PressurePlate) then
log something missing pressure plate.
OK, so now if we were to search for "PressurePlate" we have
at the top of our code, we have a useful error, and then, in all usages
we have a protection line, this. Great! What was the other thing,
in here, that was a pointer, it was an owner? We're going to choose to not worry about
Owner, because this is an component, OpenDoor.h, and it's very
likely to find the Owner. But if you want, you can go and protect Owner in a similar way. I'm not going to bother.
Let's check the PressurePlate now. Compile!
Remember previously when we removed the PressurePlate
from a door, it caused a problem? So, let's
remove the PressurePlate now, from the right-hand door, and once my compilation finishes...
OK, we're getting an error that says, "GetTotalMassOfActorsOnPlate must
return a value". Let's look at that function.
And the problem here is that we're
just returning, when we need to return total mass even though it's 0.
We need to come out of the function, but we need to get something back, because the return type that's expected is
float. OK, let's try now again! So, the
compiler is checking that all code paths are returning something useful. I have, on the door,
removed the right pressure plate. What do we get? Ah, SM_Door2
missing pressure plate. We of course can Eject, without stopping playing,
go to the World Outliner, click on SM_Door2, and then, it's highlighted
in the word so we can see exactly which one is causing the problem.
We can reassign the pressure plate, and the, we're back in business! Awesome!
Let's finish the job off now! PositionReport.h, do we have any
pointers in here? No, we should really actually do a search,
but no, so therefore we don't even need to look in the .cpp, because we're not dealing with any
pointers. OK, wow hard
work! Yes, worth it absolutely! Now, our solution is
much much more robust! I'm going to close it, I'm going to save all over here,
and I'm going to have a nice relieved commit here
that's going to be talking about the fact that we are not protected. So,
I hope you're committing your work, I hope you're using version control, I hope you're having fun,
and in the next video we will start doing even more exciting stuff!
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1:Unreal/Section3/BE38 Pointer Protection Process.srt