I'm so excited about this one, I want to get
right into it real quick! So, sometimes blueprints
are just the better choice for getting things done. For example, defining our door
swing as a visual curve is the ideal way to do it, rather than messing around with
sign waves and things in code. So, we can create an
event called OnOpenRequest, and we can declare it as
(Blueprint Assignable)* UPROPERTY
according to these documentations, but only if we do some cool things. So, let's dive
in and see how it's done!
So, now with our nicely protected code in hand, it's time
to do something pretty cool! What I'd like to do is, rather than these
doors just opening perfectly to 90 degrees instantly like that, what I want
to do is use something called a Node Editor in Blueprint. So, the first thing we're going to need is
some blueprints to work on, and that's going to be a blueprint of the
doors themselves. So, if we look at these doors right now, then they're a compount
object with an OpenDoor component on them, and the
same door is being used in more than one place. So, this is an instance where we
want to be making a blueprint of the door. So, let's start by doing that! Click on either door,
go to the Blueprints menu, and carefully choose the Convert Selected
Actor to Blueprint Class.
Let's do that! I'm going to call it Openable
Door, maybe with an underscore because that was the pattern they were using,
and Create Blueprint. Cool! Now, just real quick, before we go
any further, I'm going to click on the door itself in the Viewport, check that the mesh still
has a collider on it. It does! That's cool! I've had a problem with that in the
past. OK, so this is it! We actually have a blueprint of the door now! This we
can be using to create other similar openable doors, and what we're going to
do shortly is, we're going to have some events
here in the Event Graph. I'm actually going to delete all of this stuff. You're welcome to do that now, if you like.
Highlight everything in the Event Graph and just hit your Delete Key.
So, we will have an event come in here that says, hey there's been a door opened,
it's going to come from C++, and then, we're going to use blueprint with
something called a Timeline.
Here you go, a Timeline at the bottom here,
and this Timeline is going to allow us to do something pretty cool. It's going to allow
us to actually define the movement of the door,
or don't bother doing any of this. I'm just going to show you, using things called
Bezier Curves. Look at this! How cool is this! And we're actually going to be able to define the movement like
this! This is why we're doing it here in Blueprint, this is a better way of doing things right?
Obviously a better way of doing things than trying to write code to follow those lines.
So, I'm going to leave an empty graph and I'm just going to
compile my blueprint. All we've done with the Openable_Door_BP, as a recap, is nothing.
We've just made a blueprint. I did just check in the Viewport
that my mesh has a collider, this purple thing around the outside of it,
this collision that's flashing on and off. But I've basically done nothing apart from making a
blueprint. OK, so the left-hand door, if we look in the World Outliner,
is a blueprinted door. The right-hand one is not, so I'm going to change my
other door for a blueprinted door. Kind of grab it from there,
put it in the hole, and of course, if it doesn't fit precisely, I may need to change my
Snap Value to just make it fit snuggly. OK, let's
try this! Play, now I get 2 errors, Open_Door_BP
and BP2_64. I can Eject with their fate.
I'm missing pressure plates, but we didn't crash because of the work we've just done! Awesome!
If I look in my World Outliner, I will find that these are the two doors in question.
If you hover over them, Door_BP, Door_BP2_64,
the two doors are both missing the pressure plate. That
was the problem with the blueprint. We can't, of course, refer to the pressure plate in
the blueprint, or we could but it's not a very reusable
asset then. So, we're probably better off just getting that error, going to the OpenDoor, and going
oh yeah, this door is opened by that plate and this door is also,
in this case. And then in your game it might be different, I hope you're doing something different. It's opened
by that one! Cool! So, we have a templated door that we can use
and it is stable. If we don't have a TriggerVolume and the
game doesn't crash, we can put it in, and now we're back kind of to where
we were, except that we now with these doors have a
blueprint we can edit. The question is, how do we know when
the doors are going to open. What we need to do is create an event that's
raised in the C++, that we can see in the blueprint. Now, it
turns out that's not completely trivial to do but it's doable. This is
the documentation you need, it's linked in the original slide. You need to
do this. We need to start, by making something
(Blueprint Assignable). We're going to make a variable (BlueprintAssignable) per here.
OK, so that's a template of it and this is the example. And to make
it (BlueprintAssignable), we need to do this at the top above
our class. We're actually going to make a class called, in our case,
FOnOpenRequest, and we're not going to have any other
parameters. So, we're going to make a new class using this strange
method here, this strange macro here,
and then, we're going to define something, an event handler
of type that class and then, we're going to actually get a hold of that
Blueprint. So, let's go and do it! This is one of these things I've just got to show you how to do, but
you're going to get a chance to fiddle with the blueprint in a minute. So, with this pattern in
mind, I think I'm just going to copy DECLARE_DYNAMIC-MULTICAST_DELIGATE, because that's the
thing I'm most likely to spell wrong. Let's go into the IDE and make
this happen! So, we're going to be in Open_Door,
which make sense right because it's the OpenDoor.h
that we're wanting to extend. Above the class,
in OpenDoor, I want you to put DECLARE_DYNAMIC_MULTICAST_DELIGATES(). Whew, that's
a mouthful isn't it? Why do we need this? Let's not go into too much
detail. Basically, if we want to make an event (Blueprint
Assignable), it basically needs to be one of these guys. It turns out an
event is a special part or a sub-set,
if you like, of a DYNAMIC_MULTICAST_DELIGATE, but look,
man that's a horrible sounding thing but we are declaring something.
It is DYNAMIC, which means it's serializable, which we turn out to need, which is MULTICAST
which means one to many. And it is a DELEGATE, which means that something else
is going to handle the operation and something else is going to be the blueprint. That's basically
what that means. So, DECLARE_DYNAMIC_MULTICAST_
DELEGATE(). And then, we're going to call it, starting with F, because the Unreal coding standards other
classes start with F (FOnOpenRequest).
Now, I'm going to end, start ending all macros with
a semicolon, unless otherwise stated, just to remove confusion.
So, let's just make sure this works first. The IDE doesn't like it,
Visual Studio doesn't like it. That's because it doesn't understand about these thing. What we need to do
is go and compile over here. I very much want you to get in the habit of compiling
in Unreal, because the errors you'll get will be much more useful over here,
and it should compile just fine. What we're just doing is proving that, that made
sense to the compiler, one step at a time. Now, we want to make
a public property, but importantly it's a UPROPERTY,
which we usually use to expose things to the Details Tab
and we're going to make it blueprint assignable.
OK, not this thing that's autofilling, but that does prove it's spelled right. You can choose that if you
like, and then, take the CPF off the front. So, it's a blueprint
assignable thing, and what is it going to be called? Well, the type is going to be this
(FOnOpenRequest). You see this has actually gone the right color now that
Unreal has had a chance to run. OK, so we've made a new class, that's
why it's above the class definition. This makes a whole new class called (FOnOpenRequest) a new
type. So, we're going to make an (FOnOpenRequest)
and what are we going to call it? What do we always call things when we're not sure? Just the thing without the
prefix OnOpenRequest;
OK, so this is our thing that is
actually going to allow us to handle the event, OnOpenRequest.
When is it going to be called and how do we call it? Well, you don't call an event, you
broadcast on an event. So, over here
in our OpenDoor(), let's look at OpenDoor. Let's stop rotating the actor, you
can comment it or delete it. I'll comment it for now and we're just going
to say OnOpenRequest
dot, and it's a Request because it's the blueprint that's actually going to do the
opening, so we're only requesting an opening, .Broadcast.
And I've gone off there. .Broadcast(); and that's a method.
OK, so what on earth have we done here? [Laughs] We
have made a class, we have said that we want it to be (Blueprint
Assignable), we've made this OnOpenRequest, and then, when we open
the door, instead of setting the rotation directly, we are broadcasting on that event. Now,
let's go and compile and see how, in Blueprint,
we actually get hold of this event. This is a triumph, by the way, in your
progress in Unreal, if we can dive and dance between Blueprint and
C++ as we need to, we're in a great place right where you
use the tool that's best for the job in hand. C++ has been best up to
now, defining the movement of that door is better in Blueprint. Let's go from C++
to Blueprint, and later I'll show you how to go the other way back. So, let's open the
door blueprint. Click on the OpenDoor component. If you're not on the OpenDoor component like
this and you right click inside the Event Graph, you're not going to get the references
you need. The way the Blueprint Editor works is, you have to be clicked on the thing you want to reference
to. Now, with OpenDoor click, which is where we just wrote our code,
right-click and you'll see you have Add Event for Open Door, Event Dispatchers,
Add On Open Request. Zoom in with the Mouse
Wheel and that is the event OK. Awesome!
You can drag the execution, the white execution line off the
event, Set Actor Rotation.
So, I want you to drag off the white line, and the thing that comes up,
I want you to search for Set Actor Rotation then choose it.
Now, your challenge comes. It's very simple but it gives you a chance to catch up, because this has come
hard and fast and to make the final bit, which will be very satisfying. I want you to
set a rotation and test that it works. Set a door rotation, here in the blueprint,
test the game still plays the same, and celebrate the fact you're now
using C++ events in Blueprint. You may say, how do I set that rotation?
Just take a look in the Blueprint there, there's three numbers for X, Y, and Z. Just
choose the correct axis, and put a number of degrees in it. You can do it!
So, welcome back! Let's do this! I'm going to choose -60
in Z. OK, and I'm going to Compile
my blueprint, play the game. What happens? Nothing! We get on here... Ah,
it opens! Was that because of the blueprint or
is it an illusion? Let's test! Let's go and change that to, I don't know,
30 +30! It should come 30 degrees towards me now! Let's
see! Ah, you see I have control in
blueprint! That is seriously awesome! OK,
so congratulations, this is really big news! You can now
go from C++ to Blueprint, via asynchronous events! i.e.
events that happen at no particular time. I'm going to make it a -80
degree opening, and up next, we're going to talk about how to turn this into a smooth
fluid movement, based on a curve, that we define in graphical
interface. Exactly where we want to be for that job! Well done!