Welcome to Everything
in its Place! So. in this video. we will be
noticing that Blueprint has superseded some of our code. We previously exposed
things like open door in the Details Tab; now. we want to get rid of that and
only set it in the curve. Because it's important. there's only one place per
parameter. and we'll be creating a second event called OnClose and use it to close the
door. By the time we're finished. we will have a situation where a couple of
things are different. Firstly. if we look at a door and we inspect it and we look at the
on door component. we will have 0 amounts of
open distance or time delays. Just a different
Trigger Mass that we'll be able to set here. rather than it being hard coded. And when we play
the game. what's going to happen is the door is not only going to open smoothly. but when we come off the pressure pad. it's going to close smoothly.
So. with this blueprint we've got our door opening. The question is. how do we get it
closing? What we need is a Close or OnClose
event. coming into the Reverse pin. which will just run the animation backwards.
So. we want to be continuously. either firing OnOpenRequest
or on CloseRequest or make a slight naming change. as well.
So let's go over to the code and start preparing things.
OK. most of what we're going to do. over in the code. you can do.
and you'll do it in a challenge in just a moment. I just want to show you that the whole
spirit of this video is everything in it's place. You'll remember.
in the previous section. there was a video called a place for everything. Well. I have a lovely
saying. which is a place for everything and everything in it's place. [Laughs] And I just wanted to
jimmy that into the course some way. So. this
OpenAngle is now defined inside the blueprint. right.  so let's delete
it from the OpenDoor.h. We don't need an OpenAngle property. We shouldn't have an Open
Angle property. it's confusing to have it in two places.
We still need the PressurePlate. We don't need a DoorCloseDelay anymore.
You could orchestrate that inside the
blueprint rather. If you did want a CloseDeley. then you'd think
carefully about how and where you put it in. because it's very confusing to have the animation
or the curves determining one thing and then CloseDelay in here. So. I'm going to get rid
of CloseDelay. I'm also going to get rid of LastDoorOpenTime. The door
can immediately start closing the moment you step off the plate. now that it has
a nice smooth
movement. so we can get rid of all of those things
which is pretty cool. Now. this reminds me. by the way. that getting the total
mass in kilos... Do you remember that we had a task we left ourselves.
which was to make something into a parameter? It was the mass.
It's here. "// TODO make into a parameter". Let's just do that while we're here.
Total MassOfActorsOnPlate. rather than 30 it should be something
like TriggerMass OK.
So. I'm going to make a new EditAnywhere property
here. called TriggerMass Float
Mass =... And I'll give it a default value of.
not my previous lecture name. but 30 kilos.
OK. and then let's make it an EditAnywhere UPROPERTY. while we're messing around
with the interface here. Alright. that's cool!
Now. in our code. we are going to need to do a couple of things.
We no longer have LastDoorOpenTime. so let's get rid of that.
Well. we're calling ClosedDoor. but actually.
look if we look at this. what's the point of the whole OpenDoor() method? There's no point. is there?
It just called OnOpenRequest.Broadcast. so move
OnOpenRequest.Broadcase() down inside the TickComponent.
inside here. and just ditch the whole OpenDoor() method. We're just having a massive simplification
now. So. I'm also going to go over here and get rid of the
declaration of OpenDoor(). We don't need that. We're also.
of course. not going to need ClosedDoor(). because what we're going to do. in a moment.
or you're going to do is you're going to create a Closed
Request or OnClose event. and we're going to call it from here. So.
we won't need a ClosedDoor() method either. So. I've made a bunch of changes to
the code there. while I was talking you through. They're pretty self explanatory. Let me just
compile to make sure I'm leaving you. before your challenge. with workable code. There's a good
chance in trying to do that and talking through it that I've made a mistake. so I'm going to
compile over here and let the Unreal Editor tell me.
Yep. so I've made a mistake there. on line 48 'LastDoor
Open Time' is undeclared. so I just need to be removing that.
And the point is that. we don't need to wait for a delay. What we're going to do
now is we're going to say. if the total mass of the Actors on the plate is greater than the
trigger mass. open the door. or else close the door.
And of course. there's a TODO which is we're going to get
rid of this method. but you're going to do that in a minute. Let's make sure that we now can compile.
Second compilation. should be a bit quicker if
it's just done one. There you go! I'm just going to play. make sure that the door opens.
So. it's all working! We've just had a refactor! Remember the red. green. refactor.
Things were working. they were green. We've refactored. they're still working. that's
good! Now. over to you! I want you to do the following challenge.
Create and connect OnClose. I want you to finish this off! So.
I suggest you rename the event class to FDoorEvent. It no longer makes sense for it to
be talking about OpenDoor(). when the event is both going to be responsible for a class
that's going to responsible for open and close events. So. don't be afraid to do a rename.
Rename the OnOpenRequest to simply OnOpen. You don't have
to but it's just easier to read. Create a new Blueprint
Assignable event. exactly like OnOpen. but call it on close.
Wire OnClose. over in the blueprint. to the "Reverse" pin.
and then. test that the door now opens. when you stand on the plate. and the moment
you step off it starts to close. So go ahead. pause the video. and see if you can get this finished
off yourself! By doing this. you'll really understand everything we've just done a lot better
than just listening to me rattle on and trying to keep up with me. OK. it's all about you
doing stuff. So. pause the video. spend your time on it. and come back with it's either done
or you've died trying.
Wicked welcome back! So let's do this
thing! Over in the header file then.
(FOnOpenRequest). Well. that no longer makes any sense. it's going to be
FDoorEvent. That is what I said isn't it? Yeah.
FDoorEvent. Cool. so that rename there should have done that! Now. let's go down to where we define
it! FDoorEvent OnOpenRequest; Well. I said we want to rename that. It was
just going to be OnOpen. I have to check my own instructions. I hate failing my own challenges.
Just bear with me a second. Yep. OnOpen! So. we now want to copy that
code and make a OnClose;
And yes. by the way. we're still polling this
PressurePlate every frame. over in out Tick. and that's not ideal but it's
fine for this section! I'm not even going to change it in this section. because there's enough going on
here with events. different types of blueprint events. etc. So. let's not
confuse things. but sure. you could do the whole thing event driven but we'll deal with that in a future
section. I'm going to get rid of this TODO. I'm going to change On
OpenRequest. Now really. I should have done a refactor on there. You see how I didn't refactor OnOpen
Request. I just changed its name. The problem with that. of course. is it doesn't change in all
cases. but there's only one here. I'm looking at the red in the margin. that's
gone. Now. we don't need to call CloseDoor() anymore. do we? We don't need to set this Actor
Rotation. so you can delete the method all together. Of course. you need to delete the
declaration. otherwise we'll get an error. We can then
do a OnClose.Broadcast();
I hope you remember that bit. That's a bit I didn't explicitly tell you in
the challenge. but of course. you need to broadcast the event. Hopefully you found that
by pattern matching against what we did before. so perfectly valid way of doing things.
OK. so the next stage is. I think that I finished doing my code. I want
to compile the code. make sure that works. You need to compile the code for
the new event to even be visible inside Blueprint. Unless you've compiled. it's
not even going to be there. So. the compile has worked! Now. let's go into
Blueprint! Now. do you remember how you get hold of... Why can't
I find OnCloseRequest.OnClose or whatever? And also.
what's going to happen to the fact that this has been renamed? Well. let's try compile. see if the rename
comes through! It hasn't come through. interestingly.
Let's check our code. OnOpen. So firstly.
we're going to fix both of these things together. I want to make sure that the thing with the new name is
in here. even if this works. I don't want it working by happenstance. So. I'm
going to go to Window again. Components which will bring up this menu. Remember
that once you're click on OpenDoor. you can now find your
events. Event dispatchers you see on open. The same again. right-
click on the OpenDoor in the Components. Add Event.
Event Dispatchers. OnClose. OK. so we've
got the OnClose. Oh. I did OnClose twice. didn't I! Let's get rid of this OnOpen
Request. This OnOpenRequest. It's just not updated the name. so I want to
delete it and make sure that we do actually update the
name. And you see another way to get to it. by the way. is just to right-click
OnOpen and say AddEventOnOpen. So. there's another option. That was over there
in the Components menu. right there. Pretty cool hey! So look. we're nearly there!
We just need to get to where you can see what I'm doing. We
need to say that. OnOpen. we go into Play and OnClose we go into
Reverse. Now. let's watch this in action! Drag it to the right!
We don't. as I say. have to compile your blueprint. It's not necessary to do it every time.
because when we go over to the game and play. look what happens! I go on.
the doors. you see the doors opening. because the OnOpen event is firing. firing. firing. firing? But when
I come off the pressure plate. the OnClose event fire. fire. fire. fire. and the whole thing
reverses. Pretty cool hey! Pretty
cool. apart from the fact I can now probably get out of this room. if I really run for the door.
but we won't worry about that. right now. that's just play-tuning.
That has achieved the goal of teaching you how to finish
off this type of blueprint. And you can see that you can do blueprint. right next to your
code. We're doing as little as possible really. in the blueprint.
There is a Timeline track. called a Vector
Track. but we don't need... A vector won't work
for a rotator. so you have to convert from vector to rotator anyway. so I used a
Float Track just because I'm trying to say. I only really want to be changing one axis
of a door. right. But if this was something else. and we were changing its position. we
may want to make it a Vector Track and then put it straight into Set Actor position
or something. But the reason I've used a float here is. as I say. for simplicity. But it's
pretty simple isn't it? Pretty simple and clean! OK. the whole
project is looking pretty good now. The only remaining thing is a bit meanging.
as I would say. is that we are polling the trigger volume
every frame. rather than responding to events. but I'm going to live with that for now because it's
not causing us a performance issue. So. we're pretty much
done with this section! Of course. my room is very rudimentary! What I really want you guys
to do is go and do a lot more exciting things. multiple rooms. use these
mechanics in lost of different ways. and maybe even create your own new mechanic.
But for now. we are doing really nicely. I'm just going to look at it in full screen.
because occasionally it's nice to see your thing in all its glory.
And over there. and then to watch it close. and remember. you can
control the speed. you can control the curve. and much more like it!
So. see you soon!