Welcome to Using Variables in Blueprint! In this video,
firstly not all doors have the same absolute rotation. I've put my doors in a particular
way, but your doors might be on different walls right or your door and it might be
opening strange. It might open to 90 degrees at start and then close
and do the opposite. Whatever, it may not be behaving right! There's a good reason for it!
We want to store the door's rotation at BeginPlay(), at the start of the game.
Then, we want to use this value to make a relative rotation. The
door opens 90 degrees relative, not to 90 degrees, or minus
90 degrees. That was a world space, a global opening
angle. We want wherever the door is to open through 90 degrees, not
to 90 degrees and we can use blueprint variables for this!
And by the end of it, we're making doors that can face and
work in any direction. So, let's dive in and make it happen!
OK, so let's take a look at this! I've got two doors here, I've just kind of
casually left them there while I've been playing. But what I'm going to do is, I'm going to actually
introduce a third door at a different angle. So, I'm going to select a door and
actually its frame, holding down Shift, so I've used Shift to select the
two. I'm going to grab the Alt Key, holding down Alt right now, and
then, I'm just going to pull this door out and then spin it around. I'll place it in a wall
a little bit later on. For now, I actually want all three doors
just so I can easily test. So, here's our third door, let's see the
problem. As I come over, in fact, let me just move this door into the light.
See the light little door, because then I'll be able to well see
what's going on. [Sings] Skipity beepy dee! There it is, over there! OK, let's just see the
problem. The problem is that door immediately opens. Why does that door immediately open,
and what happens when I stand on the pressure pad? It closes! It's doing exactly the
wrong thing. Now, why is it doing exactly the wrong thing? Do you know?
Well, let's take a look at the blueprint! All the behavior of the doors is in the blueprint
now. Remember we make the decision that we come out of C++ over here in the Events, and we do everything
in Blueprint. Well, the reason is this, isn't it, that the timeline
for this open door starts with a rotation of 0. Now, remember that's an absolute
rotation. So, if I go back to the Unreal Editor
and have a little look at this door, if I hit the rotation key and go to details,
you can see now that the rotation of this door,
the door itself... There you go, let's have a look!
What is the rotation of the door? Well, we have
-90 and 0 is here. So, what's happening
is it's setting the world space, the absolute rotation, to 0
and then, it's closing it back to -90. These other guys are already at
a rotation of 0. This guy needs to start at -90. So, we
need to capture the initial rotation of the door, that's the point. How are we going to
do that? Well, let's go take another little look at the Blueprint and I'll show you a cool way of doing it.
Back to the Event Graph! So, the first thing we need to do is we need
to capture the BeginPlay() node, not being but
"beginplay". So, go find your BeginPlay
node there! Alright, now that's going to be called, obviously, at BeginPlay. It's exactly
the same as the BeginPlay() method in your code. Now, what I want to do on
BeginPlay() is I want to "getactor" rotation.
OK, GetActorRotation. So there it is! What
actor? Well ourself! Why is it ourself? Because we're a blueprint on the door., so
it is just the game object is us. OK, now you notice there's no incoming
execution node. Remember that these white lines tell you about the flow of execution.
There's nothing for GetActorRotation, and the reason for that is you can get the actor rotation
at any time, so it's time independent. What are we going to do with it?
Well, let's drag out of the right-hand side of it, and when you let go you'll have a
context sensitive list of things you can do, one of those will be promote to variables.
So let's do that, let's promote it to a variable. When you do that, your interface will get instantly
cluttered, so I'm going to get rid of the right-hand tab
just for simplicity. And you'll see New Var 0 here, but on the left-hand side
under Variables and under Details on the right. A couple of different places you'll see that you can
rename this new variable. I'm going to call it Initial Rotation, nice and
simple. We're nearly there in terms of storing the Initial Rotation,
but of course, this Set and this
this Set box, this Set node has never been called, it never executes
so that's where the BeginPlay comes in. We wire the BeginPlay,
if I can drag the right thing, into the Set node. So, are you
clear on what this does up here? The things I've highlighted simply
set the initial rotation variable, it's a blueprint variable on this thing,
at BeginPlay. OK, I'm just going to zoom out a little bit and move
this up. Fine, that's what happens! Now, what we need to do
in here somewhere is, instead of making this return value
directly setting the rotation of the actor, what we want to be doing is making
a relative rotation. So, we're going to break this link,
and we're going to hand it over to you. I want you to try and combine
the rotations. See if you can finish the blueprint off and get it working.
Look for a way of combining rotators. Connect it all,
test it, debut it if necessary. Remember that you can put the blueprint on the right
and the game window on the left and hit Alt P to get going and
see the blueprint in action, as it actually draws its execution.
And then, the last thing to say is good luck. Just see if you can get this working.
Have a go yourself, pause the video, and I'll see you on the other side!
So welcome back! Let's
button this up! How would you do it? Well, you could pull out of this pin,
and you would have here a set of context sensitive stuff.
And you may, if you browse through, find what you're looking for.
You could type the word "rotator" and then look through and see what you
get. Ah, combined rotators. That sounds good! "Combine 2 rotations
to give you the resulting rotation." Hmm, let's try that!
So, we have combined rotators. Let's just organize
the blueprint so we have no crossing paths and so it looks good. So the return
value is just going to be piped in here, but what's going to come onto the inside. You might be temped
to try and pull this in, but this would happen at the wrong time. We
want to only combine the rotations when this update
loop happens. So, we want to get
Initial Rotation OK. So, that's
GetInitialRotation. There's the value, we want to pull that at the time we
need it asynchronously, and
that's the flow we're after. Make sure you keep this update link
there. Now, let me visualize what this is doing. Sorry, excuse me, I'm fiddling with the Initial
Rotation. I don't need to. That's what we're going for! Return Value! It combines
for the Initial Rotation and sets the target. Let's put the window on the left-hand side,
like I talked about. I'm going to get rid of some toolbars, even over here.
Let's go for broke! Let's get rid of them all! Beautiful! And that, all of it!
Go away. OK, now let's play! So, what's happening right now?
Well firstly, let's make sure this Initial Variable is set. Alt P,
you can see. Now, this goes for a lot longer, obviously BeginPlay the event
lasted a fraction of a second, but visualizes it, if you watch, on the right-hand side
now for a bit longer. Well, that's just saying, OK I've set that value,
and now what's happening is, we're constantly calling closed door, so we're
just keeping those doors closed. But notice how this door here has not
opened up to 90 degrees. Watch what happens when we go on the pressure plate now.
The door does the right thing. We could change its rotation by changing its
timeline, but you see it's doing the right thing. Let's see what Blueprint is doing. Now we can
see what Blueprint is doing, let's see the whole picture. So, we come over here,
boom, and it's not actually visualizing the data
flow through here, the fact that the open Angle is changing, it's just not showing us that. But
we can see it's working, so all that remains now is to just; I'm just going to
make my level sensible, and in your case, pick yourself maybe a different door location.
I'm actually going to just leave my doors, I think, as they are.
I'm going to just get rid of this door, but the blueprint
for the existing doors has changed right. If I go to this
door, go to the World Outliner,
Edit the blueprint. You'll see it is still running the new blueprint, because there's only one. So, what
we've done is we've made the way that these doors open more general, and you can put
these doors in any orientation now and they will open in a relative
rather than an absolute way. So, that's the end of that video! Go ahead
put your doors on any wall now freely, without wondering why on earth they open into weird angles,
and I'll see you in the next video!