So,
welcome to SFX & Audio Clips! In this video, we're going to trigger
a simple sound in Blueprint. Later in the course, we'll use C++ as well,
however we'll always reference our assets via Blueprint, so that we're not
hardcoding them into the code so that we can rename them, basically.
We'll be showing you how to trigger a 3D sound. That's a sound that emanates from the position of the door,
when the engine will start to work out how that sounds from the player's position, so that's kind of fun!
So, let's dive in and see how it works! So, welcome back!
You should find the sound file, that I'm going to be using, attached to this
very lecture. And I want to say a big thank you
to Gamemaster Audio! You can Google for Gamemaster Audio, for providing
me with this free sound file, and also, there'll be some other sound files in this
course. It's part of the Pro Sound Collection, you can see here, and I do
encourage you to check these guys out. It's very kind of them to donate it for
us, for free, for this course. Now, the deal is, you're allowed to use it as part of the
course, but if you want to use this sound file in a commercial game or
for any other game, you do need to get in touch with Gamemaster Audio
and either purchase their collection or ask them for permission. So, with that
said, go grab the sound file and let's go to the Content Browser. I'm going to make myself
a new folder called Audio, here in the Content Browser. And then,
in that folder I'm going to import from... Now, in my case, I have it
in this Building Escape folder here, but you will need to go download it. Or you can use your own
sound file or just get a microphone out or your iPhone or your Android phone and
Windows phone and slam a door. [Laughs] Whatever, get a sound file. Just a .wav is fine!
An .mp3 is fine too! I'm using a .wav here. So, here's this door_
lock sound. Now, we can play this! Here you go, by right-
clicking on it, you can do all sorts of things. You can create a cue, but look, for
now I'm going to show you just how to do this in Blueprint, because we're already defining
the behavior of the door, here in Blueprint. And we're not going to go much further
with this Blueprint, because this is, of course, about C++, but I'm going to finish this
door behavior off by just putting a sound in. If we get much more complicated than this, I
would be inclined to go back to C++ and use more C++, because these things just become
horribly unwieldy if there's too many of them. Alright, so you've got your
sound available inside Unreal. If you can...
I just need to minimize this. If you can find the sound in the Content Browser and
play it, like you hear it going there, then you know it's working.
Then, what I want you to do is to work out how to make the sound play yourself.
So, get the sound working, get the sound effects playing
on your own, consider making or finding other sound effects,
and why not make a short video using Snagit or Jing
or something, and then, share the results of what you've
done, in terms of your sound. And maybe you're trying to make some music, whatever, push the boat out
a bit here and add some sound to the game, and just see if you can get at least this door sound
working, by discovering the appropriate Blueprint notes yourself. And if you're
struggling, come back and I'll show you how to do it.
So, welcome back!
Here we go, into the Blueprint for the
door. Now, what we want to do is, we search. Either drill into Audio here or
search for Audio. Now, we're going to Play Sound at Location. Sounds are 3D if you
do them this way, so Play Sound at Location. When are we going to play
the sound? Now, this is the bit that may have been a bit of a challenge for you.
How do you know when you're going to play the sound? Well, what we can do on
this Door Swing, and look it's perfectly alright if you couldn't work this out for yourself. I wanted to put
a bigger challenge in here, so that you could  get your teeth really stuck into something.
So, go into the Door Swing, and you add yourself an Event Track.
OK, I'm going to call this Sound Timing,
and I'm just going to add a node here, at lets say point
1 of a second. The value doesn't matter, because we're not using the value, but I'll set the value to
0. So, 0.1 of a second, after the door starts to open, an event
will be fired. What does that mean? Well, look over here! We get a Sound Timing
Execution Pin. We can pipe that like so,
to move this all along, into the Play Sound at Location.
So, what happens is, as we go along this timeline, we can compare the two,
then just after the door started to open we get a little bit of a sound. You might want to do it early or
later, it's up to you. You can move it graphically, it's easy! What's the location?
Well, we getactor location, so we want to play the sound emanating
from where the door is. And what's the sound asset? Well,
we go into and search for door, door lock. That's as simple
as that! Let's try it!
You hear that?! Perfect! And then, you close
and you get the same sound again! Now, you're going to say to me, I'm sure, in the
discussions of the course, how about if we want to have more than one sound,
different sounds, playing at the start and the finish? Well, of course, it can be
done! Anything can be done here in Blueprint, anything can be done in code. If you want to do that, I'm going to
leave it as an exercise to the reader, because this, as I say, is a C++ course. I'm only adding
the sound in here, in order to make things more
complete for you, and I don't really want to make a spaghetti-fied
complicated blueprint. You know, if a blueprint
doesn't sit on the screen like this, it gets too big too hard to follow, and I've
seen a lot of tutorials that are really hard to follow with Blueprint. So, yes you can do it! No, it's not that difficult.
Yes, you have to think about what state we're in and exactly when you
play it. Of course you can work it out! Of course I can work it out! I encourage you to have a go if you
want to get better at Blueprint, but if you don't want to get better at Blueprint, let's crack on! Let's
get on with the next section, where we're going to be focusing on a whole new slew of
things that we can do! It's relatively easy to deal with sounds in C++ as well,
and I'll be showing you how to do that, later in the course. What we will always be doing
is referencing our sounds through Blueprint; i.e. we won't be
hardcoding a reference, inside of our game, to the
actual asset name here, because we want to be able to rename this
with ease and without worrying about it. So, we will always be referencing via Blueprint,
even when we do things in C++. So, that's it,
we're pretty much finished with this section! Maybe a little bit more polishing to do in the next
few videos, I will leave that open, but we have all
of what we need to make a very simple Building Escape game. You've got plenty of mechanics, it's up to you now
to go and do what some of the students have done, which is make incredibly impressive
and elaborate Building Escapes, using sounds, pressure pads, and you could come up with
some novel game mechanics of your own, that use what you have already learned. So, see you soon!