So. congratulations on yet another complete section!
Obviously the game is not completely finished. but we don't all of the tools we need
yet. like the User Interface Tools we would need to put a Menu System on a
game like this or scoring. And there's a lot of things
we can add to make this into a real game. but it's enough to have really got you started.
Just look back at the last 40 or so lectures and see how much you've learned about
C++. about Unreal. about Unreal specific C++.
about Blueprint. ah it goes on. And what I'd really like you to do is
just carry on a little bit and just make this your own. Do a little bit more
than I've done. Just push the boat out a little bit and then share in the discussions
what you've done. and then. proudly and quickly get on straight
with the next section. Also. attached to the section notes. the
slides which are right up at the first lecture. you can go to the Google docs and
the slides are there. Hopefully you've found the slides useful. I'd like some feedback in the discussions about
slides. Do you like them? Do you not like them? Do you use them? Which
parts of them do you find most useful? Maybe the challenge slides or they're in this video.
And on this final slide. or the last couple of slides.
of the entire section. there's a couple of handy little checklists for you. One is how to
delete a class in C++. We're likely to be doing this in the next
section. for the first time. the first time a name a class wrongly. it's much harder
than it should be. There's a step by step process there in the slides. as to how to do it. And
I just wanted to tell you that now. because if you're experimenting and playing with your project.
then you might misname something. and feel free to be able to delete
and start again. But yes. Unreal has made it far to hard to rename a class.
The other thing to say is. if you are coming from Unity. this is a great time. now
that you've had enough exposure to Unreal for it to make sense. to look at the docs
I've linked in the very last slide of the section
notes. which is a guide to Unreal development for Unity developers.
And that's really handy. it draws all the parallels for you! So. that's
it for this section. we''ll be diving straight into the next section. and I will see you in there!