Hi! Welcome to Options for Grouping Actors!
In this video we're simply going to be discussing all the different ways that we could group actors together.
including layers and groups and tags and empty actors and folders.
etc. And then. we will be picking a scheme and discussing it with other students and cracking on!
So just before we get these NPC's actually iterating through
a list of possible patrol points. let's just discuss in general
different ways that we could actually group things together. This is a very general discussion
about how do you group actors. that are semantically related.
So the point is. there is no correct answer in a given situation. but what is
quite important is you've got some idea of the options that are available to you and
that you are able to choose between them. sensibly. You're nearly always making a comprimise in
an engineering situation like this. but we want you to make one that you and everybody else you're
working with understands. So let's start and take a look at a few things! I'm just going to play
around here and have a look! So one thing we've got is layers! So if I
multi-select say a few of these cubes. say maybe all three of these cubes
here. these EditorCubes are then multi-selected. I use the Control Key to do that.
One thing we can look at is layers. So we have to go to Window
and then Layers. and that'll bring up this funny little panel here.
And then. what we can do is right-click in there and then say. Add Selected Actors to a New
Layer. and we could just call this Cube Stack. for example.
That should be one way. And if I turn that off you can't see them. and if you turn them on you can see them!
We could add all Cubes to another layer. including those Cubes. so
we could say these three. In fact. it would be easier if I just did this
one in the Hierarchy. so let's just grab them all. And do have a play with this. as you listen to me. Now. all
Cubes are selected. and I could Add Selected Actors to a New Layer and
say All Cubes. So one thing about using layers is
that a particular
object. like this stack of three cubes. can be in more than one layer. So we can turn off
All Cubes or we can turn off the Cube Stack. but the only way that this layer.
that these cubes. will disappear is if they're turned off in both situations. If they appear
in any layer. then they will appear in your level. Layers are normally used for visibility. For
example. if you have a building with multiple levels on it. as in floors. then you may
want to turn off floors that you're not working on for simplicity. when it comes to visability.
You could also say use it for cover. we could turn off All Cubes if we're working on level
geometry that didn't include these cubes for cover. etc. So it's one way of grouping things.
I'd suggest you mainly use it for visibility. as that's what it's designed for. You can kind of
see that inherent here. in the way that there's a little eye. You can also click
See Contents in the Layers window. that that will show you the contents. I'm
going to Delete all of these Layers. Don't delete the actors. Delete the
Layers themselves. if you delete them. Delete Layer there. right-click Delete Layer. and I'm going to
close the window. So layers. that's one option. mainly for visibility. it is a possablity for grouping
things together. You could query for those but I would stick with it for simplicity
and visibility. Alright. so groups. what are groups? Well let's have a look!
If we multi-select something in the World Outliner and right-click. we have this
strange Group option. If I hit Group like that. let's see what it's done.
It's made this thing called a GroupActor here. in the Hierarchy. and it's
a kind of weird thing. If I click on any of the TargetPoints and they all end up selected. but the Group
Actor doesn't. and if I click on GroupActor. then everything including
the GroupActor gets selected. So really. a group is just a way of
rapidly multi-selecting things. and I don't really like that. I think that's a bit
confusing. There's not hierarchical aspect to it. it's a bit asymmetric the way that I
click on TargetPoint and GroupActor doesn't come up and vice versa. But there may be some situations
in which you want to use this for rapid multi-selection of things.
So I'm gong to Delete the Group. You need to do that a little bit carefully. you need to
Ungroup first. and then. well then the group disappears and you're done!
Alright. so tags! How about tags? Well tags can be pretty cool! So if we
multi-select the TargetPoint and look down at tags. then we could just add
arbitrary tags. Now a given thing could have multiple tags. so we could say patrol
and then all of these TargetPoints would have a patrol tag on
them. And you can have multiple tags on a given object. very handy. a bit
like the way Google Docs works. you can have multiple folder labels
effectively on a given file. Advantages. well one thing can have
multiple tags. it's nice and flexible and simple. it's unobtrusive.
it's relatively fast to find things by the tags. but the problem is. you've got to
remember to add them and it's quite easy to forget to add tags. Just like the problem with Google
Drive is that you can forget to assign things to folders. if you're going to be cleaver and
try and have two definite hierarchies running. So I'd prefer a hierarchy that's simple to
conceive. but tags can be useful. I don't think I want to use tags in this situation. but be
aware that they're there. they can be queried in Blueprint. they can be queried in C++.
and they're pretty cool! So that's tags. now
a parent empty actor! So here's another thing we can do with these Target Points. we could say well we've got all these Target Points.
why don't we put an empty actor in the world? It doesn't really matter where. and then. back in the
World Outliner we grab all the TargetPoints and pop them under the empty
Actor. if Provided I can find it. There it is! And I can give this guy a name. I can say
Patrol Route 1. and that's pretty cool!
When you ever add another PatrolPoint it's fairly obvious that you'll
want to be sticking under this Patrol Route. You can iterate through children
of this Patrol Route Actor. to find all of its TargetPoints. Pretty handy!
It's a bit weird if we want to add say a cube as one of control routes. because then
where do we put the cube? Does it go in this folder. because this is organizing by folders.
which is. of course. another way that you could do things. You could use empty actors.
which has a consequence that if you move the parent actor then all the
children move. and perhaps that's the best reason to use an empty actor. I'm not sure that you'd
want to do that here. Why would we move the Patrol Route around.
as a whole? You know. its shape really does depend on what's in the level.
so I think it's not really appropriate. but one of the consequences
of using a parent actor is that you can move the parent and all the children go with it.
So I'm just going to move these out. get
rid of the parent actor.
So to create a folder. you just to the top-right here of the World Outliner. and that just literally
makes a folder. which just groups things from that stand point. It's literally
a way of organizing your hierarchy. so they have no impact on how anything is actually working.
it's just an organizational tool. They can be handy as well! In fact. straight away.
all these TargetPoints should at least be in a folder. So I'm going to do that. Target
Points.
and there we go! Now. why has the SkySphere ended up under the TargetPoints? If I undo with
Control Z. it's just because it was selected. If you have something selected before
you create a folder. then you are going to put those things in that folder
straight away. So why not select all the TargetPoints and then call this
Patrol Route. And there is a folder of them or Patrol
Routes or TargetPoints is more descriptive.
OK. so I could put all my TargetPoints neatly there and then collapse all this stuff
down. Simple. folders. telling you how to use folders! So what else could we do?
We could group on the GameObject. which is what we are already doing. On the ThirdPerson
Character here we have an array of PatrolPoints. and they are
now. rather than being just TargetPoints they are actors in general.
which means that we can put into that array whatever we want. We can put TargetPoints. we
could put stairs. we could put cubes. we can put any actor. we can even put another
actor. like a player. One of the patrol points could be chasing the player. it'd be a bit weird but you could
do it. So loads of options! Let's just recap what we've done! We've talked about layers
that you access through Windows and Layers. You could use Groups. which is
just a clicking tool inside the World Outliner here.
You could use tags. nice and flexible. easy to forget to add them. You could use a parent
empty actor. particularly useful if you think you're going to be moving all the children wholesale.
together. then the way the transforms work will mean that's easy.
You can use a folder and we're going to use a combination of a
folder and then also just grouping on
the actor. because a given actor may want to share some of these TargetPoints.
so that makes life easy to conceive about. And you can use. not just
TargetPoints but other actors as well. So what I want you to do is to just explain a
grouping choice. Pick a grouping choice for the patrol points yourself.
Don't worry about what we're already doing or what I've decided I'm going to use. I just want you to
argue for a particular grouping choice. I'm going to go ahead and do it the way that I'm doing it.
but I want you to just get used to discussing it with other people. this is
really helpful to open the discussions. So click on Lecture Discussions in the Resources.
share your thoughts with others about how you may group these things. or you're
welcome. at this stage. to open the discussion wider and talk about how you may
group things like projectiles from a previous project or whatever. Let's just have a discussion
about grouping in the discussions. And.
as I said. I'll pick one and carry on with that. and the purpose of this is purely to think about different grouping
choices. the pros and cons. and also perhaps you can think of some other ways of grouping
actors. that may be useful to you. So go ahead. pause the video.
discuss grouping with your peers. and I will see you in the next video. when I
will carry on with my choice!
=======
Hi! Welcome to Options for Grouping Actors!
In this video we're simply going to be discussing all the different ways that we could group actors together,
including layers and groups and tags and empty actors and folders,
etc. And then, we will be picking a scheme and discussing it with other students and cracking on!
So just before we get these NPC's actually iterating through
a list of possible patrol points, let's just discuss in general
different ways that we could actually group things together. This is a very general discussion
about how do you group actors, that are semantically related.
So the point is, there is no correct answer in a given situation, but what is
quite important is you've got some idea of the options that are available to you and
that you are able to choose between them, sensibly. You're nearly always making a comprimise in
an engineering situation like this, but we want you to make one that you and everybody else you're
working with understands. So let's start and take a look at a few things! I'm just going to play
around here and have a look! So one thing we've got is layers! So if I
multi-select say a few of these cubes, say maybe all three of these cubes
here, these EditorCubes are then multi-selected. I use the Control Key to do that.
One thing we can look at is layers. So we have to go to Window
and then Layers, and that'll bring up this funny little panel here.
And then, what we can do is right-click in there and then say, Add Selected Actors to a New
Layer, and we could just call this Cube Stack, for example.
That should be one way. And if I turn that off you can't see them, and if you turn them on you can see them!
We could add all Cubes to another layer, including those Cubes, so
we could say these three. In fact, it would be easier if I just did this
one in the Hierarchy, so let's just grab them all. And do have a play with this, as you listen to me. Now, all
Cubes are selected, and I could Add Selected Actors to a New Layer and
say All Cubes. So one thing about using layers is
that a particular
object, like this stack of three cubes, can be in more than one layer. So we can turn off
All Cubes or we can turn off the Cube Stack, but the only way that this layer,
that these cubes, will disappear is if they're turned off in both situations. If they appear
in any layer, then they will appear in your level. Layers are normally used for visibility. For
example, if you have a building with multiple levels on it, as in floors, then you may
want to turn off floors that you're not working on for simplicity, when it comes to visability.
You could also say use it for cover, we could turn off All Cubes if we're working on level
geometry that didn't include these cubes for cover, etc. So it's one way of grouping things,
I'd suggest you mainly use it for visibility, as that's what it's designed for. You can kind of
see that inherent here, in the way that there's a little eye. You can also click
See Contents in the Layers window, that that will show you the contents. I'm
going to Delete all of these Layers. Don't delete the actors, Delete the
Layers themselves, if you delete them. Delete Layer there, right-click Delete Layer, and I'm going to
close the window. So layers, that's one option, mainly for visibility, it is a possablity for grouping
things together. You could query for those but I would stick with it for simplicity
and visibility. Alright, so groups, what are groups? Well let's have a look!
If we multi-select something in the World Outliner and right-click, we have this
strange Group option. If I hit Group like that, let's see what it's done.
It's made this thing called a GroupActor here, in the Hierarchy, and it's
a kind of weird thing. If I click on any of the TargetPoints and they all end up selected, but the Group
Actor doesn't, and if I click on GroupActor, then everything including
the GroupActor gets selected. So really, a group is just a way of
rapidly multi-selecting things, and I don't really like that, I think that's a bit
confusing. There's not hierarchical aspect to it, it's a bit asymmetric the way that I
click on TargetPoint and GroupActor doesn't come up and vice versa. But there may be some situations
in which you want to use this for rapid multi-selection of things.
So I'm gong to Delete the Group. You need to do that a little bit carefully, you need to
Ungroup first, and then, well then the group disappears and you're done!
Alright, so tags! How about tags? Well tags can be pretty cool! So if we
multi-select the TargetPoint and look down at tags, then we could just add
arbitrary tags. Now a given thing could have multiple tags, so we could say patrol
and then all of these TargetPoints would have a patrol tag on
them. And you can have multiple tags on a given object, very handy, a bit
like the way Google Docs works, you can have multiple folder labels
effectively on a given file. Advantages, well one thing can have
multiple tags, it's nice and flexible and simple, it's unobtrusive,
it's relatively fast to find things by the tags, but the problem is, you've got to
remember to add them and it's quite easy to forget to add tags. Just like the problem with Google
Drive is that you can forget to assign things to folders, if you're going to be cleaver and
try and have two definite hierarchies running. So I'd prefer a hierarchy that's simple to
conceive, but tags can be useful. I don't think I want to use tags in this situation, but be
aware that they're there, they can be queried in Blueprint, they can be queried in C++,
and they're pretty cool! So that's tags, now
a parent empty actor! So here's another thing we can do with these Target Points, we could say well we've got all these Target Points,
why don't we put an empty actor in the world? It doesn't really matter where, and then, back in the
World Outliner we grab all the TargetPoints and pop them under the empty
Actor, if Provided I can find it. There it is! And I can give this guy a name, I can say
Patrol Route 1, and that's pretty cool!
When you ever add another PatrolPoint it's fairly obvious that you'll
want to be sticking under this Patrol Route. You can iterate through children
of this Patrol Route Actor, to find all of its TargetPoints. Pretty handy!
It's a bit weird if we want to add say a cube as one of control routes, because then
where do we put the cube? Does it go in this folder, because this is organizing by folders,
which is, of course, another way that you could do things. You could use empty actors,
which has a consequence that if you move the parent actor then all the
children move, and perhaps that's the best reason to use an empty actor. I'm not sure that you'd
want to do that here. Why would we move the Patrol Route around,
as a whole? You know, its shape really does depend on what's in the level,
so I think it's not really appropriate, but one of the consequences
of using a parent actor is that you can move the parent and all the children go with it.
So I'm just going to move these out, get
rid of the parent actor.
So to create a folder, you just to the top-right here of the World Outliner, and that just literally
makes a folder, which just groups things from that stand point. It's literally
a way of organizing your hierarchy, so they have no impact on how anything is actually working,
it's just an organizational tool. They can be handy as well! In fact, straight away,
all these TargetPoints should at least be in a folder. So I'm going to do that, Target
Points,
and there we go! Now, why has the SkySphere ended up under the TargetPoints? If I undo with
Control Z, it's just because it was selected. If you have something selected before
you create a folder, then you are going to put those things in that folder
straight away. So why not select all the TargetPoints and then call this
Patrol Route. And there is a folder of them or Patrol
Routes or TargetPoints is more descriptive.
OK, so I could put all my TargetPoints neatly there and then collapse all this stuff
down. Simple, folders, telling you how to use folders! So what else could we do?
We could group on the GameObject, which is what we are already doing. On the ThirdPerson
Character here we have an array of PatrolPoints, and they are
now, rather than being just TargetPoints they are actors in general,
which means that we can put into that array whatever we want. We can put TargetPoints, we
could put stairs, we could put cubes, we can put any actor, we can even put another
actor, like a player. One of the patrol points could be chasing the player, it'd be a bit weird but you could
do it. So loads of options! Let's just recap what we've done! We've talked about layers
that you access through Windows and Layers. You could use Groups, which is
just a clicking tool inside the World Outliner here.
You could use tags, nice and flexible, easy to forget to add them. You could use a parent
empty actor, particularly useful if you think you're going to be moving all the children wholesale,
together, then the way the transforms work will mean that's easy.
You can use a folder and we're going to use a combination of a
folder and then also just grouping on
the actor, because a given actor may want to share some of these TargetPoints,
so that makes life easy to conceive about. And you can use, not just
TargetPoints but other actors as well. So what I want you to do is to just explain a
grouping choice. Pick a grouping choice for the patrol points yourself.
Don't worry about what we're already doing or what I've decided I'm going to use, I just want you to
argue for a particular grouping choice. I'm going to go ahead and do it the way that I'm doing it,
but I want you to just get used to discussing it with other people, this is
really helpful to open the discussions. So click on Lecture Discussions in the Resources,
share your thoughts with others about how you may group these things, or you're
welcome, at this stage, to open the discussion wider and talk about how you may
group things like projectiles from a previous project or whatever. Let's just have a discussion
about grouping in the discussions. And,
as I said, I'll pick one and carry on with that, and the purpose of this is purely to think about different grouping
choices, the pros and cons, and also perhaps you can think of some other ways of grouping
actors, that may be useful to you. So go ahead, pause the video,
discuss grouping with your peers, and I will see you in the next video, when I
will carry on with my choice!
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1:Unreal/Section5/TG13 Options for Grouping Actors.srt