Hey and welcome to Modular
Arithmetic and Cycles! We're going to be talking about the modulus operator.
and we're going to be writing ourselves a new Blueprint function here. which will allow our guy
to finally cycle between more than just two points. In fact. an arbitrary
number of targets points. waypoints. or any actors in the world.
this guy will now run between. So he's truly patrolling. a little bit frantically because he's
running. but he is patrolling in a very keen new employee sort of way. So I'll see you in there!
OK. so we want to get this AI finally cycling between
patrols. and he's going to need to cycle the waypoint index number.
depending on how many waypoints this AI is supposed to be visiting...
You know what. I'm fed up with turning this camera around. Give me a second. I'm going to grab the player.
spin him around until... I need to grab the right thing though. let's go to the
World Outliner. find the
FirstPersonCharacter. rotate watching the camera preview. Now. when we
go. we can see Harry or Steve or whatever his name is running without having to keep turning. Anyway.
here he is. here's the dude. Harry. Steve... What's his name? Steve.
that's him! And if we look at his patrol points then he's got a handful of them. and what we
want is the patrol point index number to go 0. 1. 2. 3.
0. 1. 2. 3. 0. 1. 2. 3. So that's what we want to achieve! How are we going to do it? We're going to
use something called the Modulus Operator. Now. if you are an experienced developer
and you think you know Modulus like the back of your hand. you probably do. and you can skip ahead to the challenge
slide or just listen to me explaining it. if you wish. So what is Modulus?
Its percent is the operator we use. it's a special kind of division which only spits out the
remainder of the division. So let's take some examples! One Modulo
3. like that. = 0 + 1/3. You'll
see why I bother with a 0 in the front. but the important thing is that 1 Modulo 3 is
a 1/3. so the Modulus is 1. it's the remainder of the division. It's a bit of a
special case below. where the left-hand side is below the right-hand side. but it'll
become clear in a pattern in a minute. Two mod 3 is 0 + 2/3.
so the modulus is 2. the remainder is 2. Three mod 3 is the first time it's
a little bit different. because 3 divided by 3 is 1 and we have no 1/3's left
over. so the modulus becomes 0. We've gone all the way around the clock!
Five mode 3 is 1 + 2/3. Remember you're all back to the
school days of working out how to turn proper into improper fractions and stuff
like that. So 1 + 2/3 so the mod becomes 2. And 7
mod 3. well you've got 6. you've gone around twice. so 2 loads
of 3 gives you the 6. and then. a 1/3 left over so the modulus is one. So if you're not
sure then pause the video there. have a look at it. and make sure that those numbers make sense. You can wiki
for mod. if you like. You can put it into Google. you can say 11 mod whatever.
by just putting. literally. the percent sign into Google and its calculator will tell you.
Whatever. play with it. make sure you understand it. but don't spend too long because on this slide
I'm going to explain it a different way. Imagine we had 8 waypoints that we wanted to
visit. then what we'd be wanting to do with the array index is going 0. 1. 2. 3. 4. 5. 6.
7. 0. 1. 2. 3. 4. 5. 6. 7. in a circle like that! So the first time around.
we use mod 8! This is a mod
8 arithmetic that we're bringing ourselves into. so 0 mod
8 is 0. 1 mod 8 is 1. 2 mod 8 is 2. it's very boring the first time around. you just
get what you put in! And the second time around it does what we said before. 8 mod 8 is
0. there's no remainder. Nine mod 9 is 1. 10 mod 8 is 2. and
so on. So you can see. as we count up with this number. then the answer
goes 0. 1. 2. 3. 4. 5. 6. 7. 0. 1. 2. 2. 4. 5. 6. 7 it just keeps
going around this circle and that is fine! So that is Modulus Arithmetic.
and it can be very useful to use this mod operator. to take a number of any size
and say how many times around the circle have we gone. You know. once.
1.3 times. whatever. that's what you're basically saying. But there is a
bug in the closet. and the but in the closet is this. if we store that index value. i.e.
the number on the left-hand side that keeps getting bigger. if we store that then
eventually we'll go out of range. For example. if it's stored as a 32 bit integer then at 4
billiionish. 2 to the 32. this thing is going to cycle back to 0. and
when it cycles back to 0. the counter will go wrong and skip.
probably. The chances it doesn't go wrong are very low. The chances are you're doing mod 5. mod
7. mod something like that. and you'll be very lucky if you
coincide. when your counter flips to 0. that you happen to be at the top of the
circle. So we don't want to leave that to chance and we don't even need to be storing those big numbers. we just
need to store the result. So all we actually need to store is what we get
out of the mod. That's all we need to keep track of. 7. because if we go 7 + 1
and mod the answer we get 8. which is 0 because 8 mod
8 is 0. So we only actually need to store the answer. we don't store the thing on the left-
hand side. So there's a got ya. that's the bug in the closet. if you like.
So what I want you to do now. reminding ourselves where we are now we're in the Blueprint
task. we're in our custom task that we've created... And
what's it called? Let's remind ourselves even what that custom task is called! It's called ChooseNextWaypoint!
Inside the definition of ChooseNextWaypoint. we've got the patrol points
off of the ThirdPersonCharacter. We have set our next waypoint like this!
So we've used things like Patrol Point arrays. Index numbers. Set Blackboard
Value as Object. we've done all that. So what I want you to do now
is to go ahead and write the contents of this Cycle Index function. write it out
here. as we did before. make sure it works. collapse it down to a function. So here is
your challenge slide! I want you to get the cycling working completely! Let's write
our final Blueprint function. There's a new node you'll have to use. which is Set
Blackboard Value as Int. whereas previously you Set Blackboard Value as Object
but that's fine. I want you to test that the AI does indeed cycle between the
waypoints. and then. celebrate! Seriously. why not stick your hands in the air and make a little whoop sound. because
you've achieved something! And share your solution with us on the forums. because we'd
like to see how you did it and how pretty your Blueprint is! So go ahead. pause the video.
and get the cycling working now!
OK. so here we are! Let's take a look! What are we going to do? I'm going to get the patrol points. for a
start. and I'm going to find out the size of this array.
So where is that? Length. there we go!
So that tells me the thing I'm modding by. so however long I make that array of Patrol
Points. I get out of here the size of the array. Do you want to prove that we
do?  Let's just go ahead and do a print node! Often. the easiest thing to do is pop a Print
node down. then drag into it. because it normally will do the conversion
for you. that way around. OK. let's pull the execution through the print.
and let's just play to ensure that we actually get the size of the array.
You won't get it until he gets to his first point. and then. it says 4. 4. 4. 4. 4.
and that is indeed how many we have! We have four items indexed 0 to 3.
Great! So that bit is working. we can stop printing that now.
So we have the length of the array. that's the thing that we're going to mod by. We're
may as well go ahead and find the mod operator straight away.
and I want to actually put it into the bottom. just because it reads better.
Well actually. it matters which way around you to it. as well. We're going to be saying. what is the
current index? So here's the Index! Mod. what is the length
of the patrol point array? Now. you can just take the
Index. which is of what type? If you hover over it. it'll tell you. It's a Blackboard Key Selector
Structure. You can't just take that and feed it in. because we need to get the value off it.
but we already did that in the previous step. If you remember. we
got the value as an integer here. in the previous
step. the value of the current Index. So if I just reorganize this
a little bit. So there's no point in us re-getting that value. because that's kind of
wasting our time. So what we'd like to be able to do is output that value in
this step of the function. So how are we going to do that?
Well what we have on the Set Next Waypoint. remember at the top.
we have Set Next Waypoint here. we never actually had a Return Node. So if we explicitly put
a Return Node in. like this. then on the Return Node we can
add an output. and we can add that output as an integer and we
can just call it Index. And then. what we can do is. we can pipe the Index that we've already got
in the previous phase through to that Return Node. So that's a way of outputting
from the function. If we compile that and go back to our top level.
which is here. you'll see that this has an Index coming out of it now. Cool!
So we can just use that Index number. so we know what the Index is. So once
we've got the mod. all we need to do now is Set Blackboard Value as
Int. so now we're setting the
value of the Index. So we've determined what the new
Index should be by doing our mod. There is the answer! What is the Key?
Well the Key is the Index. which is here. and that's all we want to do.
we want to set the Index and carry on the execution.
So hopefully. if I zoom out. that makes a little bit of sense. what we've done there. And if
you've managed to do this challenge. then congratulations. that's a good job to you! So
take a look at that. make sure you're clear on how it works. I'll uncross my streams. Now. let's just
test and see if it actually does work! So let's play the game. and watch Steve
here run off to the first waypoint. And if we're lucky. it'll increment his Index and move
to the next one. if it doesn't. then we just need to check and see what's happening.
So check. firstly. in your Behavior Tree. make sure that you've got
the Blackboard Keys set properly. and then. the next thing you want to do is play the
game and then watch his Blackboard. NextWaypointIndex. upstairs he gets
there. and he's not setting the next waypoint properly. so we have a little bit of a
debugging to do on here. And the problem is that I took the
Index from the previous iteration. we set where he's going but we never
incremented. So what I need to do. of course. is put an add + in here. not Vector
+ Vector but integer + integer. I increment
here by 1. and then. that is where I actually
move on. Without this. I'm not moving on. OK. let's try that!
So if I play the game. firstly. watch his behavior. He gets
there. runs to the next point. Now. let's tart inspecting his
Blackboard! Hopefully he's gone to the cube off to the right here. Yeah. he has! And then. he's carrying
on his merry way! OK. let's take a look at the patrol data itself!
Watch his Blackboard values. and you can see the next waypoint Index is going 0 here.
1 for UpStairs! he's already gone around the circle. so this proves the module
is working. and then. it goes up to... When he gets there.
it's taking its time. EditorCube21. which is waypoint 0
and 1. So he's just cycling between waypoints 0 and
1. at the moment. and the reason
for that is if you look on Steve. you'll see that his TargetPoints are
4 and 5. If you actually click them. are in ridiculous and unfeasible
places. so let's just fix TargetPoints 4 and 5 and put them back
inside the map. In fact. I'm going to delete all TargetPoints. actually.
like so. I'm going to move the UpStairs
under our Target Points folder. because that's the only one that's working right now.
and I'm just going to put a couple of other Target Points. I won't have him going
to the cube anymore. I'll use just Target points. and I'll bring a couple of Target Points
into the world. One could go there. one could go there.
The final thing I need to do is actually tell Steve that these are his new Target Points.
So I'm going to just find these Target Points. Target Point
there. Target Point... Oh. it's a bit fiddly!
Come on. Steve. let me set your Target Point!
It's not letting me do it. I'm just going to delete
that Target Point and add a new one.
You see. you may. in 13.0. have to be a little bit careful about
how you use your mouse there. There you go. he has UpStairs. TargetPoint. and TargetPoint2! Let's see
how he behaves now! So the reason he was failing is not
because the module is failing but because the TargetPoints were out in space. from
when I parented them to that parent. And now. you see he is actually cycling
between three different points. and again. if we watch that here. these values will
go 0. 1. 2 for the WaypointIndex. 0. 1. 2 and they will
keep repeating with any luck! And there you go! Fantastic. so you have him cycling
between waypoints. you've learned a little bit about Modular Arithmetic! All that remains
to finish this off is to take all of what we just wrote here. select it
all. Collapse it to a Function. and then. I'm going to give
that the name Cycle Index. Why not use the string I've already written. there's no point in
retyping. Cycle Index. there you go! Got to
delete the comment. because it's no longer relevant. Just going to check that Cycle Index
itself is reasonably clear! It is
reasonably clear. no cross streams. And the other thing to do is. at the top level
here you can see that we have this input is A. which is not that clear so I'm going to
bring up the Details Panel.
which is actually on my right-hand side. it's just very small. And I'm going to rename the Input to
just Index. so we have Index to Index. Great!
So now. we have a pretty clear top-level. and. we can dive into any of these and see that
we have reasonably clear logic. which the next thing we want to do is talk about how we translate
this blueprint. now that we've done it here. into C++!