So just before we get into the markdown and a little bit of a speech on marketing.
let's just sort out a couple more things with regards to this source control. When I
opened up my Unreal. I've noticed it's spawned both Oculus and
SteamVR for me. This happened in the last section. So I'm going to prevent that
by going to Settings and Plugins. Virtual Reality. then I'm
just going to turn off Oculus. for now. If we add any support
for this stuff later. then I will turn it back on. but I'm going to turn all these off. for now. including Gear
VR. and then. I am going to restart the Editor
and let's watch what happens over in the source control. Already. there are some changes to the
.uproject. and what's happened in the .uproject file. if I just tab
back to it. is it's put some plain text in here. just
saying that all of these VR platforms are disabled. false. OK.
that's cool! So we could commit that change. but let's just do a couple of things! Firstly. I'm just
going to close down the Editor again. and I'm going to close the
VR apps. Oculus and Steam VR. and just make
sure that they do actually not spawn next time. So
both are asking me to confirm to close them. Now. let's reopen the .uproject.
and hopefully that change to this
.uproject file here will result in neither of the
VR apps opening. And it does! So now. let's test
if this Source Control. Submit to Source Control actually works.
when it comes to the very .uproject file itself. I want to explore the limitations
of this thing. so we Submit to Source Control. and it says "No assets to check in!"
so it's not infallible. It would work if we say move that block up in the
air to make a floating block. If I now say. Submit to Source
Control... I better Save All first. because that's the most
reliable way for us to be sure that. when we click Submit to Source
Control that. it actually does recognize there's a change to the map. then I
would be able to commit. But if you just make a change to something like the project settings. it
may not recognize it. So I am going to do the first commit from inside Unreal
here. and actually. I think what I'm going to call it is the very name of
this video. which is called Marketing & Markdown. So the way that I
name my videos is. I prefix them with TG for Testing Grounds.
and then. I have a .cmproj on the end. because it's a Camtasia project. So I'm going to
use this as a template. and this video is going to be called TG4.
Testing Grounds video 4. and then. the name of it will be
Marketing & Markdown. there you go .cmproj.
Now. let's just let it do that! "Checking file(s) into Source Control". I'm going to
close Unreal and have a look over here and see what's happening.
Let's just do a Refresh!
And you can see that it has committed TG4 Marketing & Markdown.
but Unreal has still not got this .uproject
information here. It just didn't notice that these things changed. so as I said. it's
not infallible. when it comes to project settings. so there's a limitation. Now. say you have
this and you think. actually. I don't want this commit without these changes to this
.uproject in it. What would you do about that? Well what you could do is you could Reset that
Master Branch back here. So you'll right-click back on where I was
at the end of the previous video and you say Mixed is fine. It's going to "keep
the working copy but reset index". which means it'll move this
master tab down here. and then. all of those changes will be in our Uncommitted changes.
and just lumped together. the changes to the .uproject file and the changes to the map
that I made. remember when I made that cube float. Now I could commit from
SourceTree. with the same naming convention as before. I need to Stage
everything and Commit. Let's just go in here and say
Marketing & Markdown.
I'm just going to use exactly the same name as I used in the slides.
just for consistency. Yep. that's an ampersand!
And I'm going to push it immediately to GitHub. once I've Staged All the files.
So I've covered a couple of different things there. pretty much as an aside. but
it's more about the source control. If you've made a mistake on a very recent commit.
especially before you've pushed it up to the web. you can reset
your branch back to a previous commit and you can lump together a
couple of different commits. in that very simple way. There is another way of doing this. it's a
command called squash with git. but we don't need to go into that right now. The other thing that
we've noticed here is that Unreal doesn't necessarily notice a change to all files.
The meta files like the .uproject files and some of the Editor settings
and stuff. it may not notice they've changed. OK. So it's going to be really good at noticing
most of our changes to our assets. and it's going to allow us to commit from inside
Unreal. without having to exit it. by using that
to Source Control button but it's not infallible. So what I've done is. I've come out of Unreal and
done it the way I want it in Source Tree. Remember that source control.
in general. is a useless master
but a very good slave. That's the right saying. So by that I mean. you don't let it tell
you how you want things to be. you tell it how you want it to show your history. It's just going to
keep an eye out for you. This is how I want my history. so this is what I've
made it do. even if I have to change things. OK. Cool!
So that's that! Now let's switch gears altogether! Still talking about
source control and GitHub but a little bit more peripheral. Let's go over to GitHub and have a
look at the Unreal course organization. Now this is an
organization that contains two people. me and Sam. both of the people working on this.
and there's a few things about it. Firstly. I want this to be public. Now
you've got to decide. do you want your game code to be public? You might not. but if you do.
with these tutorial projects. why not? Why not get yourself out there. the more you can be out there the better!
Then. present it nicely! So if I look. firstly. at the
Settings of the repo. what have we got here? Well I've bothered to put in a description.
I've bothered to put in a URL. including a discount
code. Why not? If somebody's going to click this URL. why not give them a discount. give them an opportunity to buy
straight away. We don't make a lot of money through that discount code but it's still an option. And then. other
details in here like e-mails. etc. OK. so do
that! Setup some sort of profile picture. because this is the face
of your repo. at the top here. Then. each of the Repositories. let's have
a look at BattleTank! BattleTank. when you hit it. has a README.md.
md stands for markdown. And if you look at "daring fireball
markdown". it'll give you the syntax of markdown here.
It's a very cleaver system. introduced by a blogger.
to write HTML without having to mess around with
actually writing all the HTML tags. So this is one place you can find it. and all
the information is down here. as to how you write it. We'll be doing some in a minute! And the other place you could look is.
you could look at "unreal answers markdown".
and they'll give you a cheatsheet on markdown as well. because another place you can
use markdown is on the Unreal UE4 AnswerHub. And it shows you like.
on double underlines give you a heading 1. etc. So why am I mentioning all of this? Because I want
you to present things nicely. with the Battle Tank here. because I've bothered to put all
this stuff here. I've even got a Lecture List in there. Why have I got a Lecture List?
Well the reason I've put the full Lecture List in here is. in order to get
some sort of. what I would call. Google juice. [Laughs] What I mean by that is. if somebody
is searching for one of these things. then. especially
if it's something a little bit unusual. like one of Unreal's commands or
something like that. then we will probably come up on Google.
Let's try it! Let's do a Google search for Using SpawnActor to Spawn! Because
what GitHub has given us here. in this repo. is a public webpage.
provided you want it public. then I don't know. I've never even tried
this. Let's try it! Using Spawn Actor to Spawn. If we scroll down. there's a load of Unreal
docs. but I suspect we don't need to go too many pages through Google.
before we hit our repo. Maybe
I've missed it. or maybe it's not referenced yet?
OK. so let's try another one! As an example. let's go back up and try...
I don't know. here Creating Default SubOb. the C++ Compilation Process.
No. that's too common. So when you're looking for people to find your stuff.
the C++ Compilation Process. I can't hope to compete on that
keyword on the Internet. but some of the less
common things I'm much more likely to be able to compete for.
So Delegating to Components. Using virtual and
override. Let's just try that. do a search for that. "unreal".
see if we get our repo. I'm doing this live. because I'm hoping that our
repo will come up in the first couple of pages for one of these. It certainly came up for one of the things I
tested recently. Now there's a GitHub repo coming up there. someone else's OSVR
on the VR headset. OK. well I'm not getting them coming up right now. But the
point is. it depends how long it's been on GitHub and it depends on
how competed that term is and a whole load of other stuff. but you're giving yourself
the greatest chance of this coming up on Google. Let's try something that will
come up like this. because it's a ridiculously uncommon search query
and you'll get the idea. The others are filtering their way up. Here you go! GitHub -
UnrealCourse: An open-world head-to-head. Now. if I open that as an incognito window. which I
always suggest you do when you're looking at websites. you can see what it looks like to the public. and you
can see straight away that somebody looking for that will find that. They'll probably. if they're tech savvy. do an in
page search. and with a bit of thinking. they'll realize that this is one of the videos of
this course. OK enough said on that! It's a little bit about search engine marketing and just trying to
get everything you can out there. get as many handles to your work as you can. Now what I want
to do is. I'm just going to quickly setup the README for this
section. or at least I'm going to look at the README.md and I'm going to edit
it. Which you can just click on the README.md. and if you don't have a README.md.
like TestingGrounds. you can create one down here. Add Readme. And that's
going to be your challenge! So you can hang on a second. I just want to show you a little bit about the markdown
format. and then. I'll challenge you to decorate and share your README.
Notice that this. which is the markdown on the left here. looks very different
to the repo once it's been
processed on the right. It's the same stuff but you see how links work. square brackets here?
It turns out like that. and in the normal braces or parentheses you put
the URL. You can see how I've got double hash.
because I don't want too big a title. which is my level 2 heading which is
coming out there. You can see that. in this instance. I forgot to put a star
against my BT01 so that's inconsistent there. and I could edit it right here on
the website. And then. the rest of these stars make an unordered list.
etc. So you can read about the markdown format. that is all in your
documentation. You can edit and add and edit your README file
right on GitHub. by saying Add Readme. You can say that you're just doing that. Commit the
changes. and then. go ahead and get the URL for your repo. like
this like the BattleTank one. it'll look something like this.
and share it with us over on the community site. Now. when you do that.
use the link in resources. because that'll take you to just the right place on the community site. Rather than
browsing through like I am. go to Resources on Udemy. and then. you will end up
inside Testing Grounds. inside this video which doesn't even exist yet. You can create a
discussion. Now interestingly. markdown also works in here. [a link].
And then if I go open brackets (www.test
.com). You see how it's looking on the right-hand side? "Here is"
and then. I can go back tick
" 'some code' ". and then.
it formats it like code. "A list" and then you can go "1.
First". "1. Second". and now notice that we can keep going
"1.". and I suggest you do. because then it doesn't put you under the illusion these
numbers have anything to do with the actual numbering. these are numbered in sequence. If you use 1.
all the time. it allows you to reorder things like that. You see how I moved third.
in between first and second on the left? Because I'm using 1.. i.e. any number and a
dot. then the numbering still works. So I'd suggest you use 1's. as a useful tip for you.
Star star for bold. star italic.
and they're the main things you're going to need. The link format like that.
code formatting. italics. etc. Headers. some big header. it's worth just using
underlines. or I prefer just using the hashes. "Big header".
"Small header".
OK you get it. so markdown is super useful! It's useful in
UE4 AnswerHub. it's useful in the GameDev.tv community
site. it's very useful on GitHub. Make your stuff pretty.
show off what you've got to offer. get yourself out there. make yourself findable.
ask for feedback really early. and you'll do much better.
So your challenge is to decorate and share your repo! Use organizations
and teams in GitHub if you need to or want to. Add a README.md
file and use MarkDown to format it nicely. Check the
visibility in a anonymous browser. like I just did. and note. of course.
all this assumes you're OK with your work being public. And then. share the link.
share using the link in the Resources in the community side. and ask everybody for
feedback. And also think. how else can you get feedback about your game? Where else could you go. Twitter.
Facebook. etc.? Get feedback on your code. get feedback on everything.
it's fantastic! I love the feedback that you guys give me. and I really encourage you to start getting
feedback on your projects as early and as often as possible. Fail regularly
and you'll get better! That's how kids learn to walk. remember? You know. if you saw two
small kids. neither of which could walk. but one. you said to the
parent. how many times has that kid fallen over trying to walk? And they say. oh 50.
and the other said. oh he's only fallen over once. this is his first attempt. Well which kid's going to walk first?
Well it's going to be the kid that's fallen over 50 times! Paradoxically.
that's the only way to learn to walk and it's the only way to learn to market and it's the
only way to learn to code! So please. fail fast. fail regularly. have fun.
share with us. and I'll see you in the next video!
=======
So just before we get into the markdown and a little bit of a speech on marketing,
let's just sort out a couple more things with regards to this source control. When I
opened up my Unreal, I've noticed it's spawned both Oculus and
SteamVR for me. This happened in the last section. So I'm going to prevent that
by going to Settings and Plugins, Virtual Reality, then I'm
just going to turn off Oculus, for now. If we add any support
for this stuff later, then I will turn it back on, but I'm going to turn all these off, for now, including Gear
VR, and then, I am going to restart the Editor
and let's watch what happens over in the source control. Already, there are some changes to the
.uproject, and what's happened in the .uproject file, if I just tab
back to it, is it's put some plain text in here, just
saying that all of these VR platforms are disabled, false. OK,
that's cool! So we could commit that change, but let's just do a couple of things! Firstly, I'm just
going to close down the Editor again, and I'm going to close the
VR apps, Oculus and Steam VR, and just make
sure that they do actually not spawn next time. So
both are asking me to confirm to close them. Now, let's reopen the .uproject,
and hopefully that change to this
.uproject file here will result in neither of the
VR apps opening. And it does! So now, let's test
if this Source Control, Submit to Source Control actually works,
when it comes to the very .uproject file itself. I want to explore the limitations
of this thing, so we Submit to Source Control, and it says "No assets to check in!"
so it's not infallible. It would work if we say move that block up in the
air to make a floating block. If I now say, Submit to Source
Control... I better Save All first, because that's the most
reliable way for us to be sure that, when we click Submit to Source
Control that, it actually does recognize there's a change to the map, then I
would be able to commit. But if you just make a change to something like the project settings, it
may not recognize it. So I am going to do the first commit from inside Unreal
here, and actually, I think what I'm going to call it is the very name of
this video, which is called Marketing & Markdown. So the way that I
name my videos is, I prefix them with TG for Testing Grounds,
and then, I have a .cmproj on the end, because it's a Camtasia project. So I'm going to
use this as a template, and this video is going to be called TG4,
Testing Grounds video 4, and then, the name of it will be
Marketing & Markdown, there you go .cmproj.
Now, let's just let it do that! "Checking file(s) into Source Control". I'm going to
close Unreal and have a look over here and see what's happening.
Let's just do a Refresh!
And you can see that it has committed TG4 Marketing & Markdown,
but Unreal has still not got this .uproject
information here. It just didn't notice that these things changed, so as I said, it's
not infallible, when it comes to project settings, so there's a limitation. Now, say you have
this and you think, actually, I don't want this commit without these changes to this
.uproject in it. What would you do about that? Well what you could do is you could Reset that
Master Branch back here. So you'll right-click back on where I was
at the end of the previous video and you say Mixed is fine. It's going to "keep
the working copy but reset index", which means it'll move this
master tab down here, and then, all of those changes will be in our Uncommitted changes,
and just lumped together, the changes to the .uproject file and the changes to the map
that I made, remember when I made that cube float. Now I could commit from
SourceTree, with the same naming convention as before. I need to Stage
everything and Commit. Let's just go in here and say
Marketing & Markdown.
I'm just going to use exactly the same name as I used in the slides,
just for consistency. Yep, that's an ampersand!
And I'm going to push it immediately to GitHub, once I've Staged All the files.
So I've covered a couple of different things there, pretty much as an aside, but
it's more about the source control. If you've made a mistake on a very recent commit,
especially before you've pushed it up to the web, you can reset
your branch back to a previous commit and you can lump together a
couple of different commits, in that very simple way. There is another way of doing this, it's a
command called squash with git, but we don't need to go into that right now. The other thing that
we've noticed here is that Unreal doesn't necessarily notice a change to all files.
The meta files like the .uproject files and some of the Editor settings
and stuff, it may not notice they've changed, OK. So it's going to be really good at noticing
most of our changes to our assets, and it's going to allow us to commit from inside
Unreal, without having to exit it, by using that
to Source Control button but it's not infallible. So what I've done is, I've come out of Unreal and
done it the way I want it in Source Tree. Remember that source control,
in general, is a useless master
but a very good slave. That's the right saying. So by that I mean, you don't let it tell
you how you want things to be, you tell it how you want it to show your history. It's just going to
keep an eye out for you. This is how I want my history, so this is what I've
made it do, even if I have to change things, OK. Cool!
So that's that! Now let's switch gears altogether! Still talking about
source control and GitHub but a little bit more peripheral. Let's go over to GitHub and have a
look at the Unreal course organization. Now this is an
organization that contains two people, me and Sam, both of the people working on this,
and there's a few things about it. Firstly, I want this to be public. Now
you've got to decide, do you want your game code to be public? You might not, but if you do,
with these tutorial projects, why not? Why not get yourself out there, the more you can be out there the better!
Then, present it nicely! So if I look, firstly, at the
Settings of the repo, what have we got here? Well I've bothered to put in a description.
I've bothered to put in a URL, including a discount
code. Why not? If somebody's going to click this URL, why not give them a discount, give them an opportunity to buy
straight away. We don't make a lot of money through that discount code but it's still an option. And then, other
details in here like e-mails, etc. OK, so do
that! Setup some sort of profile picture, because this is the face
of your repo, at the top here. Then, each of the Repositories, let's have
a look at BattleTank! BattleTank, when you hit it, has a README.md,
md stands for markdown. And if you look at "daring fireball
markdown", it'll give you the syntax of markdown here.
It's a very cleaver system, introduced by a blogger,
to write HTML without having to mess around with
actually writing all the HTML tags. So this is one place you can find it, and all
the information is down here, as to how you write it. We'll be doing some in a minute! And the other place you could look is,
you could look at "unreal answers markdown",
and they'll give you a cheatsheet on markdown as well, because another place you can
use markdown is on the Unreal UE4 AnswerHub. And it shows you like,
on double underlines give you a heading 1, etc. So why am I mentioning all of this? Because I want
you to present things nicely, with the Battle Tank here, because I've bothered to put all
this stuff here. I've even got a Lecture List in there. Why have I got a Lecture List?
Well the reason I've put the full Lecture List in here is, in order to get
some sort of, what I would call, Google juice. [Laughs] What I mean by that is, if somebody
is searching for one of these things, then, especially
if it's something a little bit unusual, like one of Unreal's commands or
something like that, then we will probably come up on Google.
Let's try it! Let's do a Google search for Using SpawnActor to Spawn! Because
what GitHub has given us here, in this repo, is a public webpage,
provided you want it public, then I don't know. I've never even tried
this. Let's try it! Using Spawn Actor to Spawn. If we scroll down, there's a load of Unreal
docs, but I suspect we don't need to go too many pages through Google,
before we hit our repo. Maybe
I've missed it, or maybe it's not referenced yet?
OK, so let's try another one! As an example, let's go back up and try...
I don't know, here Creating Default SubOb, the C++ Compilation Process.
No, that's too common. So when you're looking for people to find your stuff,
the C++ Compilation Process, I can't hope to compete on that
keyword on the Internet, but some of the less
common things I'm much more likely to be able to compete for.
So Delegating to Components, Using virtual and
override. Let's just try that, do a search for that, "unreal",
see if we get our repo. I'm doing this live, because I'm hoping that our
repo will come up in the first couple of pages for one of these. It certainly came up for one of the things I
tested recently. Now there's a GitHub repo coming up there, someone else's OSVR
on the VR headset. OK, well I'm not getting them coming up right now. But the
point is, it depends how long it's been on GitHub and it depends on
how competed that term is and a whole load of other stuff, but you're giving yourself
the greatest chance of this coming up on Google. Let's try something that will
come up like this, because it's a ridiculously uncommon search query
and you'll get the idea. The others are filtering their way up. Here you go! GitHub -
UnrealCourse: An open-world head-to-head. Now, if I open that as an incognito window, which I
always suggest you do when you're looking at websites, you can see what it looks like to the public, and you
can see straight away that somebody looking for that will find that. They'll probably, if they're tech savvy, do an in
page search, and with a bit of thinking, they'll realize that this is one of the videos of
this course. OK enough said on that! It's a little bit about search engine marketing and just trying to
get everything you can out there, get as many handles to your work as you can. Now what I want
to do is, I'm just going to quickly setup the README for this
section, or at least I'm going to look at the README.md and I'm going to edit
it. Which you can just click on the README.md, and if you don't have a README.md,
like TestingGrounds, you can create one down here, Add Readme. And that's
going to be your challenge! So you can hang on a second, I just want to show you a little bit about the markdown
format, and then, I'll challenge you to decorate and share your README.
Notice that this, which is the markdown on the left here, looks very different
to the repo once it's been
processed on the right. It's the same stuff but you see how links work, square brackets here?
It turns out like that, and in the normal braces or parentheses you put
the URL. You can see how I've got double hash,
because I don't want too big a title, which is my level 2 heading which is
coming out there. You can see that, in this instance, I forgot to put a star
against my BT01 so that's inconsistent there, and I could edit it right here on
the website. And then, the rest of these stars make an unordered list,
etc. So you can read about the markdown format, that is all in your
documentation. You can edit and add and edit your README file
right on GitHub, by saying Add Readme. You can say that you're just doing that, Commit the
changes, and then, go ahead and get the URL for your repo, like
this like the BattleTank one, it'll look something like this,
and share it with us over on the community site. Now, when you do that,
use the link in resources, because that'll take you to just the right place on the community site. Rather than
browsing through like I am, go to Resources on Udemy, and then, you will end up
inside Testing Grounds, inside this video which doesn't even exist yet. You can create a
discussion. Now interestingly, markdown also works in here, [a link].
And then if I go open brackets (www.test
.com). You see how it's looking on the right-hand side? "Here is"
and then, I can go back tick
" 'some code' ", and then,
it formats it like code. "A list" and then you can go "1.
First", "1. Second", and now notice that we can keep going
"1.", and I suggest you do, because then it doesn't put you under the illusion these
numbers have anything to do with the actual numbering, these are numbered in sequence. If you use 1.
all the time, it allows you to reorder things like that. You see how I moved third,
in between first and second on the left? Because I'm using 1., i.e. any number and a
dot, then the numbering still works. So I'd suggest you use 1's, as a useful tip for you.
Star star for bold, star italic,
and they're the main things you're going to need. The link format like that,
code formatting, italics, etc. Headers, some big header, it's worth just using
underlines, or I prefer just using the hashes, "Big header",
"Small header".
OK you get it, so markdown is super useful! It's useful in
UE4 AnswerHub, it's useful in the GameDev.tv community
site, it's very useful on GitHub. Make your stuff pretty,
show off what you've got to offer, get yourself out there, make yourself findable,
ask for feedback really early, and you'll do much better.
So your challenge is to decorate and share your repo! Use organizations
and teams in GitHub if you need to or want to. Add a README.md
file and use MarkDown to format it nicely. Check the
visibility in a anonymous browser, like I just did, and note, of course,
all this assumes you're OK with your work being public. And then, share the link,
share using the link in the Resources in the community side, and ask everybody for
feedback. And also think, how else can you get feedback about your game? Where else could you go, Twitter,
Facebook, etc.? Get feedback on your code, get feedback on everything,
it's fantastic! I love the feedback that you guys give me, and I really encourage you to start getting
feedback on your projects as early and as often as possible. Fail regularly
and you'll get better! That's how kids learn to walk, remember? You know, if you saw two
small kids, neither of which could walk, but one, you said to the
parent, how many times has that kid fallen over trying to walk? And they say, oh 50,
and the other said, oh he's only fallen over once, this is his first attempt. Well which kid's going to walk first?
Well it's going to be the kid that's fallen over 50 times! Paradoxically,
that's the only way to learn to walk and it's the only way to learn to market and it's the
only way to learn to code! So please, fail fast, fail regularly, have fun,
share with us, and I'll see you in the next video!
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1:Unreal/Section5/TG4 Markdown & Marketing.srt