Hi! In this video I'm going to
be showing you how to use git clean. a very useful command. to revert your project. This will
tear away your derived files for you. without you having to manually delete things
like build and Intermediate and Binaries. all these sort of things here. And
it will also allow me to take an opportunity to show you what we're doing
over the upcoming lectures. in terms of AI agents. etc. So final
video on Git. before we dive into the project. Let's take a look!
So at the end of the last video. I challenge you to make yourself a README.md.
Here's mine here. and that will push up to GitHub. next time
I do a push and make the website look prettier. So because I've done that. I have an
uncommitted change sitting here in my repository. as we would expect.
OK that's great! Now. I want to show you
a little trick. firstly. called stashing. So imagine you've made a little change
like this but you don't want it for now. You want to get rid of it but not
lose it forever. so you want to go back to this previous commit state.
If you're just making a single change. like this. and you just say ah hang on. I want to go back
to where I was. you can do something called stashing.
So what you do is you stage your file and hit Stash. Now what that does. let me just say
"created readme". This doesn't actually put it in the history. it puts it
on the side. to the side of the history. So what I've got here is. on
master I created readme. and there's the details. but the master branch has
now gone back to the previous commit. I'm now back in exactly the state you were.
before I fiddled between videos and wrote my own readme file. Of course. you didn't want to watch me
do that. But having it on the Stash does mean I can get back to it later. so we'll
explore that in a bit. Let's just leave that on the side and start from here. which is where you are. Now.
something else I've been doing between videos. If we go to all branches you can
see that I left you here in Marketing & Markdown.
and since then. I've been busy doing a lot of prototyping. all these commits
are prototypes. And by the way. when you write a commit message. you can actually
put additional information under the initial commit message.
like this: Add 3rd person AI to scene. and then. you can put a space and then you can put
other information. OK. so that's some useful stuff about commits. So I've done some
prototyping. Now what I want to do is I want to show you one of these prototype
states. Let's have a look at Get perception reporting
working. So if I go Checkout. it's going to say "create a
detached HEAD". Let's look at what that means! I'll let it do it. it'll take a second because it's got
a lot of stuff in Git LFS. and we're going to end up
with the HEAD. Now. the HEAD is the indicator of your
current disk state. so the disk state is now at
Get perception reporting working. and the branch. there is no
branch. we're not on a branch. It kind of looks like we're on the prototype branch. but we're not
anywhere yet until we create a new branch. Anyway. what I've done is reset
my disk state to here. but you know that we have a load of
ignored files. so I don't know that my project is in exactly the
state it was when I made that commit. and I may get errors. because the Binaries. the
Intermediate. etc. are different. potentially different.
to when I committed because they're ignored. remember. So I want to introduce you to a
new git command. which is the core focus of this video. If you want to switch to a
different state in Git with Unreal. here's a very handy thing to do. it's called
git clean. Now let's just go git clean -h. You can also look on the
web for much more detailed documentation. I've put the link in the resources.
And the command line parameters that I want to bring your attention to
are -d. because this allows us to clear directories
even if they're empty. So if some of these were empty. like maybe Binaries.
Well it isn't as it happens. but if any of these were empty. that -d will allow us to
remove them; -x. which means that we're cleaning things that
are ignored. This is the thing that's going to make sure that. when we change our
repository state. we aren't effecting the
ignored files. but we want to clear them out and let Unreal create those ignored
derived files and we're going to use interactive mode just for safety. So we're
going to use the command line options with x. d. and i. it doesn't really matter which order. So let's
have a look at it! I'll go ahead and do that now. git clean -x
-d -i. Look what it does! It said I would be removing this lot.
had you not used -i for interactive. I say 1 or c
to clean and it goes ahead and does it. Let's look at the disk! Much better!
Now we're back as if we'd have done our manual clearing out of derived files. but
we. instead of doing it manually we've used this command. git
clean -x -d -i. Now the very advanced among you may want to use
something called a Git Hook. which you can then use
automation to do this. but I wouldn't bother for now. let's get used to it at this level.
OK. so now if I open my project at this state. I want to show you where we're going
over the coming lectures. because this is a part of my prototyping.
Before I started laying down the terrain... I haven't fully prototyped this project. by the way. I've
only just cracked the back of a couple of the most important things.
So I'm unpacking the project now. from the Git commit.
and it's having to recreate all the derived files. because we're choosing not to
store derived files in the repo. Remember the .gitignore automatically
was created by Unreal for us. in this case. and it ignores a whole
bunch of stuff. all this stuff here. OK. so we're needing to
recreate that. That's what's happening now. If you don't do this git clean. you can get a disparity
between what's in all your derived files and your non-derived. and your project's in
some strange undefined state. So here we go! Let's just take a look at
how this is laid out! What I've got is I've got a couple of AI characters placed in
here. one's read and one's blue. and then. I've also got .in
this world point. some TargetPoints. One up there. one there. one there.
one there. one there... Oh no. that's it! So there's 1. 2. 3.
and then. one in this corner down here. And then. each of these TargetPoints has a
wait time on it. Most of them are 2 seconds. but the one up here I'm pretending is like
a coffee machine and has a 5 second wait time. What I mean by a coffee machine
or water filter. whatever they call it in an office. It's what they call a water cooler moment!
That's it! Well the idea is that these characters are going to move
between these waypoints. waiting for the specified amount of time.
but they're going to wait a little bit longer up here. on this one that I'm firing these
fetching yellow balls at. And the idea is that eventually you'll end up with a water cooler moment
and they'll both end up in the same place. We may. if we have time in the final game.
once we're outdoors and everything else and got all the important stuff done. we may
organize it that they have a chat with each other or something like that. OK. so basically
what we'll be doing over the upcoming videos is using perception. Look at the top-left of the screen.
When one of these characters sees me or sees each other. they're reporting who they are
and who they've seen. and then. they are patrolling automatically using
pathfinding. between these different points. and that is basically the scope of
what we're trying to do. If you have a look here. you can see your Navigation
mesh will be on here. the green mesh. and it includes the upper surfaces
up here. OK cool! So that's all very well! I've given you a preview. now
what I want you to do is I want you to have a go at getting comfortable. Excuse the
pun. that's a terrible terrible joke there. So make some changes to your project.
For example. move a cube. add a class. whatever. Close Unreal
and then commit using SourceTree. Don't use Unreal's commit tool. in this
case. because it just confuses things. Let's use SourceTree just to make sure everything is committed.
because remember. new things. new files may not get committed by
Unreal's tools. So just to save confusion use SourceTree this time. close
Unreal. use SourceTree. Reset master to your previous commit.
run the git clean. and then. open your project and check all that stuff that you
changed as truly reverted. And this will give you the confidence to go ahead and
experiment with your project. knowing that you can very easily go back to a previous
committed state. It's a very important exercise. just have a go at it!Work until you
get it done. and I will see you in a minute! Oh. and by the way. if you're struggling with Git
LFS. for any particular reason. you can actually get a lot more information
about what it can do by coming to the terminal. which I hit here in SourceTree
and typing git lfs - help. And it'll give you lots of commands that may help
you get it running. if you're having issues. OK. go ahead. pause the video. and do that exercise
now!
OK great news! So
the thing is that I'm just going to close Unreal. I'm going to
show only the current branch... Actually. now I'll show all of the branches. so you know where we are. So we are
here. in this detached weird HEAD state. Where I want to be is just on the master
branch. So I can either right-click master on the left there and say check out master.
or I could right click here. or I could go to the Terminal and just say git
checkout master. We do have to be able to
use a Terminal as well. because sometimes there's things you can only
do there. Back in SourceTree. you may need to go View and Refresh for it to catch up
with what you did on the Terminal. and if I hide the other
branches. just show the master branch. you'll see we're back to exactly where we are. One more thing to do.
which is to come over to the Terminal. because remember that your derived
files now. in this folder. are generated for that scene I showed you with
those red and blue guys running around but we don't want that. And the safest and easiest
way to fix that is to go git clean -x -d
-i. Check that it all looks right and click 1 or c.
and now we're removed and you can reopen your project. rebuild.
and you're in a good state. So while that rebuilds.
we should see no new files come into the source control. because everything it's
building should be ignored. and that's a good sign. if we don't see any changes here.
because these are just being pushed into these directories. the Intermediate
directories. etc. Alright. one final thing to do. just to complete this lecture.
is one. I'm going to make sure that this project does indeed open with no problems.
and we're back to exactly where we were at the end of the last lecture. Yep. looks good. no
funny AI agents running around. so I'm going to close Unreal. The other
thing to do is. remember I talked about stashing? Well now I want to actually
commit something for this lecture and I want to put a readme on. So I can right-click on this
stash and Apply Stash On master.
OK let's see what it does! So it's going to do that. it should be quick because it's just a text
file. And we have a single uncommitted change. there's the readme.
That's great! So now I can just commit that as TG5.
and the name of this lecture. which is Use
git clean to Revert Project.
OK great. I'm going to Commit that! I've not pushed it
to the Internet. What does this 1 ahead mean? This means that the
remote repository. if I was to Show Remote Branches now. is behind. so I
haven't pushed it to GitHub on the web yet. I very much suggest that you do Push.
because by pushing. you're backing up your project state. And if you're ever
having another branch or prototyping. please either push that to the web as a backup
or make sure you've got some other backup on your system like Backblaze. which is what I
use which gives you the ability to recover from dodgy situations.
I accidentally. between videos. deleted the project
from here. from this EPIC Games Launcher screen. I deleted here like that. don't
do it. and that caused all sorts of problems. which meant I had to go and get the files
from Backblaze. So please have at least two different forms of backup. source
control alone is not necessarily backup. you can still get yourself in trouble if you forget to
push or you include the wrong files. Have about at least another system. I would suggest
a third system like a local hard disk backup. as well. So
the pep talk on backup's over. thank you very much for watching the video. and I will see
you in the next one. where we'll actually crack on and get this project going!