OK and welcome to the First Person
Character Overview! Notice I've changed engine versions or I will be during this video to
4.13.0, that's why it's in yellow at the top-right. And I will see you in there! Let's go and take a look!
So let's dive in and start this great project that's going to be
really using Unreal for what it was built to create, a first person shooter. So we'll
be swimming down stream, rather than up stream now. So 4.13.0
just shipped at the time of recording. You can use 4.13 anything. I'm going to
go ahead and upgrade the project now, so I'm going to open my
4.13 from here, I'm going to make sure that I have a commit, recently
with no uncommitted changes, which I do in my source control in case anything goes wrong.
I'm going to open the 4.12 version of TestingGrounds, and I'm actually
going to use, as we did before, Convert in-place here
and that will actually overwrite the existing project. It's not a problem,
because it's all under source control. If we look at the source control, while it does the
upgrade, you'll see that the main thing it actually does is just write an engine association
line into the .uproject file. It may make some other
changes but that's usually all it does. So once the project's open,
I will be tagging this commit, as well,
to say that I've changed versions. That's just a convenient way of indicating
when I changed versions, but I probably won't do that until I actually commit at the end
of this video. So there you go, we're up and running in 4.13.0.
Now, of course, it's .0, so that means things are going to go wrong! [Laughs]
We'll just live with that, for now, and as the project goes on I will upgrade through the
versions. But it will be the same for you, whatever version of 4.13 you're using.
You could do this in a more recent version than 4.13, you could use 4.14 or
whatever, but I would say that, in order to be seeing exactly
what I'm doing in the videos, it's easier if you just go Add Versions, pick 4.13 from the list.
It's not there yet, of course, because it's the current version, and use 4.13 point
something. Okey dokey, so that's open! Let's start
then the project, by saying what have we got? What have
we got here in this world, at the moment? So there's a lot of stuff going on for us,
and I just want to have a look at the world outliner and just see what
they've already put in here. They put some ArenaGeometry! If I zoom out a little bit like this,
there's a lot of walls, and these are all static mesh actors, you can see that from
the right-hand column, so they are literally just boxes. And then, it's also got in here
some Cubes, which they've put in, and they've got some physics on, as you can
see. So that's the ArenaGeometry! We then have
some lighting. There's a Light Source there of some type, we can look
over here and find out what properties it has, so you can see
what default Light Source you have there. We have a LightmassImportanceVolume covering the
entire play space, that tells the lighting system where to focus its efforts.
We have a Post Processing Volume here, which is
allowing us to do visual effects post processing. We'll leave all this in, I'm just showing you what
we've got. We have a SkyLight, so that's it under Lighting. There's some
RenderFX, there's a little bit of AtmosphericFog, and a SphereReflection
Capture. Now, all of these things are here just to improve the
visual fidelity of the game, OK. We don't need to worry about them, we're going to leave
them as they are for now. We'll start exploring these types of components, as we need them, as we go through the
project. Right, now there's a FirstPersonCharacter on here, as well. Now
that FirstPersonCharacter, if I edit the blueprint and go to the full
Blueprint Editor, there's actually a fair amount to this guy and I'm just going to overview it, at the moment.
If we have a look in the Viewport, we have a capsule collider there.
So you'll see what's happening with this first person character is, it just has arms
and a gun. Now the gun is pointing off in a weird direction, right now, and that's because it's controlled by
animation and by code. And you'll see there's a camera, roughly where his face would be,
and then, a capsule collider. There's a FirstPersonCameraComponent
here, and you can see that that has childed to it a
mesh, which are the arms. And this time
that mesh is a different type of mesh, and you can see it here, it is a Skeletal
Mesh. We'll be talking about Skeletal Meshes a lot later in the section, but Skeletal
Meshes vary from Static Meshes, because each of the vertices on
this mesh, each of the little dots are connected, behind the scenes, to a bone
that tells you how all the bones are laid out. And Skeletal Meshes
can actually deform and change their shape at runtime,
based on things called Vertex Weightings. We'll look at all that later on, this is just an overview.
You also have a Gun, which they've got as a separate mesh and a MuzzleLocation,
which is looking like it's in a slightly odd place there, but we'll leave it with it.
Let's check that the bullets actually fire properly, because that does look like a
strange place. By the way, these tabs, remember whenever you start a new project, you need to go to your
Editor settings , Appearance, Asset Editor Open Location,
and I want the Main Window. That means when I open up new tabs, they end up docked
like this. For me that's my preference. So
i just want to make sure that the bullets are actually coming out of the gun in a sensible place.
They are, so this obviously means that, at runtime, this gun
moved and possibly even this MuzzleLocation all moved
programmatically. And then, we have a CharacterMovement component, that has a load
of stuff on it! Look at all the different parameters that you can change on that,
and this is going to be doing a lot of work for us! Now, we're going to allow ourselves to let Unreal
give us this big leg up, and we're in a situation here where we have a
prebuilt character. Now look carefully, you see the character's breathing? You see how
the gun and the hands are moving? There's a lot of stuff going on here!
We can run around, we could put some steps in. In fact, let's put some steps
in, right now! That can be your challenge just for this first
video, is just to look around as I just have done in this scene, and
also we're going to put a set of spiraled stairs in here, just on the
side of the block. See if you can do that, right now! Go ahead, pause the video, no
challenge slide for you, and just put a staircase in here.
If you need a hint as to where you get that from, then
you can go into Modes,
Geometry, and then you have Curved Stair or Spiral Stair.
So I'm just going to go
to Modes, Geometry, grab a Curved Stair, I'm going to rotate it around
by, in this case, 90 degrees, by the looks of it.
Translate it, remember your keys, W,
E, R, etc. on your keyboard, a nice and easy way of switching between the tools.
Remember that the End key will snap things to the floor, and the one way you can change this
is to change the Step Height in the parameters here to maybe 30. And then,
there we have a BSP staircase, Binary
Spaced Partitoning is a way of storing this type of geometry. If we look in the
World Outliner you can see that we have a BSP brush. I actually have two
stairs, so I'm just going to get rid of the extra one. There you go!
Alright, so now let's just see what the character does when we encounters a slope
like this! He just pops up the stairs! Great! And he can jump
and lots of features! So have a look around, see what's already in this World Outliner,
make sure you're happy with how it works. Remember to
use, when you are adjusting geometry, things like the snapping settings up here,
you've got grid snapping for angles and for translation,
and just get yourself familiar with exactly what's in this environment. And
then, in the next video we are going to put in some third person
agents and give them the ability to navigate around this world. I just popped that Cube
back on the ground with the End key, and there you go, we're in a great starting position
for the project pair of stairs and we are ready to start this patrolling
behavior. See you in the next video!