So welcome to The
Third Person Character! In this video we will be adding a Third Person Character
to our scene! There he is, standing on the ground, breathing away, and the other thing
we'll be doing is adding this green Navmesh and making sure that it's nice and smooth up the stairs. So I will see you in there!
So in the last video I said I would Tag my Commit. Let me show you what that is! Here's the
commit for the last video. If you click on Tag here, you can either
Tag the branch, basically, or a specific commit. I'm going to go
ahead and Tag this specific commit, and I'm just going to Tag
it with version 4.13.0
like that. And then, or just 4.13.0.
There you go! And what that does is it just puts that tag one, and as
the master label heads up the tree, this 4.13.0
will stay there, and it's just a really quick and easy way for me to see in which video I upgraded
my version. Not a bad thing to do to keep track of where you upgraded your versions. OK
so let's go back over to Unreal and let's just take a look at what we need to do
next! Of course, what we're going to need to make this even remotely interesting, just move that
out, is a Third Person Character in here that's going to be running around and
is going to act as a guard, and we're going to be focusing on creating patrol routes for those
guards. So where do we get a third person character from? Well there's no point in us building these up
from the ground. What I'd rather do with the First Person and the Third Person
is to use what Unreal already gave us, like this FirstPerson character
here, and then, start breaking it down as we need to, because frankly it already
works. It would be weeks of work to produce this thing from scratch, and we will learn
what all these parameters mean. Now, in the previous video I talked
about parameters, but a quiz question is coming up. There's going to be a question about
how to change the CharacterMovement speed. So just be aware it's under CharacterMovement,
and then, you've got in here, you've got the idea of Maximum Walking Speed,
when you're crouched and standing and things like that. OK, so let's go ahead and get
the Third Person in! How do you do that? Well, what we come
to is the Content Browser, Add New, and then, Add Feature or Content
Pack. Then, let's click over to C++ feature, and we can actually
bring in the necessary stuff from the Third Person
Demo project. So you'll see it's a slightly different world! We started off with a
First Person as our template, because we are fundamentally making a Third Person game. But we
can bring in the assets from the Third Person project, too, so that's
Add New, C++ Feature, and then Third Person. Let's go ahead and do that!
And it's going to add a whole lot of stuff to our project! You can watch what's happening
in version control, by hitting F5, letting it refresh,
and you'll see that it's adding quite a lot of stuff in here. It's making changes to the
engine, n.e. telling it that it's got these things included, and then, it's adding a lot
of stuff meshes, textures, materials, and animations, which we'll be talking
about plenty, later in the section. So
"Added source file". "Would you like to edit the code now?" No I don't need to edit the code right now,
and here we go! If we look more carefully at the Content Browser now,
you'll see that we've got quite a few directories. We've got FirstPerson, FirstPerson
CPP, Mannequin, ThirdPerson, ThirdPersonCPP. Now,
don't just  go moving stuff around yet and reorganizing this, because it can actually
break it due to references. We will move things around
and tidy up this Hierarchy as we need to, but for now, let's just allow
ourselves to have this slightly messy content hierarchy.
And later on, I will talk about things called redirectors, which you can actually
show here in the Filters menu. We
need to be showing the redirectors, before we start moving things around, and we'll
get to that when we need to. But if you do feel the absolute urge to move things
around, then turn Show Redirectors on now, and you'll see that
there are some complications with moving files around, it doesn't just move them. As I said,
we'll get to that when we need to get to that. For now, let's go into ThirdPersonCPP,
Blueprints, and ThirdPersonCharacter. Let's just drop one in the scene, and I'll snap
to the floor. There he is! So I'm going to play the game, go find him, and have a look at him.
Where is he? What's he doing? Well he is just kind of standing there doing
something a bit strange! [Laughs] What is this ThirdPerson character and
what on Earth is he doing in our game? Well let's firstly go and have a look at him!
And there he is, there's the instance of the ThirdPersonCharacter, sitting here in our map.
If we edit the ThirdPersonCharacter and go to the Full Blueprint Editor,
we'll get a very similar thing to the FirstPersonCharacter. In fact, if I flick between them for a moment,
you can see that they're very very similar but there are some differences. So
here is the ThirdPersonCharacter, and he has a Skeletal
Mesh, one of these meshes that can actually move and deform. And he has a default
kind of breathing idle animation that he has here. The camera with a Third
Person is behind him. We don't actually need that camera, there's no harm in leaving the camera there, for the moment.
The game, if you play it, will be automatically using that First Person
camera. There is actually a camera sitting behind the ThirdPerson
Character but it's just not being used right now. OK, so back to
the ThirdPersonCharacter. Let's have a look at what's going on with this guy!
Firstly, how do we choose what default animation he
has? So he's standing on the ground quite comfortably here in the
Blueprint Editor and just breathing away. But if we look inside the actual game,
he's doing some weird stuff. So the most likely is, it's just that he is
impacting with the ground, i.e. his Capsule Collider here
or his feet are going though the ground. So the simple solution to that is to lift him up a little bit,
and then, have a look at him and see if he's any better.
It hasn't helped! Let's lift him up further, and if it still doesn't help, then, we will go further
and look at his default animation state. So let's lift him plenty off the ground.
No he's doing something very
strange! So let's click on the ThirdPersonCharacter and start exploring
a little bit about what he can do. So if you click into him
and then search, because there's a lot of properties on this guy, if we search
for animation
then you'll see it brings up some of the, just some
of the components and their details. So it's saying Use an Animation
Blueprint. Well for the moment let's just, rather than using a Blueprint to control his animation,
let's just Use an Animation Asset right now, and then, specifically
pick an idle animation, ThirdPersonIdle there.
So what I've done is, I've said the Animation Mode is a specific asset, and then, I've picked the Third
PersonIdle animation. Let's take a look!
There he is, standing there much more sensible and breathing. I'll just pop him
on the ground, with the End key now. And that little sequence just gives you an idea of how you might
want to debug these things. I mean I knew that it was the animation there, but I just wanted to point
out that those sorts of strange behaviors could also be, especially with rag doll
based characters, to do with collisions. So it's always worth checking things aren't
passing through the ground first, especially when you just dump them in the scene and not check their position.
Anyway, there he is, he's in the scene, and he's got a ThirdPersonIdle animation on him,
and he's standing there quite happily! So that's the ThirdPersonCharacter,
he will be ready now to start moving around the scene. What I want you
to do now is, to simply add a Navmesh. Of course, before
we can get this thing moving around, we're going to need a Navmesh in our level. We've done it before
in Battle Tank! Ensure it covers "up the stairs", so you need the three dimensionality, the height, to
cover the area up the stairs as well. Preview it with the P key
and then share a still of what you've got, over on the community
site at community.gamedev.tv. So go ahead pause the video, and just add yourself a Navmesh
now! Welcome
back! So this is a pretty simple challenge, what I'm going to do is I'm going to show Navmesh,
which is the Show, Navigation which I can use the Show menu or I can just hit the
P key. You'll see there is no navigation, right now. So I make myself a
little more room, grab the Modes brush, I'm going to say
Volumes here, and then, under Volumes somewhere we should have Nav Mesh
Bounds Volume. There it is! I'm going to pop it in! Now I find when positioning
these Nav Meshes, it's quite useful to use this four way view here,
because that gives me an overview of the whole level in one go. So I
can see the side, I can see the front, etc. all in one go!
So now, we need to select the Nav Mesh, one way to do that is
here, go to Details, clearing my search,
and now it's just a question of changing the size of this Nav Mesh, so that it's
appropriate. So let's recentralize it in the level by resetting its
transform. We can then pull up the X size, until it covers the level.
Now it doesn't matter if it's a little bit larger than the level, that's fine, and we can just
reposition like that. I would overspill just a little bit. Then, I can work on
the Y size. Again, the same thing applies.
Cover the level, that's fine! And now, the Z size, I said I wanted it to cover these
boxes, etc. So let's just increase the Z size, repositioning it as we
do, to something like that. OK great! So using this multi-
view is handy for that! Now, let's have a look down here! You see, we have green on the top
of all of these surfaces, and we have a continuous or at least fairly
continuous Nav Mesh moving up here. I think that'll be OK! It looks a little
broken on the stairs there. If you want to improve that, what we could do is just turn the
Step Height down a little bit and then increase the Number of Steps,
maybe just by 1. And that should be enough to get a continous
volume. So I'm going to go with 26 or 28 Step Height, maybe,
and you can see here that the Nav Mesh is more continuous, going up the
side there. So great, take a screenshot of your area, perhaps
focusing on the stairs here. If you want to select all the faces of these and apply a default
material you can, I'm not going to bother right now. And I will see you in the next video!