Hi
and welcome to Introducing AI Behaviour Trees! In this video we're going to make this
thing a Behavior Tree, which determines the actions that our AI
is going to take, so that our ThirdPersonCharacter has the foundations
ready to actually make him move and follow us and all that sort of thing.
We'll be writing a tiny bit of blueprint and making a
simple introduction to Behavior Trees! So I'll see you in there!
OK, so it's time to give our AI character some behavior, and to
do that we use something called a Behavior Tree, in Unreal. So let's go ahead and
add a Behavior Tree now. In your Content Browser Add New, scroll
down helpfully to the Artificial Intelligence section. And there are two things, we'll be
covering black boards in a minute, but for now, let's just go ahead with a Behavior
Tree. And it's going to come here into whichever folder its
in. We can over over it, once it's created, to see. It's in the Blueprints folder!
And of course, you can use F2 to rename it. So this is just going to be called
a patrolling behavior, for now, so I'll just simply call it Patrol.
OK, so what is a Behavior Tree? Let's to into it and take a look at it! It
starts off with a ROOT node, and from there, we can go ahead and go through a sequence
of actions or we can select what action to do next, based on
what's going on. So the Behavior Tree is going to be our way of mapping out how
obvious AI behavior should work. Now the first thing is to do something super
simple. We just want the AI to move to a specified point.
So how would you specify that point? Well that's what the other side of
Behavior Trees is, it's called Blackboards. So you'll see grayed out, at the top-right at the moment,
Blackboard, and you'll see Blackboard Asset and you'll see there are none to choose.
What a Blackboard does is it holds the data for a particular
instance of the AI, so a particular guard's next waypoint,
for example or a particular guard's alert status.
Has he seen the player? Is he hiding? Is he scared? Is he agro, as they call it? Whatever.
That's what you put on the Blackboard. So let's go ahead and make a Blackboard, as well! That's
over here. And we go ahead and say Add New, down to Artificial Intelligence,
and Blackboard. And what we can call this is, we can just call it
PatrolData, something like that, just to remind us what
it is. You're not allowed spaces, so PatrolData there. Back at the Patrol
Behavior Tree, you'll now be able to choose your Blackboard asset as PatrolData.
So now you've associated the Behavior Tree with that Blackboard. What
that's saying is that this is the execution flow in
the Behavior Tree, this is the methods if you like from the programming standpoint, and
Blackboard is the data, the private member variables.
OK fantastic! So that is that! Parent here we won't worry about. We're not going to
have child Blackboards yet, we just don't need the complexity. Great! So
that's all very well! We'll come back to Behavior Trees in just a little bit, because
right now, there's no reason for this ThirdPersonCharacter to take any notice
of the fact we've just created a Patrol Behavior Tree. So our job now
is to connect those two together. So let's, firstly, just play the game
and take a look in the World Outliner and let's see if we can
find an AIController in here. And there is one! In fact,
if I depossess and then click on this AIController or simply search
for it in the World Outliner and click on it, you can see that it's in the same position
as the ThirdPersonCharacter. It doesn't have to be, it could be
somewhere else in the world, but it makes sense to keep it there and that's where it comes as default. So
the ThirdPersonCharacter that we brought in has already got an
animation on it, it's already got a skeletal mesh, it's already got movement components, it's already
also got an AI Controller associated with it. The challenge is, right now,
that that AI Controller doesn't know what Behavior Tree to run, so it isn't
running currently any Behavior Tree. So what we're going to do is, we're
going to sort that out, and the way you sort that out is over in Blueprint. So before
we sort it out in Blueprint and I show you how to do that, I'm going to mention two resources.
Firstly, I have in the resources of this lecture, this is my behind
the scenes thing, but in the resources here, I have given you a link to Unreal's
docs about setting up the AI Controller. That looks like this, and it's part of a
series on this. I'm taking you through all of this but this gives you some further reading.
And the other thing is that I want you actually to do a challenge. I want you
to get the NPC the None Player Character, None
Player Character which is the Third Person that we've put in,
AI blueprint working. We can call it that, for now. It looks a bit ugly but it works
fine. I want you to create a new Blueprint class. Remember we can reparent
that Blueprint class to C++ later, if we need to. Make
it the default class for the placed AI. This is something you did
previously in Battle Tank, so I want you to recap this. Just make this new Blueprint class
the default class, and to prove it's working, go into the blueprint and then in
Begin Play just print to say, hey you know I'm working. So we want that AI
Controller to run its blueprint and to print out to say it's working. Then, I'll show you
the last bits to actually link up the Behavior Tree. So go ahead, pause the video,
and just get a new class working now! Remember it
needs to be a child of the AI Controller class.
OK welcome back!
Not too tricky, hopefully for you, at this stage in the course. So we're going to make a new Blueprint
class here. We're going to base it on, under All Classes, "ai controller",
like that, and then, we're just going to call it... I'm going to call it
what I said we were going to call it, which is NPC_
AI_BP (Blueprint), like that. It's all capitals just because it's all acronym.
And there you go, you have this class here sitting here doing very little right now,
but that's absolutely fine! So, in its Event Graph what we're going to do is go
to BeginPlay, and we're just going to print using the Blueprint print.
We'll be using a bit more Blueprint in this section, by the way, at least to prototype things in the first place,
and we're just going to see NPC AI Reporting
for Duty, or something like that. Now we can expand
out and make sure this is going to both the screen and the log, if we wish, and
then, compile that blueprint! And of course, if we play it right now nothing will happen! Why not?
Because the other part of the challenge, of course, for you is, you've got to work out how to
associate that with the AI Controller. How are you going to do that? Well,
If you look at the blueprint for this ThirdPersonCharacter,
then on the right-hand side here it says, Auto Possess AI for anything that's
placed in the world. So every time you place a ThirdPersonCharacter in the world, it will Auto Posses it with
AI, but currently, it's using the standard AI Controller class. What we want
is this NPC_AI_BP (Blueprint) class. Uh huh, let's
compile that and play the game! NPC_AI
reporting for duty! Did you see what we did there? We told the ThirdPersonCharacter
blueprint what AI Controller class to use by default,
and then, in that AI Controller class, on BeginPlay, we printed some stuff out. Let me just get rid of
this funny comment box here. There you go! So to associate
this AI Controller with that particular Behavior Tree, we're going to get rid of
the Print String, come off of BeginPlay, and just look for Behavior Tree.
And we're going to say run a Behavior Tree, straight away on BeginPlay run a Behavior Tree. Which
Behavior Tree? Well the Patrol Behavior Tree. Great! So hopefully
that's working. If we play the game, we won't see any evidence it's working. The print statement has
gone away, and in theory, this guy is running his Behavior Tree. How would we know? Well you can actually
go into the Patrol Data Behavior Tree, and you can actually see this ROOT
node is highlighted here now. So that's a good sign, it means it is actually running
this Behavior Tree. So let's just finish this off by making it do something.
And we can use to start with, for example, a Selector. What a Selector
does is it just executes all the children nodes from left to right, until one of us
succeeds and then it stops working. So we're going to pick one
child node, and let's just have it say Move To somewhere.
Now this is where we need Blackboard, which I will make the subject
of the next lecture. It cannot move to just any old position, it can only move to
a Blackboard key, which is where the data comes in. So you see the
execution flow is here. You start, you execute these children nodes left to right, we may have
another node here, and then, you move to a particular place but it needs data now, and data
is a subject of Blackboards, which I'll introduce in the next video. Let me just show you once
more that you want to get your project to this stage, which is that you click play.
If you then go to the Patrol Behavior Tree, you can see it's working.
It's gone through ROOT to the Selector,
and it's trying to do this Move To, that is what this is indicating. It's not going to
work, because it has an invalid piece of data, which we'll sort out next. So
congratulations on getting this far, and I'll see you in the next video! Just before I
leave, there's one final warning! When you try and submit to Source Control, using the
Unreal tool, even if you've saved everything first, it's going to say there's nothing
to submit, and that's because everything we just did in that video was creating
new assets and the source control only seems to be tracking, at the moment, with Git
changes to existing files. So if you go and look over on SourceTree,
you'll find that it has found the change to the map and these other assets. So just make your
Commit here in SourceTree.