So. I've got a challenge for you guys!
If you've made it this far in the course. I think you're up for it!
So. I want you to try and make a Health Bar
Prefab. that is simple but good enough to
put on the Unity Assets Store. Now. I'm not going to show you how to do it.
The course is basically over. In fact. I'm having
a lot of trouble letting go. I really should be working on the next course. which is
Unreal Developer. now. but I realize this is an important
thing and thank you. Okiliy Dokily. for suggesting it.
Now. I've realized that the best way to get it done. is actually to had it
over to you guys. So. somebody
one of you out there. at least one of you. is going to make an Assets Store
asset. on the Unity Assets
Store. which means signing up for an account.
setting up everything you need to set up. including the graphics
and the description and the instructions. and to make a simple
Health Bar Prefab. Now. it's entirely of coarse up to you how you
do it. and you can even charge for hit and you may make some money from it.
which would be great. But the sort of thing I've got in mind is very simple.
It's a component that will sit on a game
object. and look for the game object's transform component.
and on your little component.
I imagine a couple of things. I imagine the ability to
offset this little health bar by
X and Y amount. from the transform of the object in
question. So. imagine we're now in Glitch Garden.
and you want to put little tiny health bars on all the guys. I would
suggest a really simple health bar. without even an outline.
Just a rectangle. that when it's not
full. just disappears. because if you put an outline
you're straight away into scaling issues. There's a big difference between how
it'll look. if it's just a few pixels by a few pixels verses
quite large. So. as a first approximation.
just grab yourself a rectangle. literally that just
disappears and depletes. And
I would probably simply have four settings X
offset. Y offset from the transform of the
object that it's attached to. and then X scale and Y
scale. And then. you need to figure out for yourself a very
easy way for the developer to wire it
in to a value of relevance. So. in Block
Breaker. that could be the times hit. and it may just drop down three
times. two times. one time. and destroyed. If it was
Laser Defender. then
you may be talking about some other floating
point that changing. If it's Glitch Garden. the same sort of
thing. OK. so you've got to provide some simple interface.
some instructions in your package. to say to people
this is the value that you need to talk to. So. you either need to make
changes to the existing code. you probably will have
to make changes to the existing code of the game. or the
user of this package will. because if you've made your health
private. for example. on the component
of the player or the brick or the zombie
or whatever it is. then you can't reference that from the
outside right. So. you are going to have to go in and probably make a call into
the Health Bar Prefab. and say just set the Health Bar
Prefab's value to X. So. I leave all of that for you to work
out. It's a pretty simple assignment. if you're going to make your
first Unity Asset Store asset. which is of course. one of
the wonderful things you can now do. given what you've learned
in this course. This would be a great and simple place to
start. A little bit of the problem is engineering. Please
please please keep it simple. And a large part of it will be.
how do you get that through Unity's approval and
provide all the relevant graphics. at the right sizes
and dimensions that they want and provide a description
and provide enough instructions that you
or me or one of the other students on the course. can
take the link the. which you're going to share. which will be the link to the actual Unity
Asset Store asset. and try it in at least Block
Breaker. Laser Defender. and Glitch Garden. In all
three of those games. I'd like to be able to drop your Health Bar Prefab
straight onto. or at least the
component. straight onto the bricks or the zombie
player and actually have it work. following some simple instructions.
So. there you go! There's the gauntlet to you guys! I think the
spec is pretty clear. left and right offset. up and down
offset. vertical and horizontal size. and then. be
able to take a floating point value. that determine how full this little
bar is. I'll leave it to you. how you draw the bar. A UI slider maybe?
Maybe you just draw some other and go for it!
See if you can make the Unity Asset Store asset. that is usable
for all of us. and the person that makes the
first one that's on the asset store. that I can put
my idiot cap on and simply install in those games. I will then
add to this lecture we're on now. and I'll add it as a
downloadable resource for everybody else to use. So. I'm handing it over to you guys.
to help me out getting that done. but most crucially to give you the
confidence of launching a Unity Asset Store asset.
So. good luck with that! I know one of you will do it. and you'll probably do it
surprisingly quickly and surprisingly well. knowing some of you guys!
And I'll see you soon!