So hi and in this video
we're going to be talking to you about the Facebook group. So. the Facebook
group is an awesome place. we've setup for you
to use. It's a community of people. like you. And what can you
do with the Facebook group. Ben? Well. what the intention of the group. which
you can find at facebook.com/groups
/completeunitydeveloper. It's there...
The purpose of that is to allow you to interact.
not only with your fellow students. which you can already do in the discussions.
but with the wider world. We want you to invite your friends
into the group. we want them to try playing your games
with you. and then. we want to get their ideas. and maybe you can
make the games that they want. So. it's owned by the community.
it's run by the community. and it's
an open group. We really hope that you go over there and
make it your own. So. yeah! Hopefully we'll
see you in the group. where you can share your games and learn more about Unity and share
tips together. to see how to better work with making games.
So. see you in the group and see you on Facebook! And see you there!
And when you go to Facebook. there's one thing to note that. we also have a Facebook
page. which is basically a webpage on Facebook. That's
where we put all our updates and everything. You're welcome to like that
as well. and that's a great place to keep in touch with what's going on in the
course and we also share some student stories there ourselves. Basically.
the page is our voice. the banner is our photo.
it's a website within the Facebook. and it's facebook
.com/unitycourse. The group. however.
is yours and the banner is full of all your faces
to reflect the fact it's a community. The group is way more awesome.
because it's yours. Because it's yours. See ya!