So hi. and welcome to the end of the
course! Congratulations on getting this far!
I hope you've really enjoyed the journey and learned tons and you feel
a lot more confident with Unity now. Do have a
checkout on www.completeunitydeveloper.com
for all the latest courses and all the latest information
about this course and about other courses. that
we're offering. So yeah! Absolutely! That's the place to keep up to
date on what we're doing next. If you've got any ideas about what you'd like to see.
please e-mail us at team@completeunitydeveloper.com
and also on the Complete Unity Developer
website. you can play all the games we've created during the course. You can get
all the latest asset packs. There's a separate community there.
if you want to discuss things that are slightly outside of the context of this exact
course. that are more about web development or. sorry.
Unity development in general. then that's the place to do it. out in the community
page. You can join the mailing list there. That's
the best way to be sure about any future courses that come out
and that's it! We just want to say thank you! Thank you very
much for being our student! Thank you so much for getting through
all the course. and thank you so much for watching our course! See
you soon! Bye!