Hey guys and
welcome to our information interview on dynamic music.
as promised in the Kickstarter. So. I'm Ben Tristem. as
you know. author of the Unity Developer course. and I'm with...
Michael author of the Complete Blender course.
So Michael. you may not know. is also a talented
musician. a man of many talents. Thank you. He's been
playing the piano. since he was this big. So.
for the concept of this discussion or for the scope of this discussion.
what are we talking about? Well. we're going to be talking about dynamic music.
specifically in Unity. but this applies to any game engine.
And we're just going to talk about the basics of it. which is the ability
to change track and to change the
sound volume. So. we're going to assume you're allowed to play multiple different sound tracks.
There could be different pieces of music. could be different instruments. We'll talk
about that later. And we're going to assume you've got the ability to start and stop
pretty accurately. which you certainly have in Unity and Unreal and other engines.
and we're going to assume that you can control
the volume. with some finesse as well. So. that's what
we're going to do. Why is it important? A couple
of reasons why. Mikey. why do we want to change music? Well. sounds incredibly
important throughout everything. If you imagine
any films you've seen. any moments of silence. Well. that silence
itself is a sound. There's a little tip for you.
But it's a soundtrack. whether it's music or a sound
effect. it's all the soundtrack for your game. for whatever
project you're working on. Now. sound is incredible.
it can lead us up to an emotional state. I mean you
can have the same scene... Imagine some swings. swinging
in a playground and playing happy
cheerful music. well it's a cheerful scene. You do the
same and put a bit of horror music in it. perhaps
even the same theme but a bit more discordant a bit
harmonics. You know it's horrible. slow. or echoey.
It's something you've got horror. horror scene. To completely change the feeling of it. It's exactly
the same sort of... Well. there's nothing changed
in the scene. only the music. and that can change what
you're feeling. massively. OK. to summarize it.
setting the mood and for non visual
cues as well. Important Yes. OK. so we're
going to run through with you. three specific examples
and we're going to talk about how we may actually implement that.
Yes. So number one. this is inspired by an experience
we both had recently. playing Until Dawn on the PS4.
That's Until Dawn. it's a horror game interactive
horror. Pretty cool! And we just noticed. as we went to a doorway
boundary. and as we approach that doorway I think I'm not even
sure what happened. I know I felt uneasy but I think some strings maybe got  a lot
louder. Yes. so as we approached the door. it was leading us up.
It was saying. beyond this doorway and the closer and closer
you got the louder and more intense these strings became.
And I'm not sure if it made us jump afterwards.
but when we passed through the door it just went dead. Yeah. so there was a huge
amount of contrast there. So. let's talk briefly about how we might do that.
So. a simple way to do this would be
to have a AudioSource. in the doorway. just
say on the floor. just floating in the air. it's invisible who cares.
And then. you work on the Volume Rolloff Curve for
that AudioSource. and arrange that when you get within a few feet or
meters of the door. that
an audio track... So. let's imagine you've got some discordant music of
some sort. running in the background. right. And then.
you could as a separate track. attach to this AudioSource a string.
some strings or something. You could just ramp up the volume.
It's very simple at this stage. just ramp up the volume as you get closer
and closer to the door. In fact. you probably want it very subtle
as you approach the door. depending on the speed of your character and the distance
between it. But as you get closer and closer to the door. you
want it to ramp up to really make that doorway tense.
OK cool! So. we're talking about two audio tracks here. One is
music that is
compatible with the idea of having louder and louder strings.
that plays through the whole room that we're in. and then.
another one. which is specifically a strings AudioSource.
that sits in the doorway. It just gets louder
and louder as you approach. It's a 3D sound and the sound ramps up and
ramps up. as you get close to it. And you play test it. by walking up to the door and seeing how it
feels. And then. you said that in Until Dawn
you seem to remember it stopping very quickly. Yes. So.
one way we could do that. in say Unity. is just to put a collider on just the other side of the door.
for example. a Trigger Collider. and then. wire that Trigger Collider to
the AudioSource script and just say stop playing the sound. So. it gets
louder and louder and louder. and then. we walk through the door and it stops.
Now. you either scare them at that point or whatever or you don't.
Or leave them hanging. But you've created the mood right.
So. hopefully that's clear. that particular scenario. Yeah.
Anything else to add on that one? Not really. I mean
you can apply this to any sort of
context. whether you're approaching a base.
if you've made a game. or approaching home. you can make it
triumphant. etc. So. you can use that sort of thing wherever you are.
These are general geographic cues and
you can do this with your own scripting. but remember that most game engines have
a 3D AudioSource. Unity certainly does. that you can let
it do the calculations about how loud it is for the volume and you just move a curve.
I guess the other thing I noticed when talking to you about this before
was that you said. because in the case of discordant
music. because the music is already discordant. it doesn't matter really what strings
sound you put on top. but in some cases you may need to match
and get your music design or just listen to make sure that what you're
adding matches with the underlying sound track. Otherwise you end up with a
muddy mess and you do want to avoid that. And in the case
with sound. and probably most things. less is actually more.
So. if you over complicate it. you end up with a muddy mess
and essentially the character
or you as a player is just going to become confused.
Fantastic! OK. in a moment we're going to move on to the second
example of what we can do with this sound.
OK. so for our second example we're just going to use the case of a
character drawing their sword. as simple as that.
Or any weapon. So. talk us through what might be
happening there. Mikey. Before we draw the sword. what could be going on with the music?
If you imagine. let's take an RPG for example.
so you'll be trolling. strolling... [Laughs]
Trolling. strolling. patrolling! [Laughs] ...strolling around the forrest
scene and you see a potential enemy. however. you may
have the calm music playing at the moment. You want something
to trigger the sound change. and
one of the things. well if you've got your weapon out you're going to be attacking.
so you can change from calm music
to attacking music. more aggressive music. more exciting music.
the moment you have your weapon drawn. Fantastic! So in
Unity for example. you could just do that straight from the Player Animation State.
You could say that it he's in a Weapon Ready State or in
a Weapon Ready Sub-State Machine
then that's the point at which a script triggers
a different music. Yes. we do obviously have to be careful. when
we change... You can just imagine someone going oh. the music
changes. Well. what happens if I do this?
Of course. you do have to have some sort of Roll Off
with the music itself. You mean if you keep putting the music away.
the sword in and out. It's just going to sound silly if you do that. so you're going to have to
have some buffer that it's playing agressive
music for a while after...
That's a good idea. If you imagine your adrenaline. in reality. doesn't suddenly
disappear the moment you put the weapon away. you need to keep it tense for a
while. OK. so we get down to the
specifics for them of how this might work. then we'd have a
script that looks for a change in Animation State. In a particular Animation State
it would fade down the current music. over a
period of time in the script and then fade up the volume of the aggressive music
and then play that for a certain amount of time.
either using a co-routine
or using an AudioSource that plays a sound
for a particular amount of time. There's ways of doing it. we're talking about sound design here
rather than specific implementation. but I think what Mikey is saying is if the
battle has ended or you put a sword away. we don't immediately trigger the
stop of that sound. that we let that sound play for a little bit
longer and then calm it down. probably slower than we ramped it up.
So the volume. it comes in it fades in rapidly and
down slowly. And you can use that type of sound design. not only
when you're drawing a weapon but when. let's say. when an enemy spots you.
So it's a good audio cue. that you're now
in danger but you don't know where from. So that would be
triggered off the AI's state. when you've come into his line of sight.
Cool! So. so far we've had number one's
Geographic Triggers. like in the Until Dawn example on the
Micro Scale a doorway. on the Macro Scale you mentioned approaching a base.
The second idea we've had is based on states. state of view. state of the game.
state of an enemy. could even be the state of a video camera.
you know. A very strong example is Metal Gear Solid. when
somebody recognizes you it goes ding. it makes this kind rrrah sound and there's an
exclamation mark. and you know for sure that somebody has spotted you. That's
a sound effect more than music. but they kind of tie together.
OK fantastic. that's the second one. So. in a moment we'll explore a third
way that we can dive into using dynamic music in our games.
OK guys. let's
talk about the third way that we could possibly use dynamic music in our games. So.
at this instance it's going to be much longer term. timewise.
Yes. So. what are we thinking here. Mikey?
Again. I'm going to use RPG because it really works in this
context. So. if you imagine good and evil.
the more good you do in the game. perhaps the music itself
gets more angelic. so to speak. I don't know how that would
sound. you'd have to play about with your game itself.
but as you became bad. let's say if you stole stuff.
if you killed innocents. etc.. etc..  you would
end up with more devilish music.
The overall soundtrack changes the mood of the character...
Over a longer period. Yes. over a much longer period
of the game. In fact. you could script over the entire game.
OK. Then. you'd have. let's say. you'd have
five states. one being neutral. two pluses. and two
negatives. So. you're neutral or you're slightly good or your've very
good guy or you're slightly bad guy or really bad guy. Exactly. Yeah.
And you could have. for simplicity. five tracks
on each layer. and as every so
often I suppose you'd call... So. there's tracks on each layer. Let's just make sure it's
clear for the... like a playlist. Yeah. a playlist. So. we would pick a
neutral guy playlist of five. ten. fifteen songs.
If all the time the guy stays neutral. it just plays the songs back
to back. They fade down they fade up. like normal songs do. but
at the end of each song. perhaps. is a good time for a script
to say. let's check in at the character's good or badness level
and change lanes right? Yes. so you can go down or go up.
Switch into another playlist between songs. I think even
if they've been really really bad recently and their thing has gone
right down. you still don't jump two lanes. you still step down
and then step down again. otherwise it would be too
much of a sound change. Of a contrast for such a long
term play. That's a good point. So. you could say right I'm at level 0.
say we have -2. -1. 0. +1. +2. I'm at 0
I'm playing a track. but during that track the player has been
so evil that he's gone 0 to -2. but you just
say let's just move down 1. Write a little bit of script that says move
down one at a time. and then. when we check at the end of this song. if he's still
-2 well then we'll go down to the -2 sound. Yeah definitely. And the will give a
nice slow. long term sense of
a change in the mood. based on the character.
Fantastic! So. we would select those playlists that
work in their own right. so you could listen to
+2 guy. super good guy. all day on a loop.
One great example of this is Oblivion.
I mean it doesn't do the good bad guy changes. but
when you're exploring the world it has very
gentle music. etc. When you're in a
fight. etc. it changes. but you could apply that
same methodology to the actual character themselves.
Just change that background music as you go.
So. there are three clear strategies for you guys. as to how to
think about implementing Dynamic Music in your game. So. I want you to pick
a game you're working on or you have worked on and go
with one of these strategies. Either put in some dynamic music
based on state. or put some
long term dynamic music based on the kind of mood of the
game. where the theme changes much more slowly over a period many
minutes. Please implement one of those. share what you've got in the discussions
against this video. And all that remains to say is
if you want more Mikey. and who wouldn't want more Mikey. [Laughs]
then. go check out the Complete Blender Creator course.
Over on Udemy it's udemy.com/blendertutorial
blendertutorial... www.udemy.com/blendertutorial
and that is how to make 3D assets in Blender.
And if you want to know more about what we're talkng about here. which is sound and music
of course. then I'm going to give you a link down here to a
Trello card on my Course Roadmap. Now. I have a card
on there for a music course. that I would co-author with Mikey. It's
not going to happen till 2016. quarter 2
quarter 3 at the earliest. but if you are interested in learning more
about dynamic music and actually building it into games. please vote
on that card. It may change names. as we come up with the idea. but just give it
a vote. Log into Trello. give it a vote. and thank you for
lisetning! I hope you've enjoyed this interview. and we'll see you soon! Take
care guys!