Welcome! In this video we are going to be
reviewing the Game Design Document format. We're also
going to be brainstorming concepts, rules, and requirements as
we go, and we're going to outline the scope for the entire section. So let's
dive into this! First off, let's talk a little
bit about the concept of this game called Shoot Hoop! We are
going to be basically a basketball player in a deserted gym, so
we don't have to worry about other people or, you know, anything like that. No crazy
game mechanics, just a basketball player that's all. And we're going to be shooting
as many hoops as possible, in a short span of time.
OK, so let's drill down a little bit on
these rules. What does this actually mean? We're going to have an infinite number of balls that we can
throw or we can call these attempts as well.
We are going to lay out a horseshoe configuration for the hoops,
so that the basketball player is shooting in this one, then this one, and
so on, just around and around. And we will be
scoring a point for every hoop that we shoot,
that we successfully manage to get into the hoop, and
we're going to have to limit the time to 1 minute,
so we'll be able to see how many, how many I have shot in
that time. OK, so it's time to pause and
have a go at writing the requirements, as you see it. So just a quick
reminder! What assets will you need? As some of the prompting questions, what
assets will you need? What sound effects? And do you need any
artwork? And, as a bonus, see if you can write a No-
list as well. OK so pause the video, and have a go at this yourself!
OK welcome back! I
hope you've had a go, and don't forget to share what you've come up with in the discussions,
that's always a great way to share with your
fellow students and get involved. OK, so let's see,
let's have a go at the requirements. So what are we going to need? We're going to need a basketball
texture, so it's obvious we've got a ball and perhaps it's rotating
and all that sort of thing. It needs to be obvious that we're
shooting a basketball. Then, we need some models for our hoops. So
Unity does not provide much more than basic things like cubes
and balls and so on, so we do need to have
a model, a mesh that can model our hoop.
We'll need a gym floor texture, because at the moment,
very soon, we're going to be putting a gym floor in but it's going to be very bland.
We want to have something that looks a little bit more like a gym.
And we'll need some ball collision sound effects, so when it's hitting
the backboard, for example, or, you know, going through the hoop we need some sound effects
that are equivalent to that. And we might need a splash screen and
game over artwork too. OK, so that brings us to the end of the requirements,
and I'll leave the No List as an exercise to you. Let's see what you
come up with in the discussions. OK, see you in the next lecture!