Welcome! In this video we are going to be looking at
how the Unity Editor, that is every thing here, works. And how
can we move, how can we rotate
objects in the scene, and how can we, importantly,
scale objects in the scene, as well? Basically, how do we manipulate 3D objects
in the scene? And finally, how do we preview our scene?
So that's what I want to cover in this lecture! Let's get stuck right in!
OK, so the first thing we want to do is open up
the Unity Editor. And what we're going to do,
first of all, is create a new Unity project. So
with that we do New, and we are going to be
saving it anywhere. And we're going to call this
ShootHoop and that should do.
OK, and I'm gong to select this as a 3D project.
That's what we want to do, we're delving straight into 3D in this section. So let's
Create that Project!
Now what we expect is a few things to be set up for us but not very
much, and we'll be presented with this Editor view, which we'll have seen
before but now we're going to delve into a little bit more detail. OK,
so the first thing to note is the Hierarchy in the left
towards the top. There's a tab called Hierarchy and underneath it there is this
list of items. The Main Camera, so
you can see, when I select this, there's things going on in this Preview view
here, and if I select the Directional Light, that shows a different
object selected in this 3D viewport. So the Hierarchy
is all the list of objects that are here in the scene. Now
what is a scene? A scene is the file, essentially, that we're
editing, but more specifically, in a game, a scene could be a
level, for example, or it could be a splash screen or it could be a game
over screen. But essentially it is a different collection of
these game objects, as they're called, like Main Camera and
Directional Light. So how do we create
one of these scenes? At the moment, we don't start with one by default.
If you go down to the bottom-left-most section, so
the Project Pane, you'll see there is a list of
folders. You want to select the Assets folder, and then, in the right
section, this is the contents of the Assets folder and it says "This folder is
empty". You want to right-click and go to Create
and then scene. So that's right-click, Create, Scene,
and this creates us a new scene file.
Now we can give this a name, I'm going to call this the Main scene,
and we can hit Save.
It has already saved for us, this is giving me the option to...where to save it,
but let's just check that out. So what files has this created
for us? I'm going to go into my Documents, ShootHoop,
and then into the Assets folder. And in the Assets folder you see
we have this Unity...this main file, and then, we have a META
file as well, that's not as important. The main thing is this
Unity Main file, and if you double-click it, it actually opens up Unity
with this scene selected. OK, so that is what
a scene is. It is a collection of items, of game objects in
Hierarchy. Now how do we add game objects and
what's it actually do? Well let's start by this..looking at the middle here at these+
play/pause buttons. OK, so if I hit play, what
I get is a preview of my game. At the moment it's very boring, all I've got is a Skybox and a
camera, so all I see is the sky. So I'm going to
hit play again to stop the game. Let's make this a little bit
more interesting. If we right-click in the Hierarchy, we have the option to create objects.
So if I go down to 3D Object and select Cube, I can
put a cube into our scene. If I hit play now,
we can see it's a bit vague, because
the color blends in with the background but we have a cube there.
And if I select one of these arrows
on the cube, when the cube is selected, so make sure you select the cube in the Hierarchy,
and then, go onto the arrow. We can move it up and down
or backwards and forwards. Select the cube again,
go backwards and forwards, you can also select items by clicking on them in the viewport,
or left and right. And now if I hit play,
you will see that that cube has been moved higher up and it's much more visible now.
There are a few more things that we can do to edit things in the
scene. The first thing to note is, how do we navigate
around this scene? So you can use the scroll wheel, that allows you to zoom in
and out. If you double-click an item in the Hierarchy, it will
put it into focus,
and if you hold down Alt
while dragging, you'll be able to rotate around whatever it
is you are focusing on. I can zoom out, rotate,
etc. Now there's a few
more controls to note. Up here in the
top-left we have a toolbar of sorts. We
have a Hand tool, which allows us to drag our viewport
like so. It's not dragging the item, it's actually dragging the whole viewport, so basically
where our viewport camera is. We have the Movement, which we have seen.
We have Rotation, which we haven't seen. It allows us to rotate
objects like so, by dragging their different handles. If we
play, we can see what the result of that rotation has been. We now have that offset
cube. We also have Scaling, so I can
make one edge of the cube bigger, like so. I  hit play, I can see the preview.
Yep, we now have not a cube at all but more of an oblong
box. And this final element is for editing UI's,
so we won't worry about that too much. But one thing to note is that all of these can be
accessed by using your Q, W, E, R, and T
keys. they essentially align with the tools in this way. So if I hit
Q i get that, if I hit W I get that, if I hit E
I get Rotation, if I hit R then I get Scale.
So they're not mnemonic, they're basically just locations on your keyboard.
So it's time for your first 3D challenge!
I would like you to create a floor for the gym, using the
knowledge that we have just accumulated, by.. in this video. So
start by adding a cube to the scene, then use the Scale
Tool to make it large. So make it wide and
long, but it doesn't need to be high because it's just a floor and we won't
be passing through it anyway. And then, I'd like you to position it under the camera,
so that you can see it when you preview the scene. And then share a
screenshot of your achievement. It's always good to share your achievements in the discussion, it just
makes them that bit more real. OK, so pause the video, and have a go at this!
OK welcome
back! I hope you've had a go and you've had some success with creating this
screenshot of your achievements. Now let me show you how I would
do it. So the first thing is first, I'm
going to delete this cube, because I want to start afresh.
And I'm going to right-click 3D Object, Cube, and create
a new cube. I'm just going to resize these a little bit, to give me a
little space in the viewport itself. OK,
now what I want to do is scale this
cube. So I'm going to get the Scale Tool, and I don't want to
scale it in that direction but I do want to scale it in the floor direction
a little bit, like so. So what have I
done there? Yeah that's correct, that is actually scaling it
all in the right directions.
I'm going to scale out around the sides as well, just rotate a little bit around the
cube so I can see what I'm doing.
There we go! As you can see, as I scroll out my mouse actually wraps around
the screen to carry on the scrolling, which is a quite handy feature.
Then I'm going to go back to the move, and I'm going to position this floor
a little bit beneath the camera. Where's my camera? It appears to be around
here. So as you can see, the floor is a little bit
far, actually not that far down at all, so we can move it down
a little bit farther. Now I can hit play and that will
preview this for me. And there you go, you can see there is a floor
to my gym, in front of my camera. I just want to do one more
thing, is to move this floor a little bit further forward, because
we're only looking really in the forward direction. We're going to be shooting hoops
in this direction! So let's hit play, and there we go,
we've got more of the floor in front of us! Success! Now, you just need to take a
screenshot of this and share it in the forums.