Welcome! In this lecture we are going to be looking at how we can instantiate
these prefabs from code, in order to do things like this.
When I hit Spacebar, I can create a new clone just like
this. There we go! And this game finally starts to be
interactive and a little bit fun. See you in there!
Adding instances is all well and good, but it's not very
interesting if this is all we can do. What we want to be doing is adding some
behavior, adding some scripts that really make things
work, you know make things actually do stuff. So let's right-click and
Create a new Folder here, where we're going to store our scripts.
So you can see that we're getting the beginnings of a nicely organized
folder structure here. It's good to keep your files in order, right from the
beginning, that way you don't have to worry about doing a big cleanup. Now, I'm going to right-
click and create a new C# script, as we have done before. And now
what I'm going to call this is a BallSpawner,
because the purpose of this script
is to create new balls. And that's what we're
going to be doing in this lecture, we're going to be figuring out how we can create
these prefabs. OK, so I'm going to add this script into a game
object. Remember that scripts don't run unless they're on a game object, and in this
case, I'm going to add it onto the Camera and that'll make sense in later
lectures, but for now, let's just do it like that. And let's
launch VisualStudio or MonoDevelop with that C#
script that we have just created.
Now what we're going to want to do is get hold of
reference to that prefab file. Now, how do we do
that? Well the prefab has a type of Game
Object, so we can create a variable that will
hold the prefab. We'll call it ballPrefab,
and we're not going to set an equal to anything, because
this is going to happen, Unity is going to set this. Now,
at the moment, if we save that and go back to Unity
and have a look at the Main Camera in the Inspector, you
see that the component for Ball Spawner (Script) is not
actually showing anything. But if we go
back into VisualStudio and we add public in
front of this variable, in this variable I'm now going to call field,
because you'll notice it's within this declaration of a class. So
we were previously ignoring this, but classes defining a type.
And so what this says is that we have a public class, and we don't have to worry
about what public means, but we're saying it's a class called BallSpawner
and it inherits from MonoBehavior. So it's saying that this is
a MonoBehavior type, it is a MonoBehavior,
and it's a new type called BallSpawner and that's what we're defining
here. And this is one of those fields. Remember that we had a vector
dot x and vector dot y? Well this is BallSpawner
dot Prefab. Now by making it public,
we make it accessible to the Unity Editor. So if we go into the Unity
Editor and have again a look at our component, you see it just popped up,
and Unity's done something clever here, it's managed to pick apart the
name of our variable and has called this field Ball
Prefab. OK, now how do we link it up? Well it's actually quite easy!
We have to just go to our prefab in the folder and then
open up the Main Camera again and we just need to drag
the prefab onto our Ball Spawner script.
Now I'm going to hit Save. And how do we check that this is
actually what is happening? Well let's just use a print().
I'm just going to print the (ballPrefab) like so, just to
check that we are getting it in the Start() method. So hit play!
And we'll need it not to be maximized, so I'm
going to hit play again and go over to the Console
and you see we have the BasketBall is the Unity Game
Object. In fact, it's saying that it's not quite mentioning that it's a prefab
but that's all fine. OK, now one cool
thing we can do with prefabs is we can do an Instantiate
call on them. So we just do Instantiate and we take an object
and this object is the (ballPrefab).
So this uses a function called Instantiate, with the parameter or
argument of (ballPrefab), and then, remember your
semicolons always. So what happens now? What does
Instantiate do? We hit play,
you notice we just got an extra ball in there, and it's called BasketBall
(Clone). Perfect! So we are getting the scripts to
automatically create new balls for us, and we can make that super obvious by
deleting all these handmade prefabs
and just let the code do the job. So we hit play
and it's created a new ball out of nowhere. It wasn't there in the scene to begin with
and then when we click play it is!
Time for your next challenge! I would like you to spawn a ball on
Spacebar, by that I mean when you hit Spacebar, or course, so that we aren't just
doing one and we're not responding to user input. So
use your previous knowledge of GetKeyDown(), that we
used in the previous section. Just..If you can't remember, go back,
now is a good time to revise that knowledge. And put the
relevant if statements in your Update() function, so
that you can actually do something with this
GetKeyDown(), with this Spacebar. You'll obviously need to find out
which the Spacebar key is in code, but that should be
fairly easy with your completion, in either MonoDevelop or VisualStudio.
And then, I'd like you to call Instantiate(0 in this if statement,
so that you can actually create the ball when the key is down.
OK, so pause the video, and have a go at doing this yourself!
OK welcome back! I hope you've
all had a go and paused. This is very important to
try to apply your knowledge from previous lectures, this means that you will actually
be really learning and cementing that knowledge and getting to grips with how
Unity works. OK, so here I am!
Let me pause the playing of this and go into my script.
So I want to create this new if statement, and in it I'm
going to do my (Input.GetKeyDown().
Hopefully you all remember this one. And then remember, we need that Key
Code, so we do (KeyCode.). Now I'm going to guess that it
has Spacebar or something. That's Space, that is the one I need!
Now you see how I just used the completion to essentially explore
the way that this function works.
OK, so I've got my braces, and I'm just going to
put in... I'm going to copy and paste this Instantiate call
right into the braces of my if statement, and i'm just going to
cleanup some of these extraneous blank lines that we don't need.
I'm accidentally opening things! So notice
that we used these blank lines, it's just a good point to note it,
to separate out things of a larger level.
So things like this Start() block are separated by a white line
on each side. This is just visually breaks up the code and makes it easier for your eye
to go to the relevant parts of, well
the implementation. Let's go back into Unity and hit play!
And now, it won't Instantiate
it on Start(), but when we hit Spacebar, it creates new balls!
Perfect! You see when I'm trying to create them over each other, they start bouncing up.
OK, this game is actually starting to react to the user
input, and it is starting to be sort of fun, even though we have not goal just
yet!