Welcome! In this lecture we are going to be
overviewing rotation and how rotation can be a little bit weird
at times. And we're also going to be looking at parenting of
objects. As you can see, this is what's happening in our Hierarchy,
at the moment. And in total, what we're going to achieve is creating a
Camera Gimbal, which allows us to not have
any weird tilting in our camera view.
OK let's dive right in!
So you may have noticed a problem in the way that our
Look script currently works. So, for example, going up and
down, at the moment, is just fine, but when I turn off to the side and
go up and down, I start to tilt a little bit like this. And then, what's worse,
if I go left again that tilt remains. So what
on Earth is going on here? [Laughs] it's slightly making me feel sick, in fact!
So to find out the reason for this, we need
to consider, essentially, what looks like
a model of a person. So I'm going to create, very quickly, a rough model
of a person, and I'm going to do this with two cubes for the shoulders
and for the head. So first off, the cube for the body.
I'm just going to make it a little bit taller and
a little bit broader shouldered. So that is the cube for the body.
And then, I'm going to create a new cube and just have that
as the cube for the head, and I'm going to stick it there on top of the
body, just floating a little bit. So hopefully that makes sense as a person to
you. We will make the Z direction, so this direction where his
face is pointing. That will be his happy smiley face! And
this is his body with no neck, a floating head,
but I think you get the picture. Now, one concept I want to
introduce you to, in this Hierarchy, of why
it's called a Hierarchy rather than a list, is that we can actually parent
objects to or put objects
inside other objects, so it's called parenting. And I'm going to do that by creating an empty
object, and we're going to just call this object the Body.
Or in fact, I'll call it the Person,
and then, this object we said was the Body.
And this object we said was
the head, so I've just renamed these. And now I can
drag that Head onto the person. You see it goes one level indented
underneath. And basically, what that allows me to do is group the
Head and the Body into what we now call a Person.
So what happens is, what's quite nice is, if I move
this Person it moves both the Head and the Body,
and fortunately also works for rotation. So if I rotate,
I rotate both the Head and the Body. Now,
I want to show you why what we were doing ended up
being wrong. So rotation is a little bit weird, it's not like
movement that we can do. With a movement we can happily first
move in this direction, and then, so if I move in that direction
then I can move in that direction. That's exactly the same as if I had first
moved in this direction and then moved in this direction. You see, I end up in
exactly the same place. So that is a nice property of movement there, it doesn't matter which
order we move in but it's going to have the exact same result.
Now, with rotation it's not the same.
So if I rotate by this and then like this,
it's not the same as if I had
rotated and then rotated in this direction. See how the
object is now tilted? And this is exactly what we're seeing, we're seeing that these
rotations, done in the wrong order, mean that now
you can obviously see that our player is leaning off to the left and he is
going to have a tilted view. So this is the problem
with the way we are currently doing rotations. We're doing them on the
same object, essentially. What we want to do
is behave in such a way that rotating left and right
rotates the whole body, with the shoulders and head and everything OK.
So we rotate to the right. Then,
when I look up and down I don't rotate my Body, because that's a bit silly.
If I'm rotating my whole body, I'm leaning forward in order to see.
What I'm actually doing is I'm rotating my Head
up and down, so I look down by rotating there.
Now, what that means is, if I go on to rotate my Body
again, in any of the directions, my Head
hasn't started tilting. So this is essentially what we need to
achieve with our camera, by having these two levels where we rotate
the whole Body and then the second level where we rotate
just the Head, or in our case we rotate just the camera.
OK time for your challenge! I would like you to
create the Camera Gimbal, using the information that we have
about essentially trying to replicate this body movement, about trying
to replicate this person. So I'd like you to use that
structure of our person, and I would like you to...
You will need a parent object to start off with. So like
we have a person parent object, you'll need something like a player parent
object, for example. Then, I'd like you to take the camera and
put it in the place of the head, in the structure,
but obviously in the structure using your new object.
And then, I'd like you to think about the following two questions.
So with mouse X, which object are you going to
rotate? OK, so are you going to rotate the parent or
are you going to rotate the camera, and in which dimension?
And then, I'd like you to think about with mouse Y, which
object do you rotate? OK, so answer these two questions and then
share in the discussions, and then, come back to the video and we'll see how we do it.
OK, so pause and have a go at that!
OK welcome back! Let's dive in and have a go at replicating
this layout! So, as I said, first we want a parent object, so I'm going to
right-click in the Hierarchy and Create Empty. And I'm going to go to the
Inspector and rename this, and I'm going to call it our Player,
because that's a nice understandable name. Now I said
that we want to put the camera in the same place as the head, so that needs to go underneath
Player. So I'm going to take our Camera and just drag it onto
the Player, and you can see now that goes right underneath our
Player location. Perfect! So now,
let's remove the person, let's just Delete that, so that it's
not confusing us anymore. And we've got our Player and obviously
you don't see, particularly, any difference between the Player and the Main Camera, because the Main Camera
is the only thing underneath Player. So , all we need to do now is answer our two
questions. With mouse X which objects do we rotate?
OK, so with mouse X we want to rotate
the Body. So left and right and that is going to be
like so, so that is rotating our player left and right.
And then, with up and
down, with Y, which we're going to want to rotate our
Camera, like so. As you can see, this is keeping
the horizon level in our Camera Preview, that's great! But now, the nice thing is
that we've rotated down, and if I rotate the Player
left and right, then I can go back to the Camera
and I can rotate the Camera up and down again and the
horizon still stays level and we don't get any of that nasty tilting. So
as long as I rotate left and right on the Player and up and down
on the Camera, the result I get is no
tilting and exactly the sort of behavior we want. So we've got our
Gimbal, as I'm calling it, our Player rig setup, and in the next lecture,
we're going to look at how we can do this Player rig programmatically.
See you there!