Welcome! In this lecture we are going to be learning how we can
launch the balls in the direction that we are looking in, rather than simply
forward. And to do that, we are going to be recapping a little
bit about rotations and how they
work in combination with vectors.
See you in there!
So let's start by recapping what rotating a rotation
looks like! So here I have described rotations as
two segments of a circle. So this one is a 45
degree rotation, on the left, and on the right, we have a 90 degree
rotation. Now, remember that multiplying, so these rotations we can
imagine are Quaternions, and we can multiply these two Quaternions
to essentially rotate the rotations. Now, in two dimensions
it's fairly simple, because the order doesn't really matter, but as you can see,
what we end up getting is this full angle
here. The two multiplied together essentially just rotates this one around by
45 degrees, and so the resultant rotation is the sum of the
two degrees, very simple. Now, how about if
we do a multiplication with a vector? So this is a Quaternion
and we multiply it by a vector. What is the result? Now,
so as you can see, this gray was the old vector,
and now we have
rotated by the 45 degree amount and we have a new vector here,
that's the red arrow and that is the result of this multiplication.
OK, so we can apply rotations by multiplying by
vectors, in exactly the same way as we can do it to Quaternions. So
the Quaternion rotated by another Quaternion, or we can
rotate a vector by multiplying with a Quaternion, as well.
So that's quite useful to know! So how about rotating
the forward vector? So if we have this following expression, we've got
camera.transform.rotation multiplied by Vector3
.forward. So this is our camera, as you can see
it is pointing forward, so this blue vector is the forward vector
which is ppointing in the same direction as the camera.
Now what happens if I rotate my camera off to the right, like this?
So I've changed the camera.transform.rotation by a little
bit less than 90 degrees, at this point, and I
multiply that by the forward vector. Where does my forward
vector now point? And have a little guess before I tell you.
Yes, indeed, it does point forward! So
what we've got, by looking at this
expression here, is a vector that points in
the looking direction of the camera. So this is
going to be very useful for calculating which direction we want to launch
the balls in, so I want you to launch in the look direction!
You've got it, there's a challenge for you already, and I think you are capable
of this. You know all the components, you just need to maybe scratch your head a little bit
and talk in the discussions about this. So I'd like you to update your
velocity or the velocity of your ball that you instantiate,
using the camera's rotation
and using this expression that we've just seen, and then, I
would like you... So you'll be needing to rotate the
Vector3.forward, as we just saw in
the previous expression. And just think about
do you want rotation or localRotation,
and which of these two is the correct one for what you're trying to achieve? If you're not sure, perhaps
try them both out and see what the difference is. But I'd like you to discuss,
in the discussions, why one is right and the other isn't.
OK, so pause the video and have a go at doing this yourself!
OK, welcome back! So it is
time for me to have a go! So
the first thing is, well at the
moment we're launching in the forward direction, and we clearly want to be launching in the
forward drection multiplied by the camera. So let's get hold of our
camera first. So it's of Camera type, camera
= GetComponentInChildren.
Now remember this is possible because the Ball
Launcher script is attached to a parent of the camera, it's attached to
the player. So we can do this and get hold of our
camera component, and now, we just want to multiply by
Camera dot... Now what do we want?
...transform, I'm going to go with
rotation. Well actually, let's try localRotation, that's what was working before, so that's
my hunch. I think maybe it should be localRotation,
and I'll multiply by the forward vector,
Save that, hop into Unity.
Now let's give it a go! So if I click,
it seems to be... Yes, that seems to be working! But if I
rotate now, you see all I'm getting
is the up down motion, which makes sense if you think about it,
because what we're looking at is the
rotation of this Camera, and the Camera
locally doesn't rotate around the Y axis, that's this axis
here. It doesn't rotate around this axis, it just rotates
around its X axis, it's local already rotated X axis.
So it's only going to modify whether we are launching the ball
upward or downward. So we actually don't want local
Rotation at all, we want the global rotation, which tells us exactly where
the camera is pointing in our world. So if I hit play
and now I start launching, you can see that the
balls are flying in all the sorts of right direction! Now,
one more tweak I want to make is to... I'm going to minimize this,
and I want to make the balls' launcher a little bit
faster. So I select the Player and I'm going to up it about
20. Let's see if that makes a difference!
Yes, this is a bit easier to play isn't it? It's less of a
Parabolic Arc and we can pretty much look where we're firing
the ball. So to copy that across, we have to hit the cog on
the Ball Launcher (Script) component, and then, you can hit Copy
Component. So now, when we stop playing, we can go to
the Player, click on the cog again on the Ball Launcher, and this
time we can Paste Component Values and that will paste
that 20 in. But imagine, if you had been modifying lots of different fields, it would
have pasted all those fields in. So I can save my scene, and
now, when I hit play, you can see my ball is launched with
a bit more velocity and momentum than it was before!
Excellent! This game is really starting to take shape, and
I'll see you in the next lecture!