Welcome! In this lecture we are going to be looking at how we can
centralize our score keeping system, so that each of these targets
all contributes to the same score. And as a bonus, what we're also going to
be doing is making it so that these targets can score differently, so
for example, when I hit this far away target, it increments my score
by 3. OK, let's dive right into the video!
So here is the game, as it stands at the moment! As you
can see we are getting the score, but I want to show you a little
limitation of how we have written the scripts. So
if we go to our Target, and I'm going to
look from the front, which is what I'm doing here. And
I'm going to duplicate this Target, so
we have a second Target and I'm going to stick it over here. And
yet another Targer, and I will stick it to the left here.
Now, if I play I should see some targets. There we go,
arranged in front of us! However, I want to point
out what happens. So I score 1, I score 2, now I score
this one, and... OK, what happened with the log message there? So
if I minimize, we want to take a look at the Console again.
You'll notice that we've only got these two log messages, but the number at the side, and this is
quite important, is the number of times that log message was
actually printed out. And so what we're saying is that
we've got a score 1, score 2, and then score 1 again. So
the reason for that, if we look in our script. So I'm going
to pause the game, stop the game, go into the project
scripts, and open up my ScoreKeeper script.
In fact, we can see in the preview, even without having to launch
Visual Studio, that we are keeping track of this score
in the script, but it is only
on each Target. So if I add a component
here, it's not the same component as is added on this other Target,
which means that the field, the field meaning
this score, is a different variable
on each of these Targets. So when we count we get
a different count for each one. So what we want to do
is centralize this ScoreKeeper object into a new Game Object.
So I'm going to right-click and Create an Empty GameObject called
ScoreKeeper.
And you'll notice, actually, that ScoreKeeper isn't
correctly spelled, so what we have to do here is rename the file ScoreKeeper,
and then, we have to go and rename the class as well.
So we do that in VisualStudio. It's going to ask us to Reload, because we
renamed the file, so we need to open that file again because it doesn't
know which one we were talking about. And then, if you right-click on the
class name, you can hit Rename and you can just
enter the new name and hit Apply.
OK, so that has renemaed ScoreKeeper, and if you check all the
Targets, they're still pointing at the right thing.
However, we don't want the Targets to be responsible for keeping the score, we want our
ScoreKeeper Game Object to be responsible for that. So I'm going to drag
my script onto the ScoreKeeper Game Object, and I'm going to delete
these two Targets, these two Duplicate Targets. For now, we'll just deal with
one for simplicity, and I'm going to remove that
component. What we're actually going to want is a different script here, we'll do
that in just a second. So let's go back to our ScoreKeeper!
And what we want to do is allow
this method to be called from that other script. So
we want the collision detection to happen on the
Target but the score keeping to happen on the ScoreKeeper. So
let me just show you what I mean. I want to change this
method to being a public method. Now, that
means that other scripts can also call it, and it'll still
return void and it's going to Increment the Score.
That's what we want it to do. It doesn't need to take any arguments, what it needs to do
is when it's called it increments the score, and we can leave it to print out
our current score . Great! So now,
we have one game object with one component and one field
that is keeping track of the score in and that
is on the ScoreKeeper Game Object. Now we need to counterpart,
which is the Target script. I'm going to right-click and Create
the C# Script, and the name of this script I'm going to call
it DetectScoring.
So it's a script that detects when
there has been a scoring. So now,
we check that Target has that script attached. Perfect! And if we open
that script up, what do we want it to do? Well we want it to do that
OnCollision. We want a void OnCollision
Enter. Remember, with (Collision
and collision). Now this time, I think I've managed to actually spell
Collision. Ooh, no I haven't! [Laughs] There I go, making the same error again.
Spell Collision correctly, that's very important because if you don't get the spelling
correct, that's not going to be called when a collision is entered.
And then, here what we want to do is, we want
to call this method. To call this
method, we need to get hold of this object and handily in unity, there is a
method for doing that is called FindObjectOfType,
and then, we just need to get the ScoreKeeper type. So just to be clear,
this isn't finding the game object, this is actually finding
the component itself, which is exactly what we want. So we
can do a ScoreKeeper,
that's the type. That's the same as this class, it's the type,
and we'll just call it score
Keeper and we'll store it in that variable. OK, so
we've created a variable for our ScoreKeeper. We have then
found the object, using the FindObject of Type.
Now, we can simply call our
Increment method. So you should get dot
Increment coming up. So why is that not happening?
We've got ScoreKeeper, it's the right type. Let's just check our class.
Ah, I'm not doing it on the variable, so that's an interesting
distinction if you do a ScoreKeeper type.
There are methods on the type itself, but we won't go into those.
Those are called static methods. But we do want the Score
Keeper variable, so that is accessing the instance
of the type, not the type itself. So the ScoreKeeper
.Increment score is what we're looking for. Let's see if we can get the auto-
completion to come up. I spelled that
variable as Keeper in the first place. Lots of spelling mistakes
can cause problems. So I want Increment
Score. Finally, we got the auto-complete to show us that there was an Increment
Score() method. And notice that I'm naming my
methods, always beginning with a capital letter. That is a convention in Unity, it's
not necessary. I very well could name this method
with a lowercase i and that would still be correct C#,
but for Unity, our default is to
name all methods starting with a
capital letter and using capital letters at the beginning of every word. This is called
camel case. OK, so
that should now do what we want it to! Let's hit play and
just check!
It does seem to be taking the score!
So we'll have to see what it does with more than one
and that is going to be your challenge for this lecture! So I would like you
to create a Target prefab and then use this prefab
to make multiple targets. You'll need to position them apart
in the scene, as I did earlier in the video, but doing that with the
prefabs rather than just duplicates. And then, check that the
score is updated in one place, by playing the game. OK, and
as a bonus, if you are feeling quite confident and would like to
give something a bit more tricky a go. I'd like you to allow
different targets to score differently, so that will involve
creating a field and it will involve passing in
different arguments to our IncrementScore() method. So
you'll have to see whether you can remember or figure out how to do that
and use a bit of the knowledge from the previous videos to
do that. So pause the video and see how far you can get through this challenge.
Don't take more than half an hour. If it takes more than half an hour,
then just move on and mention that in the discussions.
OK,
welcome back! Let's have a go at
doing this challenge! So first things first, I said let's make
a prefab. So I'm going to go into the Prefab folder and just drag our
Target into that. As you see, it turns blue to show us that we've got a
prefab, and I can now drag the Prefab into the scene a couple of times
and just position these targets
at different points to the camera.
And if I hit play, let's check whether the scoring is indeed
central. So if I hit this one the score is 1, if I hit this one the score is
2, and this one the score is 3. So it does look like
we are getting the same score incremented, no matter
which of our prefabs we're actually hitting with the ball.
Excellent! So next up, we want to
see whether we can make the ones perhaps that are further away score better.
So let me add in a target that's quite far way, off to the side
here. So if I hit play, now that's going to be
harder to hit, so I would like that to score more than just 1
when I actually hit it. So
the way I'm going to do that is by adding an argument to
IncrementScore(), so we can increment by different amounts, depending on which
DetectScoring instance is
actually calling it. So the way I'm going
to do that is, say IncrementScore and then the
amount, and this is of type int, because the score is of type
int. And here we need to change our incrementing method
to being += amount. So
if the score that comes in is 1 we increment by 1, if it's 2 we increment by
2, and so on. OK, so that's good
there! If we go into our DetectScoring, you'll notice now it's got the red
squiggly line because it's expecting an argument to come in, so
let's provide that argument. I'm going to do that by creating a public field
and say the score
PerHit. I'm going to
default that to a 1. So we've got the scorePerHit as 1
and that is what I'm going to pass in
to our IncrementScore() method.
OK, let's just check that everything is working as it was before. It should
do, because then my default... Oops,
I'm accidentally hitting things. So
let's just check, the default score should be 1,
and that does seem to be how it's working, so let's
increase the score of this outer item to 3. As
you can see, we've got our Score Per Hit field here,
which the designer can just change, and notice that,
because this is a prefab, it's gone bold saying
that this is different from the original value in the prefab.
If I go to the other prefabs it's still one, and those aren't in bold, but the one
that we've modified is now in bold. I'm going to save the
scene and hit play. And now if I
aim to hit that, there you go my score is 3, and if I hit the other ones,
my score just goes up by 1! Excellent!
Looks like we have successfully completed that challenge! Join me in the next lecture!