Welcome! In this lecture we are going to be looking at adding text to our
splash screen and menu screen, and then, we're going to be looking at how we can
do that for both that and the game over screen, changing colors a little bit and
changing the saturation of the background like this. So
let's dive right in!
So the game is looking quite professional with these different
screens showing up, but they're not very useful without
much text. They're not very informative to our user, so
let's correct that, let's start adding in some text.
So to do that, we right-click again on our Canvas, and
I am going to go to the UI and select Text,
funnily enough, and I'm going to put in a title here, so Shoot
Hoop. And what we need to do is increase
this Font Size, and we also need to change the boundary
of this container. So if we go in here, we'll make this really large,
because I want our title to be about this sort of size. I'm going to
stick it in that black area, I'm going to bring it right out.
I'm going to change the alignment, so that it
is Right Aligned, increase
the size, change the color.
There we go! However, it does
look rather dull with this font, but before we go searching for fonts,
I just want to change some of these names. So RawImage is
the first one I don't like, I want that to be Background. Just so that
the names are always meaningful, this one's going to be Title.
And there we go! So now, this
looks a bit dull. Let's just preview it. Ariel is
fine as a font but not the most interesting, for sure. So
let's go back over and I'm going to use DaFont
for my fonts,
if I don't accidentally lock my screen.
So we'll go to dafont.com,
and you can search through their massive collections of fonts for whatever
seems most basketball related to you. I'm going to go for something
that is Brush stroke. So kind of looking like graffiti
is the thing I'm going for. Something like this but you need to check the license,
and here it's free for personal use. And because this isn't for personal use,
it's for a course, I'm going to be looking for something that is 100% free.
Perhaps like this one here, EDO SZ. So
I'm going to hit Download on that, and then,
unfortunately, because it's in a .zip, I need to show it in the folder and
I need to Extract this file,
like so. And then, I can just
drag that into my Assets folder,
but I do want to put it in a Fonts folder. So I'm going to right-click, Create a new
Folder, Fonts, and drag
that font into my Fonts folder. Perfect!
Alright, now on my title I can finally
drag that font onto the title's
Font field. As you see, we instantly get the
nice new shiny font coming up, and I can just make it a little bit bigger,
Save my scene, and hit play. Let's see what that actually looks
like! Cool, this is actually starting to look fairly
swish! So I'm going to duplicate
this Title text, so that I get all the formatting that I
previously setup, and I'm going to move it down, keep it in line, and I'm going to
use this to give the player some instructions. So
"HIT SPACE TO PLAY".
Now obviously, this is too big, so I'm going to scale that back down,
and I'm going to rename the object
to Instructions,
I'm going to hit Enter, save,
and let's play. This is looking better, I'm
going to just Bottom Align it, so
that the symmetry is a little better. Alright,
perfect! This looks really good! And remember, you'll need to check with
different screen resolutions, that everything is looking fine.
So bring it into a full by full kind of resolution.
You see everything still fits. In my case, we
may need to tweak things around, if your font is in a slightly different
location, than it is on mine.
Time for your challenge! I would like you to update the game over
scene, now with your knowledge about text and fonts. So
to do that, I'd like you to add some styled text to that scene,
and I'd like you to add some instructions, as well. So a title
and some instructions and just let your creativity run wild, do what you
like with the game over scene. Do what you like with the intro scene, in fact, and share what you
have, share in the discussions please. OK, so pause the video and have a go!
OK welcome back!
I'm going to dive in and replicate my content! So
to do that, I am actually just going to copy these two pieces of text,
to save me redoing the formatting. So I'll go into _Scenes
and open up the GameOver, make sure I Save my menu,
and I'm going to right-click on the Canvas to hit Paste, so that I...
Well, they should have been childed, so we'll need to drag them in
to the Canvas. OK, so now the message,
we've got SHOOT HOOP, I actually want this to be GAME OVER.
I'm going to Center-Align, as well. So Center-Aligning like
that. You can then drag to the
center...
...
...of the screen, like so, and it
snaps and everything. And now, we
add some instructions. So "Hit Space to
try again",
and then, we go like so
and
let's just make this into a game over text,
like so.
And while we're at it, let's just change the text to being red! And that is a
nice, good, game over sign isn't it , when your text is
red? OK, so I'm going to preview that!
Excellent! It seems fairly clear, GAME OVER and
HIT SPACE TO TRY AGAIN. Now, the background is slightly overpowering here,
so I'm gong to select my RawImage, which I should rename to background
which I'm doing right now. And what we want to
do is slightly adjust this, adjust its color
perhaps. So let's try adjusting, there you go! We can change it so it fades
out a little bit to black, like
so. And now, the contrast is good enough that we can quite easily read
GAME OVER and HIT SPACE BAR TO TRY AGAIN. Obviously, spacebar
doesn't work, but we are going to be looking at how we can fix that,
in our next lecture! See you there!