Welcome! In this lecture we are looking at how we can keep track of that
score between levels, so that when I have a game over,
it will actually print how badly [Laughs] I did in those 5 seconds
of game. So let's dive right into that!
So our score shows up just fine when
we are playing, and that is great to give the user the feedback
as they're going along, to see how well they're doing, how much time is
left, etc. However, what happens when we get to our game over screen
is that, suddenly that score information is completely not visible,
in fact, it's completely lost. So if I just minimize this game
and have a look, the object in the Hierarchy,
none of them is the ScoreKeeper.
ScoreKeeper has actually been destroyed, and this is a common thing in Unity.
What happens is all these objects, when we switch to a new
level, are destroyed to make way for the new objects in
other levels, so all these new objects replace
those objects that were there before. But there is a way of
preventing that. So if we want to get hold of say the ScoreKeeper's
score, in the GameOver scene, we
would have to do the following. So I'm going to open up my Score
Keeper, that's this one here. And what I have to do is, in the
Start () method I need to call a method called DontDestroyOnLoad.
Now, what does it take? It takes an object! In fact, it takes the game
object that this ScoreKeeper is attached to.
Now, we can get hold of that very easily, just with (gameObject);
(gameObject) is a field on ScoreKeeper. In fact, it's implemented
in this class, MonoBehavior. So remember
with a class, what we're saying here is that we've got a ScoreKeeper type,
which is a MonoBehavior. MonoBehavior has a lot
of stuff implemented already, for us, including this calling to
Start (), Update (), and having a (gameObject)
field. So that is what we're going to use, we're going to do DontDestroyOnLoad(gameObject).
Now, I'm going to hit save and let's hit play!
From here, I'm going to just reduce first the time out in full,
so that we can test a little bit more easily, back down to 2 seconds.
And let's hit play
and we move straight on! Now, I'm going to minimize this again,
and notice that, this time, we have the ScoreKeeper object!
Now, I didn't add that in. We can verify that, just go over
to GameOver, and there's no ScoreKeeper object here. So what
actually happened is, that ScoreKeeper object, thanks to the DontDestroyOnLoad,
has actually persisted between the two scenes.
OK, so that's all very well! But what happens if we
play again! We're going to get an accumulation of ScoreKeepers. Let me show you that!
So I'll just minimize this.
And there we go, we've got our first ScoreKeeper! Now, if I play again,
we want ScoreKeeper and ScoreKeeper, and we've got ScoreKeeper and ScoreKeeper.
And I just keep playing and I get more and more ScoreKeepers!
So how do we
absorb these ScoreKeepers, when we get into game
over? Well the way I'm going to do that is by writing an
absorb script! So let's right-click, Create, C# Script,
and I will call it ScoreAbsorber,
because it absorbs the score
from the other scene. So the way we're
going to implement this is, first off, we want to find the
ScoreKeeper. So I'm going to do ScoreKeeper,
just call it oldKeeper,
and we'll do a FindObjectOfType ScoreKeeper,
like so.
And then, what do we want to do? Well we want to
grab hold of the score in here, so I'm going to do a public
int, because I'm going to want to get this in the UI, public
int score. Now, we can set our
score from the oldKeeper,
like so. And finally, we call Destroy
on the (oldKeeper.gameObject). So see
what I meant, when I said that that was a field of ScoreKeeper?
When, in the ScoreKeeper, we
said (gameObject), I could well have said (this.gameObject),
this being the object, the instance, that we're
currently in, that would have been exactly the same thing, but I can just
remove that and say (gameObject) instead. So
here we are in the ScoreKeeper! We've just destroyed the old game
Object, so we have absorbed that score in essence.
Now, I'll just tidy up my new lines,
and let's put that ScoreKeeper into
our scene, our GameOver scene.
So I'm going to right-click, Create an Empty object, call it the
ScoreAbsorber,
and drag the script onto it.
Now, if we try running from our game over
screen, we're going to get an error, and the reason for that error is
because there is no ScoreKeeper. When we do this FindObjectOf
Type, there is no ScoreKeeper currently in the scene, because it has to come over
from the previous scene, here in Game. So I'm going to
Save this one. I'll go to the main Game, just to check what
I'm saying, we let it to go through, and now, it's fine! There's
no errors there, so if I un-maximize you'll see
what I mean. No errors whatsoever! So what we can do
to minimize these errors is, give the score a default value,
give it a default value of 1, and say that if
oldKeeper. What this means is, if we manage
to find the (oldKeeper), because if this was
null, so if this doesn't return anything, then
this will evaluate a false. So we can cut the
contents of this, and we only access what is in
the (oldKeeper), if we managed to find it. That
just kind of wraps our code in a little layer of safety.
So if I go to my game over screen and hit play, now I don't
have it crashing but I won't have the score object in
here either.
So here is a bit of a De Ja Vu challenge for you! I would like you
to display the score now, on the Game Over screen. So take that
knowledge, that you used in the previous lecture, and create a new GameOver
ScoreDisplay component. Ooh, that was a bit of a mouth full!
And you're going to need to put this on the relevant text
item, and find the ScoreAbsorber and update the
text. So you should be, pretty much, following the same pattern as in the
previous lecture. If you're a bit unsure, go back and have a look at the video,
for that. OK, pause and have a go!
Welcome back! I'm going to dive right in and
attempt this challenge! So let's go into the Assets.
Scripts, I'm going to create that new script, a mouth full script.
The GameOver
Score, if I can spell it, ScoreDisplay.
So this has to be a different component, because we're going to be accessing the ScoreAbsorber
instead of the ScoreKeeper. So I'm going to take that, and I'm going to
add a new piece of text here. In fact,
I'm going to not reinvent the wheel but copy over that text,
which already had all the formatting correct, from here, from
our main game, and paste it in here
to our game over screen. So I'll stick it under
the Canvas, I'm going to move it into the correct position
around the center, I think, and center it in both
dimensions and increase the Font Size.
Oh, I might need to increase the box size, too. So I'm going to increase the
font to be more on par with what else is on the screen.
There, I have the score! I just need to remove the Score Display Component,
because we want to add our new component instead. So I go to Scripts
and drag in the GameOver Score Component, onto the Text item.
Excellent! Now, if I open
up that script, it should be fairly blank,
which it is. So what I'm going to do is, I'm actually going to copy over
the body from the ScoreDisplay, because it's
actually pretty much identical, in terms of it's functionality.
So I'm just going to copy and paste and replace those Update () and Start () methods.
Now, it's complaining about Text, because I haven't copied over
this Using, from the top, so I'm going to copy that over, too.
Notice I didn't copy the whole file, because obviously the class
name is different. It's important that the class name is different,
otherwise things would break! Now, we're not getting hold of the ScoreKeeper anymore.
What we want to be getting hold of is our ScoreAbsorber, this
one here. It's obvious that's going to break the type of this, so
we need to update that, too! And while this isn't a type
problem with our scoreKeeper, I don't like the fact that it's no longer a
scoreKeeper, so if we right-click on it, hit Rename, then we should be able
to do scoreAbsorber, and hit a Apply
and there we go! Now, that is
correctly spelled, everything's looking good,
and if we hit play on our game over screen, what we should see is a score
of 1, because remember the default was set to 1. However, if we come into
the game... Oops, I pulled up my Start Menu!
If we come into the game from our previous scene, we should actually get
the real score, so the score that was scored.
In this case, it was 1. Let's try and score 0!
And 0! And let's try and score a few more than this!
Ah, there we go, I managed to score
3! [Laughs] In 2 seconds it's hard to score very many, but you
can score something and the game remembers! So success,
we have got a score printing on our game over screen!
Well done! Let's move on to the next lecture!