...
Welcome!
In this lecture you are going to be seeing my face, for probably the first
time, in the little right-hand corner of the screen, and
that is because I have this Oculus Rift on my head and I want to show you how
we are going to be using it to control our game. As you can
see, I'm using my gaze to point and shoot these basketballs.
See you in there! So setting up for the Oculus Rift
is actually surprisingly easy, so the hardest step will be
getting hold of the Oculus SDK. So I'd like you to go ahead and do that first,
if you haven't already setup your Oculus SDK. Just
Google for it, go to developer.oculus.com,
and what you're looking for is the PC SDK, that's this one here.
You'll need to obviously agree to various user licensing agreements,
and as of recording, the latest version is 0.8.0.0.
The rest doesn't matter, the important thing is that it's
0.8. So you'll be wanting that or higher, basically whatever is the
latest. As you can see, I already have it installed. When it's installed, you'll
have this Oculus icon in your status bar and there'll be a configuration utility,
and because my Oculus is all plugged in... And
you can see that I have the Oculus DK 2, obviously not the consumer version because that's not
released at the time of recording.
So to actually enable this in our game, it is
relatively straight forward. All we have to do is go to the File menu, Build Settings.
Now, the platform selected obviously has to be for
PC and obviously Mac and Linux Standalone, but PC is the important part.
And we go over to the Player Settings button down here.
Now, that will open something in our Inspector, so I'm just going to
expand the Inspector so we can see it a little bit better, and I can
close the Build Settings, at this point. Now, we want to
expand the pane called Other
Settings, and under Other Settings, there is a Virtual Reality
Supported checkbox here which, if we enable,
Unity does pretty much all the magic for us.
So you need to make sure that your Rift is plugged in
and the orange LED is switched on
here, and then, you simply have to play the game.
It is really that simple! So I'm going to go and start from the menu scene
and hit play and stick the Rift on my head.
Now, in the Rift, you won't see the
scene, because it's entirely a UI scene, and UI that doesn't show
up in the environment doesn't show up in VR, so that's an important lesson.
So you won't see anything in the Rift, you have to navigate
through the computer, at this point, but once we're in the scene, this is
entirely, all this movement is being done by my head,
and again, I can't see anything in the Rift, when the game over
screen plays, so we'd have to play again. So I'm going to just extend
the time of the game a little bit,
by going to the LevelManager and increasing this number.
And let's hit play!
OK,
and if I click in the game itself, then I'll actually be able to fire
using my gaze, which is what I'm doing right now.
...
Perfect! So as you can see, converting an
existing game to VR is very easy, especially when the camera is already
mouse controlled. So we can see the mouse control script
here is enabled and that is what is
allowing us to look around without the Oculus Rift, and in fact, with
the Oculus Rift, you still see the mouse has got some effect. But
if we don't touch the mouse or if we disable that controller entirely,
then it's just the head movement that is effecting it.
And you might notice that, on the
camera image, you can actually see some little dots on the Rift.
This doesn't actually appear in real life, this is because my camera's picking up some
infrared tracking dots, which are built
into the Rift and used for positioning. So your challenge for
this lecture is very easy, you need to setup your Rift! I'd
like you to download the SDK and install it
and then check the VR supported setting, as we just did in
this video, to see how your game plays when using
the Rift. And of course, you're going to need to play test your game,
that's the most important step. Check whether everything feels right, and
we'll be talking a little bit about how we can fix those UI problems in the
next lecture. See you there!