Welcome! In this lecture we are going to be sorting out scoring so that you can
actually shoot these baskets and successfully detect
what is and what isn't a basket, what is and what isn't going through
that hoop. So very exciting! Let's jump right
in!
In the last lecture I was a little naughty, because I didn't actually complete all of the challenge.
What I was supposed to do is also delete these Targets
here. So hopefully you did that, I kind of missed that!
Sorry my bad! Now, if we play,
there is a notable ommision, and that is that there is no way, currently,
to score, especially if we remove those triggers. So what we want to do is figure out
a way of turning a basket, like I luckily just managed to get in there,
into a score! So
what we want to do is no longer have a collider, because we don't want the objects to
bounce off. What we have, instead, in Unity is something called a Trigger
Volume, which is basically an area that triggers a
notification when an object passes through it. So how can we create one of
these Trigger Volumes? Well let's go into our RingBoard and click and
Create a new Empty object, which I'm going to call the
GoalTrigger. And I'm going to add a component
to this, and I'm just going to add the standard Box Collider.
Now, if you check the Is Trigger box, then that
will make it behave like a trigger, so it will mean that
we can pass through it. Now, we're going to have to
change the location of this trigger, because it's a little bit far
down. So I'm just going to bring it up, and I'm also going to bring it across, pretty much,
to be in the basket area.
But I want to make it a bit bigger than this! I want to make it so that it
covers the area, or just about. So you can hit the Edit Collider button in
the Inspector, and then, you have these handles on the green
trigger. It's very faint, very hard to see, but on your screen it might be slightly
easier than watching it on the video, and you can drag it to complete
the ring. Now, if we look from the front, what I want to do is add this,
make this just a trigger around the ring,
like so. I'll hit save!
And now, we want to create a script, so I'm going to Assets,
Scripts, and Create, C# Script.
And I'm going to call it the GoalTrigger, like
so. And the way we get a trigger is
very very similar to the way we got a collision. So while we
wait for Visual Studio to open up, it is almost exactly the same, it's OnTrigger
Enter, so we're going to write that. I'm just removing the Start (), at the moment.
Do OnTrigger
Enter. It returns void, just like before,
but this time, instead of taking a (Collision), it
takes a Collider, and the collider is the object,
the game object, which we are currently colliding with. So
if we print this out or say, ("trigger
Entered"), and then, we'll also print our
(collider).
Now, let's try playing the game and try to score,
seeing if we can get that message to show up!
OK, so I'm kind of missing the target a little
bit.
Aim up a bit.
And this doesn't seem to...
I seem to be unable to score.
Hopefully that works. OK, this is
not currently showing up any log messages, so that
would probably be because we didn't drag the GoalTrigger on.
So it tends to help to [Laughs] have the script, that you
want to run, on the GameObject, because otherwise it doesn't run, and funnily
enough! So let's play that again!
Let's have a go!
OK, so I haven't scored, but I've already got log messages,
and that's because there is a floor in my approach.
So let's have a look with the help of a slide. So imagine this is our basket.
At the moment, we have our Trigger Volume up here, around the ring, but
obviously, when a ball comes flying across and just skims the top
of the ring, we still get a TriggerEnter, so this
approach alone won't help us. What we need to do is add in a
second Trigger Volume down here, and get these two to talk to each other, so
when a trigger even happens here, the top trigger tells the bottom
trigger to expect a trigger event, and when that expected trigger
or collider comes through, then we can score.
OK, so that makes a bit more sense! We have this through
happening, which is exactly what happens in a basket! So how are we going
to achieve this? Well, let's start off by duplicating our
GoalTrigger, and I'm going to make the second one a child, because
the first GoalTrigger is going to want to get hold of the second one, in order
to talk to it. Well I'm just going to rename them, so it's
no longer going to be called GoalTrigger but Primary Goal
or Primary Trigger, for short.
And the second one I'm going to call SecondaryTrigger,
funnily enough.
There you are, by magic I can type that last in! While we're at it,
I'm also going to rename the script!
Remember that script names can't have spaces, neither can the classes.
So now it's reloading, because of the change in the name, so I need to open it
again, and look at all those reload messages.
And the name of the class always needs to match.
There we go!
Now, let's just check if we're getting that same behavior that we were getting
wrong, in the first place.
Yes, yes we are. OK, and this one seems to have renamed
itself, probably because I didn't hit Enter. So...
There we go!
So for this lecture I have a bit of a larger challenge for you! I'd like you to actually
write that SecondaryTrigger script. Now, that might seem daunting but I'm going to give
you some hints, and you should know everything that you need to know. Don't worry, just give
it half an hour. If you're still struggling after half an hour, come back and watch the rest
of this video. So first of all, you'll need a public method called
ExpectCollider() and it'll have to take some sort of argument.
Think about what argument should it be taking,
and where will you be saving the input, so that we know, in that second
collider, to compare? So we can compare what that second collider
coming in is. And then, I'd like you to
call that ExpectCollider() method from PrimaryTrigger, telling it to expect
a collider, and then, write the appropriate check
in the OnTriggerenter(). So you'll need an OnTrigger
Enter() in the secondary trigger, as well, obviously. That's
why it's called a trigger. And you'll need to put an if statement in there,
that makes sure that this isn't just a ball coming up from the bottom,
that is has actually been through and that it is, in fact, expected.
And then, when that case is true, I'd like you to increment the
score. OK, we have a tougher challenge, see if you can hack it! Pause the video,
and have a go! OK,
welcome back! I really hope you've had a go at this challenge, it's going to be really great
learning, even if you don't manage to successfully complete it! Just the
act of trying will help you learn. So let's dive
in and do this in the video! I'm going to
Create my new script, C# Script, and it's going to be called
SecondaryTrigger, if I can spell it correctly.
SecondaryTrigger, OK then I'll drag that onto my Secondary
Trigger, so that I don't make those same mistakes again, where I
don't have the scripts that I want. There we go, so I've got Primary
and Secondary, and it's a good job that I checked, because that Secondary Trigger actually has
a Primary Trigger script, which we do not want. So I'm going to remove that
Secondary Trigger component, and that is
more like it! That is what we want! So I'm going to
open up my Secondary Script,
and it's asking me to reload things,
it doesn't really matter. Now, what I want to do is create that public
void method called Expect
Collider, and here it's going to take a
(Collider collider), funnily enough! Never saw that one coming!
Now, we want to save this in a variable,
so I'm going to create a Collider called
expectedCollider, which is initially set to
nothing, but when we get this method called, we set it
to the collider that was passed in, like so.
Now, what happens is, with void On
TriggerEnter() we are
going to get another (Collider
like so, and we want to check
whether it is the same collider. So I'm going to do an if (otherCollider
==. Remember that == sign is there
to say equality not assignment, because if it was just like
this we would get an error, because it would say
I can't assign this. Whereas this actually says oh
they're equal. Oh, but here I've got, actually, the wrong name as well, so that was probably what
the error was. So we've got (otherCollider == expectedCollider), this is
when we count the score. So how do we count the score? Well if you need your
memory jogging, then we could go over to our other
trigger script, that we previously wrote, the Detect
Scoring. Let's go over to that! And you'll notice,
here it is! We've got this DetectScoring right here, so let's grab that and
bring it over to our Secondary Trigger,
which I think has just disappeared so let's go and open it up again.
And I'm just going to paste
it in there, and for now, I'm not going to worry about different
scores, so I'm just going to put in the score of 1. Let's save that,
go back into Unity, save the scene,
and now let's have a go! So the first thing I want to
attempt to see is that there is no scoring clearly going on
now. Obviously, there is that first trigger with the print statement happening,
and there's still no scoring when we actually manage to
score the basket. So what's going on there? Well I missed part of the challenge!
There is part of the challenge, right here, that says you will need to call
it from PrimaryTrigger and so that's what I'm missing. Let me just go back
across, and let's
make that scoring happen! So I want
to go to my Primary script, which is also
not visible at the moment, it's probably because I have so many scripts open.
And then, I can just remove these print statements, and
I want to get hold of that child object, which is a Secondary
Trigger. So I'm going to go SecondaryTrigger,
save it, I'm going to get the GetComponent
InChildren, and I'm going to get
the SecondaryTrigger, like so. And then, on this trigger
I'm going to call ExpectCollider and pass in the (collider) that
we are getting, in this collision. So hopefully that'll do the trick!
Let's go and hit play!
So what we'll notice is, actually
when I hit the ring, something
is scoring before the basket even goes in, so let's just have a look at that!
Ah, that's why! We haven't moved our Secondary Trigger
down! So we need to bring it down to around about here, so that it's actually
moving through, and it is detecting that movement through, and it looks like the
slide that we were originally looking at. So let's test that again!
See this is the reason we test, because you can never be sure whether you have made an
error or not. So let's fire and try and
aim and score. OK, now this
seems to be working better! If we go over the top, there is
no scoring, unless we actually go through.
Success! Well done! That was quite a long lecture and
I'm very please with you for getting through it with me all the way
to the end! I'll see you in the next lecture, which will hopefully be a little bit lighter!