Welcome! In this video we're going to be adding some color to our
game with sounds! [Game Music Plays]
Something like that!
So one glaring omission that we currently have with our game
is the eerie silence. As you can hear, there is nothing going
on. The balls hit the ground and no one is there to hear it.
So how do we fix that eerie silence? Well I
have handily created another asset pack for you, so we
can go ahead and import Custom Package again, and this time get
the one called AudioKit. It should be also attached to this
lecture! And, as you can see, it's much smaller, it just has a couple of
.wav files. Now, these have come
courtesy of
Gamemaster Audio. So if we take a look at his
website, we have "GameMaster audio",
and he sells on this website
called Sellfy, which is for, obviously, sound effects, funnily enough.
And you can check out his packages, and if the four
sounds that I've included aren't enough or you would like to let your creativity run a little
bit more wild, then check out Gamemaster Audio a really cool guy doing some really
cool sound effects! And you can also find him
in the Assets Store for Unity. So we haven't seen the Assets Store before but it's
this little tab next to the game, and you can actually drag it out
into its own window to make it a little bit bigger, if that tiny amount of
space isn't enough for you. And again, you just need to search for "game
master audio", and you'll find his audio collection package right
here, for sale. So if you feel like shelling out a little bit more money to
make your game a little bit more individual and creative, then that is
the way to go! OK, so now that we
have that audio kit imported, here in the AudioKit folder, you'll notice
that there are a few different sounds. So let's start with the most basic way to include
audio in a scene and that is audio that auto-plays. So let's go to our
main 01_Menu. And we can right-click in our Hierarchy, go to
Audio, and then, Audio Source.
OK, and now the Audio Source, you'll notice, needs an AudioClip,
so fortunately that's what we've got here in the AudioKit. Now, the one I'm looking
for is music_comedy_quirky_fun_knockout.
So [Laughs] a funny name but we want that, and we want to drag
it onto either the AudioSource or that field, so I just
dragged it onto the field. And then, we want to have Play On Awake checked,
make sure that's checked, and Loop as well, so the audio just keeps playing
in this particular scene. I'm going to save and preview!
[Game Music Plays]
Yep, that does indeed
seem to be definitely working! So you now know how to add some looping audio into
your game!
Now it's your turn to have a go! I'd like you to add a sound to the game over!
So find the sound that makes the most sense in that pack, perhaps even not in the
pack, find it wherever you like, go and be creative! And then should
it be looping or not? You probably do want it to play on awake, however,
and then, add the Audio Source to the game over scene. OK,
pause the video and have a go!
OK, welcome back! I'm going to go ahead and add this audio now!
So in terms of seeing which ones are most appropriate, we can
have a little listen here, by clicking on it and hitting the play button. [Chimes Sound]
Ooh, that might work! We also have this!
[Impact Sound] Probably not. How about this?
[Bell Ring] Hmm, unlikely. So I think this one, the game_over_
dark_bell_chime [Chimes Sound] might actually be the best thing
for our game over screen. So let's go over to the game over screen,
and let's add in an
Audio Source. And let's add
the AudioClip. Now, I could actually click this
little icon here, and that brings up all the AudioClips that are
around, so I think I'll do that, get the game one
and hit save. Now, let's test out this scene!
[Chimes Sound] That seems to work!
Now, what happens if I hit Loop instead, hit save and Loop?
Let's hit play! [Chimes Sound]
So it's dying off. [Chimes Sound]
OK, we don't want it to be repeating, that just sounds a bit weird. So let's take off the
Loop. But it gives us a very clear indication that the game has ended, which is what we
were lacking, previously, and it's quite easy to go on playing and accidentally click
the play again button. So fantastic, we have added some color
and audio to our scenes and our game!
Congratulations! I'll see you in the next video!