Welcome! In this lecture we are going to be adding sound effects to the ball
colliding with the hoop. We're also going to be looking at creating
little scoring sounds, just like that! Perfect! See you in
there!
So to add a sound effect to our ball, first off, let's go into our
game scene. But we're going to need to deal with the ball itself, so what I'm going to do
is go into our ShootHoopKit or our ShootHoot, but hopefully this has changed
on yours. I'm going to move this ball into my scene, select the ball,
and I need to add a component to it, and the component is, funnily enough,
an Audio Source component. So we can search for that!
And it has all the exact same components, because obviously the Audio
Source game object is just an Audio Source component.
Perfect! So we have this Audio Source component,
and we need to add an AudioClip. So, as I said, you can just click this little
dot with a circle around it and go and look for your component. Now, the
one that I'm going to use for this is impact deep thud.
I think that's the most appropriate, from this pack.
And we don't want it to Play On Awake, we want to trigger this in a script.
OK, so just check, when you play this you shouldn't hear anything.
That's correct, nothing
is being played, in fact! So if we go to the Assets, and Scripts, and Create
ourselves a new Script that will be responsible
for triggering this sound, I'm going to call it the Ball
BounceSound.
And then, we can open up this script, and we want to replace
all of this, essentially, with an OnCollision.
So void OnCollision
Enter(Collision
collision). And you should be getting fairly used to that signature, by now.
And then, what we want to do is get hold of that Audio
Source. So I'm going to create a variable for it, AudioSource, call it
source, and then, GetComponent.
And the component type's AudioSource, and
then, on the source, all you have to do is call the, funnily enough,
the Play() method. Surprise! Surprise! So we
can just try that out now! I'll save the script.
It's having trouble saving, so
we'll just move between them, and there we go, move between the tabs and then that's saved.
And then, I want to drag that script on to
the ball, so let's get the BallBounce script, put it
on the ball, save, and play!
[Ball Bouncing Sound] There we
go! Perfect, we're hearing multiple bounces! That's exactly
what we need! Now, let's go into our Assets and ShootHoop
Kit, and we want to drag this ball back onto that prefab,
so that everything that is launched is essentially just a copy of that ball with
all the audio scripts, etc.
There we go! Now, I can fire all the balls I want, and
I'm drowned out by the sound of bouncing balls. Perfect!
Finally, we're getting somewhere with this
sound! So, now we can move that ball from
our scene. And one thing we forgot to do was actually bring this
RingBoard, that we'd added all these nice boxes to. If you notice, all the
other ones don't have those, that's because we didn't drag it back onto the prefab, so
let's do that now! Now, if we check all the others, you see that they can all
now score, as well. Maybe you noticed that when you were playing around with the game for
yourself. Perfect!
So now, it's up to you to create a scoring sound, so a little
sound that we make, when we actually have scored a basket.
So I'd like you to add an Audio Source Component, and I'm not telling you to
what, you'll have to figure that one out for yourself. And I'd like you to find
a good sound, the right sort that might, you know,
sound like a goal scoring, and then, find and trigger
in the appropriate place. So again,
just try and use all your knowledge about how
we place things and what structures we use to figure this out,
and just, you know, try for 30 minutes. If you can't figure it out and you're still scratching
your head, then come back to this video. OK, so pause and have a go!
OK, welcome back! So I hope you've had a go at this head
scratcher, and let's dive right in! So
the place I'm going to put this is actually... Well let's think about where I'm going to call it,
for the first place! I'm actually going to call it where we score a goal. So where do we score
a goal? Well we actually score a goal in our LevelManager.
So if we look at our LevelManager, that has a LevelManager
script, and that's where we're going to call it from. So if I go to my
Scripts, I can go to the LevelManager script.
Let's open that up! And, as you see, we have a
LoadNextScene. Nope sorry, LevelManager is not the one I'm thinking
of, I'm thinking of the ScoreKeeper! My bad! So it'll
open up the ScoreKeeper instead, and in fact, we have the IncrementScore. So
that's exactly what we want, we want to call it, instead of this print statement let's get rid of that,
that obsolete print statement. What we want to do is essentially get
this code, which was in, if I
can remember correctly... I cannot remember
correctly from there, so I think it's in here somewhere. Yes, it's the BallBounce
script. We want to copy this code over
into our ScoreKeeper. So we Increment the Score, then
we play a score sound. Now, this is not going
to work right now, because we have no AudioSource on the ScoreKeeper, but
we can fix that. So we'll go to the ScoreKeeper, Add a
Component, add an Audio Source, and find
the sound. And the sound I'm going to use is this chimebell.
Let's get that! OK, let's hit play
and find out what the sound of scoring is! [Loud Chime Ringing] Something
vaguely like that, by the sounds [Laughs] of it!
Let's just try and get it to
go in, rather than bounce around the rim. [Repeating Popping Ball Sounds]
[Ringing Chime Sound] There we go, our chime sound!
But you did notice, that when we start the game, [Chime Ringing]
we get that chime, and the reason for that is I forgot to uncheck
Play On Awake. So if we now save our scene, hit play,
and try that again, now
it should only play [Chime Ringing] when we score!
Perfect! So well done, you have a really nice immersive game now,
which has sound effects and it has music and is
starting to look quite pretty. Just one thing I'd like to change to make it look
a little bit better is this ground, it's a little bit small. So let's make it
extend 1,000 in each direction, and this should basically
take it off to the horizon.
There we go! Now, let's hit play! There we go!
We've got balls until the horizon, it's perfect!
OK, all this game needs now is for you to give it to a friend and
see whether it's as good as you think it is!