So well done completing that section! I'm with Sam, I think
he's a pretty amazing instructor! And you should be really proud of yourself for
what you've built! So as a recap, Sam, what have they learned? So you've built this
awesome shoot the hoop game and you've even previewed it in Oculus,
if you have one of those devices. So well done, that is a massive step, and we're really proud!
And you've really taken your first step on the ladder with Unity, with C#, with
the fundamentals of VR development, you're really coming on a long way. I really encourage you to
share your game, in the discussions, with the other students the best way you can! Screenshots is
fine! If you want to take a video and link to a YouTube video, that's even better!
So please consider doing that. And while you've got all this momentum
behind you and the taste of victory in your mouth, we'd like you to go and
plow on with the next section, where we'll be making the Squashy Toad game, a really cool
VR game! Absolutely, go dive straight into the next section, keep the
momentum! Well done!