Hey and welcome to the course! If you haven't
seen the promo video above. recently maybe
you signed up a few weeks ago. take a quick
look now. because it'll remind you of the
projects in the course. I'm really excited
to have you here. because I can see in the
discussions all the amazing things that you
guys get up to and the progress that you make.
So. I want to tell you a little bit about
the people that I see get the most from this
course. You guessed it. they're the people
who put the most into the course. so please
be active in the discussions. Please try all
of the challenges that we set you. and really
just try and do a little bit more than you're
asked all the time and you will literally
get out what you've put in; I really see that
pattern with other students on the course.
I want to explain the Unity version we're
using. So. back in the summer of 2014. we
re-recorded the course to make sure that it
was using the new User Interface from Unity
4.6. so that was in the summer of 2014. By
the spring of 2015. Unity 5 was released.
so we re-evaluated and decided that the changes
in Unity 5 were so small. because most of
the changes were already incorporated into
Unity. in Unity 4.6. So. we didn't and we
haven't and we won't re-record the beginning
parts of the course. in Unity 5. because it's
simply not worth it. the differences are so
minor. Come the summer of 2015. we released
our first Unity 5 section. which is Bowl Master.
so from Bowl Master onwards you will be using
Unity 5. because at that point we first need
some features that are available in Unity
5. so we install Unity 5. And now. it's winter 2015 and the production of the
main course if over. but I'm now remastering
the first section. We're committed to continuous
updating of this course. and this is just
a part of that. So. you're going to be starting
with Unity 4.6. and as I say. at Bowl Master
we'll upgrade to Unity 5. Don't worry. you
can have both versions installed at the same
time; that's not a problem. What do you expect?
Well. students are on 24/7. and so please
use the discussions. look at Brice's great
video a few down. and it tells you how to
pose good questions. Pose your question in
there. and there are students on all around
the world. There's typically a dozen. several
dozen actually student on at any one time.
and you're likely to get a response from somebody
else very quickly. I will be diving into the
discussion myself. regularly every two or
three days. something like that. and Brice
doesn't take an active part in the discussions
anymore. he was involved in the initial production
of the course and you'll see him at various
points. but you'll basically see me in the
discussions and the other students. So. that's
all I've got to say in this intro. I want
to dive straight in. in the next video and
start downloading Unity. Attached to this
video. you will find the section notes. and
that is a print-out that you can do without
the slide backgrounds. of all of the slides
for this section. and you can print that out
or just keep it on your computer and save
some trees. And the slide backgrounds are
taken off. so that you don't waste too much
ink. So. good luck! Let's dive in. in the
next video. which will be a screen cast diving
into Windows 8. and let's get Unity Installed.
=======
Kind: captions
Language: en
Hey and welcome to the course! If you haven't
seen the promo video above, recently maybe
you signed up a few weeks ago, take a quick
look now, because it'll remind you of the
projects in the course. I'm really excited
to have you here, because I can see in the
discussions all the amazing things that you
guys get up to and the progress that you make.
So, I want to tell you a little bit about
the people that I see get the most from this
course. You guessed it, they're the people
who put the most into the course, so please
be active in the discussions. Please try all
of the challenges that we set you, and really
just try and do a little bit more than you're
asked all the time and you will literally
get out what you've put in; I really see that
pattern with other students on the course.
I want to explain the Unity version we're
using. So, back in the summer of 2014, we
re-recorded the course to make sure that it
was using the new User Interface from Unity
4.6, so that was in the summer of 2014. By
the spring of 2015, Unity 5 was released,
so we re-evaluated and decided that the changes
in Unity 5 were so small, because most of
the changes were already incorporated into
Unity, in Unity 4.6. So, we didn't and we
haven't and we won't re-record the beginning
parts of the course, in Unity 5, because it's
simply not worth it, the differences are so
minor. Come the summer of 2015, we released
our first Unity 5 section, which is Bowl Master,
so from Bowl Master onwards you will be using
Unity 5, because at that point we first need
some features that are available in Unity
5, so we install Unity 5. And now, it's winter 2015 and the production of the
main course if over, but I'm now remastering
the first section. We're committed to continuous
updating of this course, and this is just
a part of that. So, you're going to be starting
with Unity 4.6, and as I say, at Bowl Master
we'll upgrade to Unity 5. Don't worry, you
can have both versions installed at the same
time; that's not a problem. What do you expect?
Well, students are on 24/7, and so please
use the discussions, look at Brice's great
video a few down, and it tells you how to
pose good questions. Pose your question in
there, and there are students on all around
the world. There's typically a dozen, several
dozen actually student on at any one time,
and you're likely to get a response from somebody
else very quickly. I will be diving into the
discussion myself, regularly every two or
three days, something like that, and Brice
doesn't take an active part in the discussions
anymore, he was involved in the initial production
of the course and you'll see him at various
points, but you'll basically see me in the
discussions and the other students. So, that's
all I've got to say in this intro. I want
to dive straight in, in the next video and
start downloading Unity. Attached to this
video, you will find the section notes, and
that is a print-out that you can do without
the slide backgrounds, of all of the slides
for this section, and you can print that out
or just keep it on your computer and save
some trees. And the slide backgrounds are
taken off, so that you don't waste too much
ink. So, good luck! Let's dive in, in the
next video, which will be a screen cast diving
into Windows 8, and let's get Unity Installed.
>>>>>>> 1d882d5df15102d9c45644c583da4ffc34bcfea1:Unity/Section1/02 - Welcome To The Course.srt