So, let's dive in and get ourselves a copy
of Unity. Then, I will talk about how it fits
in your range of game development programs.
So, let's start with a Google search for get
Unity or download Unity may be better. And
then, there's a specific URL you're looking
for, which is the download archive, you can
see it at the bottom of my screen there, and
I'll click on it. www.unity3d.com/getunity/download/archive
Now, if for any reason you have trouble finding
that or the URL changes, just look for Unity
download archive on Google. And we want version
4.x, now just get the latest version of 4.x,
as long as you're on 4.6.3 or newer, then
you will be absolutely fine. And then, choose
your platform. in this case it's Windows,
most of you will be on Windows, a very similar
process on a Mac, and you click Unity Editor
there. So, just take a look at the screen,
you can see the URL, where you click, and
Unity Editor. That's to say, if what you see
on the screen is later than this, no problem,
just get the latest one, as long as it's 4.6.
something.
Hi Sam here with a quick post video edit. I just wanted to say that
a lot of people ask whether you can use Unity 5.3
or whatever newer version of Unity. Now the general answer is
not really you should be using Unity 4.6. Just as
described; that we're downloading here in order to get exactly the same experience
as we are demonstrating in the videos in the coming sections. However,
if you feel very brave then you can go ahead
and get a newer version but you will have to check in the Q&A for differences
as things aren't exactly the same.
OK, cool! So, you click that and
the download starts of course. Now, this is
going to take ages; it's going to take like
an hour to download. So, while that's downloading
I just want to talk you through a few other
things. Firstly, I want to explain that Unity
is not to be used in isolation. What you're
downloading is the Unity Editor, but you will
also be downloading a integrated development
environment, an IDE. Now, in the case of Unity
4.6 that's something called MonoDevelop, which
is a IDE that is bundled with Unity 4.6. Here
it is! OK. And on the Mac, you will also be
using MonoDevlop in Unity 5 at the moment,
but on the PC, when we go to Unity 5 we'll
be using something you may have heard of called
Visual Studio. Now, for the level of coding
that we're doing, at least in the early part
of the course, it makes very little difference
whether you're on MonoDevelop or Visual Studio.
But for Unity 4.6, we will be using MonoDevelop.
And MonoDevelop is where you're going to be
writing your code. So, we've already got two
programs. We've got Unity, for manipulating
all our game objects and everything, and it's
where we'll spend most of our time, but we'll
spend a fair amount of our time in this IDE,
Integrated Development Environment, which
is as I say MonoDevelop or Visual Studio.
There are also other things that you're going
to need longer term. We have a course on Blender,
and Blender is a 3D asset creation tool. This
is a free tool that lets you make even full
movie quality 3D effects, so if you want to
do anything more complex than a simple cube
or sphere, you're going to need something
like Blender. There's also programs like GIMP.org,
which is a free PhotoShop clone. I'm mentioning
only free programs, because I want to make
this as accessible to everybody as possible.
And also for sound, you're going to need something
like Audacity for editing and changing sound.
So, Unity doesn't sit on it's own, it sits
in an eco-system of programs, and what you're
downloading is going to be two things, Unity's
Editor and a Integrated Development Environment.
In this case with Unity 4.6 it's going to
be MonoDevelop. So, let's let that download
in the background. And in the next question,
lecture rather, I'm going to be helping you
to know how to ask good questions, and it's
going to be my co-instructor Brice talking
you through that. So, grab yourself a cup
of tea, take some notes, and get ready for
Brice to give you a really good heads up on
how to ask good questions in the course.