OK, my Unity Download has finished.I hope
yours has, too, otherwise you'll just need
to wait a little bit, until it's finished
downloading. So, let's go ahead and look at
the installation process. Pretty standard,
double-clicking on it. Of course, on a Mac
the installation process is very similar.
You double-click and get a disk image, and
then, you'll do the normal things that you
would do on a Mac installation as well. In
fact, a lot of the rest of this course is
recorded on a Mac, so I am very familiar with
Macs, but for the installation, because the
majority of people are using PC's, I'm going
to be showing it on a PC. Alright, so let's
take a look. Has this window popped up? Here
we go! Welcome to the Unity setup, so we just
go through, we agree now. Slow down! Don't
just click everything. We want to check all
of these boxes, that's fine. We want the example
project and then, MonoDevelop IDE we've talked
about, and the web-player plugin, that you'll
find out about later, but look, when you get
the the destination folder instead of Unity
I want you to call it Unity 4.6. Alright,
this means that later on you'll be able to
install Unity 5, without it going over the
top of this, and Unity will know where it's
version of 4.6 is. So, put it in a folder
called Unity 4.6, and then, it'll go ahead
and install. Now, this may take a long time,
it may not take very long, it depends entirely
on your computer. I suspect it's going to
take several minutes, because this is an SSD
based machine, relatively very fast and it's
still taking a while. So, one thing you'll
also need to know about with Unity, is whether
you're allowed to use it for free. Now, it'll
explain this actually, after it's installed,
but the bottom line is, until you make $100,000
you're fine. And the other thing to be slightly
aware of is if you are being naughty and installing
Unity 5, which by the way won't cause you
too much trouble you'll just have some changes
in the code, when you get to block breaker.
But if you are installing Unity 5 then, it
comes with a free version of Visual Studio
Community, so you need to be careful about
the license rules on Visual Studio Community,
but in general if you're using Unity 4.6 here,
with MonoDevelop and you are just an individual
and you don't have $100,000 of revenue from
Unity Games yet, and if you did why are you
taking this course? [Laughs] But actually
in fairness, some people have been very successful
already and still got stuff from this course.
But look, don't worry, just install it, start
making games. You don't have to report your
revenue to anybody or anything at the moment,
alright. And then, as you start to actually
publish games and receive income from the
games, then start looking at the license terms
on Unity's website, and you may also want
to look at the license terms on Visual Studio's
website, if you're using Visual Studio for
any reason, but for now, you are golden. Now,
let's just look at where this is going, where
it's installing. It's going into C, and then,
Program Files. Oop, probably Program Files
x86 and then, Unity 4.6. Now, you may have
another folder here, called Unity, which could
be your Unity 5 version, but this is 4.6,
and it's installing two things, the Editor
and MonoDevelop, which we talked about. So,
the Editor is going to be where you'll spend
a lot of your time, and MonoDevelop will be
your Integrated Development Environment or
IDE for short. So, we just wait for this installation
to finish. Now, I've got a challenge for you,
so one of the things that happens during this
course is, we regularly stop you in your flow
and say, look let's challenge you to do something.
So, your challenge is to get Unity 4.6. something
running. It's your very first mini challenge.
If you have problems, try checking you have
at least 10 Gig of free space, reboot your
machine, and install again, but get Unity
5 installed yourself, that's the challenge.
So, with these challenges, we like you to
pause the video, hence the pause sign down
at the bottom right. Go and get the thing
done, try your very best, and then, un-pause
the video and come back, and I'll show you
how I did it. So, go ahead and get your Unity
4.6.x running now. OK, welcome back! So, I
am just going to continue my installation.
So, it should be a pretty simple question
now, if you've had other versions of Unity
installed, it may ask you like you saw that
prompt there for me. that a folder already
exists do you want to overwrite it? Well,
that's fine. The key, the proof of the pudding
here will be that we can just open Unity 4.6.
OK, let's run it and make sure it runs, and
then, if it does, we have achieved all we
need for this section. We get a splash screen,
which is good! And we have Unity 4.6 running
here on our machine, which is fantastic! So,
that's it! You can get to all of the menus,
etc. So, I could do with just pinning this
to the Task-Bar, so I can get back to it later,
and then, I'm just going to exit Unity now.
And we're good to go! Fantastic! See you soon!