Hi guys. Brice here. and welcome to your introduction
to the Unity Editor! So. without further ado
let's just straight in and have a look at
the home for the course. the home we're going
to be taking for the course. So. let's jump
into our Unity Editor. and this is what you'll
be confronted with in an existing game. So.
this is an existing game and we have something
on the screen already. There' s a whole bunch
of stuff and this can sometimes be a little
bit overwhelming. if you're not used to it.
So. let's break it down and let's look at
the key elements of the editor. so that you
feel a little bit more comfortable having
a look at your games. So firstly. I want you
to notice the very top of the window has three
different things. it has three different things
separated by dashes. Now. the first thing
is the scene you're in. so a game can have
multiple scenes multiple dungeons. multiple
rooms. those kind of things. and you can break
those down into scenes in Unity and the first
thing you can see in the top window. the Window
Title. is the scene itself. And then. secondly
is the name of the game. so this game is called
Laser Defender. that's the game we're currently
editing and currently working on. So. by looking
at the top of your window. you'll know immediately
which game you're working on and what scene
you're working on. in that game. And finally.
PC. Mac. Linux. that's just what you're going
to be building game against. so we're currently
building a PC. Mac. and Linux game. Now. the
first thing we want to do when we hit the
game. is to play. We want to try and see what
it does and how we can have a look at the
game. and we can do that by just simply pressing
the play button. at the top center of our
screen. So. if we press the play button. we
shall see that the game comes up in the Game
Window. so we have a Game Pane and the Game
Pane turns up with the game in it. So. that's
the first thing we can do. Now. if your editor
for any reason doesn't quite look like that.
if it looks like something else. you can always
go at the top right of your Unity window and
go to reset it to Default. You'll have a bunch
of different options. you have 2 by 3. 4 Split.
Default. Tall. and Wide. that are already
baked in. and those are just different views
and different layouts of the Editor for designing
your games. You already have a bunch of default
layers. some of them are better for one monitor.
some of them are better for two monitors.
and you can play around with that. And the
point is if you ever no longer find your way
around the editor and you're not sure where
you are and how everything is positioned.
you can always go back to reset you layout
to Default. so that's what you can do. Now.
next is how do we play the game. but right
now. it's only a small pane. We want to be
able to see the game in its glory. like cover
most of the screen. So. if we click on the
Game Pane. so you'll notice there's in the
center top there's a scene in the Game Pane.
so if we click on the Game Pane. and there's
a button on the right top of the Game Pane.
called Maximize on Play. If we click that
and play it again. you'll see that the game
will take up a majority of the real-estate
on the screen. so you'll get a face full of
game. and it's a lot easier to see what you're
doing in the game itself. when you Maximize
on Play. Now. you can remove Maximize on Play.
by just clicking it again. Now. you have a
Game and a Scene Tab. and the difference between
the two is the Game Tab is what your player
is going to see and the Scene Tab is what
is actually in your game. And you can see
they look radically different for us. the
Scene Tab and the Game Tab. And that's just
because we've put in a bunch of objects in
our scene. that are not necessarily visible
to the player. So. that's the Scene Tab. that's
the thing you are going to be editing and
working in. and the Game Tab is what you're
going to be previewing the game in. Now. you'll
know something. when I press play. I don't
know whether many of you have noticed it.
but the entire Editor goes a little bit darker.
Now. the reason for that is called the Play
Mode Tint. and the reason we have a Play Mode
Tint is. whenever we've got a game player.
changes we make to the game are not persistent.
They're not going to persist beyond a single
play session. so if I started modifying my
game now. which I could do. I could go into
my scene. modify things around. let's say
select an object and move it around. that's
not going to persist beyond my play session.
So. when I stop playing again all my changes
have been reverted back. So. in order to show
us that. we've going to use a Play Mode Tint.
so right now. it's very light gray. What we're
actually going to do is go into File. or rather
Unity Preferences. in Windows it might be
somewhere else. have a dig through your menus
to find the Preferences or Options Menu. And
you go to your Preferences and you'll go to
Colors and find the Play Mode Tint. and here
you want to find a color that's going to be
disgusting enough and noticeable enough that
you really can't miss it. So. let's try this
pale green. play the game. and now you can
definitely see that the Editor is in Play
Mode. and when it's in Play Mode the changes
will not be persistent. So. that's really
useful to note. because otherwise you can
often make mistakes and not be quite sure
why your changes have been lost. when in fact.
it's just because you made them in Play Mode.
So. now let's get started with creating our
first project. So. let's go to File. go to
New Project. and I want you to do that in
your Editor too actually. if you can follow
along now. Instead of just having a look at
a project that we've already made. you're
going to create a new project. too. Now. we're
going to call this project something like
Number Wizard. in preparation for the next
section. Number Wizard. and we're going to
select a default for 2D. So. you'll notice
there's a drop-down. you can choose between
2D and 3D. You want to choose 2D for Number
Wizard. and then. let's go click Create Project.
And here we go. now we're back in our brand
new project. for Number Wizard. So. now let's
create the new scene. You'll see at the very
top of your window. there's untitled. that's
because you're not currently in a scene. So.
to create a new scene. what we're going to
do is we're going to go to File and then Save
scene. It'll come up with a name. we're going
to call our scene Game. with a capital G.
so Game scene. and you'll see something appears
in the Assets Folder in the Project Pane.
So. you've got the Project Pane on the bottom
and you've got the Assets Folder and Game
appears in the Assets Folder.Now the next thing
I want you to see is. how to move panes around.
so you can click on a pane and you can move
it around. and it'll snap intelligently to
different areas of your screen. So. you can
also detach it. this is now in detach mode.
and reattach it. this is now in reattach mode.
I want you to grab the Console. which is the
thing I'm currently moving. from the bottom
left pane. to be on the right hand side pane.
so add the Console to your right hand side.
This is the layout we want you to use for
the next section of the course. Right. so
next bit is the modes. and just to give you
a short introduction to the modes. you have
a bunch of buttons at the top left hand side
of your Editor and they do different things
and let you do different things inside the
Game Space. So. in particular the first mode
will let you move things around or move the
entire Game Space around. where the second
mode will actually let you move objects around
instead. So. the first mode moves the entire
area. the entire scene. the second mode moves
individual objects. the third mode rotates.
fourth mode scales. and the fifth one is for
UI elements. so the User Interface. And that
is basically it. you can also switch those
modes by Q. W. E. R. and T. by using your
keyboard. and that's basically it for our
introduction to Unity. I hope you'll find
it useful. and I hope it wasn't too overwhelming.
We'll go through it step by step and you'll
learn a lot more about all the things that
you can do with Unity. in future lectures.
So. see you then. and bye for now!