So, in this video we're going to talk
about saving and closing your projects! So, the project
I've got on the screen has, firstly, a
script here, that is unsaved. I know it's unsaved
two ways. There is a dot up here, near the top, rather than
a cross, and also at the very top of the
screen, where it says NumberWizard.cs, there's a star. So, the way to save this
script is Command S or Control S on the PC, or File
and save. So, go ahead and save your script!
We're nearing the end of the section. At the end of each section is a great time to save
everything. You might want to close Unity, close Mono, restart your
machine or whatever, so you need to know how to close things down gracefully.
So, that's how you save your script and exit. By the way, if you try to exit
Monodevelop and you have anything unsaved, of course, it will warn you.
Alright, so now let's look at the
Unity Editor, and take a look at a few things here.
Firstly, it's a good time, at the end of a section, to
tidy up. Generally you want to be tidying up
anything you've created that you don't want. Well, we don't actually want this NumberWizard
.cs script at the moment, because we've done nothing
with it. So, it's a good time to tidy that up. The way to delete a script
is either right click and Delete or Edit and Delete
or you can go Command and
Backspace on a PC. So, get rid of your NumberWizard.cs
script! Another thing to mention, at this stage, is
you may, when you started your project, have chosen 3D
instead of 2D as the default. It really doesn't make a lot of
difference, to be honest. The main difference you're going to notice, if you did
choose 3D, is that this toggle here at the top of the
scene will not be pressed in and you will have a
3D environment like this, with a plain disappearing off into
the distance and this gizmo up here looking kind of
3D or you may be in 2D, like
that. So, it doesn't really matter, you can leave it in 3D
for now, it's absolutely fine. We're not going to be using the
scene anyway, so that's just fine! So,
the next thing I'd like to do is just to remind you how to
move windows around. So, this tab here, this Console Tab,
let's move it back down to the Project, so it's back to
Unity default for now. So, grab hold of Console, move it
back down next to Project, and leave yourself
on the Project Tab. That's fantastic! Now, I also want
to show you briefly how to rename a scene. So again, when you're closing down and
tidying up a project at the end of a section, you may want to rename
scenes to make more sense. The way you do that is you right click,
or just click on the scene once and then
again say the name of the new scene. So,
let's call it Main, for practice. Game, Main, it doesn't matter!
Who knows what to call a scene, when there's only one scene? But rename your
scene to Main, just for practice, for me please. And then, you'll see, at the
top of the window, that it now says Main.Unity and Number Wizard,
etc. So, that's done!
Now, you could just exit Unity. That would
be fine, and it would ask you to save everything. I want to show you a couple of save
options. Under the File Menu, you can save the scene or
Command S, and that will actually save this main
dot Unity scene, which basically is everything in the Hierarchy. So, that's
saved for you. You've also got a Save Project option.
I don't use that very often, that will save all your assets
and anything else that's changed. You can use it if
you want, but again, when you exit Unity, it will automatically save
your project for you. So now you are safe, basically, to
exit Unity. In summary, you could have exited Monodevelop
and Unity without doing any of that, and it will ask you,
like most programs do, whether you want to save your changes. But I prefer
to save by volition, by thinking about it,
rather than relying on that, because it's all too easy
when you exit a program to exit and choose the wrong thing and say no
I didn't want to save or yes I did want to save, either way, causing yourself
a problem. So, it's a good habit to save specifically, when you want
to, and then, when you quit, you won't have any errors. You'll just be
out. OK, the final thing to say now
is, that you can now safely move your project folder,
the entire folder that you created. If you put it where you didn't want it.
Well I've got it in this folder here, called
Run Through and then Number Wizard. Because both Mono
and Unity are closed, if they
are not closed. For instance, on a Mac, if your Mono has a little kind of
glow below it's not closed, and do just quit it go be sure.
But if you have quit mono and Unity completely, then you can be sure
everything is saved, and that is a good time to
move your Number Wizard Folder. For instance, I've got Number Wizard inside
Number Wizard here. A bit of a mess! So, let's just fix that! I just
move the stuff in the Number Wizard Folder up a
level, to here, or
rather to here and then delete my Number
Wizard Sub-Folder, and I've tidied things up. So, that's
absolutely safe to do, once you've closed Unity and
Mono. Now, if you want to reopen your project later, say you want to
shut your machine down now, that's absolutely fine! If you want to carry on the
course immediately, then the way to reopen your project, there's lot of ways...
One is to go into Unity and Open
Recent, but of course, that won't work if you've moved the folder around.
So, the sure fire way to reopen your project is to find the Assets
Sub-Folder and then double click on the .Unity File, any of
the .Unity scene files, so this Main.unity.
And when you do that, then you wlll be back into Unity.
You can be in 2D or 3D, it doesn't matter! You've got a
camera, you've got a Main Scene, you've got an Inspector, and
that's it! So, you want to end up looking like this, at the end of this section,
to make sure that you're ready for the next thing. So, there you go! You know how to leave
Unity and come back in with confidence! See you soon!