OK, let's talk about the difference between
the Unity versions on Mac and PC. So, here
it is on the PC again, looking a little fuzzy
a little strange, because what you're seeing
here is the outer window, which includes my
team viewer which is the way that I'm logging
into a PC, but anyway, don't worry about that.
This is the version on the PC that you can
see here, that you're becoming familiar with,
and then, I have here the Mac version. It
looks very similar of course, now there are
some differences. I just want to show you
the differences, because most of this course
is actually recorded on a Mac. So, let's flip
back again, hardly any difference, you're
seeing some font differences, that's the main
thing really. The title bar is a smaller font
on the Mac, but the Unity Menu, and this is
what normally causes confusion, on a Mac you
have a Unity Menu with About Unity, Preferences,
Modules, Manage Licenses, they're are the
four main things. Well, those things are split
out on the PC, into the Help Menu and the
Edit Menu, so if you're looking for About
Unity or Manage License, on a PC, you go to
Help and then, you get... sorry, you go to
Help within Unity and you get About Unity
and Manage License. On the Mac, where you
have the Unity Menu and you have Preferences
and Modules, well on the PC, that's under
Edit and then you have Preferences and Modules,
so that's the main thing. Now, I want to show
you some differences in MonoDevelop, so I'm
going to create... You don't need to do this,
by the way. ...create this script, but I'm
just going to create a new script. I'm going
to open MonoDevelop on the PC. Sorry that
it's a bit fuzzy, it's just the screen resolution.
Now, here it is on the PC, and then, let's
have a go over into the Mac and do a very
similar thing in the Project Window. In fact,
I've already got a script here. I'm going
to let it open. Basically what I'm trying
to tell you is that they're very very similar
indeed. So, here on the Mac is my MonoDevelop.
Now, just because I don't have the left hand
column open, the left hand view, I could be
bringing in a pad on the left hand side; I
think it's called the solution pad, there
you. And then, that makes it look very similar
to the PC version, which is just for reference
back here. OK, so they look very similar and
they act very similar, so you have slightly
different menus in MonoDevelop. On the PC
you may need to go to Tools and Options, whereas
on the Mac for MonoDevelop, you might well
be needing to go to MonoDevelop, Preferences.
OK, so not much difference, just the difference
in which menu you first go to, otherwise we're
talking about two very very similar beasts.
So, hopefully you won't have any problem following
along this course, given that we are generally
using the Mac version, even though you are
in the PC version. OK, so that's that. Good
luck! Have a quick explore, make sure whichever
platform you're on you know where to find
things. Have a look for the Help Menu the
Edit Menu, etc., and then, I'm sure you'll
be able to make the translation now. OK, congratulations!
I'll see you soon!